Chapter One: Ash and Dust

I suppose if I have to start somewhere, it would be with the day I was reborn.

☢

The first thing I knew was hunger.

Not the kind of hunger that sends you to the pantry to find a quick snack. Not even the kind of hunger that slowly wears you down as you starve to death. I mean the kind of hunger that tears at your very soul, consuming your every thought.

My world was hunger; everything else was a mere flicker of light in the background.

Then my hunger-deranged mind caught the one thing out there that mattered to it: love. It latched onto the intoxicating sensation, pushing me toward a single, simple objective:

Feed!

I surged forward. In the distance, past the hunger, I could feel a body—my body!—move in response. It felt so remote, so detached from the hunger and sweet sense of love that had become my entire world.

I pushed forward, and something resisted me. Numbly, instinctively, I lowered my head and pushed again. I was only vaguely aware of the cool sensation that met my horn as I drew a little closer to my prize. Clumsy limbs pushed and flailed as the sensation spread, and I flowed forward. I felt pin-pricks all along my body as everything twisted and turned with my movement, the world momentarily losing all sense of cohesion, then solidifying abruptly as I struck something hard. Past the laser-like focus of my hunger-addled mind, I only barely recognized that it was the ground.

Thick fluid coursed over my body as I reoriented on the love I sensed. My hooves wobbled and slid against the hard ground as I coughed up copious amounts of fluid, but I ignored the difficulties of my body. I scrambled blindly forward, over inconsequential obstacles, until I fell upon the source of the tantalizing emotion.

I didn’t know exactly what I grasped in my hooves. It was small, hard, and most importantly, filled with love.

I fed.

I drew in every little bit of love, and the terrible hunger relaxed its grip on my mind.

Devoid of the powerful, all-consuming drive, my head sunk to the wet ground, feeling so incredibly heavy. Then everything was gone once again.

☢

To this day, I still can’t remember the dream that had followed. The only thing I remember was the voice that had been at the center of my world. My Queen. Queen Ephema.

I don’t remember what she said in my dream. I just remember that she was there, speaking, and that her voice was happy and kind. I wish I could remember more.

I like to think that the dream was of the day I had left the hive for my first solo assignment. The day I had truly stepped up to embrace the mantle of Infiltrator. The day that I could finally return all the effort she and the rest of the hive had invested in me. Queen Ephema had spoken to me many times before, as she did with all of her children, but that day was special. That day, she told me how proud she was of me; how happy she was for me.

I felt as light as a feather at her kind words, a happiness that I clung to during my long months away from the hive.

I don’t know for sure if that’s what I dreamed of, but I like to think it was.

It’s how I want to remember her.

☢

Sound was the first sense to creep its way into my reluctantly conscious mind. I slowly became aware of a quiet, repetitive squeaking nearby. Somewhere in the distance, a klaxon sounded, muffled and echoing, mixed with indistinct words from some far-away speaker. As consciousness returned, I began to notice the soft hum of electronics all around me, and the steady dripping of liquid.

A faint glow caught my attention. A ghostly flicker of orange barely seen through my eyelids, just on the edge of my perception. After a few moments of drowsy contemplation, I finally opened my eyes. A wavering orange splash of light weaved back-and-forth around a blob of green light. It took several slow blinks before my vision started to focus. The wavering orange light was cast by an emergency light. It squeaked as it spun in place, casting its rotating light across a bare concrete wall and filling the dark room with deep, flickering shadows. The green I saw was the light shining through the deflated remains of the chrysalis I had just escaped.

Now, I want to clarify for any who might be confused: that’s lower-case chrysalis, a changeling cocoon, not upper-case Chrysalis, the changeling queen. I figure it’s probably clear from context, but I wouldn’t want anyone to think I came from her.

After contemplating the limp, dripping remains of the chrysalis, I raised my head. Thick fluids dribbled from my chin as I took in more of the room. The first detail I caught stopped me cold. On either side of the cocoon I had emerged from hung many more. The first one I looked at was still full, though the fluid was dark and murky. The spinning light cast shadows across the empty husk of a dead changeling floating within it.

A faint flicker of adrenaline, cold and acidic, began to chase away the remaining sleepiness.

The husk sat still, suspended in the dark muck of its own decay. Vacant eyes stared out, the empty carapace tangled up in wires that attached to it in several places. I stared numbly at it for several seconds before I swallowed—despite the fluids still slowly dripping from me, my mouth felt dry—and looked back to the chrysalis I had escaped. Similar wires hung from the gash my horn had torn in the clear membrane, the pads that had attached them to my body dangling.

I looked slowly over the line of cocoons, ten in total. Only one other was still full, and its occupant had fared no better. The rest were torn and deflated, dangling in tattered ribbons from the pipes above. A couple more husks hung in mid-air, entangled in the remains of the chrysalises that had held them. Others had fallen to the ground. Some, I realized in horror, had survived their internment only to die shortly after gaining their freedom. One of the obstacles I had blindly stumbled past was the dead husk of another changeling, sprawled out on the floor as if it had been trying to reach the same life-giving store of love I had just devoured. The empty eyes of the exoskeleton stared in my direction, as if blaming me for her death.

I lay my head down, eyes shutting again. My heart rate and breathing had accelerated, and I focused on breathing slowly and deeply. I had to focus and stay calm. I had a responsibility. My hive had invested years of training, preparing me to deal with stressful and dangerous situations. I hadn’t anticipated ever finding myself in such a horrible situation, but I knew I couldn’t let that stop me. I owed all of them that much and more.

Especially the ones who lay dead, where I had lived.

So I wrestled down the feeling of fear and despair that clawed at the back of my mind. I slowly relaxed, stilling the trembling that sought to take over my body. I lay there in the room as I focused on the quiet, repetitive noises all around me.

I’m not sure how long I simply lay there in that shallow puddle of fluids. I knew I couldn’t stay there forever, that I had to eventually get up and deal with whatever had happened. That was slightly complicated by having no idea what had happened. My mind was still slow and groggy from the induced hibernation within the chrysalis, and my memory was spotty at best. I needed to get up, figure out what had happened, and find my way from there.

But still, I just lay there, ignoring the world around me, as if by refusing to acknowledge it, it might cease to exist. I ignored the empty husks of my dead siblings. I ignored the uncomfortable object beneath my chest, which I had collapsed atop after my meager feast. I ignored the form that lay beside me, glimpsed in the corner of my eye; a large form, still and silent, looming over me.

I didn’t want to look. I wanted to lay there, as if I could pretend there was nothing wrong. It was tempting, but I knew I couldn’t. I owed it to my hive, my Queen. I had to look.

I had to face the truth, no matter how it hurt.

So I opened my eyes again, shakily raising my head, and turned to look at the empty husk of Queen Ephema. Even in death, she still looked regal, laid out with her head leaning against the concrete wall.

I trembled, giving a weak sob around the tightness in my throat. I might have even cried a little. Part of me wanted to just give up; to curl up beside her, close my eyes, and join her. My Queen was dead. My hive, likely, as well. Why else would she still be lying here, uncared for? It was a disgrace, a defilement. Noling would have permitted this, had they been able to do anything about it.

Another dead changeling lay beside her, a foreleg draped across one of the Queen’s. The gaping eyes showed me—in more detail than I could have ever hoped or wanted—the emptiness that lay within the exoskeleton. Everything that had made them who they were had decayed away long before I had woken, leaving nothing but empty husks behind.

I looked to the other changeling lying beside the Queen, and wondered if she had given up, preferring death at her Queen’s side over carrying on with such a horrible burden. I quickly cast the thought aside. Whoever she had been, she deserved better than such dark thoughts.

A sudden fit of coughing wracked my body, wet and phlegmy. I managed to cough up another mouthful of liquid, spitting it to the floor.

Recovering from the coughing fit, I suddenly realized the lump under my chest was the Queen’s other foreleg. Ignoring the weakness in my limbs, I quickly scrambled to my hooves. It wasn’t out of disgust or fear from contacting a… a corpse. It simply seemed disrespectful to treat her remains as if they were a common cushion.

As I stood, a flicker of light and a quiet clatter drew my attention down to the concrete floor by my hooves. A crystal the size of one of my fangs lay there, reflecting the spinning light. I knew immediately what it was; a love crystal, a wonderful little device for storing, as you might guess, love. A small one like it could hold enough love to keep a changeling fed for weeks, but this one lay empty. I had consumed what little love was left in it.

Several more lay encircled by my Queen’s forelegs, as if she were protecting them. All were empty, without even the faintest trace of love remaining. Had they been consumed? Or had their love leaked away, like a spoiling apple? How long could those crystals hold love?

I saw it as an offering; one final gift to her children. I didn’t doubt it for a second. She lay there as if she knew what was coming, and still she sought to provide for us. I shuddered, eyes tearing up again. Her gift was the only reason I was alive.

Even with that gift, my hunger still had its claws sunk in deep. I needed to find a source of love soon, or her gift would be wasted. A few days, maybe. Even refraining from the use of magic, I wouldn’t last a week.

Only then did I notice the object held between her hooves. I stared at it through blurry eyes for several seconds before I realized what it was.

A data-store. Small, sturdy, able to hold tremendous amounts of digital data. And she held it, as if offering it to me.

I lurched forward only to halt myself. Then, slowly and reverently, I took the data-store gently in my hooves and lifted it away, a few droplets of water falling from the device. I held it like some holy relic, staring at it as if I could read its contents through my rapt attention. Whatever was in there, my Queen had held on to it, protecting it even more than the crystals she had left for us. A message for us, her daughters, who had survived her. I needed to know what secrets it held.

Which meant I needed a computer.

I wiped a hoof across my eyes—managing only to smear around the fluids clinging to my carapace—and looked about, finally taking in the room around me.

The chrysalises filled the center of the room, hung from the exposed piping and arranged in a semi-circle around a slightly raised central platform. Machinery was arranged behind and beside each one, with cables and tubes leading to the various cocoons—or, in many cases, splayed out across the ground where they had fallen upon their cocoon’s failing. Most of those loose cables lay in puddles, and not all of it came from the dripping, just-vacated chrysalis. The walls were stained from the trickling of water running over them, and drops fell from some of the pipes, and from the rusted-over sprinkler head set beside the spinning light.

Along the back wall lay pieces of torn-apart machinery. Several empty egg-shaped devices, large enough for a fully grown changeling to fit comfortably inside, had been partially disassembled. Their remains lay discarded in a heap, cables twisted like electronic entrails. What really caught my attention, however, was the faint green glow of a terminal.

It was the first good news I had received since waking up, and I stumbled my way over to it, doing my best to ignore the protests of my legs; my muscles ached from disuse.

The ache made me think. The magical energies within a pod slowed muscle atrophy, but did not eliminate it, and my legs were already feeling the strain. They trembled slightly as I moved, a burning fatigue spreading up through my shoulders. I had been in that chrysalis for a long time. But how long?

A glance at the pod I was hobbling past told me it was a very long time, indeed. Many months, at the very least. Years, most likely. My mind couldn’t help pondering the changeling within; how long had it taken for her to die, and then rot away to an empty shell?

I shuddered, which quickly devolved into another coughing fit. A bit more of the viscous fluid dribbled from my lips as I recovered. I did my best to ignore the growing ache in my gut, taking small comfort that the fluids within a changeling pod were not foul-tasting; it had little flavor, like water with a hint of salt and sugar mixed in.

Once I felt sturdy enough, I continued past the pods to the terminal. I needed answers. Information is a powerful weapon, and right then, I was disarmed. I needed to fix that. I needed to arm myself with knowledge so I could begin to figure out what to do next.

And to tell the truth, I could desperately use something to distract me from the death that surrounded me. Something, hopefully, that might give some sense that things could, somehow, be made right.

I faced the terminal screen, ignoring how the brief trip had already rendered me short of breath. Stress, I reasoned to myself, as I wiped away the thick layer of dust on the screen and hit a key. The terminal woke up with a faint whir and hum, the blank glow of the screen replaced by a simple message:

Welcome back, user CoolBugz.

I choked out a weak laugh, halfway between humor at the login and crippling depression at finding amusement while surrounded by my dead hive-mates. I’m pretty sure my mind was not terribly stable at the time. I forced myself to swallow my grief and continue on.

With another press of the button, the welcome message disappeared, replaced by a logo in monochrome green text.

Crystal Life Technologies

For a better future

Resuming session...

The terminal hummed for a few more moments as it worked, while I considered the name. It was vaguely familiar, though I couldn’t quite place it. The logo vanished before I could remember, presenting me with an alert message and a very rude bleep.

Danger!

S.A. pod #4 (Experimental) failure!

Biomed control system failure!

Lifesign monitoring failure!

Check occupant immediately!

A quick count placed my chrysalis as the fourth from the left. At least there was some small comfort that the computer was concerned with my well-being, for what little that was worth.

I pressed a key to continue, and the warning was replaced by a new one.

Warning!

Primary power system failure.

Emergency power systems activated.

Containment locks released.

All personnel evacuate immediately!

Containment locks? I looked to the door of the room, standing open. It was one of those heavy, powered doors, the kind that probably weighed five hundred pounds and could stop a good-sized explosion. My gaze drifted to my Queen, resting just beside the door. Was that what was responsible for this? Had she woken, as I had, only to be trapped in here by this ‘containment lock’?

I swallowed around the returning lump in my throat, and hit the key again.

Caution!

External environment is not safe.

External radiation at 168% of safety threshold.

Minor atmospheric contamination detected.

Moderate water contamination detected.

Environmental seal compromised.

Structural breach detected.

Environmental isolation can not be established.

All personnel evacuate immediately.

I was trembling again. This was not the good news I was hoping for.

A final press of the key cleared away the last of the warning messages, returning the terminal to its standard interface. I ignored the message that opened automatically to look for the time-and-date display. I stared at it in confusion until I realized that there was some sort of error. The time-and-date display was showing nonsense. For some reason, the terminal thought it was a couple centuries in the future.

A little disheartened by the lack of sensible information, I read over the displayed message. It was titled “Daily Report”, and consisted of an extensive list of technical problems. The first entries were the condition of the cocoons, or “S.A. pods, (Experimental)” as it titled them. Nine reported complete failures, with the last reporting several warnings of degrading systems. Other warnings noted problems for the rest of what seemed to be a sizable facility, such as a pressure failure in the fire suppression system, flooding in “level two”, complete failure of the water processing and pumping system, and the failure of two of three air intake and purification systems.

The only thing of interest I caught in the long list of failures was that three of the eight spark generators had apparently still been working when the daily report was generated. Judging by the warning I had received on starting up the terminal, they had all failed simultaneously today.

At the bottom of the message, the clean and formatted text abruptly changed.

***Bugz***

***WakeUpCall***

EnvExternalRad1.68

EnvExternalAirTox0.63

EnvExternalWatTox3.32

EnvExternalAirTempTRUE

EnvExternalAirLiveTRUE

WakeUpCallFALSE

Whatever it was, it looked like something crudely hacked onto the end of the existing report. I noted right away that “EnvExternalRad” matched the warning message I had received about external radiation levels. Whatever this was, it seemed to be making note of what conditions were like outside, and if I had to guess, deciding whether or not to wake us up based on what it found.

Or in short, it said the world outside was poison, and I shouldn’t be awake yet.

Really not what I wanted to hear right now, I had thought. I’m pretty sure now that the fact I was silently talking to the terminal within my own head was a sign I was uncomfortably close to simply losing it.

An option flashed near the top of the screen, titled “New unread daily reports.” It was a moment of hope for me; if this terminal had been generating and storing daily reports ever since we had entered our chrysalises, the number of messages it contained should tell me how long I was gone!

I hit the option, and the screen changed to a list of reports. The “new messages” number exploded.

I was completely unsurprised when it almost instantly hit three digits, and only a little disappointed when it added a fourth digit, barely a second later. I sighed, slumping a little, but I was hardly surprised. A few months was beyond optimistic. A few years was much more reasonable, given the state of the room and the… decay.

The number kept going.

Horror started to dig at my gut as the number climbed higher and higher, refusing to stop. Years rolled by before my eyes.

It hit five digits, and my hindlegs gave out. I sat down, staring numbly. My brain did some quick math, completely without my bidding. Roughly thirty years. And still, it counted higher.

I continued to stare, unmoving, transfixed by the impossible horror of what I was seeing.

Finally, it stopped.

You have 73,741 unread daily reports.

Again my brain did some quick math. If that number was correct—and I really didn’t want to believe it!—that was roughly two hundred years. Part of me suggested that it was wrong. The terminal had the wrong date, maybe it made up a bunch of daily reports for a bunch of days that didn’t actually happen!

Even at the time, I knew I was grasping at straws, but it was either that or drown in the realization that everyling was dead. My hive was gone.

I trembled, leaning against the terminal, and sobbed. Tears flowed down my snout as I shook, on the verge of giving up, but I let out a weak, angry cry as I thumped a hoof against the terminal’s housing. I was alive! My Queen had gone through all this effort for us, and I was alive! If I was alive, others could be, too! I couldn’t just lay there, crying like some spoiled filly as I threw away my Queen’s gift!

I pushed myself upright, doing my best to control my sobbing, and wiped at my eyes again, to no better effect than the previous attempt. I hit the “back” button with more force than necessary, eyes narrowing as I did my best to channel all my pain into determination. I glared at the terminal like it was an enemy I needed to extract information from.

A quick search turned up a socket, and I plugged in the data-store. The terminal hummed again, punctuated by the occasional whine. It kept working, and working, and working. After half a minute, it finally displayed a message.

Error: could not read external device.

File system corrupted.

The fire that had been growing in me died. I managed to hold on for a couple seconds against the wave of depression, but I finally buckled with a loud sob. I slid down against the terminal until I lay curled up before it, trembling and crying.

My Queen’s final gift, and it was denied to me.

My sobbing mixed with coughing as I spat up a bit more fluids, my chest aching as the muscles complained. A particularly bad coughing fit left me groaning, clutching my gut. At least it gave me something else to occupy my mind. The desperate sadness was shunted to the background as I simply focused on breathing.

I think that’s the moment that I really returned. The moment my brain finally woke and came up to speed. The grogginess from my extended rest still left me in a faint haze, but as I focused on the burning ache in my chest and belly, my mind started to tear apart the situation, evaluating it. My crying died away as I lay there, thinking.

I am on my own again, I thought. That wasn’t so bad, even if the reason for it was horrific. I was an Infiltrator. I worked on my own regularly, often for months at a time. I had been trained to work independently, to approach and deal with problems without the guarantee of assistance. Yes, I didn’t know if anything of my hive had survived, especially if it had really been as long as the terminal claimed it had been. But I was equipped to work on my own in uncertain situations.

If anything of my hive had survived, I could find it.

My Queen had brought us here for a purpose. She brought us here to preserve the hive.

I had a mission.

Slowly, I pushed myself back up onto wobbly legs. I blinked away the last of the tears, refocusing on the terminal. After a deep, steadying breath, I reached out, hitting a key to back out to the main menu once again, and started searching through the rest of the terminal.

The search turned up little. There was no personal correspondence, though there were lots of research notes that flew over my head. The only thing I got out of that was the mention of “suspended animation”. It led me to finally recognize where I recognized “Crystal Life Technologies” from. C.L.T. was some small-bit company that had managed to have dealings with five of the six ministries of the Equestrian government, thanks to its research in cryonics and suspended animation. It wasn’t a big player, not even close, but those connections drew enough interest to be one of the companies we kept tabs on.

Unfortunately, that recognition didn’t help me any, now.

The terminal seemed to be used solely for research and operation of the “experimental” suspended animation pods. There was nothing useful to me. It didn’t even have a map.

I sighed as I turned away from it. Looking back at the rest of the room prompted a moment of hesitation and sadness, but it faded quickly. I had cried too much already. Now it was time to act.

Step one: survive.

Considering my situation, I knew that might be a bit of a challenge all on its own. I had hardly done anything since waking, and already my body was exhausted. My magic was almost depleted, and I was sure I’d need plenty of food and water soon. I had no knowledge of what was out there, except for the vague environmental reports the terminal had provided. Sadly, of all the technical jargon and analysis the terminal had contained, none of it gave even a vague idea of what those environmental measurements actually meant. I’d have to dig around in the actual code, and I didn’t have the tools for that.

Not that I really needed fine details to get the idea that “minor atmospheric contamination” was probably a bad thing.

I needed supplies, and I needed a way to carry them. I retrieved the data-store, hoping that I might be able to extract the data it had held with the proper tools. The love crystals were definitely coming with me, with the hope that I might someday acquire enough love that I might need to store some of it—and if I’m entirely honest, in part because they had come from my Queen. And, since I didn’t want to spend more of my limited magic than absolutely necessary by levitating them all the time, I needed something to carry it all in.

A quick scan of the room turned up one of those ubiquitous wall-mounted Ministry of Peace medical boxes, the paint mostly peeled away. Half of the box was badly corroded by the years of water trickling down the wall and over it, but it would serve my purposes. It took a couple good jerks to free it from the rusted mounting brackets, and I set it down on a table and opened the box.

It had once held a healing potion, but it had long ago broken, the liquid pooling and ruining most of the contents. Only a single bandage had survived. I set that aside and dumped out the rest of the contents. Glass shards clattered across the table, along with the rotten remains of a couple more bandages, a pair of corroded injectors, their labels decayed away and their contents likely ruined, and, of all things, a badly rusted Equestrian Army service pistol.

I stared at the pistol for a couple seconds, unable to help thinking that the M.o.P. would have been quite upset to find such a thing stored within one of their medical kits.

Still, a pistol might come in handy. They weren’t useful for infiltration and impersonation—in fact, weapons could be a major liability!—but they could be useful in case of emergencies. Every Infiltrator received basic weapons training because of that. Some, those trained up for more direct action, received even more, but I was not one of those operatives. Still, I had practiced on a model just like that pistol, albeit in much better condition.

Unfortunately, the condition of this pistol was far too poor. A few quick tugs revealed that the slide had rusted firmly in place, and I expected the internals had fared no better. It would probably need serious work to ever fire again, and I would hardly know where to start. I might be able to cludge my way into getting it working if I had a full tool shop and many hours to poke and prod at it, but that was time I simply didn’t have.

Leaving the gun behind, I tapped the medical box against the edge of the table until it was more or less dry, then placed the crystals and data-recorder within it, with the latter carefully wrapped in the intact bandage.

I closed the box, picked it up in my mouth, and looked around the room. My eyes lingered on each of my fallen sisters before stopping with my Queen. I knew I couldn’t leave them. I had to go, but I couldn’t just leave them, lying there, abandoned.

I stepped out the door and into the hallway. It was long and dark, illuminated at one end by another spinning emergency light. The entire area screamed utilitarianism and practicality: all bare concrete, with a simple metal grate along the floor for traction. Pipes ran along the ceiling under dead lights. One pipe had broken in half, jagged ends fallen to the floor. Whatever they had carried had stopped flowing long ago. At least it was dry, unlike most of the floor in the room I had awakened in. The regularly spaced drains seemed to still be doing their job.

I set the medical box beside the door, and began the slow process of gathering the remains of my fallen sisters. Their husks were disturbingly light, producing hollow drumbeats any time a part of the empty exoskeletons bumped against anything. I winced every single time.

The last two were the trickiest, still contained within their pods. I looked at the first, floating almost ghost-like in the murky fluids. The rotating light gave the sight a spectacularly creepy vibe, occasionally lighting the silhouetted form within.

With no knife or other cutting implement, I knew it was going to be messy, but I wasn’t going to let that prevent me from giving my sister this one final honor.

So, lacking a more obvious solution, I stabbed my horn through the membrane, just as I had done to free myself.

It was not, in retrospect, one of my brighter decisions.

The chrysalis burst around my horn with a spray of fetid muck. I recoiled in surprise even before the smell hit me; the overpowering combination of rot and bile sent me staggering blindly away, eyes screwed shut. I stumbled into and scrambled over several pieces of machinery as I fled the horrible geyser of awfulness, until I finally collapsed in the back corner of the room, heaving.

The first few heaves vomited up what fluids I had ingested from my own chrysalis, but they didn’t stop there. My gut clenched again and again, my muscles burning as my stomach tried to purge itself further. I used my hooves in an attempt to wipe the vile fluid from my face, groaning between heaves, and doing my best to ignore the few tiny bits of squishy stuff that I flung away.

I could barely stand by the time my gut finally relented. I only made it a few feet, to a shallow puddle of murky water, and sank down to the ground again. Every muscle hurt, protesting even at the mild activity of splashing some of the water over my face. I’d never wanted a bath as badly in my entire life.

Once I had finally washed away enough of the mess to no longer feel completely revolted, I heaved myself up to sit back against the row of gutted machinery. I was panting, a hoof draped across my snout in an attempt to block out some of the vile scent filling the room. My body practically screamed at me. I would have gladly lain down and slept, but I knew that wasn’t an option. I likely had a long couple of days ahead of me if I was going to survive, and every moment I spent idle meant another moment closer to death.

The deflated chrysalis taunted me from across the room, the sodden and decayed husk tangled up in its dripping remains. Reluctantly, I rose back to unstable hooves, and started slowly rooting among the scattered parts. One of the egg-shaped pods in the back eventually gave me what I was looking for. Part of its curved, white outer shell had been broken away when it had been disassembled, leaving a large chunk of plastic with a jagged edge. I grabbed it in my mouth and got to work.

Cutting the final strips of the pod away to free my deceased sister was awkward with my crude blade, but it was over quickly enough. I dragged the husk over to join the others, ignoring how slimy the shell felt under my hooves, and then it was time to deal with the final pod.

I gripped the plastic shard in my hooves, giving a couple beats of my wings as I balanced on my hindlegs, and jammed it into the pod. It took a couple jabs, but the chrysalis tore open just like the last, though without me getting a faceful of its contents. I drew back and retreated to the hall, taking the opportunity to get some relatively fresh air and let my aching muscles rest while the cocoon drained.

It was even harder forcing myself to rise again, but I knew it was almost done. A little bit of crude sawing and a few moments of dragging, and I had finally gathered all of my fallen hive-mates together. My Queen lay there, still impressive even in death, her daughters clustered close around her. I suppose it was some small comfort that I didn’t recognize any of my sisters. A few looked vaguely familiar, but that was it. Perhaps I had interacted with a few of them in a professional sense, but I didn’t see any of those I had been close to. It left some tiny hope that they had survived, as I had.

Eventually, I lowered my head, pushing a little of my dwindling magic into my horn. I knew every bit of magic I spent was a little less to sustain me, but I had to do this one last thing. They deserved that much.

A green flame burst into being beneath my Queen’s chest and rapidly spread. The dry, empty husks caught quickly; the more sodden remains took longer, but soon they too succumbed to the flame. The room flickered and danced in the light of the green fire.

I rested, watching the flames transform their bodies one final time. Eventually those flames faded, guttered, and died, leaving nothing but ash in their wake.

I sighed as the light died away. There was nothing left to tie me to that place. My duty to my fallen kin fulfilled, I stood, turned, and left.

Retrieving my commandeered medical box, I set off to find my way out of the facility. The hall only went one way, the other blocked off by a door that had only opened a couple inches before wedging firmly in place. I had to hope that wasn’t the way out, as I was certain I couldn’t move it even with a full reservoir of magic.

Rooms branched off from the hall, pricking at my curiosity, but I didn’t have the time or energy to indulge more than a quick glance. Most were uninteresting. There was a cleaning closet, restrooms, and even some quarters. A couple rooms looked much like the one I had woken up in, though they were in various states of completion. One held a dozen of those egg-shaped pods I had seen before, though only half of them were assembled and hooked up. Those rooms that were not damp from leaking water were caked in dust.

Eventually the hall opened into a larger room, looking much like a lobby. The far side had partially collapsed, the mess of rock and rubble corroborating my impression that I was underground; unless this place had been built to contain a small megaspell or had secret passages riddled throughout it, there was no way an above-ground structure would have so much dead space between rooms.

I could finally make out the voice, repeating an endless loop from a speaker in the wall. It was a mare’s voice, speaking calmly, though the speaker warbled badly.

“Attention all personnel: please exit the facility and proceed to designated evacuation locations.”

Opposite of the partial cave-in were wide doors leading into a vertical shaft. The stairs that had once occupied the space had collapsed, leaving a heap of rubble partially submerged in the water below. Above, a doorway opened out into the void of the collapsed stairway.

A short flight landed me on the upper landing, a warmth spreading through my chest as my wing muscles began to join all the others crying out at my abuse. I ignored them and continued on down the hall I found myself in.

The first room I glanced in was filled with pony skeletons. At least twenty of them had been heaped up in the small storage room, laid two or three deep. I quickly continued on.

The next room held a completely different form of desolation. The room, about the same size as the one I had woken in, had been destroyed in a fire. The walls were scorched black, and the multitude of storage boxes within had been destroyed. The room would have been a treasure trove if it had been intact. One crate had held at least twenty medical boxes, now warped and ruined from the flames. Another held the remains of a couple dozen rifles. Beside that were the twisted remains of a metal box that had been torn apart from the inside; I was guessing that had been ammunition for the rifles, or maybe explosives, and I wondered if it had succumbed to the fire or been its source. Along the side wall hung six sets of armored security barding, complete with riot-style helmets, now all tattered rags, loose-hanging plates, and warped plastic.

If I had the time and the skill, I might have been able to cobble some things together from the remains, but I had neither of those things.

One box sat outside the room, and as such, had been spared the flames. I opened the lid, and was greeted with the sight of dozens of military-style rations. I quickly opened my medical box, loading it until I could barely close the lid over them. Then I tore open another ration, scarfing down the contents. My stomach, still aching from the earlier exertion, felt slightly more comfortable.

Tossing aside the wrappers, I continued on. There were more rooms, and more signs of decay. There were even a spattering of bullet holes in one of the walls, and another bore a scorched crater left by some sort of magical energy weapon.

The further I went, the more familiar it started to feel. It was vague at first, walking by a small lounge area that I felt I had seen before, in better lighting than the flickering emergency lights that dotted the facility. A look back down the hallway I was walking gave a sense of deja vu, even with the lights hanging unevenly and the water dripping from broken pipes. When I stepped out into the lobby at the end of the hall, I could swear I’d stood there before.

A faint breeze of fresh air met me, drawing me toward the glow coming in through the open door. I stepped into the doorway, and I remembered.

☢

I remembered the end of the world.

I had been flying.

I left Appleloosa that morning. I had woken to an encrypted message I had never expected to receive. It was an emergency recall, and not just any. It was the most extreme category; drop everything immediately, abandon all resources, and flee the country as fast as you possibly can. It was the kind of message we dreaded getting, the sort of warning one would get moments before the Ministry of Morale burst in.

And it was being sent out to every single Infiltrator in the world.

I fled. I didn’t call into the shipping department that I worked at to excuse my impending absence. I didn’t grab anything to take with me. I simply changed into a pegasus, ran out the back door, and flew as fast as I could. The message had given me a rendezvous point, only a couple hours away.

I was flying when a flash lit up the sky. I continued flying as more lights flashed behind me, and then off to the sides. Then another flash, but in front of me, far away enough that it had to be beyond the border of Equestria. Far off to the south, in the Badlands. There were no pony settlements there. No zebras. Only changelings.

As more flashes lit the horizon, I dove toward my destination.

☢

I stepped out into a compound that I had remembered seeing from the air. The nearby shelter had collapsed, smashing the pair of skywagons that had been parked beneath it. The guard shack, looking over the broken gate in the chain-link fence, was missing its door and windows, its paint having mostly peeled away. Only the train tracks looked more or less intact, leading away toward the main line in the valley beyond. A worn sign stood beside the guard shack, faded letters declaring this to be, “Crystal Life Technologies Experimental Site Alpha.”

Behind me, the small concrete entryway poked out of the side of a hill, just as I remembered.

I didn’t recognize the huge thing lying just beyond the fence, but judging from the way it smoked and sizzled, I was guessing it was new. It was as large as the skywagon shelter, with a smooth, slightly curved surface on one side, and ragged edges and bits of metal on the other. It looked like it had once been part of a large structure of some sort, though the deep furrow gouged through the earth suggested it had traveled a good ways from there. I couldn’t imagine the amount of force it had required to throw something so large.

Looking away from the strange debris, I was surprised at just how bleak the place looked. Sure, much of southern Equestria was fairly barren and dry, but there was plenty of life to be found if you knew where to look. I saw nothing like that, there. I saw only a few living plants, and they were brown and sickly, barely clinging to life. A few dead trees dotted nearby ridges, roots partially exposed in the crumbling, dry soil. Even the air, while fresh in comparison to the musty scent inside the facility, seemed stale and bland.

At least it was sunny and pleasantly warm, though the dark clouds that filled half the sky, dominating the horizon, threatened to change that. The more distant lands were darkened by their shadows, looking dull and oppressive. The clouds seemed particularly unruly and chaotic, as if the pegasi arranging them couldn’t be bothered to care, and had simply tossed them wherever.

I set down my box, taking advantage of a deep puddle—only slightly muddy—to finally get an acceptable pass at bathing. Being plastered with dried ichor and smelling of rot would probably not help me survive the next few days.

A couple minutes later I emerged, feeling a little better about myself.

I reclaimed my medical box, and looked around once more. I had a pretty good idea of what direction was what, if my hazy memory of this place was right. I couldn’t remember much of what happened after I arrived—mostly just my Queen, in all her glory!—but I was fairly certain I had come flying in over the skywagon shelter.

So that just left the question of what direction to go. Ultimately, I wanted to go south; if there were any sign of my hive’s survival, the hive itself would be the first place to look. Unfortunately, pony settlements were increasingly sparse the further south you traveled. Then again, who knew what had changed while I was asleep. Especially, though I still wasn’t ready to accept it, if it had been two centuries.

North would lead me deeper into Equestria. Sure, I’d seen the flashes in the distance, and I’d seen the predictions of the effects of a full megaspell exchange; major population centers would have been reduced to ash, but two hundred years was a long time to recover—though my mind momentarily rebelled at using such an absurd figure as a good thing. In any case, there would almost certainly be more ponies in that direction.

But it also took me further from my hive.

Eventually, I settled on a third option: east. Dodge City lay somewhere in that direction, and there were many smaller towns that likely would have escaped targeting. It would be as close to my hive as I could reasonably expect to find a good number of ponies.

It seemed to be an ideal compromise.

I pulled out a cable from the wreckage of a skywagon, running it through the brackets on the back of my medical box and tying it into a loop. It was difficult to do without magic, but I’d spent a lot of time imitating an earth pony. I slipped the loop around my neck, spread my wings, and took to the air.

I only managed to make the next ridge before I had to land, my wings aching horribly, but that part at least went to plan. I had no idea what was out there, so the plan was to go slow and careful. I landed just before the ridge and creeped up to peer over, instead of just flying blindly over it. It took longer, but even with the frequent pauses to scout ahead and rest my wings, I figured it would take me less than a day to get to my destination. Probably half that, even.

After a couple minutes' rest, I was ready to move on to the next rise, perhaps half a mile away across a shallow valley. My wings ached even worse as I landed again, but it was progress.

My rests grew longer with each stop, quickly seeding doubts as to my expected rate of travel.

Then, on the fifth stop, I saw movement. The railroad tracks had snaked their way through the sparse terrain, and just half a mile away to the south, it curved around a small hill. I had peeked over the ridge just in time to see the hindquarters of some quadruped disappearing around the corner, following the tracks.

I waited just long enough to make sure nobody came back, then took off again, flying low over the ground. I ignored the protests of my wings and the slowly spreading fire of overworked muscles, limping the final stretch before practically collapsing on the slope of the small hill. I crept up, slowly peering over it.

I was rewarded with the wonderful sight of ponies! Five of them, two mares and three stallions, along with a pair of cattle. They were armed, too. The ponies, that is, not the cattle, who simply carried large packs. The ponies had various small arms, and two of the stallions wore light, armored barding. They didn’t look like any military group. They seemed disorganized and irregularly equipped. Then again, maybe they were deserters? Or were they simply armed travelers? I had no way to tell.

Whatever the case, it was all secondary in importance. I had found ponies!

Now, I suppose I should make it clear: I don’t hate ponies. I know some ponies got their entire impression of changelings from Queen Chrysalis and her hive, but that would be a very incomplete picture. Me, I actually like ponies. Sure, they can be skittish and scared of things they don’t understand, and yes, they did not handle the tremendous stress of the decades-long war they found themselves in very well, but they’re basically decent beings. Few creatures held so much love, even if their hardships had made them a bit paranoid about sharing it.

My point is, my hive didn’t view ponies as being just prey, much less enemies. If anything, they’re more like… valued livestock. I know, that probably sounds horrible, but it’s the best comparison I can think of. I won’t try to spin it, to portray us as some sort of silent, benevolent protectors. We had selfish reasons for our actions. Ponies were good food, and we wanted to keep that food safe. That was our primary focus.

But when you spend much of your life living among ponies, forming friendships in order to get the love your hive needs, it’s hard to not start liking the ponies that feed you. They could never compete with the bond I shared with my sisters, much less my Queen, but I still enjoyed their company.

So finding a small group of them here offered me not only food, but the chance of some small degree of comfort.

That was getting a bit ahead of myself, though. Before I could do any of that, I had to gain their acceptance. To do that, I wanted to get a better idea of what I might be walking into.

I hung back, keeping myself as hidden as possible as I watched them. They were following the tracks, and while the cattle merely plodded on without concern, the ponies kept looking to the sky. One mare, the only unicorn in the group, had a huge smile on her face as she looked around the sky. She stumbled a few times, not watching where her hooves were going, but each time her gaze turned upwards again.

The other mare and the unarmored stallion also looked quite pleased, walking close side-by-side and quietly talking with each other. I was guessing they were a couple.

As for the other two stallions, one looked to be as unconcerned as the cattle, though he wore a pleased expression. The other stallion was the most severe of the group, his eyes scanning the horizon, looking for threats. Yet even his gaze was drawn upward on occasion, the tension in his stance fading for a few moments. Then his eyes dropped, and he returned to looking around.

I drew back just a bit to hide myself as I looked up, to see if I could find what was drawing their attention. I didn’t. There wasn’t anything up there but the sky.

I returned to observing them.

The next two hours were pretty repetitive. I watched while they walked. Once they were out of sight, I flew up to the next piece of cover to observe again. Ten minutes of watching, a minute of flying, repeat. I didn’t mind the pace. It gave my poor wings time to recover between flights. By the time they stopped, with the sky steadily darkening, I was actually feeling halfway rested.

The ponies pulled off beside the tracks, unpacking bedrolls. Finally seeing the cattle from the front as they turned, I was surprised to see that one of them had two heads, and the other, while having only one, looked badly malformed.

Soon the ponies had a small campfire going. The unarmored stallion tossed ingredients into a cooking pot while the others relaxed. The severe-looking stallion kept a wary eye out even as he lay back against a rock, a crude-looking rifle set in easy reach.

I got a bit better look at the small arsenal they carried. The other armored stallion had a similar rifle slung on his back, while the couple had holstered pistols. The unicorn mare had a very long and narrow rifle, cradled in her forelegs as she lay back. She was still smiling.

The amount of weapons on display was a little concerning. If they carried weapons, that must mean there was something dangerous out there. My first thought was zebras, but it seemed a little silly to think that the war would still be going on after so much time. Maybe it was dangerous wildlife? Sure, I’d seen hardly any signs of life, and most of that was just desert brush, but that didn’t mean nothing lived out here. There always seemed to be some horrible monster wandering into Equestria and causing drama.

With that thought, I was even more thankful to have run across ponies so soon. If there was something dangerous out there, I didn’t want to run into it on my own. I found myself glancing backwards to ensure nothing was sneaking up on me, and becoming very aware that the sunlight was quickly fading.

I would have liked to observe longer, but I figured they’d likely be going to sleep soon. Considering the vigilance the one pony displayed, I expected they would have someone keeping an eye out, making it hard to sneak up even in the dark. And, to be honest, I was thinking that I really didn’t want to wait out there, on my own, for whatever had made them so wary.

I silently retreated back down the slope, getting well out of sight. I didn’t want them to see the flash of my magic.

Once I was far enough away, hidden in a small depression beside the tracks, I called up a little bit of magic. The green flames washed over me, replacing black chitin with a smooth gray coat. I shook my head, fluffing out my new silver mane, long and sleek, and flicked my new tail. Finally, I stood up, looking over myself to ensure I had gotten the form correct. I hardly had to worry, though; it was the same form I had worn for a few years in Appleloosa.

It seemed an ideal choice. With no pegasi and only a single unicorn, an earth pony form should fit right in, and the fairly even split of sexes gave me no reason to not remain female. The cutie mark of a closed scroll was amazingly versatile; given just a bit of creativity, I could make it mean whatever I wanted. I could even use the same name: Whisper Winds.

Now, I know re-using disguises is generally a bad idea, but all things considered, I really doubted I would run into anyone who might recognize me. For that matter, I’m sure some might think that simply tacking “Winds” onto the end of my real name was a bad idea, but it’s not like anyone had a database of changeling names to check it against. As long as I didn’t re-use it for a different disguise, it was just fine, and it can be very beneficial to have a name you’re used to hearing.

With one final check of my new form, I returned to the ridge. Transformation was an easy spell, but I could feel how my hunger grew at the small expenditure. The sooner I could make some “friends”, the better.

I remember feeling a bit of irritation that my new earth pony muscles should feel just as worn out as my natural ones, but that’s just how shapeshifting goes. A proper meal would fix that.

Settling in and carefully peeking out once again, I saw nothing had changed during my short absence. They were all settled in and talking.

I braced myself, mentally going over several quick “facts” for an improvised backstory. Then I put on a pleasant smile, stood, and began to walk toward them.

They didn’t notice me, at first. The only one who seemed focused on looking outside of their small circle was facing away from me. The others were too preoccupied with their conversation. Soon I was close enough to make out what was being said.

“...But seriously, rainbows!” the smiling mare said, looking up again to the darkening sky. “I’ve never even seen a rainbow before.”

“We know,” the vigilant stallion said with a resigned tone. “You’ve only told us like fifty—”

He had turned to look squarely at the mare, which brought me into his edge of his vision. His reaction speed was impressive. He immediately bit down on the grip of his rifle as he rolled onto his hooves. I staggered to a stop, suddenly looking down a frightfully large barrel.

His voice came out harsh and menacing, his eyes narrowing at me. “Don’t you fucking move.”

It was at that moment I began to worry that I had made a terrible mistake.

Chapter Two: Ways of the Wasteland

I was not entirely a stranger to stressful situations. Infiltrating a group required intruding into a social dynamic where you couldn’t know all the variables. A mistake in judgement or inability to adapt and improvise could easily result in imprisonment or worse. The threat of the Ministry of Morale always lurked in the background of our thoughts, made worse for the fear that our failure could be a danger to our sisters. Ponies had the terrifying ability to rip memories from our very minds and turn them against us; death was preferable.

One could not be an Infiltrator if one was weak of will.

Yet I have to admit, I had no experience with the fear that comes from staring down the barrel of a gun.

The stallion practically growled around the rifle’s bit. “Who the hell are you? And what the hell are you doing here?”

The other ponies were quickly collecting themselves. The other armored stallion, a bit larger than the one questioning me, had retrieved his own rifle. He trained it on me, but he seemed much more calm; wary, but not angry.

The unicorn mare lifted her weapon as well, but didn’t level it at me. She looked uncertainly over the scene, her weapon pointed in the air above my head. It was only then that I could see the glint of a lens at the end of the long, thin weapon. She was carrying a magical energy weapon. Two, in fact, as she had a pistol of some sort tucked into a holster.

I also couldn’t help but note the PipBuck she had, though she didn’t wear it on her leg. Instead, it hung on a strap looped around her neck.

The couple—both older ponies, I noted—looked even more uncertain. The mare had her gun in her mouth, but it was still pointing at the ground. The stallion hadn’t drawn his.

I remembered then that I had been asked a question, and I was fairly certain that it was generally a good idea to oblige well-armed individuals when they ask you something. That goes doubly so when they seem so incredibly angry. Sure, I had expected a bit of wariness at my approach, but between the profanity and the amount of arms being pointed in my direction, I was concerned that I had done something terrible to offend them. “M-my name is Whisper Winds,” I said, trying to aim for just the right amount of nervous and innocent in my tone. “I saw your fire, so I wanted to come and say hello…”

That didn’t seem to impress him. “Really? You’re telling me you were just wandering around the wastes and happened to stumble across us?” He was surprisingly good at talking around his gun’s grip, and at keeping his aim steady while doing so. The combination made me think he might be an experienced combatant. That would explain the attitude, too; plenty of ponies responded poorly to the stress of combat. Some grew particularly erratic, which was of special concern when a flick of his tongue could end my life.

Fortunately, the unarmored older stallion came to my rescue. “Easy there, Sharps. She don’t exactly look like some terrifying raider, now does she?”

“Lots of dangerous ponies out there that aren’t raiders, Pops,” the pony I took to be named Sharps replied. The gun still refused to waver.

“Lots of potential customers, too, so long as you don’t go shootin’ ‘em, first,” the older stallion said as he stepped up beside Sharps. “And if you call me Pops again, you can just go findin’ your own dinner.” He delivered the last line with a disarming smile, as if to tell Sharps he was just playing. ‘Pops’ was a talker, it seemed.

Sharps lowered his gun a hair, visibly considering the other pony’s words for several seconds before finally rolling his eyes. “Fine, but I’m keeping an eye on her, all the same.” He proceeded to sit again, his rifle resting in easy reach. Contrary to his own assertion, his eyes instead swept every direction except mine, searching for other threats.

“Don’t mind him,” the older stallion said, smiling as he stepped up to me. “Sharps means well, even if he can be a bit prickly at times. My name’s Long Haul, and this lovely mare here is Silver.” He gestured to the mare that I assumed was his partner. She was pale white to his orange, and about the same age, though she wore the years quite well. She even smiled and nodded to me, once she had re-holstered her pistol.

“You’ve already met Sharps,” Long Haul continued, before motioning to the other armored stallion. “This here is Thunderhead. Don’t mind if he doesn’t say much, that’s just his way.” Thunderhead gave a small smile and nodded, a scruffy blond mane bobbing over his face. His rifle hung from its strap, set aside for the moment.

“And the lady there with the long gun is Starlight.”

With the potential conflict seemingly averted, Starlight smiled brightly at me, giving a friendly wave of a hoof. The dark-blue mare seemed a fair bit younger than the other ponies.

“Now then,” Long Haul said, turning his smile back to me. “How about you tell me what a pretty little filly like you is doing out all on her own in the middle of nowhere?”

It seemed he didn’t entirely trust my sudden appearance, either, even if he was being much nicer about it than Sharps was. That was just fine with me, though. I much preferred a confrontation of words over arms. It was time to put my improvised little backstory to work. “I’m sorry, I didn’t mean to startle you all. It’s just… I have no idea where I am, and you’re the first ponies I’ve seen.”

Sharps gave a quiet grunt, but Long Haul simply nodded. “Well, you must have come from somewhere, am I right? Figure if you know where you came from, you gotta know where you are.”

“Oh, yeah, of course. I came from a farm.” Because an isolated homestead was a perfect excuse to have absolutely no knowledge of current events. “Back that way,” I added, sweeping a hoof vaguely in the direction I came.

“Wait,” Sharps said, abandoning his scanning of the horizon to look back at me. “You’re trying to tell us you lived on an actual, working farm, and just decided… what, ‘fuck it, I’m going for a walk?’”

I winced at the harshness of that, though I appreciated the disapproving look Long Haul shot his way. “N-no, I—”

“Wait!” Starlight said, her pale-blue eyes lighting up. “You went by the tower, then, right? You saw what happened?”

Sharps groaned. “Enough about the fucking tower already!”

I quickly looked back, to see if I could catch any sign of what she was talking about. “I… don’t know. What happened to the tower?”

“It exploded,” she cheerfully replied. “With rainbows!”

With rainbows, I silently repeated in my mind. Yeah, that sounded so incredibly pony. At the same time, I hadn’t seen an explosion. She seemed likely to pump me for details about it, and I was sure to get something wrong. I had to improvise to cover my ignorance. “...I guess that might explain some things,” I slowly replied, reaching up a hoof to rub at the side of my head. “I woke up a few hours ago with a horrible headache, but I didn’t remember falling asleep. And there was this big chunk of wreckage nearby. It was the size of a house and looked like it just dropped right out of the sky.”

And, you know, some big explosion happens at the same time I woke up from a (possibly) two-hundred year nap? That seemed unlikely to be a coincidence.

“Woah,” Starlight said, surprised. “You must have been pretty close. Wait, does that mean you missed all the rainbows?”

Sharps cut in again. “How about we get back to where she walked off a damn farm to go wandering the Wasteland? I want to hear about that.”

Long Haul made a silencing gesture toward him before looking to me. “Well, how about it, miss? Seems kinda odd to walk off from someplace with food, without havin’ any idea where you’re goin’.”

Yeah, it wouldn’t, but… “My… my mother died recently. She was the one who did the farming. I-I could never figure it out. Heck, I couldn’t even grow a weed.” I swallowed, managing to tear up a bit as I put on an act of trying to stay strong. “I-I mean, I spent all my time reading all these dumb old books instead, and then she… I couldn’t…” I paused, sniffing, then took a deep, steadying breath. “If I didn’t find that box of military rations in those ruins earlier today, I might have starved. I’m not even sure how long it had been since I had something to eat.”

Long Haul nodded understandingly. “So the farm’s a bust, and you went out lookin’ to find some food?”

“Yeah,” I said. “Or better yet, some town where I could get a job. It’s just… I don’t really know anything outside the farm and what I’ve read in a bunch of old books.”

“I see,” Long Haul said, nodding, and raised a hoof to his chin. After a few seconds, he looked back to me. “Well, tell you what. We’re heading to a little town called Rust to do some trading. If—”

“Oh, hell no!” Sharps said, rising to his hooves again. “Look, Pops. You’re paying me to protect you. You’re not paying me to foalsit some tag-along, and especially not some weird filly we found in the middle of nowhere. She could be working with some fucking raiders, buddying up with traveling merchants just to see if they’re worth hitting.”

Long Haul rolled his eyes. “She don’t look like no raider to me, Sharps.”

“That’d be the point,” Sharps said. “Besides, I didn’t say she was a raider. You know they’ve been getting worse, lately, that’s why you hired me. Maybe they hit some other group, and they’re forcing her to work for them. You know, ‘do this or your mom gets it.’” He glared at me. “That what this is?”

I almost recoiled at the accusation, but I held firm; it would have likely been seen as confirmation of his suspicions. I shook my head. “No.”

Still, I was concerned about this talk of raiders. “Dangerous ponies,” Sharps had called them, and evidently the reason for such a hostile greeting. They were scared of other ponies.

How bad had things gotten?

“Sharps, look here. I get that you’re tryin’ to protect us, but this is my little caravan, and I ain’t leaving somepony out here all on her own. It ain’t my way.”

“Yeah, fine, whatever,” Sharps said. “But this still isn’t the job I signed on for. You start bringing in extra ponies like some fucking Wasteland tour group, you’re making my job harder.”

“Fair enough,” Long Haul said in a reasonable tone. “I figure most of the work is in guarding the brahmin and the group as a whole rather than any one individual, and we’re halfway to Rust already, but I’ll round up a bit. Figure an extra... five percent on your pay should be generous enough.”

I have to admit, I kind of liked the old guy. He kept his cool, negotiating a compromise to satisfy both sides of the situation. I could appreciate that.

Sharps stared back for a moment before grunting again. “Fine,” he grumbled, sitting once again.

“Um…” Starlight started to say, raising her hoof.

“Y’all too, yes,” Long Haul said, to which Starlight grinned even more.

Thunderhead just gave a soft, pleased-sounding grunt.

“Thank you,” I said to Long Haul, who turned his smile to me.

“Just doing what’s decent, miss,” he said, giving a little chuckle. “Can’t really be a good merchant if I’m turnin’ ponies away and all that. Now, I’ll be ‘spectin’ you to pitch in if we need an extra hoof and all that, and if you got anything you can spare to make up for the extra expense, I’d appreciate it, but I’m not gonna insist.”

“I’d like to,” I told him, “but I’m afraid I don’t have much to offer, other than those rations I found.” I almost didn’t want to mention them, but I figured that he was the kind of pony who would appreciate honesty. I also figured that a pony who was so charitable in giving up bits for my benefit wouldn’t deprive me of my only food, and I was right.

“Heck, it don’t feel right takin’ food from you if that’s all you got,” he said, even frowning at the thought. His smile returned a moment later. “Still, I could probably get some pretty good caps for some military rations. How ‘bout a trade, then? You trade a meal of your rations, and I give you a meal of my own cooking?” He chuckled, putting a hoof to his chest. “I promise, it can’t taste any worse than two-hundred year old army chow.”

“Ehahaha!” I blurted out, then cringed and placed a hoof over my face. It took a few moments before I was able to still the sudden rapid breathing and re-order my thoughts. I lowered my hoof, doing my best to look as if I weren’t in a very fragile mental state. “S-sorry. It’s… been a very exhausting day, both physically and mentally.” I smiled. “I think that’s a very fair offer, thank you.”

“Well… okay then,” he said, an eyebrow quirked questioningly at the outburst, but he refrained from asking. “Grab a seat by the fire and make yourself at home. Dinner should be ready soon.”

I thanked him again and carefully made my way to an open spot near the fire. He returned to his pot, pulling out a few more ingredients to add to the mix. I had hardly sat down—my limbs thanking me for the chance to rest—before Starlight leaned in. “So, you lived on a farm?”

“Yes, I did,” I said with a nod, and returned her smile as evenly as I could manage, given my shaky mental state at the time. She seemed eager and excitable, which might also mean easily swayed. A good, quick “friendship” had sounded particularly appetizing, at the moment.

Of course, it also prompted her to ask a question I would rather avoid.

“So, what was it like?”

“It was… boring,” I said, exhausting the majority of my knowledge of farming within three words. I diverted. “It’s why I spent so much time reading old books. All stuff from the war, and before.” I swallowed, trying to fight down my growing nervousness. “What he said… has it really been two hundred years?”

“Since… what, since the megaspells? Yeah, something like that.” She floated up her PipBuck, hitting a couple buttons as she looked over the screen. “Two hundred and two years,” she said, dropping it to hang from her neck again.

“Ah,” I said, suppressing a tremble as my hopes were crushed under the unyielding hooves of fact.

After a couple moments of my silence, Starlight decided to prompt me for further conversation. “So… what are you planning on doing, now?”

Her question snapped me out of my silent mourning. “I… don’t really know. Hopefully someone at Rust will have a job I can do.” I disliked that so much of my plan amounted to nothing more than improvisation.

“I’m sure you’ll find something,” she said. “I, uh… I know it can be a little hard, suddenly being on your own, but don’t worry. There’s plenty of opportunity out there.”

Sharps gave a dismissive exhale, but she didn’t seem to notice.

“Thanks,” I said, smiling again, which made Starlight smile more. “Problem is, I don’t even know what’s out there.”

“Afraid I can’t help much with that,” Starlight said. “I only hooked up with Long Haul a week ago—”

Sharps quietly muttered. “It’s only been a week?”

“—And I didn’t travel much before that. I lived in Dodge Junction, a little run-down town not far from the Dodge City ruins. Traveled between the two every now and then for scavenging runs, but that was about it.”

I was disappointed to hear that Dodge City was in ruins. Not surprised, mind you, but still disappointed. A large pony settlement would have been convenient. I forced myself to continue on, rather than slipping into silence once again; I wasn’t going to make friends by being reclusive. “Why did you leave?”

She shrugged. “Eh. It was just… well, boring.” She flashed me a smile at hitting a common element between us. “I wanted to get out there and do something. Long Haul came through on his rounds, and I thought it was perfect. I’m a great shot, and I’ve got the most awesome gun in the Wasteland. A guard job lets me earn caps, and I get to help keep ponies safe. What could be better than that?”

I noted that she referred to money as caps, rather than bits. I remember thinking it was strange to name money after headwear, but figured it was probably just a name. It wasn’t as if bits actually resembled mouth-bits, after all. And then there was the concerning repetition of the word “Wasteland”, which sounded more than a little ominous—and this coming from someling hatched in a place called the Badlands.

Despite the slight mental sidetrack, I kept up the conversation. “That sounds pretty good,” I said. It sounded pretty pony-like, too, and in a good way.

“Yeah, it’s great,” she said. “Best decision I ever made.” She reached over, picking up her long weapon. She ran a hoof gently along the long, lean frame. “Heck, I pretty much had to, after getting this. Seems a waste to only ever use her for hunting.”

I almost missed what she said. My hunger dug at my mind, almost frantic at the traces of love I could feel radiating from her. It was faint and weak, but at the time, it was the most amazing thing I had ever sensed. I fought back a fresh trembling. “That’s… very nice,” I said, struggling to keep my voice even. I was so hungry!

It was probably a good thing that Long Haul interrupted when he did, before I could do something reckless. “Alright y’all. Chow’s ready!” Bowls clattered as he served out portions of a thick vegetable stew and passed them around. When he set a bowl before me, I gripped my medical box in my hooves and popped open the lid.

Sharps jerked so hard he almost spilled his own bowl, biting down on the bit of his rifle again, and I froze, the lid only barely open. “Woah, easy. I don’t have a weapon. I was just getting a ration to trade.” While Long Haul frowned at Sharps, I slowly opened the box the rest of the way to show the contents, then gingerly reached in to slide some of the rations aside. Having done so, I picked one up, passing it to Long Haul, who gave another smile and nod to me.

Eventually, Sharps relaxed, though he didn’t entirely relent. “What are those crystals?”

“They belonged to my mother,” I said, ears drooping.

“And that… device?”

Starlight spoke up before I could, her words slurred around a mouthful of stew. “Es uh dahah-hor.” Then she coughed and sputtered a moment before managing to swallow, thumping a hoof against her chest. “Oof… yeah, data-store. They plug into PipBucks and you can read stuff off them.”

“Or any terminal with a proper slot,” I added, picking up my bowl as I started to eat. I have to admit, Long Haul could cook. “It was my mother’s, too. She left a message on it for me.”

“What was it?” Starlight asked.

“I don’t know. It’s damaged.”

“Oh,” Starlight said, her enthusiasm curling up and dying.

“I might be able to fix it,” I said, and was rewarded by a hopeful smile. “I just need to find the right software tools, and I might be able to extract the data.”

Out of the corner of my eyes, I could see Sharps leveling a suspicious look over his bowl. I took another swig of my stew—we seemed to lack spoons—and added, “We had an old terminal at the farm, dug out of some ruined building, and a bunch of books on programming. I poked around at it a lot when I wasn’t reading. Got pretty good at it, I guess, but it didn’t have the tools I’d need to fix this.”

It was a weak excuse, but I hoped it would be enough to explain my training in computer intrusion techniques. I also hoped that those techniques would be enough to help me retrieve whatever my Queen had left for me. I was already getting the impression that there were not many computer specialists left.

It worked well enough for Starlight, at least. “Cool! Hey, think my PipBuck would have what you need?”

“Maybe,” I said, my ears perking up. “Stable-Tec loads all sorts of features in those things.” I hastily added, “Or at least that old Stable-Tec manual said they did.”

She quickly gulped down the rest of her stew, setting the bowl aside, and scooted up next to me. “Just don’t break it, okay? These things are hard to replace!” Her tone was joking, but it struck me as that kind of joking one does to soften just how serious they really are about it. Considering that it was a two-hundred year old piece of advanced arcano-science computer tech, I couldn’t imagine these things were common. If there were still cities in ruin, I had some serious doubts about Equestria’s manufacturing capabilities.

She leaned in close as she shifted the PipBuck around so I could use it, and I immediately lost my train of thought. She was so close! If I could just coax out that feeling of love again, I could get a quick snack. “Thank you,” I said as I held the PipBuck in my hooves, practically leashing her in place thanks to that strap around her neck. As I began flipping through the various menus, I asked, “So, you said something about the most awesome gun in the Wasteland?”

“Oh yeah!” she said, and ducked her head to slip easily out from my imperfect leash. I mentally cursed as she moved away to retrieve her gun. “This beauty! It’s a Lancer, and it’s pretty much one-of-a-kind. It ain’t some old-world antique, either. No factories or nothing; just some old unicorn in Gemstone that made some of the best weapons in the world!”

It was quite graceful looking, for a weapon. It was twice as long as her and very narrow, with an open metal frame around a central, barrel-like core. The whole thing was painted dark brown, like wood. The only protrusions were the mouth-grip and telescopic sight near the midline of the weapon, and the bulge at the rear.

That faint sense of love flickered into being again. It taunted me, just out of reach.

“It doesn’t fire very fast,” Starlight said. “In fact, it can only fire once before I have to swap out crystals to charge. But Celestia above, one is all she needs! I could hit a galloping radhog a mile out with this thing. Hell, I’ve done it!”

“Right,” Sharps muttered.

“Hey! I have!” She shot him a glare before turning back to me. “Don’t mind Captain Grumpy-Pants over there. He’s just jealous because I’ve got the cooler gun.”

“Guns don’t need to be cool,” Sharps said in a weary tone. “They just have to do the job right.”

“Uh-huh,” Starlight said, smirking. “And how far away can you hit a pony with that hacked-together hunk of junk?”

I glanced to the gun in question. It seemed far less impressive when not staring down the muzzle. It looked as if someone had simply taken a pipe and welded on a bit, stock, and sights, stuck a magazine in the bottom of it, and hung a worn strap between the two ends. It looked crude, but functional.

Sharps shrugged, playing nonchalant, though I saw his jaw tighten. “A few hundred yards.”

“Sounds like your gun sucks.”

“And I can shoot a half-dozen ponies and make all their buddies scramble for cover in the time it takes you to get off a single shot. There’s more to a gun than range.”

“That sounds like the excuse of a pony that misses a lot.”

“Children,” Long Haul said, his voice cutting through the conversation despite remaining calm and conversational in tone. “Settle down, now. Y’all have your own merits, no need to make it a contest. Way I see it, we can use the diversity. Y’all with the automatics can put out enough firepower already. I figure having one piece with a bit more range and punch should complement that nicely, don’t you?”

Thunderhead was nodding, his sole contribution to the conversation thus far. Sharps held out for a bit before finally sighing. “Yeah, fine.”

Long Haul nodded, then looked to Starlight. “As for you, I get that you like your gun. Heck, it’s a mighty fine piece, I gotta say. I can see why you’re proud of it. But don’t you ever let me hear you insulting another pony’s piece again. Critique, sure. But insulting it, to a pony like that? One who hangs their life on their gun? Way I figure it, you insult his piece, you might as well be insultin’ his soul.”

Starlight cringed back, eyes wide and ears drooped. “I-I didn’t mean—”

“Now, now,” Long Haul said, reaching out to pat her on the shoulder. “I know you didn’t mean nothin’ by it. Least, not like that. You’re a good filly, even if you just don’t think quite so much ‘bout what you’re sayin’ at times.” He drew back, returning to his playful smile. “And maybe tone down the braggin’ a bit, okay?”

She weakly smiled back. “Okay.”

He nodded, and we all returned to eating. I took quick sips of my stew as I browsed through the PipBuck. Eventually I sighed, holding it out to Starlight. “Thanks, but it looks like it doesn’t have any of the tools I need.”

“Aww,” she said, frowning as she slipped the loop over her head. “Well, I guess it was worth a try.”

“Of course,” I said, smiling. “Thank you.”

Her smile returned. “You’re welcome.”

The food was finished quickly. Tired from a long day of walking (Or, in my case, from my body’s complete lack of endurance), the conversation died down pretty quickly. We were all ready to get some sleep. All but Sharps, who volunteered to take first watch. Apparently things were dangerous enough around there that we needed to keep an eye out even while we slept.

Bedrolls were laid out and ponies settled in for the night. Lacking any such supplies myself, I simply found a patch of dirt free of rocks and lay down, using my box as a makeshift and fairly uncomfortable pillow. I missed my chitin.

A minute later, a blanket hung in front of me. I looked up to see Thunderhead holding it by one edge. He dropped it in front of me. “Got an extra you can use.”

I smiled. “Thank you.”

“Mmmhmm,” he replied, giving a nod and a soft smile. Then he turned back to his bedroll and lay down.

I remember hoping that his barding was warm. He lied to me. He didn’t have an extra blanket.

☢

I woke to the faint light of pre-dawn and the ache of my entire body protesting my own existence.

It was better than the previous night, but it would evidently take more than a single night’s rest to recover from two centuries of inactivity. I wanted to just lay there for a while, but I couldn’t help mentally grumbling that I had spent far too long doing nothing for the past two hundred years, thank you very much.

I had apparently moved past denying reality and on to being bitter about it.

Still, the irritation gave me enough motivation to finally push aside my borrowed blanket and get up.

Everypony was still asleep, except Silver, who was lying back against the side of one of the cattle a short distance away—the single-headed one, it turned out. She looked over as I rose, giving a silent nod that I returned.

I took the edge of the blanket in my teeth, dragging it back over to Thunderhead. The pre-dawn morning was chilly, but it didn’t seem to be bothering him any. He was sprawled out on his back, legs askew. Still, I pulled the blanket over him. He mumbled something in his sleep, curling up and immediately entangling himself in the blanket’s folds.

I slipped away from the sleeping ponies, making my way over to where Silver sat.

She smiled as I approached, her voice just above a whisper. “He likes you.”

“What?” I said, wincing as my voice came out louder than I meant. Quieting down, and casting a glance back to who I suspected she meant, I asked, “Who, Thunderhead?”

“Mmmhmm,” she said with a nod.

“I thought he was just being nice,” I said. I hadn’t sensed any particular affection from him. Then again, I wouldn’t have off of such a brief encounter. There was quite a difference between liking someone based off a first impression and forming the kind of close connection that would produce affection I could feed on. “You sure?”

“Oh yeah,” she said, laughing softly. “I think he said more to you last night than he has since leaving Mareford. Ain’t like he’s shy or nothin’, he just doesn’t seem to have much use for words. He’s about as nice as they come, though.”

I smiled as I glanced over to him again. He did seem like a pretty nice pony, from the little bit I’d seen of him. If he really did like me, I could culture a nice friendship out of it. Maybe even something more.

She chuckled softly at my smile, then patted the ground. “Go on, take a seat. Probably be a little bit before everypony’s up, anyway. Wouldn’t mind the company.”

I accepted her offer and sat, though I groaned softly as I did so. My legs felt rubbery. Silver looked concerned. “I’m just feeling pretty sore from yesterday,” I said. “I’m not used to traveling. I just hope I can keep up with everypony.”

“Well, we tend to take regular breaks for the brahmin to graze,” she said, gently placing a hoof on the head of what was apparently called a brahmin, now, because ‘cattle’ was so two centuries ago. “And heck, if you’re feeling like you need more of a break, you can probably take a load off and ride for a while. Old Chuck here could use the company.”

I had to ask. “Chuck?”

“Yep,” she said, cracking a smile. “Odd name, I know. It’s what Moorice named him; I think it was some sort of joke. He was Chuck’s better half.”

Silver nodded to the other side of Chuck, at the scarred tissue along one side of his off-center neck. “Moorice got a face-full of barbs from some mutated fly… thing. Poor thing got a nasty infection from the wounds, just started rotting him away from the inside. When he passed, we amputated the head. Old Chuck here may not have had much upstairs, but he’s a tough one. Pulled through strong as ever.” She smiled softly, giving him an affectionate rub between the ears. “He’s kind of become our good-luck charm, I guess.”

That was both somewhat charming and horrifically morbid. I hardly noted it, though. I was too preoccupied by the glorious sensation of love! Silver truly cared for Chuck. It wasn’t the powerful love of a romantic relationship, or even the affection of a close friendship. It was more like the gentle love of a favorite pet; not nearly as filling, but it would suffice. I carefully slid in closer as she was distracted by the brahmin, hoping to pretend I was merely sitting closer to keep our conversation quiet.

I nearly trembled as I drew in the emotion. I couldn’t draw it in very fast without getting uncomfortably close, but that was just fine with me; I wanted to be slow and gentle, so as to not alarm her. Even that little trickle of love was spectacular to my starved mind.

Sadly, it faded before I could get more than a little nibble, but I was content. I hadn’t even drawn enough for a half a day’s survival, but I would have many more opportunities. A little here, a little there, and I would be just fine. It just required a little bit of patience.

I covered for my closeness by reaching out to lightly run a hoof along Chuck’s side. Silver smiled softly at that.

“Well I’ll be,” came Long Haul’s quiet voice, as he stepped quietly over to us. “Somepony who gets up before I do. Now that’s a pleasant change.”

Silver broke into a wide grin. “You must be getting old,” she teased, rising up to meet him. “Sleeping in so late, letting this wonderful day waste away while you’re lazing about in bed.” It was still mostly dark, and the dark clouds that filled most of the sky, scattered about in the most chaotic fashion, were anything but wonderful. At least it was still clear above us.

He chuckled as they both leaned in, nuzzling fondly. I’m normally loath to use insect metaphors, but I have to admit, the one about a moth being drawn to flame seemed particularly apt at that moment, especially when it would probably end just as poorly if I followed the instinct that welled up in me. The love I felt between them was intoxicating!

Eventually they parted, starting on morning routines. A fire was lit, and the cooking pot came out again. Meanwhile, faint wisps of love still lingered between them. I considered moving to be between them, hoping to catch a little of that love between them. Sure, it would be inefficient, drawing only a tiny fraction of it, but even a little bit would have been wonderful. Despite that, I stayed put. A little patience would get me all I needed, without needing to act strange and drawing attention to myself.

Sadly, Long Haul turned down my offer to help with breakfast, shooting down my best excuse to be close to him. “It’s a bit too simple to need much help with,” he said, despite the appreciative smile. I’d have to wait just a little longer for my opportunity.

It wasn’t long before the scent of cooking vegetables reached the noses of the sleeping ponies, and within minutes they had all woken. Food and water was passed around, bedrolls and blankets were packed, and a few discreet trips were made to an unfortunate dead bush a short distance away.

“It’s still clear,” Starlight said, in quiet wonderment, her eyes to the sky. Sure enough, the ring of clear sky still hung over us, the last few stars twinkling in the growing light. I pondered her reaction.

“Better dress warm, all the same,” Sharps noted, tugging on the straps of his barding. “Those are some dark clouds we’re heading towards. I wouldn’t be surprised if it starts raining soon.”

The statement seemed immediately strange to me. I spent enough time in Equestria to be used to weather happening on a precise schedule. There was never any question about whether it would rain or not on a certain day, unless some weather pony screwed up the schedule. Something seemed off to me, but I certainly wasn’t going to speak up and highlight my own ignorance. Even as a recluse on an isolated farmstead, it would be hard to explain a misconception about the weather. I’d simply have to roll with it.

Starlight tore her gaze away from the sky to root around in her small saddlebags. She eventually pulled out a light jacket and put it on.

Sharps, who had supplemented his thick barding with a large poncho, simply stared at her for several seconds before giving a soft snort, shaking his head, and turning back to his packs.

He made no comment about my attire, as nonexistent as it was. I was tempted to ask Thunderhead if I could borrow that blanket again, or a spare jacket, or anything in case it did rain. When I glanced his way, his look immediately changed my mind. I got the impression he was considering the exact same thing. I didn’t need to ask. If it did start to rain, it would spur things on quite well if he were to “come to my rescue”.

Soon the brahmin were up and ready to go, with Long Haul giving a few final tugs on the straps holding the bulging packs on. “Okay,” he said, glancing back to us. “Looks like we’re all set, and if we keep up the pace, we should make Rust by tomorrow night. Let’s get this show on the road.”

☢

The tiny bit of love I had pilfered was just enough to keep me going. It pushed that ache in my limbs to the background. They were still sore, and still eager for some rest, but I was able to persevere.

That tiny bit of love probably saved my life.

By mid-day, we had passed under the edge of the cloud cover, following the train tracks as they wound through the broken, barren terrain. The dark clouds above continued to slowly churn and drift. They bunched up in places, stretching thin in others. Every now and then a thin crack would form, a spear of sunlight lancing through the gray dimness to light some small, distant piece of land before inevitably fading away once again.

There were no pegasi, I noted. It was as if the clouds were left to float aimlessly on their own. Was the weather really left entirely uncontrolled here? Sure, we were toward the edge of Equestria, but I thought it strange.

Contemplating the strange weather led me to an epiphany: I knew where I had seen that strange piece of debris near the C.L.T. facility. The curved white surface was just like those weather-control towers the Ministry of Awesome had been working on, and would explain what Starlight meant by a “tower” exploding. Had they actually gotten those online?

The tower’s destruction made sense of what I was seeing above. If they’d been using it to keep the weather under control, its loss would explain why things had ended up in chaos up above.

And yes, my hive knew what those towers were all about. They built almost 50 cloud-high spires at tremendous expense. Every single ministry was involved in them, in some part. It was the MAw’s greatest secret. Of course we knew.

I was contemplating what—if anything—that information might mean for my situation when I was interrupted by a shockingly loud SnapSnapSnap!

The three sharp sounds were so close together that they were almost one. A couple puffs of dirt kicked up beside Thunderhead, who was walking just in front of me, and the stallion toppled forward. His chin and chest hit the dirt, hindquarters lifting up with his momentum before flopping to the side.

Sharps lunged forward past me, shouting. “Ambush right!” He bit down on the grip of his rifle, and everything became explosions.

I lurched back a step, ears pinning back against an assault of sound so loud I could feel it in my chest. I barely noticed the dark-blue blur of Starlight throwing herself off the path and into a narrow depression beside the tracks, and I followed, wincing as something hot smacked me on the cheek.

I collapsed on my side beside Starlight, covering my head with my forehooves. Sharp’s rifle continued to fire in an unbroken string, each shot brutally loud.

Then the assault of sound ended. I pried a hoof away from my face to see Sharps reach up to his rifle, and the magazine fell away, spent. He shot a look over at us and shouted, his voice oddly small and distant. “Fucking shoot!”

Starlight yelped something as she scrambled up, her “Lancer” swinging around while Sharps pulled a fresh magazine from a pouch at his side. Another sharp snap sounded, and Starlight yelped again, ducking down below the edge of the depression once again. Sharps merely flinched, but didn’t stop. He slammed the magazine into the bottom of the weapon, pulled back the handle protruding from the weapon’s side, and fired again.

This time I put my hooves over my ears, muffling the powerful sound. Sharps paced his shots, firing short bursts as he advanced up onto the rise we were hiding behind. Starlight, as if encouraged by his firing, poked up again. Another pair of sharp cracks made her flinch, but she stayed up.

The brahmin we had been beside—the one with both heads—staggered along the far side of the tracks, stumbled, and collapsed. Thunderhead hadn’t moved at all, lying still atop the tracks.

A strange, hissing snap sounded, and Starlight ducked down again. “Shit!” she cried out as her magic practically tore open the chamber at the rear of her rifle. She pulled out a dull red crystal, quickly replacing it with a glowing one, and sealed it up again. Then she rose up once more.

The flicker of flame caught my attention. I watched in stunned fascination as a pinwheel of fire silently arced through the air, fixed to the neck of a bottle. It came down to shatter against Chuck’s side, fire bursting forth and flowing across Long Haul and Silver.

Several sharp snaps made me wince, and dirt sprayed over me as Sharps fell back into the depression with a mangled curse, limbs flailing. Starlight shrieked something, wavering, but resumed her aim, snapping off another shot. Then she ducked down, reloading again.

Sharps had managed to haul himself into a sitting position, though his left foreleg was held close to his side, injured. He fumbled for a moment to get a good grip on the bit of his rifle and brought it up again, emptying the rest of the magazine in a brief string of hammering shots. One of his casings landed on my side; I yelped at the searing pain, kicking it away.

I couldn’t see Long Haul and Silver. The depression they had been in was smokey and smoldering. I hoped they had gotten out. Across the tracks, Chuck was lowing and galloping awkwardly away, his packs burning.

Only having one good foreleg slowed Sharps’s reload. He had just slammed a new magazine home when there was a soft thunk, and a spear appeared, buried in his neck so deeply that the tip jutted out of his back.

The stallion’s eyes went wide, his rifle falling to the ground. I stared in horror.

For some reason, the thought my mind decided to focus on was: shouldn’t there be more blood?

I looked to Starlight in time to see her fire off another shot, another whining hiss and snap sounding as her weapon loosed a red beam of light, searing a line in my vision. As she reloaded, I realized that she was the only one still in the fight. The only one between me and whoever was out there, trying to kill us all!

My eyes fell to Sharps’s rifle. I lunged forward, grabbing the bit in my teeth, and ignoring the grit of dirt as I scrambled back into cover. Taking just a moment to steady myself, I took a deep breath, then raised up, leveled the rifle up the rocky slope in the same direction Sharps had been firing—I didn’t actually see anypony at the moment—and tongued the trigger.

Nothing happened. There wasn’t even a click.

With a distressed whimper, I dropped back down behind cover, dropping the rifle into my hooves. It should work. I’d just seen Sharps reload it before he went down. I played back watching him load the first time. I pushed on the magazine to make sure it was in all the way, and then grabbed the handle on the side, pulling it back. The breach opened, and the handle locked back. I pushed and jiggled it, trying to get it to shut and chamber a round, but it wouldn’t move.

I heard a distant yell, and in desperation, I lifted the rifle to try again, hoping the weapon was working as intended. As I rose up, I saw the movement of a pony coming down the slope. I don’t remember any details about them in that frantic moment. I think it was a mare, and she might have had something in her mouth. She must have seen me rising up, as she turned and dove for a large rock. I tongued the trigger again, and the rifle roared.

It also slammed back against me, nearly pulling free of my mouth and bashing the stock against my shoulder and neck. I have no idea where my shots went. Honestly, I was probably lucky I didn’t hit Starlight.

I slumped back, getting a good grip on the bit again. When I rose up this time, I cinched the semicircular base of the stock snug against my shoulder and the base of my neck. I squeezed the trigger again, and the thundering crack of the shot drove the rifle squarely into my body, but this time, I kept it under control. A spattering of dirt puffs kicked up all around the rock the pony had hidden behind, even knocking off a few shards of stone.

Another searing flash of light dazzled my vision, and I dropped back down again, blinking. A glance back showed that Sharps had pulled free the spear—there’s blood, now, I noted—and had collapsed on his side. He was weakly fumbling at a pouch on his chest. I, however, had focused on another pouch, the one that held more magazines for his rifle. I felt I was going to need it, very soon.

I scrambled out again, snatching the pouch and pulling against its strap. Sharps even relented in his own efforts, lifting his foreleg to let me pull the strap free before returning to his fumbling.

I threw the strap around my neck, the pouch thumping against my medical box. I could hear more yelling. Lots of yelling.

I took one look back to the fallen brahmin, just past the tracks. I didn’t even think before I was on my hooves, running as fast as my weary legs could carry me. I dove over the fallen animal a moment before several sharp snaps sounded, all around me.

After only a moment to take a breath, I rose up, just barely exposing my head as I laid the barrel of the rifle across one of the brahmin’s packs, sighted in on a cloud of dust drifting down the slope, and fired a long burst. Dirt kicked up all around the slope, leaving the ridge in a dusty haze.

The rifle lurched with the final shot, the bolt slamming shut. I dropped behind the brahmin, releasing the bit and quickly pulling back on the handle once again. When it locked back, I saw that there were no more bullets in the magazine. This was followed by a few frantic seconds as I scrambled to find the release, which ended up being a small lever just behind the magazine. Pulling the empty magazine free, I fished out a new one—I didn’t even see how many I had, just that there were more—and fumbled with it for a moment before finally sliding it into place.

I took up my firing position again, only to see Starlight, her Lancer’s chamber sitting open and spent as a pony leaped over the edge of the depression she lay in. Of all the odd bits and pieces that adorned the pony, the only thing that caught my eye was the machete clenched in her teeth.

I swung around the rifle, but it was too late. The mare came down on Starlight, the blade slicing at her head.

There was a flash of sparks as Starlight instinctively raised her rifle to protect herself, the other mare’s blade cutting into the weapon. Then the other pony crashed down into her, sending them into a tumble, obscured by the slight rise of the train tracks.

Movement on the slope caught my attention again. At least two more ponies were running toward us, one of which held a spear in his teeth, with several more on his back. I sighted in on him and tongued the trigger, blasting out several shots. Both ponies dropped behind cover once again.

A rapid series of sharp discharges sounded from just across the tracks, and Starlight scrambled back, her pistol floating just in front of her, firing frantically. Blue lines of light struck out. With the rise of the tracks obscuring my sight, all I could see of the other pony was a leg that spasmed up into view, which promptly burned away into a cloud of blue particles. Starlight’s pistol jerked several more times, no longer firing.

I caught a glimpse of movement up on the slope above, and immediately squeezed off another burst; Starlight winced and dropped behind cover again. Sharps, I noted, was no longer moving.

Letting go of the bit, I shouted out. “Starlight! We have to go!”

Now, I’m sure some of you wonder why I didn’t just leave her. After all, I had just met these ponies the previous evening. They were nothing more than food to me, at the time. Heck, I could drop my disguise and fly off.

I’d like to say that it was a carefully measured decision of logic. I was in the middle of nowhere, more than a day’s travel on hoof from the nearest settlement, dangerously low on love, and physically exhausted. If Rust didn’t lie on the tracks we’d been traveling along, I might completely miss it, assuming I could even make it there. I needed guidance, I needed assistance, and I needed food; Starlight could give me all of those.

But that wasn’t my reason. The simple fact is, I didn’t even think of it.

I was so preoccupied with the hellish chaos all around me that I wasn’t thinking in terms of logic and reason. I was lost to emotional response. Two of them, actually.

The first, terrified of the terrible and abrupt violence of the previous minute, was screaming at me to run away.

The second, possessive and protective, insisted that these ponies were mine.

I suppose it was that “valued livestock” thing I mentioned earlier. Yes, I had just met them, and yes, I was probably going to part ways with them upon arriving in civilization, but that would be done on my terms. These ponies had value to me. I liked these ponies. I didn’t like seeing ponies get hurt, much less when they were ponies I liked. These other ponies were hurting my ponies. They were killing my ponies. They were taking from me, and I didn’t like it. I hated it. I was terrified of it.

The emotions combined, dragging me along to flee with any ponies I could salvage.

Starlight stared at me with wide eyes, and I beckoned to her. She glanced over to Sharps, trembling for a moment before snatching up her bent rifle and galloping toward me.

I saw the puff of dust near the top of the ridge an instant before another snap hammered at my ears, and tongued the trigger to send another burst his way. Dirt kicked up, clustered loosely around where the shot had come from.

Starlight collapsed at my side, panting and trembling, but intact.

I cast a quick glance backwards, hoping the glimpse I had caught during my dive across the brahmin had been correct. It was; just ten yards away was a shallow gully, just deep enough to conceal a galloping pony. I pointed a hoof, shouting at the top of my lungs over the muffled buzz in my ears. “Go!”

Then I turned back and fired again. The rifle blared twice more and fell silent, its magazine spent.

I dropped down and turned, to find Starlight still laying beside me. “Go!” I repeated, and hooked a leg under her shoulder to haul her up. I half-dragged her along until she finally got the idea and got her hooves under her, and together we dove for the gully.

A burst of snaps sounded all around me, puffs of dust kicking up from the far side of the gully. Then we fell, collapsing into the dried streambed.

I panted, my heart hammering in my ears, clear even past the buzzing. Starlight was staring straight up, eyes wide and glistening as she trembled. She suddenly blurted out, “Fuck!”

Keep going, my mind insisted, and I obeyed. I hauled myself up despite my fatigue. “Are you okay?” I asked as I kicked out the spent magazine. Retrieving a fresh one—the second from last—I slammed it home.

“I… y-yeah,” she stammered, patting herself with her hooves a couple times. “I-I’m okay. I’m okay.” She pushed herself up, shaking. “Uh… you?”

“I don’t think I’m injured,” I replied, my words sounding mushy to my ears. I pulled back the rifle’s handle, gripped the bit again, and peeked over the edge of the gully.

More shots sounded, but they were quieter; distant, echoing pops, not the brutally sharp snaps and cracks from before. I saw a few ponies, clad in patchy, cobbled-together barding. They were galloping, but not toward us. Instead, they were chasing after the flaming, lumbering bulk of Chuck.

I dropped back, silently hoping that he would give them a good, long chase. “We’ve got to run,” I said, pointing away from where the other ponies were headed. “Down the gully. Go.”

Starlight struggled to her hooves, looking dazed for a moment as my words processed. “R-right,” she said, staggering for a few moments before working up to a canter. I could see tears trickling down her cheek.

Slowly, the rush of adrenaline faded. The jittery tremble stilled, and a tremendous fatigue crashed down on me. After only a couple minutes, our canter slowed to a trot, then a walk. Not much later, I started to stumble, unable to lift my hooves enough to clear the occasional bump in the dirt.. We’d just left the gully when I fell. Starlight cried out, stumbling back to me. “W-Whisper! C-come on!”

I tried to push myself up. If not for Starlight’s magic, I wouldn’t have been able to. I panted. I couldn’t even hold my head up as I staggered another step.

“Come on, Whisper!” she cried out, voice wavering as more tears flowed. “W-we have to keep going!”

“I… I can’t,” I weakly murmured, staggering again. Only her magic kept me from falling. My body, atrophied by centuries of inactivity and pushed to the extremes by adrenaline, was failing.

“No,” she whimpered, coming close against my side. “No, no, no! Were you hit?”

I swallowed, shaking my head. My leg tried to give out, and I ended up leaning heavily against Starlight’s side. “No… muscles… giving out…”

She pulled with her magic, staggering forward. Even as light as I was, it seemed a tremendous strain on her. I pressed on, my abused body feeling numb and heavy and sick.

I pushed away, stumbling another step before collapsing to the ground and vomiting. For the second time in as many days, I lay there, gut burning as I retched. Starlight dropped to my side, crying as she tugged with her magic “Whisper! Whisper, come on, w-we can’t stop. They… they’ll…”

I coughed and spit. Somehow, with the help of her magic lifting me, I got my hooves under me. I almost fell as my stomach clenched again, sending agonizing stabs through my abdomen, and I spit up a bit of bile. “Please,” Starlight cried. “Please, come on! Please... don’t…”

I wavered as I made one more step. I was suddenly completely preoccupied by the fact that I had dropped the rifle somewhere. I almost fell when I looked back, and Starlight gave another tug with her magic, her shoulder pressing firmly against my side. I felt a dull sense of relief when I noticed the rifle floating along beside her.

Then I stumbled again, almost knocking Starlight down.

My words came out slurred and muffled. “I… can’t…”

Starlight shuddered with a quiet sob. “Please.”

“...Hide,” I mumbled. “There.”

She turned to where I was looking; a few large rocks just a hundred yards away, a few of many that dotted the landscape, and nestled in the crook of a tiny ravine. It was small and inconspicuous, and a pony would have to walk right on top of us to find us hiding there.

She pulled with her magic, pressing her shoulder against my side, and we slowly limped our way over.

We collapsed in exhaustion in the tiny hiding place, sprawling haphazardly against each other. For a few moments, we lay there, trembling and panting with exhaustion. My body was done. Then Starlight’s breathing hitched, she shuddered, and finally rolled against me, hooves grabbing at me as she cried into my chest. I forced a barely-responsive foreleg to lift up and drape across her shoulder as she clung tight, muffling her anguish with my body. I caught myself starting to sob, and struggled to keep myself under control. Tears flowed down my cheek as I clung weakly to her.

I didn’t understand what had just happened. It wasn’t just chaotic; it was wrong. This wasn’t some minor scuffle, or even a battle. It was ponies—ponies!—ambushing other ponies, for… for what? The merchant’s wares?

I didn’t understand, and that, more than anything else, terrified me. I had come horrifyingly close to dying, and I didn’t understand why. If I didn’t understand why, I couldn’t take action to avoid it. If I didn’t understand why, I was helpless against whatever cause had nearly killed me. All my life, all my training, all my experience, relied on understanding how ponies thought, but I could not understand the motivation for what had just happened.

If I was going to survive for long, I was going to need to learn, and learn fast.

But that was long-term.

Short-term, I was in bad shape, too. I was beyond exhaustion. Everything hurt. I could hardly lift a hoof to defend myself. My ears were filled with a strange buzzing, and everything felt lopsided. I was still terribly low on magic and lost in the middle of a barren and empty land.

The one thing I did have, however, was a pony.

I didn’t want to hurt her.

I kept a hoof gently on the back of her shoulder as I focused a little bit of magic. Crying into my chest, she didn’t notice the flash of green above as a horn sprouted from my forehead.

I didn’t want to hurt her, so I took my time crafting the spell that followed. When I released the bolt, Starlight didn’t jerk at all. She just slowly went slack, relaxing against me as she lost consciousness.

My own vision wavered, my head growing even heavier as everything skewed and wobbled. The tiny effort I had given was exhausting, and for a moment I feared I would fall unconscious before I could act, but I clung on.

Then I pulled. This wasn’t the gentle, subtle feeding that comes from drawing on the love a pony feels toward something. Those feelings are at the front of their mind, drawing the energy out toward the object of their affection and leaving it exposed and vulnerable, easy to feast upon.

No, this was reaching deep inside of her, into the depths of her mind, and tearing out the love within.

She tensed, giving a little gasp and fidgeting in her sleep. Moments later she gave a weak, strangled cry, her legs kicking out.

I fed, and as the strength flowed into me, I tightened my grip. I held her head tight against my chest, muffling the whimpers and cries of anguish, her limbs weakly struggling against me. I could only imagine the horrible dreams that flooded her mind as I ripped the love and happiness from her.

I didn’t want to hurt her, but I did.

Chapter Five: Friendly Faces

The Enclave.

For once, I was not the only one lacking in knowledge. Starlight hadn’t heard that name before, nor did she know anything about what the pegasi had been up to since the war. We both had much to learn as Dusty gave us what details he knew.

After seeing the devastation that had befallen the land, it was hard to believe that there was an entire nation up in the clouds, thriving so far as to still field mighty warships like the one we had seen—dozens of them, according to Dusty, and even several of the tremendous Thunderheads!

I won’t lie; I was tempted to abandon the wasteland of mud and misery to fly up to those clouds. It would be far easier to find an abundance of food in a safe, comfortable city in the sky than it would down here, surrounded by raiders and the constant struggle to survive. Still, I had reasons to resist that temptation.

If I were to find any sign of my hive, it would be down here, on the ground. Yes, if my hive still existed, I figured they would probably have Infiltrators up in the clouds, feeding on the ponies that lived up there. That didn’t help me. Infiltrators are intentionally hard to find, and even if I did somehow find one, there was a good chance she would not be a friendly Infiltrator. If my hive survived, others might have survived as well, and we did not always get along. My path might eventually lead me up above the clouds, but for now it remained below them.

Of course, I could go up there to find food and safety—although the destruction of the Raptor made me question the latter—and return down to the ground once I was more prepared. That would mean leaving Starlight behind, however. If it came down to her or my hive, there was no contest, but between my own comfort and having both a source of food and a potential ally on the ground? That was a much more difficult quandary, but I had the feeling that keeping Starlight would be more beneficial to my mission.

Which was convenient, seeing as I’d feel a little bad about just abandoning her. I liked her.

But even if I decided to go above the clouds—not dying to raiders would be even more beneficial to my mission!—there was still one thing that troubled me: the Grand Pegasus Enclave was supposedly a thriving nation, and yet the ponies down on the ground lived in horrific conditions. How much love and safety could I find in a nation that would turn a blind eye to the suffering of their fellow ponies?

Dusty was particularly blunt in his evaluation.

“They’re monsters,” he had said, taking a long drag on his cigarette. “They’re worse than the raiders. The Enclave, they make every single pony in the Equestrian Wasteland suffer because they just don’t give a shit about us. It’d make their cushy little lives a little less luxurious if they had to share with us on the ground. So instead, they just roll up the sky so they don’t even have to look at us. They stole the fucking sun and moon from us!”

He took another drag of his cigarette, scowling.

Starlight’s voice was small. “I saw the sky.”

Dusty’s scowl disappeared as he looked her way. She was looking off into the darkness. “One of those towers exploded,” she said. “This wave of rainbows tore open the clouds, and… and I saw the sun. I’d never seen the sun before.” She smiled, almost dreamily. “And that night, I saw the moon.”

A small smile crept up behind Dusty’s cigarette, and he gave a quiet, sympathetic nod. “I wish I could have seen that.”

“You probably still can,” Starlight said, her smile holding even as she addressed Dusty. “The tower’s gone, and I don’t think the clouds are coming back. It’s just open sky, for miles.”

“May have to make my way over there after we’re done,” he said. His smile slipped away, replaced by a more thoughtful look. “Wonder if that’s what kicked the Enclave into making a move.”

When he was met by a questioning look from Starlight, he gave a dry, humorless laugh. “I’m guessing you don’t get the radio this far south if you ain’t heard of the Enclave. Yeah, they finally decided they’re going to get involved. Came down ‘bout a week or two ago. Said they were here to ‘save us’.” He snorted, flicking the butt of his cigarette away; the glowing ember spun off into the darkness. “So far, their version of ‘saving us’ has been to wipe out every single settlement they can get their hooves on. Fucking butchers, the lot of them.”

Starlight slumped, her ears drooping. “Oh…”

While they were having their little exchange, I listened in horrified silence. It was just… too much. Raiders attacking ponies to steal food at least made some sort of sick, twisted sense, even if it was hard to wrap my mind around. But a nation, living in relative comfort, coming down to the Wasteland and slaughtering the ponies they should be helping? “...How have ponies become so horrible to each other?”

Dusty looked at me. I expected a look of scorn for my naivety. Instead, I saw only sadness in his eyes. The gaze held for just a moment before he looked away, looking much more tired than he had moments earlier. “Wish I knew.”

On that cheery note, we turned in for the night.

Dusty took first watch, leaving Starlight and myself to sleep. It was then that we realized we still had only a single bedroll and blanket between the two of us. While there had been no hesitation before, when the shared bedding was a matter of survival, Dusty’s presence seemed to change the context of the situation for Starlight. I would have found some other course, to spare her the embarrassment of having our situation potentially misinterpreted, but I couldn’t see any way of doing so without one of us spending the night without a blanket.

Well, I could ask to use Dusty’s bedding while he wasn’t using it, but that seemed an entirely different sort of awkward. After working to prove ourselves competent traveling companions, it seemed counterproductive to announce that we had failed to acquire sufficient bedding for the two of us.

Fortunately, despite the blush she was trying to hide, Starlight was still gracious enough to raise the edge of the blanket toward me in a silent offer. I accepted, settling into the slightly too-small bed to sleep as best I could beside the fuzzy ball of awkwardness lying beside me.

☢

We arrived at Gemstone around mid-day, despite Starlight’s attempts to divert us. “Think of all the salvage!” had been the core of her argument, combined with eager gestures made in the direction we had seen the Raptor falling.

“Think of all the Enclave,” had been Dusty’s retort. “That wreck is going to be crawling. Even if it’s not the Enclave or whoever—or whatever—shot it down, every scavenger and raider within fifty miles is going to be saying the same thing you are. They’re all going to go swarming all over it like vultures, and there’s going to be blood.”

“But we could be rich!” Starlight said. “Salvage like that, we’d just need to hold onto it, and we’d be set for life!”

“Sure we would,” Dusty replied. “‘Specially since that ‘life’ would probably be just a few hours.”

“Hey, we can fight!”

“I don’t care if you’re the best damn soldiers in the world,” he said, scowling. “Three ponies ain’t holding against what’s coming down on that, and we don’t want to be anywhere near it when it does.”

Starlight steamed over that for most of the trip, but she did finally relent. The argument that finally seemed to sway her was that, if everypony around was swarming toward the wreck of the Cumulonimbus, there would be fewer ponies trying to make their way to Dusty’s claim. It wasn’t a particularly persuasive argument, as I could see it giving more reason why another detour wouldn’t hurt us, but she seemed to accept it.

In more pleasant and personal news, the bandages had worked their magic, and my scrapes had closed up. There was no sign of infection, though my chest still itched if I thought too much on the subject. At least I was free of the bandages. I like to make a good first impression, when possible.

Gemstone was nestled in a particularly rough and rocky patch of land, rising up into a string of jagged hills. An old rail line ran up a shallow slope to the base of what used to be another mining camp. Just beyond that, where the tall, jagged rocks formed a small valley, a wall of wood and steel formed the border of the town.

While still small, the initial impression the town of Gemstone gave was significantly greater than the one Rust had given. Mostly, that was from their fortifications; while the wall was nothing new or impressive, what was set atop it certainly was. Having considered Rust’s heavy machine-gun to be potential overkill, I was at a bit of a loss at how to categorize Gemstone’s defenses. The wall was topped by three emplaced magical energy weapons! The one in the middle appeared to be a multi-barrel plasma cannon, of the type one might have seen mounted to a sky-tank, and looking little worse for wear after so many years. The others I did not recognize, looking more hacked-together; they were crude-looking devices of tubes and wires built around large crystals, but I couldn’t say they looked any less dangerous to someone who found themselves in their sights.

Several ponies were idling atop the wall, with another visible in a tall tower set behind it. The pony in the tower was the first to see us as we approached the walls. She walked to the edge of her platform, calmly ringing a bell that hung there. It didn’t have the sound of an alarm, lacking any sense of frantic urgency. It was less “look out!” and more “hey, come look at this.”

The ponies atop the wall milled about, joined by a few more. Each of the three mighty weapons had a pony beside it, with two more ponies posted between them, though they all seemed quite relaxed. Given the amount of firepower they had at hoof, I could hardly blame them.

The earth pony mare by the plasma cannon was leaning casually against her weapon, eyeing us as we drew nearer. She eventually looked back, stomping a hoof and calling out. “Open up!”

With a few dull thumps, the gate slowly swung open. “Come on in,” the mare called out, sounding quite congenial despite resting against a giant machine of magical death.

We passed through the gate, into a small town built among the remnants of the old mining structures. Despite the somewhat run-down and pieced-together appearance, the town was refreshingly colorful after our stay in Rust. Somepony had discovered the invention of paint, and applied various colors to different buildings. Strings of lights and a few colorful signs accented the town. Past the mildly decrepit construction and the lingering mud, they gave Gemstone a true appearance of civilization.

And behind all of that, it simply felt like a pony town.

The mare who had called out to us hopped down from the wall to join us, landing heavily before offering a pleasant smile. “Welcome to Gemstone. So what brings you three ‘round our way?”

Her heavy barding suggested that she was a guard, possibly Gemstone’s equivalent of Steel Shot, and the way she shook off the drop spoke well of her physical condition. That was put into strange contrast by her short but elegant purple mane and pristine white coat, both of which looked expertly cared for. She also wore a weapon strapped across her back, a rifle-shaped device made of polished metal and neatly bound wires, with a purple crystal at its core. It was a magical energy weapon, for sure, but not any pre-war design I was familiar with.

In fact, as I looked around, I saw that almost every pony in sight had a similar weapon. They were of different sizes and designs, but they were all similar in the basics of their construction.

“Heard there was a pony here good with energy weapons,” Dusty said, taking the lead. “Was hoping to get some repairs done, maybe pick up some supplies.”

“You could say that,” the mare said with a laugh. “You’d be looking for Arclight, then. He’s got the huge workshop right by the mine entrance, can’t miss it. Anyway, I’m Dazzle.”

She held out a hoof, and after pausing to wipe his own hoof off, Dusty shook it. “I take it you’re in charge here?”

“Hah, nah,” she said, continuing down the line to shake our hooves as we introduced ourselves. “In charge of the guards, sure, but that’s about it. If anypony were in charge, it’d be Arclight or Emerald.” She paused to point to the nearest building, with its colorful sign. “Emerald runs the store and inn, you’ll meet her if you’re looking for supplies. Arclight brings in the trade, but Emerald’s kind of become the heart of our town.”

For just an instant, Dazzle’s expression flashed to one of searching suspicion, but it was gone a moment later as she smiled again. “Why, you looking for some sort of contract work or something?”

“Nothing like that,” Dusty said, offering a dry smile that quickly faded away. “Just like to know where I stand. Tend to step on fewer hooves that way.”

Dazzle gave a soft laugh in reply. “Sounds good to me. If you go stepping on too many hooves, I have to get involved, and that’s a conversation we can both do without.”

Dusty nodded. “Agreed.”

“Well, I’ll get out of your manes and back to my post,” Dazzle said. “It’s a small town, but if you need any help or directions, just flag down a guard or ask around, somepony should be glad to help.”

We parted ways after a quick goodbye, and made our way through town. Dusty left us alone, heading to the store while we headed further into town. Dazzle hadn’t been kidding about not being able to miss Arclight’s place; it was the one pre-war building still standing, some old workshop or warehouse, and easily the largest building in town.

On entering through the front door, we found that the place was absolutely packed with machines, workstations, parts, and several complete weapons. Despite the size and the sheer number of objects within the large space, there was only a single pony within. He was a young yellow unicorn, wearing the kind of head-mounted lenses I associated with jewelers. A loupe, I believe it’s called. It seemed particularly appropriate for him, as at that moment he was examining a pale-blue crystal. He paused in his work to flip up the lens and look our way, and smiled as he saw he had visitors.

“Oh, hello there!” he called out as he stood, working his way through the crowded shop. “I thought I heard the bell. Did you come to do some shopping? Maybe a commission?”

Starlight drew in a slow, deep breath. “Actually, we were hoping to find somepony who could do repairs.”

“Ah, yes! I do tune-ups and repairs as well, especially for my own—”

He staggered to a halt as his eyes fell on the broken weapon Starlight lifted in her magic. His mouth hung open as he sat, gingerly reaching out to take it in his hooves. “Oh,” he said, his voice hushed as he looked over it. “Oh, what happened to you?”

Starlight spoke quietly, as if following his lead. “We were attacked by raiders,” she said. “One tried to take my head off. She hit my gun, instead.”

“Oh.” He looked to her, then back to the gun, nodding. “Well… better it than you, yes. Still…” He gently caressed the weapon’s length with a hoof. “It’s sad to see her in such a state. It’s rare that I get to work on a Lancer. My grandfather did such incredible work on these.”

“Can you fix it?” Starlight asked. I think she was trying to remain still and calm, but I noticed her subtly shifting her balance back and forth in anxiety.

“Maybe,” he said, focusing his attention on the point of damage, with its mangled barrel and crushed-in supports. “The lasing chamber is wrecked, but the damage is all in the housing. That’s the easiest part. Internal damage should be minimal, if any. Yes, I should be able to get her all fixed up.”

Starlight sagged in relief. “Thank you! I don’t have many caps right now, but I’m finishing a job in a couple days, and I should have plenty to pay for any repairs after that.”

Arclight frowned slightly, his eyes still fixed on the weapon. After a few moments of silence, he asked, “You said it was a raider that did this, right?”

Starlight must have noticed the change in tone, as her reply came hesitantly. “Yes?”

He slowly nodded. “In that case… well, I don’t think I’d feel right charging you.” To Starlight’s expression of confusion, he smiled. “My family’s got a policy. Well, several, actually, but the one I’m talking about is that anypony who takes one of our weapons from a raider can bring it here, and we tune and fix it, free of charge. It’s not quite the same, but… close enough, I think.”

“That’s… very generous. Thank you.”

I couldn’t help but note the pause, as if Starlight was searching for some sort of ulterior motive. I couldn’t blame her; weapon crafting never struck me as a terribly altruistic profession.

“My family has always made weapons to protect ponies,” Arclight said. “We don’t like the idea of raiders getting their hooves on our work and using it to hurt the ponies we’re trying to help, so we do what we can to prevent that.”

“And you don’t have problems with people lying about where they got their weapon to get free repairs?”

Arclight swept several scattered parts off of a workbench, setting the Lancer down and gathering several tools. “Nah. Our weapons aren’t very common, and it’d be pretty obvious if a pony keeps “finding” the same gun. Might happen every once in a while, but I’m not really worried about it.”

Starlight finally smiled. “Well… thank you. That’s a lot more than most ponies would do.”

He shrugged in response, levitating several tools. “It’s just how we are, here. Gemstone’s a nice place. Besides, I couldn’t pass up the opportunity to work on one of my grandfather’s Lancers. I might be better at the practical side of making weapons, but I could never match his artistry.”

As he started unscrewing the outer frame, Starlight leaned in, watching intently. She chewed on her lip for a few moments before asking, “How long will it take to fix her up?”

“Hard to say,” Arclight mumbled, eyes fixed on the weapon as he worked. “I’ve got to disassemble everything to see if there’s any internal damage. If there is, those will need repairs or replacement. Then I need to patch up the housing, seal up the chamber. And then it’s the long process of carefully tweaking and aligning everything so it doesn’t vaporize itself when you try to fire.” Detaching the base of the frame, he slowly slid it off, leaving the long barrel exposed. “We’re looking at at least a day of work, maybe two. More if the emitter or lens is damaged, since I’d have to fabricate those from scratch. Nothing I have now would match. These Lancers are pretty amazing, but they’re practically antiques, and incredibly finicky.”

“Oh.” Starlight looked to me. “We can’t wait that long, can we?”

“We can get it on the way back,” I offered.

“Yeah,” she said, though hesitantly. She eyed the partially disassembled Lancer, a hint of that love cropping up once again. “I just don’t like the idea of leaving it behind.”

“You’ll have to leave it with him, anyway. At least this way you won’t be sitting around, waiting for it.”

“At least then I’d be nearby,” she said, but then she shook her head. “But you’re right. I… I guess we can do the job while we wait.”

Arclight had looked up from his work again. “Is there anything else I can help you with?” He looked to me in particular. “Maybe I could interest you in a better—uh, new weapon?”

“I’m afraid I’m fairly poor at the moment,” I said, “but I may have to take a look at what you have when we get back.”

“I’ll be here,” he said with a smile, though his attention was increasingly distracted by the weapon he was disassembling. I turned to leave, looking back to Starlight. She hesitated a moment longer, heaving a long, deep breath before turning to follow me out.

She remained silent as we walked down the dirt path, her head held low and eyes on the ground. It didn’t take a genius of psychology to tell that this was a big deal to her, or that she might need a bit of comfort and reassurance. “You okay, there?”

Her head snapped back up. “Yeah, I’m fine,” she said, and managed to do a halfway reasonable job of sounding it. “Why?”

I replied with a faint, uneven smile, measured to be gently comforting without seeming insensitive. “You care a lot about your rifle, don’t you?”

She drew her head back, mouth opening. I could see the denial forming, but she stopped herself, and after a moment, she sighed, head drooping again. “It was my mom’s. She gave me most of my stuff, even my pistol, but… but the PipBuck and Lancer were hers.” She swallowed. “They’re just… you know, important to me.”

I slowly nodded in understanding. “I know what you mean.”

Again her mouth opened to reply, a flash of anger crossing her expression. Again she stopped herself, her mouth closing again, and her expression softened again. “...Yeah, I guess you do.”

There was a long moment of silence that followed before she abruptly perked up, putting on a slightly too-large smile. “Anyway! Let’s go get you some saddlebags and stuff!”

I allowed her the sudden change of topic and followed along as she picked up her pace. It was a fairly short walk, and we soon entered the town’s only store.

That’s where we met Emerald.

My first observation of Emerald was that she was green. As in, excessively green. She had a light green coat, while her long and flowing mane and tail were dark green. Her eyes matched her mane, as did her cutie mark, which was, as you might have guessed, an emerald.

This all came from a single second of observation as we stepped in the door of the shop to see her standing behind the counter, her forelegs crossed atop it. She was middle-aged, and possibly a bit on the lean side for an earth pony, but only a little. She was also looking right at us, a smile already making its way across her muzzle. “Ah, and you must be Starlight and Whisper,” she said, her voice soft and friendly. “Welcome!”

I should probably note that I have something of a dislike for ponies knowing more about me than I know about them. Dusty must have been talking, and I found myself worrying how much he might have said. I knew it was a mostly irrational fear, as he hardly knew anything about me, but some ingrained reactions can be hard to shake. I shot a glance his way, seeing only his flank as he looked over some goods, before looking back to Emerald.

With my momentary delay, Starlight spoke first. What she said, however, wasn’t a greeting, but an observation. “You have a PipBuck!”

I know that seems like something I should have noticed right away, but in my defense, it had only been a few seconds since I had stepped into the store. And let’s be honest, a pony’s legs are the last place you look when first taking in their appearance. Face, mane, and cutie mark, those are useful identifiers. If anything, I’d trained myself to disregard ponies’ legs. They were useful identifiers for changelings, but not so much for ponies.

As I reconsidered that order of priority, Emerald gave a momentary look of confusion before laughing softly. She had a nice laugh. “Oh! Yes, this old thing. Heck, I’ve had it so long I forget it’s there half the time.” She nodded to Starlight, looking to the PipBuck that hung around her neck. “They’re remarkably useful things, aren’t they?”

“Yeah,” Starlight said, nodding in a way that I can only describe as “dumbly”; she was entirely fixated on the other mare’s PipBuck. “Are… are you from a Stable?”

“Oh, no!” Emerald said with a chuckle. “I try to avoid those places. Nothing but trouble in most of them.” She patted the case of her PipBuck. “No, I found this beauty in my days of wandering, back before I settled down here.”

Starlight nodded again, her ears perking up. “You found it? So, um… you had to put it on?” Suddenly, her interest made perfect sense. “Do you have the tools or keys or whatever it is to unlock them?”

She had her hooves on the counter by the end of her question, leaning in with wide, eager eyes. I found myself saddened as Emerald’s expression fell. “Sorry, hon,” she said, giving a lopsided but sympathetic smile as she raised her hoof to show the backside of her PipBuck. “I’m afraid the one I found is kind of different.”

I stared in confusion at what I saw. Instead of the mostly blank plate that I understood to be the underside of a PipBuck, the backside of hers was dominated by a large, heavy latch. For whatever reason, her PipBuck was designed to be easily removed.

Okay, yes, it makes sense to design it that way. Semi-permanently bolting something to your leg always struck me as a poor idea, and I’m pretty sure that’s not simply a changeling’s natural aversion toward permanence. It just seemed more convenient to be able to remove it. If nothing else, I know how much of a hassle proper coat-care can be, and can only imagine how oily and grimy it must get under one of those things after a while.

No, what really bothered me was that I had never heard of Stable-Tec designing another model of PipBuck with a latch instead of a lock. I paid attention to stuff like that. There was never any press announcement or advertisement for such a thing, and if any Infiltrator had heard word of it, it hadn’t come my way. I suspect that meant noling knew of it, as PipBucks were a potential danger to Infiltrators, one we would surely be apprised of. A device that can detect hostile intent is a dangerous and scary thing to one who relies on subterfuge and deception.

That did leave the possibility of it being a post-war modification. Perhaps one of the Stable populations had gotten tired of needing to lock and unlock the things every time somepony wanted to take it off, or even just to transfer one onto a new generation of ponies?

I nearly missed the following conversation as I mentally grappled with how casually I had just thought of the many generations I had missed. Generations that had been born, lived their lives, and died, all while I slept.

While I quietly recovered from that thought, Starlight was withdrawing from her conversation. “Oh,” she said, her hooves returning to the floor, her expression crestfallen. “Uh, thanks anyway.”

Emerald gave her a sympathetic smile. “I can always keep my eye out for a set,” she said. “They’re not common items, but I’m good friends with a lot of traders. One of them might be able to find something.”

That glimmer of hope, as small as it was, was enough to turn around Starlight’s expression. “Thanks,” she said, with much more warmth.

“Until then, is there anything I can help you with?” Emerald’s smile grew. “Need a place to stay for the night? Maybe some shopping?”

“We can’t stay,” Dusty called out from the other side of the store, near a glass counter displaying various types of ammunition. “We’re moving out soon.”

“No on the room, then,” Emerald noted, chuckling softly. “I take it you’re here for supplies?”

“Yes, please,” Starlight said. “Whisper needs some new saddlebags.” Quietly, she added, “Also maybe a bedroll and blanket.”

I’m sure she thought she was being subtle. Unfortunately, the sudden change of volume was more likely to draw Dusty’s attention than it was to cause him to dismiss it. Sure enough, I caught him casting a glance our way.

“Sure thing!” Emerald said with an eager grin, and quickly escorted me over to where a large variety of clothing and wearable items were displayed; despite the somewhat worn-down and generally post-apocalyptic look about the town, she had quite the inventory. Rows of shelves were stocked full of items, all carefully arranged and cared for.

While Starlight said I could get what I wanted, I was very mindful of the price. After a few moments of browsing, I eventually selected a set of small but sturdy canvas bags.

Emerald insisted I try them on, to make sure they fit right. I agreed, unslinging my rifle and setting it aside so I could do so.

I’m not sure which concerned me more about what that simple action said, in regards to the world I found myself in: that a store owner would show absolutely no reaction to one of her customers handling a very lethal weapon in close proximity to her, or that I had done so without even thinking anything of it at the time. Three days seemed far too brief a period of time to have become so accustomed to carrying such a weapon, but I’d taken it off and set it aside as if it were no more significant than a jacket. I really didn’t like that.

In any case, Emerald helped strap the bags on. “How’s that?” she asked, giving one of the straps a gentle tug. “Are they sitting well? Not too tight around the barrel?”

I rolled my shoulders and swung my hips, testing how the bags sat as I moved. “That’s good. It fits perfectly. Thank you.”

Emerald grinned upon seeing my smile. “Of course! Now let’s see about getting you some bedding.”

Soon I had a blanket and bedroll strapped atop my bags, and Starlight bought a few boxes of antique food, rounding out our supplies. Emerald didn’t stop there.

“So, any other supplies I could interest you in?” She swept a hoof enthusiastically across the store. “Some ammo? Maybe some barding? It can be pretty rough out there, and I’d really like to see you all again.”

She spoke to all of us, but her smile seemed to favor Starlight. I’m not sure if it was because she was the one spending caps, or something else. Starlight appeared to believe it was something else, judging by the awkward expression and ensuing heavy blush. I made a silent mental note of that for possible later use. “I, uh… we’re kind of low on caps.” She rubbed one foreleg nervously against the other. “Maybe when we get back?” The light of inspiration brightened up her expression, abruptly chasing away her embarrassment. “Actually, we might be coming into a good deal of salvage soon. Is there anything you’re looking to buy that we could look for?”

Dusty turned from the display he was looking in. “We’re not coming back here. We’re getting the stuff, then heading right back to Rust. No more detours.”

“We’ve got to come back here,” Starlight replied. “Arclight won’t be done fixing up my Lancer until tomorrow, so unless you’re wanting to stay here that long, we’re coming back through here. Besides, she might give us better prices for some things.”

She quickly looked to Emerald, who had raised a hoof thoughtfully to her chin. “Well now, I don’t know what kinds of prices they’re paying in Rust, but I can certainly try. I could sell just about anything, especially if it’s intact pre-war tech that doesn’t need repairs. Other than that, I’ll pay top value for any electrical components you might find. Arclight can always use more.”

“Ugh, fine,” Dusty said, rolling his eyes in exasperation.

“Wouldn’t that mean Arclight would pay more?” Starlight asked, as tactless as it was, but Emerald took no offense.

“Nah.” She smiled. “It’s not like I’d be charging him for the parts I buy off you, so I don’t have to buy low and mark it up.”

“Wait, you’d just give it away for free?” Starlight tilted her head, looking on with clear skepticism, which drew a laugh from Emerald.

“Of course. Arclight’s business is the reason we get so many traders, so anything I can do to encourage that means more business for me.” She shrugged. “And besides, I’ve always had a thing for Kindness and Generosity.”

Now there were a pair of words that caught my interest. On their own, they might have just seemed like words, but paired together, and the way she had said them? The Elements of Harmony were heard of less and less as the war progressed, but here was a pony two centuries later, making casual mention of them. It was even more notable to me for being two of the Elements that seemed most alien to the Wasteland. Only Laughter seemed as far removed from what I had seen.

It made me very curious about what had happened to them.

“Pardon me saying so,” Dusty said, intruding once more, “but ‘generosity’ is an unusual trait to find in a businesspony.”

Despite his bluntness, Emerald laughed again. “Or most ponies, it seems,” she said. “But that’s just how we try to be here in Gemstone. We’ve got a wonderful community, one that knows you don’t fight the Wasteland by embracing its ways. You fight the Wasteland by being better than it, by helping each other. Kindness returns kindness.”

I’ve got to say, I really liked the sentiment.

“Be nice if the more ponies thought that way,” Dusty said. “Too bad there are so many who’d see kindness as a chance to buck your face in and steal all your stuff.”

Emerald’s smile turned mischievous. “I’ll admit, having an excessive amount of firepower thanks to our local weaponsmith makes the altruism a bit easier.” Her expression turned more serious. “But that’s all part of my point. Everything we have here is because we decided to work together, instead of just for ourselves. Sometimes that means giving a friend some free supplies or a warm meal. Sometimes it means taking up our guns to protect somepony. Sometimes it even means doing something nice for a stranger. We all do our part to make the world a little bit better for somepony else, and that makes the world a little bit better for us, too.”

The mischievous smile returned as she touched a hoof to the display case he had been eying, full of bullets. “So, ammo?”

Dusty gave a snort of amusement, but quickly returned to his frowning expression and shook his head. “I’m good for now. I guess we’re swinging by again later, so we’ll see then.” He looked toward Starlight and myself. “How many rounds do you two have?”

“Enough,” Starlight quickly replied, which earned her a scowl from Dusty.

“‘Enough’ isn’t a number.”

“Okay, infinite then,” Starlight shot back, matching his glare.

“Bullshit. How much—”

“Don’t ‘bullshit’ me, you colossal jack—”

“Hey, hey! Calm down,” Emerald said as she stepped between the two. She didn’t raise her voice, but they both halted. She looked between the two of them. “It’s better to talk things out before assuming the worst about each other.” Her eyes settled on Starlight, smiling softly. “Could you tell us what you meant?”

“What I meant—” Starlight’s angry retort died on her lips in the face of Emerald’s gentle smile. When she tried again, she spoke much more calmly. “What I meant was, my pistol doesn’t use ammunition.”

Dusty blinked. “What?”

I saw Starlight’s jaw tighten, but she managed to keep her voice level. “It’s a Recharger.” Her horn lit, and she slid the pistol from its holster, showing it off. I hadn’t taken a good look at it before, but I studied it then. It was a fairly sleek weapon, with a frame that held three angular barrels, each with a blue crystal at its base. A thick cylinder extended a hoof’s width from the rear, and I could see various wires snaking out from it, all nestled neatly behind the crystals. “It’s got a miniature spark generator or something. Holds about twenty or so shots, and it slowly recharges them.”

“Huh,” was Dusty’s initial reply, which was rather more mild than my own response.

“That’s quite impressive,” I said, earning a smile from Starlight. Possibly more impressive since I’d never heard of a pre-war weapon that did so. It did lead me to question why, however. All the pieces were there. Small spark generators were uncommon and fairly expensive, but the military seemed to spend so much money that I could hardly imagine it being a drain on its resources.

“How long does it take to recharge?” Dusty asked.

“A few minutes.”

He looked as if he were about to say something more, but his eyes darted Emerald’s way, and he quickly turned to me instead. “How about you? How much ammo do you have?”

“Thirty six rounds,” I said, feeling fairly happy that I could give an exact number. Unfortunately, that number produced a grimace from Dusty.

“Thirty six rounds for an automatic pipe rifle,” he grumbled. “Yeah, she’ll need more ammo.”

“‘She’ can’t afford more ammo,” I said, staring back at him.

“You can afford it a lot more than you can afford dying because you ran out in the middle of a fight,” Dusty replied, fixing me with a glare.

“That won’t do me any good if I can’t afford to eat.”

Emerald cut in again. “I think I can solve those problems for you.” When we looked to her, she smiled. “You’re coming back through here for the gun she’s getting fixed up, right?”

We nodded, even though it seemed a rhetorical question.

“So how about this: I can lend you some spare ammo for your trip, and when you get back you can pay for it then, or just return it if you didn’t need it. Sound good?”

I blinked, staring at her smiling face for a couple seconds. Dusty was staring at the back of her head with a deeply suspicious expression. I have to admit, I immediately felt the urge to be suspicious of her motivation as well, but I couldn’t see any tangible way that she could take advantage of us by giving us free ammunition.

That didn’t mean it wasn’t there, just that I couldn’t see it. The closest I came was the possibility that she planned on ingratiating herself with us in hopes of influencing us in the future, but that posed no meaningful threat when I could simply say “no”.

That, or she was truly genuine in her embracing of Kindness and Generosity.

“That’s very generous,” I said, smiling softly. “Thank you.”

“Of course,” she said, her smile brightening just a bit more before turning back to the ammo display and opening it. “Half-inch pipe rifle, is it?”

“Uh…” I had no idea, but I did know that “close enough” wasn’t exactly a thing where firearm ammunition was concerned. I glanced helplessly at Dusty, who rolled his eyes and nodded. “Yes,” I said. “Yes it is.”

She started plucking items out of the case, while Dusty stared at me. He stared long enough that I was starting to get concerned, when he abruptly walked over to me and grabbed the barrel of my rifle.

I objected, but he replied calmly. “Oh, settle down. I’m just looking.”

I was not happy with him tugging on an extremely lethal device strapped to my back. Neither was Starlight, whose “Recharger” pistol was again hovering beside her. Still, I restricted my reaction to merely glaring at him. “You could have asked.”

“Yeah, I could have,” he said, pulling the barrel of the rifle around to look into the muzzle, though he had the sense to look into it from an angle rather than staring straight down the barrel. He frowned at what he saw, though it was a more thoughtful expression than a disapproving one. Finally, he released the barrel. “Well, at least you got one with rifling.”

“It’s not like I had much selection,” I said, grumpily shrugging my shoulders to get the heavy weapon to rest comfortably again. “And seriously, ponies make rifles without rifling? That’s kind of an important part of a rifle.”

“Yeah, it is,” Dusty said. “But it’s also harder to do, so when ponies make cheap-ass weapons like yours, it tends to get skipped over.”

You know, I might not particularly like the big, cumbersome, obnoxiously un-subtle weapon I was carrying, but I dislike hypocrisy even more. Despite that, I laced my voice with only a little bit of irritation. “You’ve got the same kind of gun I do.”

Dusty turned away, a growl entering his voice. “Not by choice.”

I wasn’t entirely sure how to reply to that, as there was clearly something going on that I wasn’t quite seeing. I was distracted from him when I saw Emerald had finished rooting around, and three fresh and fully loaded magazines were sitting atop the counter. “Here,” she said, patting them with a hoof. “Might want to make sure they fit right. You never really know with that kind of gun.”

It was a reasonable concern. Standardized measurements in manufacturing probably went out of style with the bombs. I unslung my rifle again. While I busied myself with making sure the magazines all fit correctly in the weapon, Emerald turned to Dusty. “So, what happened?”

He looked back over his shoulder. “What?”

“‘Not by choice’ makes it sound like something bad happened,” she said, her voice soft and comforting. Inviting.

He considered her, face contorting to a scowl, but it slowly relaxed. After a few moments of silence under her attention, he relented. “There was a pony I worked with, a while back. It’s always good to have somepony watching your back, right? Working together, and all that.” He snorted in disgust, looking away again. “We just finished a big job, one that would have set us nice and comfy for a good while. Fucker stabbed me in the back. Took all the caps and my rifle, and just split.”

Emerald nodded, silently.

Starlight’s reaction was far from silent.

“What a dick!”

We all looked over to her. She stood wide-eyed and incredulous, and quickly turning toward anger. “You don’t know where he is, do you?”

“No,” he said, though hesitantly. “Why do you care?”

“Why?” she asked, as if surprised to be asked that question. “Because… because! You just don’t do shit like that!”

He grunted. “Yeah, well, they did.”

“Well I kind of want to kick his stupid flank,” Starlight said.

“Sorry, I’ve got dibs on it,” Dusty said. I even saw a hint of a smile trying to make its way past his grimace. It didn’t last long as he quickly changed the subject. “Now if you two are done shopping, let’s go.”

He paused long enough to thank Emerald, then walked out of the store. I tucked the three gifted magazines into the pouch with the other one, and adjusted its strap so it sat across my shoulder instead of hanging from my neck. Meanwhile, Starlight paid for our acquisitions with a large part of our—and by that, I mean her—caps.

Oh, yes. I believe that was when I found out what caps really were. I’ll spare you the lengthy ranting I could probably level at that discovery. Suffice to say, there were many things about this new world that I found to be strange, and the idea that ponies would use bottlecaps for currency was well up there on the list.

I refrained from making comment of it, and soon we headed out to rejoin Dusty, who was waiting just outside. It was a short walk to the gate, and we left with a wink and a wave from Dazzle, still lounging beside her cannon.

As we walked off past the remnants of the mining camp below the town, I couldn’t help looking back at Gemstone. I still had concerns that there was something seedy lurking under the surface. After the horrors I had seen since waking up, that concern was hardly unjustified, but those experiences were limited. They comprised only a couple days and a single settlement. Gemstone seemed like a genuinely nice place. There was love there. Despite the guns that adorned their walls and the armaments they produced, there was a sense of peace and happiness that had become uncommon during the war. It gave me a small glimmer of hope that maybe, just maybe, the Wasteland wasn’t quite as bad as I had been led to believe.

That hope didn’t last long.

☢

“How bad is it?”

Dusty grunted, peering through his binoculars. It was still fairly early in the morning by the time we reached the sandy ridge we were lying upon. Out in the flat and empty basin beyond, perhaps a mile away, was the depot Dusty had guided us toward. That, and a fair bit more.

“Bad,” Dusty said, passing the binoculars my way.

I took them, bracing against a rock for stability; despite the relatively short walk and the night’s rest, my legs were still quite unhappy with the workload I’d given them lately. I peered through the binoculars, my view swinging around until I finally found what I was looking for.

Even with the binoculars, I couldn’t make out all the fine details at such a range, but I didn’t need to. The recent construction was perfectly obvious.

The perimeter was lined with a chain-link fence that had been reinforced or patched in several places with scrap. What had once been a wagon shelter had partially collapsed, but fabric hung from the remaining parts to form simple shelters, swaying in the light breeze. A rope bridge ran from a patched-up watch tower to the roof of a warehouse, where a few more crude structures had been built. Just beyond the warehouse was a line of railway tracks, with a second line running along the loading dock of the warehouse. The most significant construction was a haphazard wall, anchored by the watchtower at one end and the fence at the other, with a large gate in the middle. It was nothing compared to the gates of Rust or Gemstone, but that hardly mattered. Somepony had found our claim.

In front of that gate was an object that I thought might have been a pony. On scrutinizing it in the binoculars, I came to the horrified realization that I was close. It was most of a pony. Specifically, a dismembered and decapitated torso, impaled on a pole. Several dark birds appeared to be gathered around, presumably feeding on it.

I passed the binoculars back, not needing to see further details of that. “So… raiders?”

“Probably,” Dusty replied, taking his binoculars back. He continued to silently scan over the depot.

I watched as well, though there was little I could make out from so far away. “So… that’s it, then? We’re not planning on fighting a bunch of raiders, are we?”

“No, we’re not.” He continued to watch the compound. “I don’t think we’ll have to.”

“I’m not sure I like the sound of that,” I said, giving him a concerned look.

“The sound of what?” Starlight called up to us. She was watching our rear, at Dusty’s insistence, and was sitting a ways back from where we lay. It occurred to me that meant she had no idea about the torso-pony.

“I’m not seeing any ponies,” Dusty said. “Nopony’s manning the lookout posts, and I haven’t seen any movement inside the fence. I do see two… maybe three bodies. Plenty of crows, too. It looks like whoever it was got hit.”

“I’m liking the sound of this even less.”

“What do you mean, bodies?” Starlight asked.

“The depot has dead ponies in it,” Dusty called back.

“And we have no idea who killed them,” I added.

“But whoever it was seems to have moved on.” He mulled the situation over for a moment before making a decision. “We need to get a closer look. If they really have cleared out, we could still find a lot of salvage.”

I frowned. Even if everything he said made sense, I disliked the idea of getting closer to the depot of death. Still, I had to admit I agreed with him. In fact, I’d much rather take the chance and scope it out rather than stay away due to personal risk. The risk was there either way; our supply of caps was rapidly dwindling, and we were unlikely to find another prospect so promising on our way back. The life of an Infiltrator often demands risks, and he was just proposing a scouting run.

“Okay,” I said, nodding. “We should be careful, though.”

“Of course,” Dusty said, lowering the binoculars. “You see that streambed off to the left of the depot?”

After a moment, I found what he was talking about: a shallow crevice in the ground, only a few feet lower than the terrain around it and snaking slowly off to our left. “Yeah, I see it.”

“That’s our approach. It should keep us in defilade to anypony on the ground most of the way there. The last hundred yards will be in the open, but we can scout it out before crossing.”

I nodded again.

“Scoot back,” he said, and we shuffled backwards until we were out of sight of the depot. Keeping low, we crept back to Starlight. “Let’s see that map.”

Starlight levitated her PipBuck out between us, flipping over to the map screen. After zooming in, Dusty pointed to it. “Okay, there. That stream on the northwest side of the compound? It hooks around this high ground just to our north. That’s our entrance. It’s also our primary exit. The ground around the compound is barren with almost no cover, so if we have to retreat, we want to go that way. Once we make it to the streambed, we can either retreat back north, or continue on south.”

“Makes sense,” Starlight said, though she seemed reluctant to admit it. I merely nodded.

“If you see anypony, you’re only to fire if they see us, and either have a weapon pointed at us or are shooting at us. Anything else, you wait for my word before shooting.” He looked around at us, his expression sharp and deadly serious. “Understood?”

“Sure,” Starlight said. I nodded once more.

Dusty continued to stare at her for a second before speaking again. “Just remember, that was part of the deal. Until we’ve cleared the entire compound, this is a combat zone. That means you need to do exactly what I say, when I say it. No questions asked or second-guessing, no improvisation, just following orders. You got that?”

“Yeah,” Starlight said, with only the faintest hint of bitterness. “It’s your show. I got it.”

The twitch of his jaw was subtle, but I could tell he’d caught that tone. He decided not to press the matter, though. “Okay. Check and ready your weapons.” He pulled his own rifle around to hang from his neck, in easy reach, and pulled back the bolt. I did the same. Starlight merely looked at us both with a bored expression, her pistol hovering beside her.

Dusty nodded. “I’ll lead. Starlight, you’re on me. Whisper, you’re bringing up the rear. Let’s move out.”

With the first tingles of adrenaline playing at the edge of my senses, we started to walk.

Chapter Six: Carrion

I was not a soldier.

That’s not to say I was entirely averse to violence or danger. I had often idly pondered what it would be like to conduct assassinations, or even to have served in a commando group. They were entertaining fantasies. If I were selected to play such a role in the hive, I would have done so willingly, happy to contribute to the well-being and security of the hive. My preferences, however, lay along a different course.

To an Infiltrator, violence is a tool. A particularly extreme and unsubtle tool, but a tool all the same. Usually the screwdrivers and pliers and micrometers are the best tools for the job, but sometimes you just have to break out the hammer.

To a soldier, violence is a method. The method. Their tools are focused on applying the proper form of violence most efficiently, but a soldier’s role revolves around violence. I don’t intend that as a criticism of soldiers, as violence (Or just as frequently, the threat of violence) can solve problems that more subtle means may be unsuited for. I had been given a very stark example of that truth. I am not so conceited as to assume those who walk a different path are inferior to myself. I may prefer to avoid violence when possible, but I recognize that is not always possible. Soldiers have their place, perhaps now more than ever.

As for danger and the threat of death, I am familiar with those things. It may have been in quite different contexts, but it was there all the same. Every single action taken within Equestria was done with a lingering background concern, worrying that a minor misstep might leave the clues some clever pony needs to piece together the hidden truth. When the Ministry of Morale comes for an Infiltrator, death is generally the preferable outcome. We learned to evaluate our actions through reason, rather than emotion, because the most natural emotion was that of fear.

The difference in context, however, was everything. While an Infiltrator was faced with an ever-present low-level danger, the lives of soldiers were often punctuated by moments of extreme danger. While Infiltrators had a great deal of ability to control what dangers they faced, soldiers often did not have that freedom. As an Infiltrator, the typical course was to avoid danger as much as was reasonable. To put it somewhat disparagingly, if an Infiltrator came across something particularly dangerous, the general recourse was to run away from that danger.

Soldiers were expected to run toward it.

The chill of adrenaline continued to course through my veins as we moved down the shallow gully. It teased at my nerves in a way I hadn’t experienced since my first time slipping into a pony settlement, under the watchful eyes of one of my instructors. I was going into the unknown, in a situation that was likely to demand largely untested skills. There remained the distinct possibility that I would have to stake my life on skills I had no experience to accurately judge.

We paused for a moment where the streambed neared the depot. It was not as dry as I had initially assumed from a distance. A tiny trickle of water still remained from the torrential downpour. The ground was muddy, but I kept myself crouched low. Dusty had me watching our rear this time, while he and Starlight observed the depot once more.

We were there for less than a minute when he whispered around the bit of his gun. “Follow me.” He rose up, advancing toward the crude wall. He moved at a swift walk, barely below a trot, and with so little bounce to his step that he seemed to practically flow across the ground. His gun unerringly tracked the gate.

Our path led us directly past the torso-pony, giving me a clear view of the grisly scene.

I can’t really say it was the first time I had seen a dead pony. That first time, however, had been a fleeting glimpse while scrambling for my life, obscured by heavy rain and lit only by the weak light of a PipBuck screen. This time it was in the broad light of day, searing the image into my memory in every gruesome detail.

I don’t like lingering on such things, but this was the first time I got such a clear view of the sort of atrocities that take place in the Wasteland. Though I had no idea who this pony had been, that made it feel important to me. Horrible, but important.

The remains were in a far worse state than I had originally thought, looking at it from a distance. The pony hadn’t just been dismembered and decapitated, but disemboweled as well. The gaping space that had once been a belly showed that the body was hollow and empty inside, letting us see the pole that ran through the vacant cavity. It was a pipe, with a jagged blade welded to one end to form a spear, and the other end buried in the ground. It had been inserted through the groin, up through the torso, and out through the neck. A bone had been lashed to the pole just beneath the pelvis, keeping the grotesque display suspended.

A few tattered clumps of purple were the only sign of the pony’s coat, giving just a hint of the once-colorful pony it had been. The rest of the hide had been torn away, as had most of the meat. The ragged flesh, ruddy brown from decay, clung to the bones. The pony’s limbs were scattered around it, half-buried in the ground where they had sunk into the mud, only for the ground to dry up around them. Flies filled the air with buzzing, while several crows picked over the remains. One of the crows paused in plucking at the remains of the pony’s neck to caw angrily at us as we passed by.

I hurried past, gagging at the horrific stench of rotting flesh, one that brought back far too vivid and painful of memories. In a more calm moment, I might have stopped and retched. Instead, I pushed on, riding the mounting adrenaline to safety.

We paused at the gate, which was opened just enough for a pony to pass through. Dusty crept up to the corner, halting a few feet from the opening. He placed a hoof under the barrel of his rifle, holding it in place as he released it to look back at us.

Once we had gathered up, he gripped his rifle again, and moved through the gate.

Immediately on the other side was another corpse, and our entrance scared off the crows that had been feeding on it. I avoided looking closely at it; my attention was instead focused on the ruins of the wagon shelter, where the hulks of dead vehicles and hanging cloth of shelters gave many places for some hostile pony to hide. The space beyond the gate was an open field, bordered by the warehouse and wagon shelter, a wide space with no cover.

Dusty moved the other way, toward the warehouse that dominated the depot. It was a large sheet-metal building with no windows. A pony-sized door hung from one hinge. Further down the wall, the large loading-bay doors were wide open, showing the collapsed racks and scattered boxes within. He again paused just short of the pony-sized door, waiting for us to draw close, then moved in.

The warehouse was huge, and the boxes and towering shelves gave me the terrifying feeling of being watched from a hundred different places at once. That feeling was enhanced by the dimness, as the entire space was lit only by the open doors and a few holes in the huge roof. Just to make the scene even more unsettling, we were immediately confronted by another corpse.

Being somewhat sheltered by its location, this body was less decayed, but possibly more gruesome for it. He—for I think it was a stallion, despite the most identifying parts having been torn away—lay on his back atop a table, split open. A pair of deep gashes paralleled each other down his chest, cutting through the last few ribs before opening into the cavity that had been his belly. His torn-open barding hung from his body, stained dark. What entrails remain lay strewn about the table and dangling off the side, while dried blood coated the surface and left a discolored circle on the ground. Only a few patches of off-white coat were left unstained.

I didn’t know a pony contained that much blood. Conceptually, sure, but it was shocking to see demonstrated so clearly.

Just to cap off the horror-show, his neck was a mess of torn meat. His head was missing. I found that discovery to be particularly unsettling. An all new feeling of horror started to bubble up in the background.

Dusty hadn’t hesitated for even an instant. He moved forward along the front end of the warehouse, his rifle tracking each aisle of shelves as he moved across it. I followed as the number of possible hiding spots rapidly dwindled.

We reached the end of the warehouse, exiting through the loading docks, and moved toward the ruins of the wagon shelter.

The hulk of a ruined skywagon formed a wall for the area, with several spans of canvas dividing the space beneath the tilted shelter roof. Despite the ruined conditions, it almost looked liked it could have been a pleasant place in different conditions. The simple, airy shelter the fabric provided seemed ideal for desert living.

That was ruined by the pair of corpses lying around the entrance. One lay entangled and half suspended in the canvas that had once formed part of a shelter, forelegs crushed and contorted, with the handle of a machete protruding from the shredded remains of what had once been a neck. The other was sunk chest-first into the dirt just off the concrete pad, spine laid bare while crows plucked meat from the pony’s ragged back. Both were missing their heads.

Dusty slowed as he approached the shelter. After peering in, his gun sweeping around as he checked the nearby area, he drew back to the entangled pony. I crouched next to him, looking for any sign of movement within the canvas-enshrouded space..

Keeping his gun leveled, Dusty reached out to pull on the canvas. It took a couple of tugs before it pulled free and the body flopped limply to the ground. Partially protected by the fabric, it was the most intact of the corpses we had found. I could see clearly that it had been a wiry mare, with a ragged pale-blue coat and a short red tail. She wore barding, with a heavy metal plate encircling her chest, but it hadn’t helped her. The side of the armor was caved in, mangling her chest, and from the way she flopped and twisted to the side in a most unnatural fashion, I was guessing the blow had broken her spine.

Just in case the place hadn’t been delivering enough disturbing content, her cutie mark consisted of a pony skull with a knife driven into the top of it.

Cutie marks could be a terrifying concept at the best of times, but that mark brought an all new level of concern. It left me wondering what kind of horrific special talent that mare had once possessed. I would have questioned how a pony could even discover such a talent, but that day had already provided me an ample answer to that question.

For a moment, it seemed as if Dusty took comfort in that cutie mark. He relaxed a little, his posture softening, though he kept his gun ready. “They were raiders,” Dusty said. “Looks like someone killed them all and took off. We should be clear, but keep an eye out, just in case.”

“They took all their heads,” Starlight said, tearing her eyes away from the face-down corpse to glance my way.

“They were probably hit by some other band of raiders,” Dusty said, relaxing further and standing tall as he slowly looked around. “Raiders love taking trophies.”

“Yeah, I know,” Starlight said. “It’s just, I think we ran into the raider who did this.”

He looked her way. “Oh?”

She nodded. “Yeah. Just a few hours away from Rust. Some giant of a mare in full metal armor, hauling a bag of heads.”

Dusty’s head drew back in surprise. “Oh, shit. You met Sickle?”

I stepped in. “As I doubt there’s another mare of similar size and attire, I’m going to assume, it seems so.”

Dusty stared at me for a few seconds, mulling that over. “Huh,” was all he said at first, but eventually shook his head and looked around again. “Yeah, that’d explain the mess. She’s a nasty one. Guess I’m not surprised she’d take trophies.”

Starlight snorted. “Yeah, probably decorating her little shithole with them.” Despite the angry tone, I could see her shudder.

“What shithole?” Dusty asked, looking to her with a questioning look. “You saw her home?”

“We were in her home.”

His eyes widened, and I quickly clarified. “It was in the middle of that storm and getting dark. We thought it was abandoned, so we took shelter there. She got there a couple hours later to find us there.”

“Shit,” he said. “How’d you manage to get away from her?”

“We didn’t exactly get away,” I said. “It was more like she grabbed us and threw us out. Well, threw me into a wall and then out.” I rubbed my chest, where she had pinned me to the wall. “She wasn’t very nice about it.”

“No shit,” Dusty said, though he sounded more surprised than condescending. “I’ve got to say, I would have expected her to kill you. Like I said, I’ve only met her a couple times, but she always struck me as excessively violent.”

“We did just come out of a day-long storm,” I said. “We were soaking wet and exhausted. It would have been hard to look much more pathetic.”

Dusty stared at me with a lopsided expression the clearly communicated how utterly stupid he thought I was. “You don’t know a fucking thing about raiders if you think that’s going to stop anypony.” He shook his head and turned away, moving to the entrance. “Come on. Check out the rest of this shelter, see if there are any survivors or salvage, then we search the warehouse. Hopefully we can get something out of this disaster.”

Starlight and I shared a quick glance, and followed him in.

The raiders’ living space was in shambles. Tables were turned over, bedding was shoved aside, and containers lay open and ransacked. A severed foreleg lay in the middle of a walkway, reduced to tattered strings of flesh clinging to bones. The matching body was in the next room, deposited in a box. His hindlegs stuck out over the edge. One ended in a stub, the lower leg having fallen to the ground when the scavengers tore away the tendons. A crow stood on the other, picking at the intact knee. It interrupted its meal to caw at us, as if warning us away.

We left the crow to its meal and continued on.

I can not emphasize too strongly just how awful the place was. The grotesque remains, the choking stench of decaying ponies, the ever-present buzzing of flies, and the crows picking away at the bodies. It was a horrorshow, beyond anything I had ever imagined. I struggled against my own stomach as it rebelled, trying to purge itself. I breathed through my mouth in an attempt to avoid the stench, despite how awkward that was with my rifle’s grip clenched between my teeth. It only did so much; I could taste the decay in the air.

Then there was the occasional scene that seemed to transcend mere violence, rising to the level of outright sadism. One sleeping area had a corpse suspended from the wagon-shelter’s supports by a length of rope, hanging by one hind leg while the other limbs dangled at awkward angles. The pony had been disemboweled, though I couldn’t be sure if it had been by this Sickle pony or the scavengers that came afterward. The bed he was suspended over was stained entirely black with blood.

But for all that, for all the carnage and decay, there were two that stood out above the rest. One was the first, the torso-pony posted like a warning sign of what lay beyond those gates.

The second was a young colt.

Even Dusty paused as we came across that scene. The small pony’s body lay crumpled, chest-down atop a heap of blood-stained canvas, surrounded by shards of broken wood and an overturned table. I would guess the pony at around ten, maybe twelve years, though I was never all that good at guessing ponies’ ages. That was made harder by his body being misshapen, his ribs crushed in so severely that several had punctured out of his back.

The nearby wall, made of wood that looked to have once been crates, had a ragged hole broken through it; it was easy to picture the monstrous pony I remembered, throwing the colt’s tiny body through that wall. The difference in size struck me as monumentally unfair to the poor colt.

And of course, he was missing his head as well. The ragged tatters of meat and the glint of exposed spine made it look like it had been torn away rather than cut.

Dusty was the first to approach, and placed a hoof against the colt’s side to roll him onto his side. I looked away the moment I realized his intentions, but not quickly enough to miss the way part of the young pony slopped out as his belly parted. The sickening wet sound made my stomach twist again, and the air was promptly filled with the buzzing of flies as their meal was disturbed.

“Another raider,” Dusty said, without any apparent remorse. I looked back to see what had drawn that conclusion. Then I saw the colt’s cutie mark; an eyeball, impaled on a thin blade.

I walked out, past all the blood and corpses, until the stench no longer filled my nose. I sat there in the dirt field, slowly breathing in and out. I sat there, still, despite the way my limbs tried to tremble. I tried to focus on how I should just overlook it, how this was all in the past and nothing I could do would affect it. It didn’t help much.

A minute later, Starlight and Dusty emerged. Starlight looked miserable, and as she stepped out she coughed a couple times before spitting into the dirt. She looked close to vomiting. I could sympathize. I’m honestly amazed that I managed to hold it in the whole way through.

Dusty looked grim, but undisturbed.

Actually, a correction: while he looked undisturbed upon leaving the shelter, the expression soon turned to one of disapproval as he looked at us. “Not as fun as you imagined, is it?” He snorted softly. “If you really want to be some hot-shot merc, you better get used to it. That’s what combat looks like.”

“What, sticking ponies on pikes and hanging them from the rafters?” She shot him a glare, pointing a hoof back at the shelter. “That isn’t combat. That’s… something else.”

“It’s on the bad side, but death is never pretty.” He gestured the way she was pointing before walking on. “You kill a pony, that’s what you leave behind. Just keep that in mind.”

I think Starlight wanted to argue the point further, but she didn’t have any fight left in her. She instead spit again, pausing for a few moments to suck in the cleaner air. She waited there beside me as Dusty continued on, heading around the ruined wagon shelter. Eventually, she looked my way. “I guess we should get on with the salvage, huh?”

I nodded, taking another deep breath, and hauled myself up to my hooves. We weren’t done yet.

Fortunately, we didn’t come across any more bodies. We did come across the wreckage of another skywagon, its frame twisted and half covered by the collapsed shelter. The remaining metal curled away from the body, with a gaping hole where the front had been. If I had to offer a guess as to its demise, I would have to say that the spark battery had ruptured and exploded. The only question I had was whether it was a consequence of the shelter collapsing upon it, or the cause.

On the far side of the shelter, a motorwagon was parked on a bare patch of pavement. It was an unusual find, I thought. Motorwagons were uncommon even before the end of the world, as the few factories capable of producing such vehicles instead spent their effort on producing tanks for the Equestrian army. Even those were few in number.

Two hundred years had worn on the vehicle, but had not destroyed it. That looked to have come much more recently. The panel over the mechanical innards of the vehicle lay open, with many parts removed. Several tool sets lay around. The raiders had been working on it, but even though my knowledge of motorwagon engineering was practically nonexistent, I was fairly certain they were doing it wrong.

Starlight was even less impressed. “What the fuck,” she muttered, approaching the open panel to peer inside. I could hear her angry muttering continuing, growing in both vehemence and incredulity by the moment.

Dusty checked out the tool sets while asking, “How bad is it?”

“These ponies had no idea what the hell they were doing!” Starlight shouted, her head still stuck within the motorwagon’s body. “This casing is pristine, but… shit, they just tore out these wires. Half these gears are stripped. Look, the metal’s all clean there where they broke it. That was recent. And… and for fuck’s sake, did they use a cutting torch on the transmission? They… they…”

She sputtered and fumed for several seconds before pulling back. “Damnit!” she shouted, slamming a hoof against the side of the vehicle. “This thing was probably a minor tune-up from running, and these raiders gutted it like—”

She swept her hoof back to the shelter, and the anger immediately drained from her. Her hoof dropped to the ground. After a moment, she sighed. “Too bad. Would have been quite the prize, huh? This thing would probably be worth a small fortune if it worked.”

“Or a large one,” Dusty said, frowning as he looked over it. “Doubt there are more than twenty motorwagons still running, and most of those are in Trotsen. Heard a merchant ask one of their caravaners how much they’d sell one of their wagons for. I didn’t bother remembering how much they said, I just remember thinking that I’d never see that many caps in my life.”

Starlight sat with a weary huff. “Shit.”

“You seem to know a little about machines,” Dusty said, which I think might have been the nicest thing he had said to her at that point in time. “Any chance you can fix the damage?”

“Oh, hell no,” Starlight said, weakly kicking the side of the wagon. “I can kludge together simple stuff and do basic repairs and cleaning, that’s all basic scavenger stuff. This? This is insane. They tried to cut the transmission casing open to get at the internals, but managed to cut into the feed from the spark battery! Somehow, they didn’t blow themselves sky high, but they did dump the entire battery’s charge into the engine. The transmission is nothing but a lump of fused metal. I’m surprised the whole damn engine didn’t just pour out into a puddle!”

“And those are the parts that can’t be replaced,” Dusty finished for her. “Shit.”

In hindsight, it seems strange to me that we should linger there, silently mourning the death of a machine when there were so many dead ponies there. Strange, and a little concerning that I might have been subconsciously avoiding anything that would lead me to thinking about the death all around me.

“We should check the warehouse,” Dusty said, turning to head that way. “Hopefully we can find something to make this trip worth the time.”

“Yeah,” Starlight said, banging a hoof one last time on the motorwagon before turning to follow. “‘Cause, no offense Dusty, but this claim of yours is looking kinda shit so far.”

Dusty grimaced, but otherwise seemed to agree. “At least somepony killed off all the raiders before we got here.”

“I’m not sure if I count that as a good thing,” Starlight grumbled. “‘Cause I kinda want to kill them myself, now.”

Dusty snorted. I caught a faint suggestion of amusement in the sound and curl of his lips, but he hid it well from Starlight.

As for myself, I couldn’t help but note Starlight’s use of humor as a coping mechanism. I think that’s what jolted me out of the numb stupor I had descended into. Sure, she had the advantage of having years to become familiar with the Wasteland, even though I had no idea if she’d ever experienced anything remotely like this, but I was an Infiltrator. I’d been trained, extensively, to work in stressful situations, and I was failing to uphold the expectations put upon me.

I took another deep breath, mentally shaking off the death and destruction. I had to focus on analyzing the situation with clinical detachment. I had to carry on, despite my fears. The fact was, I was not in imminent danger. What surrounded me was not a threat, and it was not time-critical. I could step back and think, rather than worry.

The true horror of the Wasteland did not lie in the carnage around me. They were just a symptom. The true horror was the the reason for that carnage; the motivations that had led to this and other atrocities. And motivations, those were something I could handle. My profession was all about motivations, and in shaping and manipulating them. I might not know or understand the motivations that could lead to such a grotesque excess of violence, but I could learn.

In a way, it turned the scene around me into a puzzle. A morbid one, but it was still something I could grasp and understand. There was some comfort in that.

We entered the warehouse, with its many shelves and crates. Entering from the loading dock, the first thing I noticed was the elevated office above where we had first entered. It was likely a manager’s office, with its commanding view over the warehouse floor. The catwalk leading to it had collapsed in the middle, leaving the office stranded, like an island in the air.

Starlight came to the same conclusion I had. “Looks like an office,” she said, and started to trot its way. “I’ll go check it out.”

“Anypony seen a ladder?” Dusty asked, but Starlight simply let out a short laugh.

She turned, leaping atop a box, then scrambled up the side of a twenty-foot-high shelf. From there it was a casual hop to the next shelf, right below the catwalk. She leaped up, catching the edge with her forehooves, then flipped her hindquarters around to hook a hindleg over the edge and pull herself up.

She paused just long enough to shoot a smug grin our way before disappearing into the office.

“Okay,” Dusty said, his head tilted to one side. “That… was actually kind of impressive.”

I managed a weak chuckle as we turned to look over the contents of the shelves. For the most part, it was a few hundred identical crates, all stamped with Stable-Tec logos. A couple were already opened, presumably by the ponies that now lay dead. Apparently they had been unhappy with the crate of Stable jumpsuit uniforms, and had used that crate as a latrine. The box full of pipe ends and joints were unsullied, a fact which failed to provoke any enthusiasm from either of us.

As we worked, I considered Dusty’s comments on Starlight. It was possibly the nicest thing he had said about her, as sad as that was. Despite how vile and depressing the place was, it presented an opening; seeing as we were only halfway through our little endeavor, I hoped I could encourage a more friendly atmosphere between them.

So as we continued looking into already-opened crates, I spoke with him. “Hey, Dusty?”

He looked over. “Hmm?”

I paused in my fruitless search, turning to address him. I gave a weak smile, mixing in just a hint of feigned awkwardness; it’s amazing how much that can soften a pony’s reactions. “Well… I know you and Starlight have kind of butted heads a fair bit, but she means well. I don’t think she means to be abrasive, it’s just that she’s outgoing and used to being friendly with ponies. I, uh… I get why you might not be all that trusting of other ponies, but it comes across as a little rude at times.”

“I’m not here to make friends,” he said, turning to move to the next box.

“I know,” I said, as placatingly as I could. “And I’m not asking you to trust us, at least any more than you need to for us to work together. I’m just saying that you don’t need to drive ponies away to do that.”

He hooked a hoof over the edge of the next open crate, casting a glare my way. “What, are you a psychologist, now?”

“Not professionally,” I said, my smile growing just a touch, and throwing in a weak chuckle for good measure. “I just listen to ponies. You seem like a very nice and decent pony when you’re not trying to keep other ponies away.”

Dusty turned away again, but this time he remained still, thinking. It was many seconds before he finally sighed and spoke. “Look, you two seem like good ponies, but neither of you has a clue what you’re doing. Yeah, sure, you know about scavenging, but you’re both naive and inexperienced when it comes to anything else. You keep going like you are, thinking you know everything, you’re going to end up just like the ponies outside.”

My smile died away at the thought; I really didn’t want to imagine myself in the place of one of those corpses. “I... think we might know more than you give us credit for,” I said, and quickly held up a hoof as he opened his mouth again. “No, I know we don’t know as much about combat as you do. That seems pretty obvious. But we aren’t completely clueless, and more importantly, we’re trying to learn more.”

He sighed, and relented just a little. “Well… just try not to get killed while you do. Learning by experience tends to mean learning from mistakes, and out here, mistakes get you killed.”

A yell from the office pulled our attention that way, and Starlight emerged onto the catwalk with a thick folder floating beside her. “Hey, guys! I found the inventory!”

Dusty quirked an eyebrow. “Uh… congratulations?”

She smirked down at us. “Hell yes, congratulations,” she said as she hopped down atop the shelf beneath the catwalk. “There are, like, five bajillion crates in here.” She leaped across the gap to the next row of shelves. “You want to open crate after crate of steel floor-grates, rebar, and concrete?”

She slid sideways, dropping over the edge of the shelf. She dangled there for a moment before twisting and dropping to the floor with a clatter of hooves. “Or do you want to go right up to, say, a crate loaded with two-dozen blast-door servos and all their electrically-powered, hydraulically-operated goodness?” She thumped a hoof triumphantly against the crate she had landed next to, grinning smugly.

“Okay,” Dusty said, slowly nodding. “That’s actually pretty useful.”

“Oh, what’s that?” Starlight said, her smirk returning as she cast a smug glare his way. “I actually know what I’m talking about?”

His expression fell to a flat glare, and he turned it my way. “Yeah, that went well.”

I responded with a sigh, burying my face in a hoof.

Starlight looked back and forth between the two of us. “...Did I miss something?”

Dusty responded by turning his flat glare her way. “Whisper here was just talking to me about being nice, so we wouldn’t be at each other’s throats the whole time.”

“Oh?” She replied, seemingly confused for a moment. “Oh.” She looked over at the folder floating next to her, then the crate she was still leaning against. She lowered her hoof again. “Um, sorry?”

He continued to stare for an awkward moment before finally rolling his eyes. “Good enough. Come on, there’s a door to a back area. We’ll check through there real quick, then we can look for any valuables in that inventory.”

“Sounds… good?” Starlight said, casting a confused and questioning glance my way.

We followed along behind Dusty. Sure enough, there was a doorway leading into another area. The door itself had been torn free of its hinges, with a massive dent right in the middle, and lay half atop another dead pony. Three more corpses were scattered around the room.

I’ll spare you the details. I think you’ve gotten the idea by now. Suffice to say, each was gruesome in its own uniquely horrific way, and the stench was absolutely appalling.

The room they lay in was in shambles. It seems to have been used as a common room, but the table was now broken under one of the decaying ponies, with chairs and even a couch overturned. Signs of violence abounded, and not just from the bodies. There were casings scattered about, and bullet holes peppered an entire wall and the one chair that remained standing. A stubby rifle, as crude as my own, lay near one of the dead ponies, its barrel dented in and bent. A couple crude knives and a length of pipe with a spiked end lay near the other ponies. The weapons had evidently done them no good against their attacker.

Playing cards were scattered around the broken table, and empty bottles lay all over the room. Even with my attempt to focus on empirical data, that little detail led my mind on unpleasant paths. It was hard to imagine these ponies as murderous raiders. It was much easier to imagine a group of happy, colorful ponies, laughing and drinking and playing games.

Starlight gagged again, pulling out her jacket to wrap around her muzzle as best she could without blocking her sight. I tore my gaze from the scene of destruction, and looked to Dusty. “So, about Sickle,” I quietly said. “We didn’t see anypony else with her.”

“Yeah, you wouldn’t,” Dusty said, holding a fetlock to his nose. “She doesn’t play well with others.”

“So she came here, killed… at least a dozen raiders, and did this all on her own?” I looked around the room, with its shattered furniture and scattered bodies. It looked like it had been a hell of a fight. “How?”

“Well, to start with, shooting her tends to just piss her off,” Dusty said. “She’s huge, probably the strongest and toughest pony I’ve ever met, and that’s not even counting her armor. I only saw her in a fight once, but I saw a raider with a pipe rifle put at least five rounds into her chest plate. I don’t think she even noticed.”

“That’s damn good armor,” Starlight said, her voice muffled as she pulled on the sleeves of her jacket, tying her makeshift face-mask in place.

“It probably weighs more than you do,” Dusty said. “Hell, probably more than I do. And if that all wasn’t enough, she’s usually loaded up on just about every combat drug you can think of.”

“Probably doesn’t help that these ponies emptied enough bottles to leave an entire town blackout-drunk,” Starlight said through her makeshift face-mask. “Can we move on, now?”

“Yeah,” Dusty said. “Come on.”

We moved past the bodies, stepping over the overturned chair blocking the walkway. The smell improved only marginally as we stepped through the doorway and into another room. It was a barracks, with a dozen bunks and plenty of lockers. It also contained at least a hundred more bottles, as well as their source: a couple of crates were set near the center of the room, the packaging material that had secured the bottles within strewn about them.

Starlight stepped up to the box, squinting to read the worn label, then flipping open the folder levitating alongside her. “Two times one gross, Serene Skies Quality Cider.” She looked back at the scattered bottles. “Two hundred and eighty eight bottles, and they’re all empty. Shit, these guys must have been wasted.”

“Serene Skies is non-alcoholic,” I said. A moment later, I had to correct myself. “Well, it was. I have no idea what two hundred years does to cider.”

While I couldn’t see her mouth under the jacket, I could see the corners of Starlight’s eye rise with her grin. “You know the coolest shit, Whisper!”

Even Dusty chuckled, though it came out more as a choked snicker as he made his way past us. Only three doors remained. One led back outside, hanging halfway open but undamaged. Another led into what looked to have once been an office, complete with desk and shattered terminal. Opposite the office was the most unusual room of the entire place. Unlike the rest of the building, with its exposed supports and sheet-metal walls, it was made of solid, poured concrete. The door was normal size, but made of heavy metal, even having another metal plate welded on to cover the latch, likely to prevent easily shimmying it. It was battered, scraped, and dented by these ponies’ assault, but it had held firm.

Dusty was grinning as he looked over the door and the wall it was set in. “Now this looks more promising.”

“Yeah,” Starlight said, the corners of her eyes wrinkling with a grin. “Nopony makes a room like that unless they want to keep something important in it.”

I nodded along. “So, how do we get in?”

“Can either of you salvage experts pick a lock?”

Starlight gave a short, humorless laugh. “It looks like they took a chisel to the lock,” Starlight said, opening her bags and rooting around. “I doubt anypony could pick it, now.” A moment later, she pulled out a pair of dark goggles, minus the strap, and what I soon discovered was a hoof-held cutting torch. “But don’t you worry. I got this.”

We stepped back as she moved in, not toward the lock itself, but the heavy hinges on the opposite side. She started to cut, and we looked away, watching the sharp shadows dancing around the room as she worked.

Less than a minute later, the torch winked out, and she gave a satisfied laugh. We turned back as she pulled out a small pry bar, wedging it into the gap of the door, and pushed. It took several tries and a bit of grunting before a grinding sound emanated from the door, and with one final push of the bar, the severed hinges slid free and the back corner of the door thumped down to the floor.

“Stand back,” Starlight called out as she took a step away, and we held back as the door teetered and fell outward. The top crashed into the opposite wall, tearing into the sheet metal and denting the support behind it before coming to a halt barely a foot from the ground.

Eager to see what we had uncovered, we entered the room.

The first thing I noticed were the many different shelves, the lockers, and the two dead ponies lying in the center of the room. It was a strange relief that these bodies were unlike the ones outside. They had been there much longer, possibly since the war itself. Nothing remained of them but skeletons and the strips of cloth that had once been uniforms.

That relief was slightly spoiled on seeing the jagged, gaping holes missing from the back of each pony’s skull, and the old-model service rifle laid across the abdomen of one of them. The implication was clear to me, but where the scenes outside had evoked horror, this one produced a sympathetic sadness.

We didn’t linger long on that before turning to the contents of the room.

As it turns out, the locked and heavily reinforced room was an armory.

Granted, it was an armory for a small army depot well away from the frontlines, and it was equipped as such. We didn’t find a grand arsenal of military weapons, but we found enough that it began to look like the trip might be worthwhile after all. Dusty and Starlight worked together for once as they stripped the small armory, sorting the contents into two sets. One consisted of the items that were in good condition, while the second, larger group included all those that were not.

By the time we had finished, there were three old service rifles, complete with slings and cleaning kits, ten pistols with holsters, and three grenades. Aside from the weapons, there were also a half dozen ratty uniforms, which we tossed aside, and helmets, which were added to the pile. Of the firearms, only three of the pistols were judged to be in acceptable condition. None of the rifles made the cut, though Dusty noted one of the rifles as being “pretty close”. There was also an impressive amount of ammo, totaling about three hundred rounds for both the rifles and pistols. Dusty had put most of those in the “questionable” pile, and was in the process of doing the same with the magazines.

“Well, it’s not great, but it should get us some good caps,” Dusty said. “There’s always a market for guns and ammo.”

I saw a different opportunity for advancement, however. “Would you mind if I keep one of those pistols?” I asked. “It’s the model I trained on, and I’d like to have an alternative to this rifle.” And as much as I disliked this whole deal of needing to be armed, I’d much rather one that was small and easy to conceal. Consider it an old habit, if you must.

“Fine with me,” Dusty said with a shrug, looking over one of the rifle magazines. “You can do whatever you want with your share of the loot.”

I picked one of the “good” pistols, checking it over. My firearm training had been a long time ago—even perceptually speaking—but I still remembered my lessons well enough for that. To tell the truth, I may have made a little bit of a show of checking over the weapon. Showing competency with firearms seemed like a good way of earning some degree of respect from Dusty, which could only smooth things over for the rest of our outing.

With my check of the weapon done, I slid in one of the “good” magazines, loaded with “good” ammunition. Then I hesitated. My instructor had focused primarily on firearm safety, with marksmanship as a largely secondary concern. One of the lessons of that training was to only chamber a round when a shooting engagement was likely.

Reluctantly, I pulled back the slide. The Wasteland is a dangerous place.

I engaged the safety and slid the pistol into its holster. Then it was just a matter of finding the best place to strap it. The outside of the right foreleg, like Starlight wore hers, seemed the most sensible position. I strapped it on, testing out the fit and position. It put the pistol’s bit within easy reach, while keeping it out of the way of the rifle’s stock. It was acceptable.

The holster also had a pouch for a pair of spare magazines, so I picked out two more and loaded them up. I tried not to think too much on the size of arsenal I was quickly amassing.

“Looks good on you,” Starlight said, sharing a smile. I had more mixed thoughts on the subject, as I wasn’t sure I liked the fashion statement it made. Despite that, it was clear she meant it as a compliment, so I smiled back. She seemed happy with the reaction. “So, we should get back to the warehouse. There are a few crates of stuff that might get us good caps.”

“You two go ahead,” Dusty said, picking up one of the rifles. “I’m going to see if I can get one of these fixed up.”

“Sure thing,” Starlight said, while I enjoyed the improvement in her mood. “Oh, and when you’re done here, maybe look around, see if there’s a wagon or cart or anything we can use to haul stuff. The more we can carry, the more caps we make.”

“Sounds good,” Dusty said, and we parted ways. We remained silent, holding our breath as we passed the bodies, until we emerged into the warehouse proper once again.

“Okay,” Starlight said, leading the way. “Let’s get that crate of servos open and emptied out, then we can look for other good stuff.”

“Rust was wanting machine parts,” I said, trying to remember the exact list Scrap had rattled off. “I remember rubber was important. Lubricant and bearings. Oh, and tools.”

“Oh, tools! We’ll have to swing back by that motorwagon, they had a bunch out there. Those should sell well.”

She broke out the pry bar once again to pry the lid off the crate she had indicated before, the nails squealing loudly as they resisted. “Soooo,” she said as she shifted to pry further down the lid. “What did you say to Dusty that got him to pull his head out of his ass?”

I shrugged. “I think he’s got trust issues. You heard what happened with the last pony he worked with. He seems pretty nice when he isn’t trying to drive us away. I basically just pointed that out and convinced him he didn’t need to do that with us.”

“Huh.” She gave another sharp pull of the pry bar, and the lid finally came free. “Surprised that worked.”

“He’ll probably be a bit critical of our fighting ability,” I said as I took one end of the lid and helped her haul it off. “But let’s face it, neither of us are really hardened soldiers.”

“Yeah, well, he doesn’t have to be a dick about it.”

We dropped the lid to the ground, returning to the crate to begin unloading it. “No, and I told him so,” I said. “I expect he’ll still have some criticisms to make, but hopefully he might be convinced to be more helpful about it.”

She snorted, pulling apart the packaging to retrieve the contents. “I don’t need his help. I was hunting with my mom since I could float a rifle, and I’m an excellent shot.”

“Oh, I know,” I said, nodding along as I helped. “It’s just that I imagine he’s got a lot more experience with the tactical side of a firefight. Sounds like he’s been doing that sort of thing for a while. He might have some useful things we could learn.”

She grunted. “Yeah, I’d rather just get this all done with and ditch the dumb prick.”

I resisted the urge to sigh. Things would go much smoother if ponies would just get along. Instead, I was stuck in a much trickier situation: trying to convince two ponies of very different mindsets to react the way I wanted them to react. I cast a quick glance toward the back door, making sure Dusty wasn’t listening in, and spoke slightly quieter. “Just play gentle with him. I may have convinced him to be a bit nicer, but he seems pretty quick to upset.”

“Right,” she said, smirking. “Coddle the big baby, got it.”

I chuckled softly, even though I found the situation anything but funny. “Something like that. It’s more that we can avoid a lot of headaches by playing along.”

She paused, leaning on the edge of the crate. “Eh. Yeah, I guess you’re right.” She smiled, slowly. “Sneaky little Whisper. I like it.”

We chuckled quietly, continuing to unload the crate. When we finished there, we moved on to other crates, following the inventory Starlight had discovered. Before long the servos had been joined by a case of industrial lubricant, 8 large rolling bearings, and a whole crate of pneumatic hoses. The final crate we opened held four high-energy power distribution arrays. They were bulky devices, intended to split the powerful output of large-scale spark generators, and full of all sorts of electronics that might fetch good prices from Emerald.

We were just unloading it when Dusty walked up to the loading dock. “Found a cart,” he said around his cigarette, and shrugged off the collar. The cart it was attached to was small, with spiked poles rising from each corner, and the rickety wood frame was splashed in purple paint that had long ago faded. “We’ll need to strip it, though. I’m pretty sure it belonged to these ponies, and we don’t want the problems it’ll bring if somepony recognizes it.”

It was quick work to pull the poles off and scrape away the chipped paint, and soon we were loading our loot into the wagon. That loot joined the weapons Dusty had already loaded into it, which included his old pipe rifle. He had one of the service rifles strapped across his back, instead. Even though I really wanted to get out of there and have a chance to just think and sort things out, it seemed like a good opening. Put the mission before personal comfort, and all that. “Got that one working, then?” I asked rhetorically.

“Yep,” he said, giving a little shrug of his shoulder to shift the rifle. “Picked out the best parts and oiled her up. Should do well. It’s not quite what I’d prefer, but it beats the hell out of a cheap pipe rifle.”

“Equestrian Army Service Rifle, Infantry, Model 3.” I couldn’t help but smirk a little at the way his eyebrow quirked upward at that. “The first self-loading service rifle. Not as common as the later Model 4, but I’ve heard good things about them.”

“Yes. Well.” Dusty shrugged again. “It’s also a lot heavier, and kicks like a mule. I guess the effective range is a bit longer, but it’s not as flexible. Not as good for suppressing fire, for example.” He frowned, then shook his head. “Guess it might fit my situation a bit better now, though. I’m too used to fighting in a team.”

“Well, you’ve got a team for now,” I said, giving as genuine-looking of a smile as I could manage. “At least until we’re done with the job. And heck, my rifle’s pretty much only good for suppressive fire.”

I felt a little proud of myself as he chuckled. Combine a little bit of Ironshod Firearms internal design documents, a passing interest in military developments, a couple classes of very basic firearm safety, and a good deal of faking it, and even I could look like I knew what I was talking about.

We finished loading the cart, including a quick trip out to grab the tools near the motorwagon, while Starlight gave the inventory one final read-through. “Yeah, I’m not really seeing much else here, unless somepony wants to buy about five hundred tons of concrete. I don’t think anything else would be worth the weight to haul back.” She closed the folder. “Kind of annoying that they had two crates of cider but not a single piece of food. Who planned that?”

“Let’s get going,” Dusty said, sliding his rifle to the side as he slipped the cart’s collar on once again. “If we make a good push, we can probably get back to Gemstone before it’s too dark to travel.”

With our carefully selected load of salvage, the cart gave only the barest squeal of protest as it started to roll. I almost started feeling good that something had gone right. Of course, we had to roll past several decaying and mutilated ponies on our way out. It’s fair to say that put a damper on things. One could pretend the corpses weren’t there when they were out of sight—and smell—but it’s much harder when you’re walking past the bodies as crows picked away at them.

Passing through the gate, I slowed, looking at torso-pony once again. I couldn’t help it. It was just so grotesque, so violent, so sadistic.

The few scraggly remnants of purple fur rustled in the dry breeze, the one last hint of what that pony had once been. Soon even that would be gone.

“I feel like we should do something about them,” I said, my voice somber. “It doesn’t feel right just leaving them like this.”

“They were raiders,” Dusty called back, his pace never wavering. “Fuck ‘em.”

I winced at the coldness.

Starlight stepped up beside me. “Come on, Whisper,” she said, her voice soft and quiet. Comforting. She tried to give a sympathetic smile, though given our surroundings, it ended up as more of a grimace. “Crows have to eat, too.”

I sighed, turning away from the desecrated body. “Yeah,” I murmured, and followed along, while my imagination pictured black forms feasting on ponies.

We all have to eat.

Chapter Seven: A Job Well Done

We put our commandeered wagon out of our misery on the slope below Gemstone.

The rickety thing had started breaking down barely an hour out of the depot, when one of the wheels started to wobble. We had to make a couple of stops to shore it up, but it kept getting worse and worse. I’m surprised it made it as far as it did.

It seems the jolt of crossing the old train tracks below Gemstone was a bit too much to expect of the decrepit vehicle. The joint that held the wheel to the axle gave one final wobble, and then splintered and broke free, followed by the crash of the wagon collapsing to the ground.

We gathered up our spilled loot, loosely tying things together with pneumatic hoses so we could balance them across our backs. Sure, we probably could have patched up the wagon for the last quarter-mile of travel, but we were ready to be done with the thing. Starlight even pulled out her Recharger and put a shot into the wreck, for good measure.

We trudged up the slope toward the lights shining in the rapidly growing darkness, grumbling and grunting the whole way.

“I swear,” Starlight said as she took slow, laborious steps. “I need to find some sort of spell that can bring ponies back from the dead.” She grunted as she shifted her load. “And then we can go back there and revive those raiders so I can kill them again.”

I disliked this more bloodthirsty side of Starlight, even if I was fairly certain she wasn’t serious. I also found it slightly concerning that the first objection to come to mind was related to the difficulty of casting such a spell, if it even existed, rather than objecting over its intended use.

While I had the lightest load, I was still struggling to keep up with my companions. It seemed a perpetual state of fatigue was to be my fate, or so I had grumpily thought to myself at the time. I was physically and mentally exhausted. Everything else was falling into the background. I wanted nothing more than to collapse somewhere safe and sleep. My mission could wait until I was in any shape to do anything about it.

The one comfort I had during that agonizing little hike was Starlight expressing similar sentiments. “Ugh. I am so done with all of this,” she grumbled, shifting her load once again, though I doubt it helped any more than all the other times she tried it. Up ahead, Dazzle gave us a wave from atop the wall, before turning back to call for the gate to be opened. “Screw the salvage,” Starlight said. “That can wait for morning. Hell, even my Lancer can wait for morning. All I want to do is find a nice, comfy bed. A place like this has to have something.”

Still struggling to stay upright, I somehow managed to balance that task with talking. “Emerald runs the inn, if I remember correctly.”

“To Emerald, then!” Starlight called out, though the enthusiasm was a bit dampened by a stumble in mid-declaration. “I knew I liked her for a good reason.”

Dusty gave a faint, muffled snort of amusement. Or maybe derision. I’m not entirely certain.

Perhaps it was the exhaustion, or perhaps it was just the depressing day that seemed to drag on and on, but Dusty’s hint of amusement—I assumed it was amusement—seemed to plant the idea in my head to brighten the mood. I immediately thought of the blush she had shown during our previous encounter with Emerald. So, in an effort to lighten the mood, and maybe even shore up her self-esteem, I said, “I think she might like you, too.”

If I’d been less exhausted, I might have been a bit more cautious about trying a delicate social maneuver like that. There was a fairly narrow window between excessive taunting that could damage the relationship I had built up with her, and encouraging somepony into another relationship that could detract from it. Looking back, I’m not sure if it would have mattered. My misjudgement had taken place the day before, when I had been in a considerably better state of mind.

“Oh?” she asked, making it another two steps before some further implications of the simple statement processed. She almost stumbled again, her nose scrunching up. “Eww, Whisper! Gross.”

Needless to say, that was not the response I was expecting. “Eww?” I asked from under my small mountain of salvage.

“Yeah, eww,” she said, sticking out her tongue as if she’d tasted something rotten. “She’s, like, thirty years older than me!”

Dusty gave another snort; while my attempt to brighten Starlight’s mood seemed to be falling short, it seemed to have done an excellent job with him. “What are you, two?” he asked.

The look Starlight gave him was one of ultimate shock and betrayal, which seemed a bit ironic with how often the two had been butting heads during our short journey. “Dusty, what the hell?”

He was smiling, even if he tried unsuccessfully to hide it. “It’s just that she can’t be that much over thirty, and if she’s thirty years older than you…”

Starlight groaned. “Oh, fine. So it’s like… ten or fifteen years, whatever. Point is, she’s a lot older than me.” She snorted, looking away. “Besides, I’m not into mares.”

“Uh-huh,” Dusty said, in a tone that made it clear he wasn’t buying it. “So Whisper having to get her own bedding wasn’t some lover’s spat, then?”

That brought Starlight’s blush back full-force. “What? No, it’s not like that!”

I almost winced at her reply. It wasn’t for being “shunned”. It was because of how poorly she worded her reply. Some ponies can’t even tell the truth convincingly.

I had to come to her defense. “I didn’t have any supplies,” I said. “After the raiders hit our caravan, we were stuck with only enough bedding for one pony, but we’re good friends, so we shared.”

“Uh-huh,” Dusty said again as he led us through the gates.

“I’m not into mares!” Starlight said again. “It wasn’t like that.”

“If you say so,” Dusty said. “Sure heard a lot of rustling around that first night.”

“It was a small bed!” Starlight said, her voice rising. “There wasn’t enough room for both of us to get comfortable!”

Dusty barely held back a chuckle. “Uh-huh.”

“I like stallions!”

Starlight froze at the snicker that came from above us.

“Aw, you’re breaking my heart, little Star!”

Starlight slowly looked up to meet the cheshire grin of Dazzle, lounging against her plasma cannon. “But don’t you worry,” Dazzle said, giving a wink. “I’m pretty sure every stallion in town heard you there.”

Starlight stood there, stuck between crushing embarrassment and horror. She finally turned away, as if to use the large pile of salvage as a shield, and hustled as best as she could under that weight toward Emerald’s shop. I hung back just long enough to shoot Dazzle a dirty glare before following.

Emerald was kicked back behind the counter when we entered, reading on her PipBuck. She lit up the moment she saw us—and possibly the amount of material we had brought to trade—and quickly stood, making her way around the counter. “Well, well! It’s good to see you three again, and so soon! I take it the trip went well?”

Starlight halted, a blush still coloring her cheeks. “Uh, y-yeah. I guess so? Kind of.”

“Well now, it sounds like there’s an interesting story behind that answer.”

Starlight hesitated, and I stepped forward again, despite my exhaustion. “Maybe we could tell the story in the morning? We’re just about dead on our hooves and need a place to sleep. We can tell you all about it while we trade some of this salvage.”

She nodded, smiling graciously. “Of course. You three have probably had a long day; I won’t keep you up any longer. We’ve got regular rooms for eight caps, or one of the bigger upstairs suites for twenty.”

“Just a regular room,” Starlight said.

“Sure thing,” Emerald said with a nod. “Though, um, it might be a little cozy fitting three ponies in one bed.”

The playful smile she gave brought Starlight’s blush back in full force. Starlight quickly gestured toward Dusty. “He can pay for his own room.”

Dusty just snickered.

After looking around at the three of us, Emerald asked, “So am I going to get this story in the morning, too?”

“There’s no story,” Starlight quickly said. “He’s just being a pervert.” She tried to change the subject by digging out some caps, but Emerald just held up a hoof.

“You can pay me in the morning.” She pointed the same hoof to the doorway in the back of the shop. “All the ground-floor rooms are vacant. Just grab whichever one you want, and get some sleep. I’ll see you in the morning.”

We thanked her—although Starlight’s came out half-mumbled—and made our way further in. Starlight and I claimed the first room, and faced only a little bit of difficulty getting the couple hundred pounds of salvage through the doorway. Dusty left his load with us, to sell in the morning, and headed off to his own room.

While small, it was very nice and well-kept. A shuttered window would let in light during the day, and a rotary switch by the door controlled a simple ceiling light. Though there was only the single bed, it was a large one, and in very good condition for being two centuries old. It was topped with several pillows and a thick comforter, and looked like the most wonderful thing in the world.

With Dusty out of sight, Starlight was a lot less awkward about sharing a bed again. That, or she was simply too tired to care, a sentiment I could certainly agree with. She quickly shed her saddlebags, dumping them unceremoniously on the floor, and slipped in under the covers. I made sure to give her plenty of room when I joined her.

I went out so quickly that I hardly remembered crawling into bed.

☢

I slept in fits and starts.

I had no problem getting to sleep. The fatigue took care of that. I had hardly drifted off when I was awake again, my heart pounding and my throat tight. I would calm down again, and fatigue would take hold once more, and the cycle would repeat. The night passed in a slow blur, an indistinct jumble of dreams and wakefulness.

When light started to seep around the edges of the window shutters, I gave up on sleep. Physically, I was rested, yet I felt every bit as exhausted as I had the night before.

Starlight was already up, sitting on the floor and fiddling with one of the door servos we had salvaged from the depot. She stopped as I pushed the blanket aside and heaved myself up into a sitting position. “Hey, Whisper.” Her words were soft, almost delicate, and when I looked back to her, I could see the worry in her eyes. “Are you okay?”

“Yeah,” I said, though it sounded doubtful even to my own ears. “That is, as okay as I can be, all things considered.”

The worried expression didn’t go away as she set the servo aside. She seemed hesitant, but forced herself to speak. “I... heard you crying last night. I was just… worried for you.”

“Oh.” My expression, already slack and bleary, fell further. My ears hung low, my eyes drifting down to the floor. “Sorry. It’s been a rough couple of days.”

Starlight nodded, though the motion came slowly. “Was it about what Dusty was saying?”

In my state, it took me a few moments to realize what she was talking about. She wasn’t asking about what Dusty had said, himself. The conclusions she had drawn from the previous evening were so far off the mark that it took little effort to crack a weak smile. “I wouldn’t listen to Dusty. He doesn’t know what he’s talking about.”

“Yeah,” Starlight agreed, without conviction.

The smile I had conjured died away. She was drawing all the wrong conclusions, and that could only lead to problems. As much as I would have preferred to avoid lingering on those details, I knew it was a mistake I would have to correct. I sighed, and spoke again. “I was dreaming about my mother.”

That caught her attention, her ears perking up. I continued on. “And then I started mixing in stuff from the depot, yesterday, and…” I trailed off, shuddering. It wasn’t even an act. I actually, physically shuddered. Just a week ago, seeing my Queen’s empty husk had been the absolute height of horror. I knew now that it could have been worse. As terrible as it had been to see her body lying there, hollow and devoid of life, there was at least some sense of peace and stillness. After the carnage of the army depot, my imagination had gone to great lengths to show me just how much worse it could have been.

I’d been so caught up in my own emotions that I hadn’t noticed Starlight moving until she wrapped me in a hug. I hugged back, almost mechanically, and we held each other as I focused on breathing slowly and smoothly.

At the same time, I could feel that the sense of affection Starlight held for me had grown stronger. I drew on a tiny bit of that feeling. It was just a nibble, too little to actually make a difference for either of us, but I still found it encouraging. I think I needed that at the time. The faint tremble that had persisted finally faded away.

She eventually released the hug, sitting beside me on the bed. We sat in silence for some time before she spoke. “What was she like?” she asked. “Your mother.”

My first reaction was to evade, to avoid the subject and steer the conversation toward something else, but I realized that wouldn’t work. So I took another deep breath, and focused on the task at hoof. “She was… wonderful. She was wise and brilliant, and always seemed to know the right thing to say to make you feel better. She was kind. And… and she always made me feel like she was proud of me.”

I realized then that I was smiling. My throat was tight, and my eyes watered, but I was smiling, even if it was still faint. I blinked back the growing tears and looked to Starlight. She was smiling, too, and when our eyes met, she gave me a little nod.

Then she chuckled and looked away. “My mom was the coolest mom ever. Like, total badass, but laid back about it. She taught me everything I know about scavenging, shooting, stuff like that. Guess she was like a role model or something. I want to be just like her.”

I nodded, my smile growing a bit more. “I know the feeling.”

Starlight looked back to me. We sat in comfortable silence for a couple of seconds before she asked, “What was her name?”

I hesitated. There had been only a few dozen ponies who knew of my Queen’s name, and it struck me as exceptionally unlikely that the information would have survived the intervening apocalypse and two hundred years’ wait, and even more unlikely that they would think to connect the two. That miniscule risk was outweighed by the benefits of being able to use the truth, rather than having to create and remember a lie. Besides, if giving a name helped Starlight bond with me, it would be a secret well-spent. “Her name was Ephema.”

Starlight cocked her head to the side. I’d heard many different kinds of pony names—though I had no idea if naming conventions might have changed over two hundred years!—but that was evidently not the kind of name she had expected. “Huh. Neat name.” She shrugged. “Mine was Midnight.”

I nodded, and we fell into silence once again.

It didn’t last long before Starlight rose to her hooves. “We should get out there before Dusty gets more stupid ideas.” She gave a nervous chuckle. “We need to sell off all this stuff, too.”

I agreed, and we gathered up our salvage once again.

☢

While Starlight talked with Emerald, I wandered the store.

I’ll admit, there was a little bit of discomfort at leaving an inherently adversarial social interaction in the hooves of someone else. I was used to depending on my own abilities in that field, and as much as I like her, Starlight didn’t strike me as having a very diverse range of social skills; she was friendly and energetic—at least when she wasn’t butting heads with Dusty—but those did not translate into being particularly good at bartering. Despite that, I felt like my hooves were tied. She had experience salvaging, and I assumed that must include experience in selling that salvage. I also lacked a firm understanding of how much value different items demanded, and of how that value translated to the new bottlecap standard.

I suspect my incredulity at the particular form of currency was not aiding my attempts to understand the Wasteland’s economy.

The shelves of goods bore only a vague resemblance to the shops I had been used to before the end. I suppose an antique shop or thrift store might be the closest comparison; old and used items that covered a broad spectrum of goods, often with signs of old repairs. There was no packaging, much less the rows of identical pristine items, fresh off the assembly lines, that filled the shelves of the major stores.

I spent a lot of time looking, though there was little that I had any real interest in buying. Mostly, I was satisfying my curiosity while gathering potentially useful information: what sort of items might be available in the Wasteland.

The barding got a bit more interest, though. Even at the time, I recognized the thought process that had drawn my attention. With everything that had happened, I was feeling particularly vulnerable. Alone, having narrowly escaped death from multiple sources, and most recently, having received a vivid picture of what could happen to me if things went wrong. Barding might be little more than a safety blanket, but I had to consider that the possible peace-of-mind it could bring me might allow me to focus more on important matters.

Of course, that line of thought had a troubling number of conditional statements, not to mention my natural revulsion toward the idea of self-deception. Most importantly, the same logical process that led me to recognize the possible emotional benefit would likely strip me of most of that benefit. It’s hard to trick yourself when you know you’re trying to do so. I would still be vulnerable; the solution was not to delude myself into thinking I wasn’t, but to act accordingly.

That said, barding could offer some degree of physical protection, which made it worth considering. Physical dangers were best defended against through avoidance, but it seemed likely I wouldn’t be able to depend on such protection.

Which meant it all boiled down to a simple, logical weighing of costs versus benefits. That was something I could do.

Barding gave protection, but the better the protection, the more it would weigh. I did not yet have a source of food sufficient to sustain a high-strength form. I could wear very light barding, which would do little more than protect from scrapes, bruises, and the elements, or I could wear heavier barding that might protect from more significant threats, but in turn slowed me. That didn’t strike me as a particularly good trade. Looking over the few outfits in Emerald’s shop made the prospects look even more limited. With them all being of post-war construction, the only one that looked as if it would provide decent protection against firearms also looked to be far too heavy for me.

I was also wary of something so constrictive. It would limit my abilities to transform, should the need arise. A form with a smaller frame would find the armor suddenly loose and encumbering; a form with a larger frame would be uncomfortable or impossible. On top of that, none of the armors were designed for pegasi, eliminating the possibility of taking a flying form. Sure, I was hoping to avoid the need to transform, as that would rather blow my cover and complicate my mission, but I disliked the idea of limiting my options unnecessarily.

And of course, there was the cost of, well, cost. We hadn’t made enough yet to be making purchases that weren’t necessary, and by the sounds of Starlight and Emerald’s negotiations, we weren’t making the small fortune we had set out imagining. Not that I fault Starlight’s bartering for that; if anything, I got the impression Emerald was being quite generous with her prices. I’d caught hints of surprise in Starlight’s voice at some of the prices offered.

Though I dismissed the armored barding, I did consider some of the clothing. I wouldn’t mind something to protect me from the elements, even if Starlight had assured me that storms of such intensity were rare.

The other group of items I considered were weapons; and yes, the fact that only two categories I considered to be worth investigating were weapons and armor did trouble me, if somewhat less than it might have a few days earlier.

I skipped right over the small assortment of melee weapons; if things ever descended to the point where such a weapon was useful, it had gotten excessively desperate to the point that I might as well shed my disguise and try to use my magic to fight back. The other option would be to die, which would reveal my true nature anyway. If I had to be discovered, I’d much prefer the option that leaves me alive.

Admittedly, browsing Emerald’s small selection of firearms was somewhat pointless. I already had a pistol I was familiar with. The rifle I had acquired from Sharps worked well enough, given my poor skill with it. An upgrade seemed decadent when the differences would largely be wasted on me. Still, I looked. If nothing else, it would give a good idea of what sort of threats I might face.

For better or worse, the selection was slim. I barely even looked at the post-war weapons, which consisted of a pair of mismatched rifles and a clunky looking revolver, and instead turned to the old-world relics on display.

There wasn’t much selection. There was a huge drum-fed Equestrian Army combat shotgun that hurt my teeth just to look at, a small-caliber civilian bolt-action rifle of some sort, one of those submachine guns that Ironshod had been trying to convince the Army to buy in bulk for vehicle crews and support personnel, and no less than three pistols identical to my own.

The item that caught my attention the most wasn’t one of the weapons. Instead, it was an attachment on one of those weapons: a suppressor.

The cost/benefit analysis immediately labeled it of little benefit. If I needed to shoot my weapon, volume was likely to be unimportant. Still, I couldn’t help but consider the idea of it opening my possibilities. Perhaps I still entertained a little bit of those assassin and commando fantasies. It seemed unlikely that I would need to quietly remove a pony, but it was possible that could be useful at some point in the future. And, judging from what I had seen of raiders, there were certainly some ponies whose death could only be an improvement for the world.

So I decided to inquire about its cost. If it was too expensive, perhaps I should make my own. I had been taught how they worked, and they were simple devices. It would probably be cheaper. Still, a professionally made suppressor made to carefully researched designs was sure to be superior to anything I could craft.

I returned to the front counter of the store to find the bartering complete, with Starlight idly rolling a small bag of caps in her hooves as the two mares talked.

“I’ve been to a lot of places before settling down here,” Emerald was saying, “but I’ve never been there. Everything I heard of Dodge City sounded like trouble. I can’t imagine living there.”

“Oh, I didn’t live there!” Starlight said with a laugh. “But we did go in there a couple times a month. Heck, I pretty much grew up there. It’s not that dangerous if you know what to look out for.” She tapped the PipBuck hanging around her neck. “Having one of these to avoid the irradiated parts helps, too.”

“They’re very helpful things,” Emerald agreed. “So if not there, where did you live?”

“Oh, a little place called Dodge Junction. Wasn’t much to talk about.”

“Ah, I went through there, once,” Emerald said, smiling. “Seemed like a nice place. Well, except for the creepy dead orchard.”

“Yeah, you got that right,” Starlight said with a laugh. “Anyway, how about you? You mentioned all the places you’ve been before coming here. Where’d you start out?”

Emerald’s smile slipped, and she hesitated before replying. “Ehh… a little place called Serenity.” Her smile turned wry. “Just a free survival tip: if the first thing you think of when hearing about a place is, ‘hey, that sounds nice,’ be suspicious.”

I saw Starlight’s skeptical expression, but she didn’t inquire. I, however, found myself curious at the apparent double-standard. “I don’t mean any offense, but Gemstone does have a certain ‘too good to be true’ feel that might make certain ponies suspicious.”

Emerald laughed. “No offense taken! I couldn’t blame you for feeling a bit suspicious. Heck, I’d even go so far as to say it’s good that you are. We might be genuine, but there are far too many twisted ponies out there that use kindness as a lure.” She shook her head, her expression having fallen with that last statement, but it brightened up once again. “So I’m not even going to tell you that you don’t need to be suspicious of us. I don’t expect anypony to just take my word about it. Instead, we’ll just carry on, doing our best to show the rest of the Wasteland a better way through our example.”

Starlight cast a curious look my way before smiling at Emerald. “Well I think Gemstone seems like a lovely place, and I hope more ponies start thinking the same way. The world could use more good ponies.”

“That it could, hon,” Emerald agreed. “There are too few of them, these days.”

Starlight slowly nodded. “Is that why you left Serenity?”

Again, the older mare’’s expression fell, and there was a moment of silence before she replied. “Kind of, but not exactly. They’re not really bad, just far less friendly than you’d think with a name like that. They didn’t like outsiders. Too many raiders and slavers and such, so they keep others at a distance; by force, if necessary.” She smirked. “Was kind of a problem for me. I like meeting new ponies. So I headed out here.”

“Sounds like a Stable,” Starlight said, earning a dry chuckle from Emerald.

“It was about as isolationist as one,” she said. “Still, my family lives there. I’d like to see them again, some day. I don’t think they’re bad ponies. Just… wrong.” She shook her head and shrugged. “But, hey, maybe if what we’re practicing here starts to spread, they’ll see that ponies aren’t that bad.”

Starlight nodded. “Well, I hope you have luck with that. It’d be nice.”

“Thank you,” Emerald said. “I hope you three have luck, too. You all seem like nice ponies, and it’s like you said; the world could use more good ponies.”

“Thanks,” Starlight said, then frowned. “Wait, three? You mean Dusty, too?”

“I do,” Emerald said with a nod. “He might act all gruff and cynical, but he strikes me as a good pony under all that.”

“Yyyyeah,” Starlight said, cocking an eyebrow. “If you say so.”

“I like to think of myself as being pretty good at reading ponies,” Emerald said, shrugging. “He’s been hurt by other ponies, but I don’t think he’s given up on them yet. But we’ll see, I’m sure. If nothing else, he’s helping you two.”

“It’s just for the one job,” Starlight said.

“Ah. Well I hope you two stay safe once that’s over with.” She chuckled as she pointed a hoof at the bag of caps Starlight was still playing with. “Speaking of which, I’ve got plenty of protection for sale if you’re looking to send some of those caps back this way.”

Starlight chuckled. “Thanks, but I think I’m good for now. I might be back for some of that barding once we’ve got a bit more caps to spare.” Having said that, she looked my way. “Unless you’ve spotted something you want? A quarter of these are yours, after all.”

She shook the bag, which jingled and clanked in the most un-musical fashion possible.

“There was something I was considering,” I said. “I saw that one of the pistols had a suppressor attached. I was curious if you’d be willing to sell it separately, and if so, for how much?”

“Ah, so Whisper likes it quiet, does she?” Emerald chuckled softly. “That’s a fairly uncommon item, but one that seems to have rather little demand. I could sell it for twenty-five… no, twenty caps.”

I contemplated that for a couple of seconds before concluding I had no idea if that was a good value. I turned to Starlight and asked, “Does that sound like a fair price?”

She was already digging out the caps. “Oh yeah,” she said, counting out the little metal trinkets.

Emerald opened the back of the display cabinet holding the pistols, and retrieved the weapon in question. Holding the grip in her teeth, she spun the suppressor between her hooves until it slid free, and held it out to me. “‘Ere eh oh,” she grunted around the bit before setting the weapon back in its place. “Make sure it fits right.”

I copied her actions in reverse, while she swept away the tiny offering of caps without even counting them. It was awkward, lining it up while holding the gun in my mouth with my vision limited, but I managed. “Looks good,” I finally said, giving it a little tug to ensure it was firmly in-place.

“I’d give it a few test-fires, just to make sure everything’s running smoothly.” Then she smiled. “Just, not in my shop, please.”

“Of course,” I said, and went to holster it. Then I stopped, realizing I had a new problem. “Right. I might need a new holster, too.”

“Oh yeah. What do you have there?” She leaned over the counter, looking at the holster strapped to my leg. “Oh, Army holster. One of the good ones, too. Pass it over here. I’ll cut a hole and stitch the edges for you.”

I happily unstrapped it and passed it to her.

Dusty’s voice came from right behind me. “Seriously?”

Naturally, the first reaction I had was to look at him. That resulted in my newly purchased suppressor smacking into the hoof he quickly put in its way. “Watch your muzzle, kid!”

I recoiled, turning my head away and down as I looked at him out of the corner of my eye, pointing my pistol away from him. I felt like a fool, especially for how easily I had slipped into such casual treatment of a very lethal weapon. Just in case my shame wasn’t complete, my assumed body betrayed me, a blush spreading across my cheeks.

“And seriously, a suppressor for your pistol?” Dusty frowned as he stared down at me. “Should I even ask what you plan on doing with that? Or about where you plan on getting subsonic ammo for it?”

Hoping to redeem myself in some small degree, I quickly—but quietly—spoke up. “Reducing the powder load by thirty percent puts the standard Equestrian Army ten-millimeter round below the speed of sound, while retaining enough energy to reliably cycle the weapon. I can do that with just a pair of pliers, if I have to.” My barely remembered improvised tools and methods training came to the rescue as Dusty’s frown deepened at the unexpected reply. And to think, it had been entirely useless trivia up until that moment.

“Or,” Emerald cut in, “you can get some professionally made ones from my stock. I’ve got more ten-mil than I know what to do with, and if I remember correctly, a couple of them were some lightweight civilian brand. Pretty sure those were subsonic.”

She dug around behind the counter for a moment before returning, setting two faded boxes of ammunition on the counter. I took one box and looked it over. Most of the data listed on the box meant little to me, but I knew what “hollow-point” meant, and the listed muzzle velocity was subsonic. “Yeah, these could do. How much would you charge for these?”

“Nopony wants to buy low-power ammo,” Emerald said with a shrug. “Say a one-to-one trade for any regular rounds, and one-and-a-half caps per round for the rest?”

I agreed, pulling out my magazines and emptying them as she went to work on my holster. In the end, I had thirty five rounds sitting on the counter. Thirty six, once I remembered to clear the chamber. Starlight counted out six more bottlecaps, and I went through the slow process of loading the new rounds into the magazines. It was a tedious task to perform with mouth and hooves, but I managed.

By the time I was done with that and had pocketed the remaining four rounds, Emerald had finished altering my holster. I tried it on, satisfied with the fit, and slid my pistol into it. It fit well, even if it seemed strange to see the suppressor extending out of the bottom. Holstering was a little awkward with the added length, as I had to draw my head back further to clear the edge of the holster, but it was manageable. I wasn’t likely to be in any quick-draw competitions any time soon. At least, I hoped not, because that sounded like a fight I would lose.

“Are you done toy shopping?” Dusty dryly asked, while Starlight rolled her eyes in reply.

“I think that will do,” I replied, then offered Emerald a smile. “Thank you very much, for everything.”

“Of course,” she said, beaming. “I hope I’ll see you guys around soon. And if I see any more subsonics come through, I’ll make sure to snag a box for you.”

We gathered up our remaining salvage, and Emerald waved as we left. I continued to smile even after we stepped outside. It was a small thing, but it was nice to have something go right.

The moment we had stepped outside, Starlight spoke up, her voice full of tired irritation. “So what’s the problem now, Dusty?”

He shot her a glance before gesturing toward my side. “What, that? There are only two kinds of ponies who tend to get suppressors. Professionals who need them for a specific purpose, and amateurs who think they’re cool.” He gave me a pointed look. “You’re not a professional.”

“Perhaps not in the way you’re thinking,” I said, while refusing to let my smile slip. “But I do actually know what I’m doing.”

“Do you, now?” Dusty said, but Starlight cut him off before he could say any more.

“Oh, what do you even care? You’re only with us another day or so. Let’s just get this over with.” She huffed, turning away and heading down the street.

Dusty paused a moment before shrugging and following along. “Sure. Fine.”

We walked silently through the town. Starlight’s shoulders were tense and her ears were pinned back, but as we drew near Arclight’s workshop, the tension quickly faded. Her ears suddenly perked up to the sound of a hissing pop from beyond the building, her scowl quickly replaced with a grin. She broke into a trot, and we quickened our pace to keep up.

We made our way through an open gate and into a junk-filled shooting range, and Starlight let out a very filly-like squeal of glee. Arclight had the Lancer set on one of the benches, straight and whole. He looked up from his examination and smiled as he saw Starlight approaching. “Ah, good morning!”

Starlight giggled and pranced up to him, eyes lighting up. “Is it fixed?”

“Yep! It—”

He was cut off as Starlight threw her hooves around him and hugged, letting out another high-pitched sound of glee that only eventually broke out into words. “Oh, thank you, thank you, thank you!”

Despite the surprise at the sudden show of affection, Arclight managed a good-natured chuckle. “I’m glad to help,” he said, patting a hoof against her back. “Emerald told me you were back in town, so I made sure to get it done as soon as I could. Helps that none of the internals were damaged, so it was all easy stuff. I was just double-checking the alignment and sights, but it should be all good to go.”

She finally released him to turn her attention to her weapon. “So, it’s all ready? Can I fire it?”

“Of course,” he said, chuckling a bit more. “It’s your gun, after all. Just needs a freshly charged crystal and you’re set. We kind of forgot about the charging rack, but it’s no worry; I was able to rig something up.”

“Oh yeah, sorry,” Starlight said, though her attention was now focused entirely upon her Lancer. She hefted the lengthy weapon in her magic, and the handle in the rear pulled back to open the chamber. She removed the dull-red crystal within, and swapped it with a glowing one she pulled from a small case on her saddlebags; I caught the sight of another four crystals within it, resting in strange wire cradles and glowing with magic.

“Also, the sights were way off even after I straightened the frame,” Arclight said. “I didn’t know how you had them before, if you had any sort of convergence point or the like. I just sighted them in parallel to the beam, but you can always adjust that if you’d prefer.”

“That’s exactly how I like it,” Starlight said with glee as she brought the weapon close. The hairs on her cheek barely brushed against the side of the frame, one eye closing as the sight settled before the other one. She took a deep breath, then slowly let it out. As her breath ran out, she seemed frozen for just an instant; then there was the familiar sound of the weapon firing. I was close enough that I could hear the discharge of magic within the weapon itself, though it was almost entirely hidden behind the sharp snap and trailing hiss of the beam burning its way through the air.

At the end of the crude range were an array of bottles, cans, boards, and other debris that served as targets. One of those bottles flashed brilliant red and shattered, throwing off glowing embers that slowly burnt away in mid-air. Only a few pieces of molten glass peppered the ground around where the bottle had sat.

I knew magical energy weapons could be powerful, and had even fired an energy pistol in my training, but I’d rarely seen them in practice. And yes, a glass bottle is hardly the most durable of targets to demonstrate a weapon’s power upon, but it had vaporized most of the bottle’s mass, as if burning it to a fine ash. Glass is not terribly known for its flammable properties.

Okay, so it probably turned it to gas rather than literally burning it. I don’t have a clue what kinds of temperatures and energies that involves, but that’s still pretty scary.

Starlight slowly lowered the weapon, grinning. She looked back to me, blinking a couple times, then stepped in and gave me a hug. I accepted it gracefully as she buried her head next to mine, eyes closed to hide how they had watered up. Dusty made a point of looking away.

I could feel the love flowing out from her. It was more than a simple liking or preference. It was true love, deep and powerful, even if it felt strangely unfocused to me. It wasn’t about the gun itself. It was more sentimental. I could appreciate that.

And yes, I fed on that love. I would be a fool not to.

When she released me, the hint of tears were gone. “I’m, uh… I’m going to try a couple more shots. Just to be sure, you know?”

“Take all the time you need,” Arclight said. “And let me know if you want anything tweaked, I should be able to take care of that pretty quick.”

She thanked him and turned back to the range, and I took the chance to ask a question. “Would you mind if I fired a few rounds from my own gun?”

“Go right ahead,” he replied. “I leave the range open for anyone who wants to use it.”

I stepped up beside Starlight and drew my pistol. I gripped the bit firmly in my teeth, the stubby sights floating right before my eye. The balance felt odd, though I wasn’t sure if that was from my own lack of experience or the weight of the suppressor.

I shifted my grip slightly to line the sights up, and placed the front post directly over a tin can some twenty yards away, resting atop a bullet-riddled table. I disengaged the safety, then slowly pulled the trigger.

The gun bucked, nearly catching me by surprise with the force of it. The sharp clack of my weapon echoed for just an instant around the range, but it was dominated by the solid whack as the bullet took another chunk out of the table. It had been just a bit low and to the right. Still, not bad for a weapon I hadn’t fired in two hundred years.

Beside me, Starlight’s ear twitched, and she looked away from her own shooting to give me a worried look. “I don’t think that suppressor is, uh, suppressing.”

“Seems about right to me,” I said around my pistol’s bit. “It’s a lot quieter than a regular gunshot, at least.”

She looked unconvinced, but shrugged and returned to her own weapon.

I lined up another shot, this time adjusting up and to the left by a tiny bit. That time, the tin can spun away from the table, followed immediately by Starlight’s sharp cry. “Ow!”

I quickly looked her way, and only just stopped myself from pointing my pistol directly at her. She had a hoof to the side of her head, and was looking to me with an utterly shocked expression. That lasted for just a moment before she broke out in a laugh. “You just shot me in the head!”

That was not the response I had expected. “What?”

Through her giggling, she said, “You pulled the trigger, fired off a round…” Her horn lit up, floating up a spent casing. “...and a little piece of metal hit me in the side of the head.”

“Oh!” Her giggling was surprisingly infectious, and I soon found myself chuckling as I raised a hoof under the casing. “Heh, um, sorry.”

She just chuckled in reply as she dropped the casing into my waiting hoof. I immediately jerked back and dropped it, holding my hoof up as I stared down at the offending—and still very hot—piece of metal. “Right. That was stupid.”

“Sorry,” Starlight said, though it barely interrupted her chuckling.

“That was my fault,” I said, shaking my head. “We might want to swap places, too.”

“Yeah, I think I’ve been shot in the head enough for one day,” Starlight teased, sounding far too cheerful for such a statement. We shuffled around each other as we changed places; a quick glance back at Dusty showed him with his head bowed, a hoof resting firmly across the bridge of his nose. I didn’t hear his deep sigh, but I’m sure it was there.

Once we were re-situated, I took aim and fired a third and fourth round. My accuracy was mediocre, but the weapon itself functioned perfectly. I reengaged the safety and holstered the weapon before removing the magazine and fishing out the four spare rounds I had purchased. I reloaded the magazine, watching the rounds slide down through the small holes in the back of the magazine. Once I put the last round in, I frowned; the little holes said it was one round short of being full. It took me a couple of seconds before realization struck, and my ears dropped. “Right.”

“What’s that?” Starlight asked while lining up another shot.

“Nothing,” I said, swapping out that magazine for one of the full ones, and inserting that into my pistol.

Once he had recovered from our stunning show of competency, Dusty decided to fire off a few rounds as well. Arclight dug out some earmuffs for Starlight and myself, while Dusty used his own earplugs.

“Okay,” Starlight said, raising a hoof to her earmuffs after his first shot; I could feel the sound in my chest, if only weakly. “Yeah, I like your pistol more. Wow.”

He only fired a couple rounds at a chunk of wood on the far end of the crude range, then stopped to adjust his sights. He did that a couple more times before nodding in satisfaction, swapping out the rifle’s magazine for a full one, and slinging the weapon across his back again.

Arclight collected his earmuffs. “Come on back if you need anything. Adjustments, upgrades, repairs, whatever. I also have plenty of other weapons, and I’m always available for a commission.”

We thanked him, promising to come back if we ever needed anything else. After that, it was a short walk back to the gate. Dusty was eager to set out, as he reasoned we could make Rust before nightfall if we hurried.

Personally, I’m glad Starlight was so distracted by her weapon. She missed Dazzle’s wink, and the snicker from the stallion standing beside the guard-mare. I stared flatly at Dazzle, who at least had the good sense to raise a hoof in mock-surrender, as if saying she didn’t mean anything serious by it. She was still smiling.

We had left the town and made it halfway down the slope before Starlight could no longer contain herself. “Okay, no, I’ve got to shoot it again!” She quickly unslung the Lancer as she called out. “Hey, Dusty! You think I can’t shoot? Point to something, anything, and I’ll hit it.”

Dusty frowned as he halted, and for a moment I thought he was going to tell her no. After a moment of wavering, he rolled his eyes and gestured downslope toward the tracks. “That fence-post, just to the right of the collapsed water tower.”

“Oh, come on,” Starlight said. “That’s, like, a hundred yards at most. Give me something harder!”

“More like two hundred,” Dusty grumbled, then pointed out past the tracks. “Okay, that withered little cactus-thing with the two tops.”

Starlight rolled her eyes dramatically. “I said harder. Fine, I’ll choose.” She scanned the narrow valley for a moment, then lifted her hoof to point. “There! You see that old dead tree?”

We both looked for several seconds before Dusty finally said, “No.”

“Come on, it’s right there,” she said, jerking her hoof as if pointing harder would make it easier for us. She finally added, “Right there, on top of the hill. It’s silhouetted and everything!”

We looked up from the valley to the top of the opposite hill. It still took us a moment before we spotted the twisted remains of some long-dead tree. It was probably only a little taller than a pony, which made it hard to see at such a range.

“That tree?” Dusty asked, his voice expressing the skepticism I felt.

“Yeah, that tree,” Starlight shot back as she leveled her weapon and squinted into the sight. “How far do you think that is?”

“At least half a mile,” Dusty said. “Maybe three quarters.”

“Well, as long as Arc set these sights right…” She went silent as she took a deep breath and let it out, repeating the same procedure as before. Again, a sharp snap pierced the air.

More than half a mile away, a cloud of red embers burst forth, filling the air around the tree with motes of light that quickly burnt away. When it faded, it revealed the stubby tree slowly collapsing onto its side, with the faint light of flames dancing around the edges of a gaping hole.

Starlight lowered her weapon, grinning. “I told you I knew how to shoot.”

☢

Despite the bleak landscape and constantly overcast skies, the trip to Rust was quiet and peaceful. It was also fairly easy going; while I didn’t like being recognized as the weakest of the group, Starlight and Dusty carried most of what remained of our salvage. While my hooves were still sore from walking all day long, at least my back wasn’t aching.

Seeing Rust again was oddly bittersweet. It was still a decrepit little settlement fitting of its name, yet I couldn’t help feeling an odd sense of happiness to see its giant steel gates once again. I suppose there was some comfort in the familiar.

The gates opened, and we were met once again by a couple of armed ponies. Steel Shot was at their head. “Hey there, Dusty. Welcome back. How was the job?”

“Tedious and boring,” Dusty replied. “And not the good kind of boring, either. Didn’t turn out as well as I hoped, but it’ll pay the bills.”

“Sorry to hear that,” Steel Shot said as the gate squeaked and ground shut behind us. “Might have some good news for you, though. Some fancy-pants mare turned up just after you left, looking to hire somepony. She’s been hanging around since then, waiting for you to get back. Smells like caps to me.”

“How many caps?” Starlight asked.

The question earned a sharp glance from Dusty before he looked back to Steel Shot. “I’ll go see what she wants. She staying at Mustard’s?”

“Eeyup,” Steel Shot replied, then looked over to Starlight and myself. “Guess if you’re friends of Dusty, I can let you hang onto your guns.”

“They’re not my friends,” Dusty said, but Steel Shot just shrugged and waved a hoof.

“Coworkers, whatever.” He turned, heading back toward the overlook. “I’ll trust you to keep them in line. Good night, Dusty!”

Dusty grimaced as the other stallion walked off.

We all made our way to the foundry. Mostly, we wanted the caps. Myself, I appreciated it as being the least depressing part of the little town.

Scrap and Singe were sharing a meal when we arrived. The mare, her mane slightly shorter than the last time I met her, grinned upon seeing me. “Hey, new-face!” she called out, setting down the big bowl she had been slurping from. She stood. “Never did get your name, you know.”

“It’s Whisper,” I said, and shook her offered hoof. She greeted the other ponies with me, though she had to prompt Starlight for her name; she evidently knew of Dusty already.

“So is all that stuff for us?” she said with a playful grin and a gesture to my back.

“It is,” I said, and we set down our loads.

Singe dove right in, pulling apart the bundles and looking through the parts. “Well, they got plenty of rubber for you,” she said, tossing a couple of the hoses to Scrap. “Hydraulics. And lubricant. Lots of it, too.”

“What kind of lubricant?” Scrap asked.

His question was met with a playful smirk. “The machine kind,” she said, then slid the case toward him. “Looks like good industrial stuff. We can put that to good use.”

She turned back to the remaining items, and her eyes widened. “Oh, wow, is that… it is!” She hefted one of the large roller bearings. “What even uses bearings this size? I could rotate a building on these!”

Starlight, as our resident salvage expert, stepped in. “They came from a Stable-Tec shipment. It might have been for some big blast door.”

“That gives me some ideas,” Singe said. While she idly pondered various plans, murmuring excitedly to herself, Scrap stepped in to sort through the offering we had brought. I once again left the negotiations to Starlight. The bartering was much more involved this time, but they soon came up with numbers that left both sides satisfied. Scrap retrieved the requisite number of caps from a heavy, home-made safe, and we happily parted ways.

After splitting the caps in half, and accounting for the purchases we had made along the way, Starlight and I were a few hundred caps richer than we had been just a few days earlier. It was a small thing, but to me, it was tangible progress.

“And here’s your half,” Starlight said as she passed the bulging bag of caps to Dusty. He hefted it, eying it warily, but finally shoved it into a saddlebag.

“You two stay out of trouble. I don’t want to have to deal with it.” He turned and walked off. “Goodbye.”

Starlight stared at him, mouth hanging open and hoof half-raised as she watched him go. Soon her expression hardened into a glare. “Asshole,” she grumbled, though her expression softened as she looked at me, and she threw a foreleg around my shoulders. “Fuck it, we got our caps, it’s time to celebrate! I’m going to get the biggest, most unhealthy meal I can find and gorge myself until I pass out!”

She grinned broadly at me as she released her grip, and I smiled back. With a fresh plan at hoof, we headed toward the center of the little town. It was a detour from my grander plans, but even I had to admit that I could use a little break.

Chapter Eight: The Next Big Score

What’s the one thing I remember the most from that night?

Bacon.

It had been a bit surprising to see that bacon, and a few other kinds of meat, were even offered at the “Food” place. I hadn’t seen a single non-pony there, and couldn’t imagine they got griffon—or other!—visitors enough to regularly cater to a non-herbivorous diet. I was even more surprised when Starlight lit up upon seeing the bacon, and quickly ordered some.

Don’t get me wrong, I was quite happy to order some for myself. It was good bacon, too; nice, thick strips, and the cook prepared it almost perfectly; cooked all the way through and firming up, but not scorched and brittle like inexperienced cooks tend to make it. I enjoyed the opportunity to break from the herbivore’s diet that I had been largely restricted to during my time in Appleloosa. Ponies weren’t entirely strict vegetarians, often making use of eggs or milk in their cooking, but actual meat tended to be a bit too extreme for their tastes. A few of the more bold and experimentive ponies might try it, perhaps emulating griffons or other such cultures, so I had used that excuse to snatch the rare nibble of meat.

That ended after the second such treat in as many months, at which point I found I was getting a small reputation for it. That put a halt to my divergence from the standard pony diet, and after another month I had eradicated most traces of that reputation; to an Infiltrator, few things are as dangerous as standing out as “unusual”, even if that reputation was entirely playful.

So on the one hoof, it was a great relief to be able to broaden my dietary horizons without suffering suspicion or condescension for it.

On the other hoof, it was yet another reminder of how much things had changed.

I had many questions, ranging from cultural to historical to biological, but I set them aside for the moment and simply enjoyed my meal. I’m not normally one to set aside questions and concerns for the pursuit of personal pleasure, but I think I can make an occasional exception for really good bacon.

I did somewhat regret having to voice any concern at all, when I noted how much more expensive the meat was than the vegetables they grew there. Our funds were still quite limited. Starlight laughed softly and soothed my fears.

“Trust me. You know what the best trick is to keeping from blowing all your caps? My mom taught me; you give yourself one splurge, one little extra you’re going to get with your next big payoff, so you’re not always regretting saving everything else for more practical stuff.” She popped a slice of meat into her mouth and grinned. “And this time, I want bacon.”

So we had our little celebration, such as it was. We had a huge, tasty meal, finishing up with a whole box of snack cakes and a couple chilly bottles of Sparkle Cola. It cost us as much as several days’ worth of meals, but I couldn’t say it wasn’t worth it.

With full bellies and high spirits, we stumbled our way to Mustard’s to get a room and sleep off the excess of food.

☢

In hindsight, stuffing ourselves with fatty and sugary foods right before lying down to sleep was probably not the brightest of ideas.

My stomach, having seen such little use in the preceding centuries, was not quite ready to handle the monumental task I had set upon it. Starlight fared no better than I, leading me to wonder whether the pony digestive system was properly capable of handling the amount of greasy meat we had stuffed in it. We both woke early in the night to the bubbling and churning in our guts. We tossed and turned, keeping each other up as much as ourselves, while our stomachs slowly sorted things out. There was the occasional groan, hooves pressed to our own bellies, and at least one quick run to the toilet when our digestive tracts decided they had done all they could and quickly expelled the remains.

Relieved of their burden, our guts quickly settled down, and we drifted off, sleeping until noon.

And you know what? We still agreed that it was totally worth it.

Well, not at first. I woke to a feeling of crushing fatigue and a pounding head. I struggled to sit up, more out of determination to not remain lying there all day than a personal desire to be upright. I immediately found a bottle of water floating in front of my face.

When I pushed it weakly away—my stomach still felt a little funny—Starlight insisted. “Drink it. You’ll feel better.”

While I could have argued with her, it didn’t feel like a worthwhile expenditure of energy. I took a small drink at first, but under Starlight’s continuing insistence, I downed the whole bottle. I felt bloated afterwards, and lay down once again. But you know what? Just ten or twenty minutes later, I was feeling much better. I didn’t feel as worn out, and that headache was quickly receding into the background.

Starlight smiled, looking quite proud of herself.

Feeling better, we headed out. The first order of business was to get some breakfast; despite the size of our celebratory meal, we were both hungry once again. And then? Then it would be time to work out what we would do next.

Those plans derailed as soon as we made our way downstairs to the inn’s common room, to find Dusty sitting there, hooves steepled and staring off into space. He was one of only three ponies in the room; while the other two were sharing a light meal and talking, he simply sat there, with an untouched glass of water set before him.

We might have just passed right by, but something about it caught Starlight’s interest. That, or her ire. She changed course to pass by him, and halted a short distance away. “What’s up with you?”

He didn’t even blink. “Thinking.”

“Yeah,” Starlight dryly replied. “We could smell the smoke. Thinking about what?”

That finally brought Dusty’s attention back to the room he was in. He glared flatly at her for a moment before looking back the way he had been. “About a job offer.”

Seeing as he didn’t seem very talkative, I nudged Starlight. “Come on, let’s get some food.”

Whether it had been curiosity, belligerence, or the mention of a job, Starlight’s attention had been thoroughly set upon Dusty, and she shrugged off my nudge. “What kind of job?”

He mulled the question over for several seconds, as if deciding whether he should answer. Eventually, he did. “Go to a research park. Get computer records from several companies. Bring them here.” He idly tapped his hooves together. “Pays five thousand caps. Maybe more.”

Starlight’s eyes went wide. “Holy shit.”

Having less of a sense of the value of caps, I wasn’t so startled by the number. I was, however, concerned by Starlight’s reaction and the implication that had for Dusty’s job. Her reaction didn’t suggest that it was a large amount of caps so much as it spelled it out in giant, flaming letters and beat me over the ears with it, all of which led me to one particular question: “What’s the catch?”

There was a ghost of a smile, lingering only for a moment before fading into a grimace. “It’s raider territory.”

A smile slowly spread across Starlight’s face. “Ah! And you need ponies to go with you.”

“Yeah,” Dusty grumbled. “And I don’t exactly have the greatest of selection.”

Starlight’s smile grew into a full-blown grin. “Seems to me you’ve got a great selection right here. Question is whether we want any part of your job.”

His eyes narrowed. “Don’t get too full of yourself, kid. I ain’t even decided if I’m doing the job, much less if I’m actually going to ask you to come along.”

“So you were thinking of asking us,” Starlight said, full of satisfaction.

“Thinking,” Dusty echoed. “Very long and hard.”

“It’s a lot of caps,” Starlight said in a singsong voice.

I couldn’t help expressing doubt. “I don’t know. I don’t like the idea of picking a fight with a bunch of raiders.”

Again, that hint of a smile appeared. “Neither do I. But she’s right, it’s a lot of caps, and with a bit of luck there won’t even be any fighting.”

I frowned. “I’m not staking my life on luck. And I don’t think you are, either.”

He did smile at that, if faintly. He even exhaled in a way that suggested a chuckle.

“Okay, enough,” Starlight said, nudging out one of the chairs and sitting. “You’re going to ask us to help you, so spill the details. Let’s hear about this job.”

I think it should be pretty obvious to you that I didn’t like where this was going. Still, I figured it was worth hearing out the details. At least then I could give more concrete reasons to decline.

Dusty resisted only a few moments longer before speaking. “That mare Steel pointed me to, she wants me to hit this old compound that was built in the hills south of here. Some sort of community setup by the Ministry of Technology for wartime research. Stable-Tec, Equestrian Robotics, Ironshod Firearms, Crystal Life, and some group called “The Canterlot Medical Research Group”.”

As much as I hated it, he suddenly had my interest. I still thought it was dangerous, possibly too dangerous to undertake, but I now had a much more compelling reason than caps. Money could be acquired through many means. Information, however, was a much more difficult commodity, and Dusty had unwittingly dangled it in front of me. One Crystal Life Technologies facility had been home to members of my hive for two centuries. What might I discover at other facilities?

“She wants me to go to each of those companies’ facilities,” Dusty continued as I took a seat, “and download all their computer records onto a data-store. I bring that back to her, she pays caps. Trick is, it sounds like it was built with security in mind, so some raider band saw the high walls and towers and thought it’d make a great base. We have to get past them.”

“Three of us against a fortified raider band,” I said, frowning. Despite my interest in C.L.T., the information it might net me would do little good if I didn’t survive to use it. “I don’t see this going well.”

“Ideally, there wouldn’t be any fighting,” Dusty said, though I felt he lacked conviction, “but I always plan for worst-case scenarios, and that means being ready for a fight.”

“All right,” Starlight said as she leaned forward, crossing her forelegs atop the table. “So what is the plan?”

“Even if I bring you two along, we’d have to be ready for a fight, even if it’s just to escape. A big fight, too. There’s probably a few dozen raiders in there. Whisper’s right; three ponies aren’t going to cut it. We need more firepower. I’ve been thinking all night on it. I’ve only come up with two ideas, and I don’t really like either of them.”

“Let’s hear them,” Starlight said.

Dusty slowly nodded, then raised one hoof. “Option one is to hire some mercenaries. There are lots of ponies out there willing to kill for caps. Problem is, most of them are amateurs, if not outright psychotic, so they could be more dangerous to us than the raiders. Hell, some of them might be raiders. I’d want to get somepony professional, like Talon Company. They’re good, but they charge it, too. That’s a problem. Not much point in even taking the job if we just give all the caps to somepony else.”

“Still salvage opportunities,” Starlight said. She blinked, and her expression darkened. “Well, unless the raiders all trashed that place, too.”

“I wouldn’t count on salvage,” Dusty said. He sat there, frowning for a moment before slowly raising his other hoof. “Which leads us to option two. We hire Sickle.”

There was a moment of silence before Starlight expressed my own thoughts, albeit with a touch more profanity than I would have used. “You’re fucking kidding, right?”

“There aren’t many ponies as good at killing raiders as her,” Dusty said. “And she works cheap. Hell, we can probably just let her keep the bounty on the raiders we find.”

“Seriously?” Starlight said, her voice rising. “What was all that ‘amateur and psychotic’ stuff you were saying?”

“She’s not amateur,” Dusty said. “Psychotic, that I’ll give you. I worked with her once. I’d really rather not do so again, given the chance, but I think it might be the best option. She’s got some sort of hate for raiders in specific. Not sure why. She… wouldn’t tell me.”

“Oh, so she’s a professional psychotic!” Starlight said, throwing up her hooves. “Oh, well I feel so much better! There’s no way some raging sadist that loves carving up ponies would ever turn on us!”

“Hey, I’m not saying I like her or anything,” Dusty said. “I don’t. But the only ponies she kills are raiders and ponies that cross her. Hell, you two broke into her home and she just threw you out.”

“After nearly throwing Whisper through a wall! And you saw the bandages she needed after that!”

“Still milder than I would have expected,” Dusty said with a shrug. “Hell, if it was me I might have shot you.”

Starlight stared at him for several seconds before replying, her words dripping with sarcasm. “Wow. Thanks, Dusty.”

“Oh, calm down,” he said. “Walking into my home in the middle of the night to find a pair of armed ponies? Never thought I’d say Sickle showed restraint in anything, but there you go.”

“Doesn’t change that you’re wanting us to work with a psychotic murderer!”

“I wouldn’t call killing raiders murder, Starlight.”

“Well what would you call gutting somepony and hanging them from the rafters!” Starlight shouted. Needless to say, the other ponies in the room were eying us.

Dusty kept his voice much more level and controlled. “Hell, I’ll be the first to say she enjoys killing a bit too much, no argument there. But really, so long as it’s raiders she’s doing it to, I can’t really say I’m too troubled by it.”

“And what about that little colt she killed, huh?”

He grimaced. “...I’m not terribly comfortable about the idea of killing a kid, but you saw that cutie mark same as I did. You have any idea what you have to do to get a mark like that?”

I shuddered, just a little.

The same statement also made Starlight pause. Her mouth moved in twitches, as if trying to come up with words but falling short. Finally, she looked to me for help. “And what do you think, Whisper?”

I frowned, giving a show of mulling it over for a few seconds before speaking. “I think I’m willing to consider the idea.” Starlight’s shoulders slumped, but I was already raising a hoof. “But on one condition: if I think for even a moment that she’s going to cause a problem, we’re out. Gone. Period.”

Dusty nodded. “If I think she’s going to cause a problem, I’ll be walking out right with you.”

Starlight grumbled for a moment, sitting back in her chair and crossing her forelegs. After a moment, she practically spat out the word, “Fine.”

“Good,” Dusty said. “And I think I’ll talk to Amber, see if she’ll agree to six thousand.” He paused, then added, “Same split as before, fifty-fifty.”

Starlight nearly knocked over her chair as she rose. “Oh, fuck you, Dusty! Enough of this half-share crap. We each did just as much as you did on that last job, and you know it. Maybe more! You can either pay us a full share each, like we deserve, or you can have fun playing with psycho-mare on your own!”

Dusty stewed over that. I have to admit, as much as I disliked seeing Starlight so angry, I felt just a little proud of how she had maneuvered him. I felt like a predator moving in for the kill as I spoke up. “It’s a lot of caps, Dusty. You still get plenty, even if you pay us a fair share. Certainly a lot more than you’re likely to get without us.”

He looked back and forth between us, remaining silent for several seconds. I could see the battle raging in his eyes, and I could see the moment the lines broke. “Fine,” he grunted. “An even three-way split.”

Starlight let out a sharp laugh in celebration, while Dusty stood, fishing out a pack of cigarettes. “Think I need a smoke after that,” he grumbled. “For some reason, it feels like I just got fucked.”

That drew a snicker from Starlight. “Yeah, love you too, Dusty.”

He turned to her, meeting her own smug grin with a scowl. “Oh, shut it, kid. I know you two ‘not-lovers’ are joined at the damn hip, but if I had my way, I’d only be bringing one of you.”

“Yeah, you told us,” Starlight said, the smug grin growing a bit more.

“Yeah, I did. What I didn’t tell you is that if I were to bring only one of you into a fight, it’d be her.”

He leveled a hoof at me; Starlight’s smugness vanished.

“Seriously?” Starlight said, voice laced with incredulity that, even if it seemed critical of my own ability, I had to agree with. She quickly looked my way as she realized how it had come across. “I mean, hell, Whisper’s great at a lot of stuff, but shooting is kinda my thing and all.”

“You’re cocky,” Dusty said, leaning in over the table. “Overconfidence gets ponies killed, and not just the pony who’s full of themselves. I don’t care how well you can shoot range targets or trees. I’ve never seen a range target shoot back, or a tree moving to flank a position. I want a pony who is good in combat. You’re arrogant and hot-headed.” Again, his hoof pointed my way. “I may not be entirely happy with her, but Whisper is cautious, and at least seems to think things through instead of acting impulsively. I think she has better hopes of becoming a good soldier than you do.”

That was certainly the strangest piece of praise I’d received, and possibly the most troubling.

“Seriously?” Starlight said once again. “Why?”

Dusty shrugged, his response simple and calm after the preceding tirade. “She keeps both eyes open when she shoots.”

Starlight stared at him. “...What?”

His expression darkened again. “Yeah, you wouldn’t pay attention to something like that, would you? You’re so wrapped up in yourself—”

I’d had enough. “Dusty.” I didn’t shout the name, or even elevate my voice, but I said it with a sharp firmness that caught his attention. His head snapped around to me as I rose from my chair, standing tall and meeting him with a firm stare. It wasn’t an angry stare; I kept it level and dispassionate. I didn’t want to rile him up even more, but I needed to make it clear how serious I was.

“I may not have much experience with combat,” I said, “but I know that in any team endeavor, it’s critical for everypony to work well together. Tearing into another pony on the team and encouraging strife is detrimental to the entire group, and if we end up in a fight, it could get us killed. That wasn’t constructive criticism you were giving; you were just insulting her. If you want to educate us, that’s fine. I’d even welcome the opportunity to learn, and if you’re polite about it, I’m sure Starlight would, too. But if you continue to be insulting, and putting us all at risk, then we’re done.”

His jaw was tight by the time I was halfway through my statement. He glared back at me, while I hoped I hadn’t misjudged him.

The face-off lasted only a couple seconds. His glare wavered, and his anger crumbled. “...Yeah,” he said, his gaze dropping away from mine. “You’re right.”

He closed his eyes, his muzzle dipping to face the ground and ears folded back. He drew in a deep, calming breath, and let it out again.

I nodded, though he couldn’t see it. “Okay. Then let’s go see this Amber.”

“Yeah,” he said, quietly at first. He straightened up again, his expression firm once more. He grabbed the yet-untouched glass of water, downed it all in one long drink, and thumped it back down atop the table. “Let’s go talk to Amber.”

Behind him, Starlight was staring at us with wide eyes; mostly, she was staring at Dusty’s back. When she caught my glance, that expression changed to a wide grin, and she brought her forehooves together to mime clapping.

I gave a tiny smile, and we both followed Dusty.

Our destination was one of the big top-floor rooms, opposite the one we had shared our first time in Rust. Dusty knocked sharply on the door.

A well-spoken but bored-sounding voice answered us. “Who is it?”

“Dusty.”

There was silence for a few moments, followed by the sounds of hooves and the shuffling of furniture. After a few seconds the sounds stopped, and the door opened.

The mare beyond had a golden-orange coat, perfectly cared for. The warmth of the color contrasted with the haughty look she leveled our way, which managed to achieve that perfect balance of contempt and disinterest. With the care and styling put into her smooth coat and short but stylishly cut mane and tail, she looked as if she would fit right in among the snobbiest Canterlot socialite.

Beyond her I could see two pairs of saddlebags, with one set large and stuffed with items, and the other set small and fashionable. Both looked brand new, without a hint of dirt or wear. The outfit hanging from a hook beside the bed was practical and sturdy, but apart from a bit of dust looked just as new as the bags. Beside her stood the dresser that had, moments earlier, been keeping the door shut.

She looked over the three of us before speaking in that same bored tone. “I do hope you didn’t bring these ponies in some sort of foolish attempt to rob me.”

“What?” Dusty said, blinking. “No, these are some of the ponies coming along for the job.”

Starlight stepped forward, offering a hoof and a smile. “Hi. I’m Starlight, best shot you’ll find around here. You must be Amber?”

The mare looked down at the offered hoof, but did not return the gesture. “Lady Amber,” she said, and looked back to Dusty. “I don’t particularly care what ponies you decide to subcontract, so long as you meet the objectives I have detailed. Have you decided to accept the contract?”

While Starlight’s happy expression slowly withered at the cold rejection, Dusty nodded. “For six thousand caps.”

Lady Amber’s head tilted just a hair to the side. “I believe we had agreed to a final price of five thousand caps.”

“That wasn’t the final price,” Dusty said. “That was the starting price.”

“No, the starting price was three thousand. I’ve already been generous enough raising it to five.”

“You raised it to five because that’s how much it cost to get me to even listen.” Dusty replied. “Then I find out you want me to break into a raider fortress, hit five separate objectives, and extract ancient computer records from secure wartime research facilities. Six thousand is a bargain. Talons would charge you twice that or more, which I figure is why you’re talking with us instead of them.”

She stared back, inscrutable, for several seconds. Then she gave a curt nod. “Very well. Six thousand.”

“And one thousand of that will be upfront.”

“So you can run off with the caps without even doing the job? I think not.”

“So we know you can pay, rather than getting us to do your dirty work only to find out there’s no reward.”

She considered that for a moment. “I suppose that would be reasonable. However, my patron did not supply me with any caps to offer upfront. Payment was to be conducted after the data had been delivered.”

Dusty’s expression had tightened, his head drawing back a hair as he eyed her suspiciously. “You mean you don’t even have the caps to pay us? You better dig something up. You’re not going to find any mercenaries willing to risk their neck for you unless they know you can pay. Part up front is the way this business goes.”

Amber’s head tilted a tiny bit the other way. Several seconds later, she let slip a tiny smile. “It’s still worth a try,” she said, and the smile vanished. “I should be able to provide your fee from my travel budget. Remain here.”

With that, she shut the door in our faces.

Starlight turned to us with a smirk. “What a lovely and absolutely charming bitch.”

Dusty answered with a near-silent snort, as if amused but not willing to show it. As for myself, I allowed a slim smile.

Half a minute later, the door opened again. Amber held a sizable—and spotless—satchel, which she deposited before us. “One thousand caps, plus one very rare data-store. Do not think of running off and selling it; my patron has ways of tracking this device down, and as I’m quite sure you can see, has substantial resources to deal with ponies who become a problem.”

Dusty snorted again. “Wouldn’t be pushing you for a bigger payout if we’re planning on taking the up-front payment and splitting.”

“Unless you planned on using precisely that sort of argument,” she said, eyes narrowing slightly. She returned to her bored expression a moment later. “No matter. This is not particularly time critical, but my patron would appreciate a speedy resolution to this endeavor. Would one week be sufficient?”

“Should be,” Dusty said with a nod, “unless something comes up.”

“Then I will expect you within a week. If that time passes and you have not notified me of any delays, I will assume you’ve broken your word.”

“Won’t come to that,” Dusty said. “See you in a few days.”

“Good,” she said, and shut the door for good.

The moment it was closed, Dusty huffed out a breath and rolled his eyes. “Well, that’s all settled,” he said, then bent down to open the satchel. Inside was a large data-store, probably twice the size of the one I carried. It was one of the rugged military types, made to survive in rough conditions. It sat atop a large number of smaller sacks. There were ten in total, and Dusty pulled out a couple to check their weight. They jingled and clinked as he did so, and returned them to the satchel. There must have been five or six pounds of bottle caps in there, and we’d be getting five times as many when we returned.

“This looks in order,” he said, slinging the satchel over his back. “Go gear up. We should head out soon to find Sickle.”

Starlight smirked as we fell in beside Dusty, making our way out. “Such charming ponies you introduce us to, Dusty.”

Even Dusty gave a snort of amusement at that. “Yeah…”

☢

The walk from Rust was much quicker in the dry mid-day warmth than it was in a pounding, night-time storm. The dry ground crunched faintly beneath our hooves, while the faint breeze teased at our manes. The signs of the torrential rain had entirely passed. We saw the land there for the first time; the only familiar part of the journey was the train tracks we followed.

Less than two hours after leaving Rust, we laid eyes on the tiny ghost town. Again, it was a hint of the familiar, even if viewed from the opposite direction. Unfortunately, that familiarity brought with it a growing tension; I knew what lived in these ruins.

So did Dusty. “Starlight. How much punch does that Lancer have?”

She cast a curious glance his way, then looked back to the distant shack that slowly drew closer. “A lot. Tends to blow rocks apart when I shoot them, even fairly big ones. It’d put a hole right through Rust’s gate.”

“Good,” Dusty said, then looked to me. “If this does go bad, our job is going to be keeping Sickle distracted long enough for Star to get a shot. Shoot her, yell at her, whatever. And Star?” He turned her way. “You’ll get one, maybe two shots before she kills us all. Make it count.”

“You’re not exactly inspiring confidence here,” she replied.

“I don’t think it’ll come to that,” he said as he pulled his rifle from his back, leaving it to hang across his chest—in easy reach. “I just like to be prepared.”

I did the same, and Dusty looked my way once again. “Don’t expect that thing to do anything more than piss her off. Unless you get lucky and put a round right in a joint or something, those bullets won’t get through her armor. I doubt mine will, either. Maybe if I had some AP rounds, but I don’t.”

“Noted,” I said, stifling the tremble that threatened to seize my legs.

The last hundred yards were crossed in silence, save for the jingle and creak of our equipment.

After pausing for a moment to take a breath, Dusty stepped up onto the porch and gave three firm knocks.

A moment later there was a loud thump from within the shack, accompanied by the muffled sound of a large number of bottles knocking together. Then a deep voice called out from inside. “Who the fuck’s making all that noise?”

“It’s Dusty.”

There were a couple more thumps, followed by a much louder one that knocked dust from the wall beside the door. A narrow board halfway up the wall pulled back; in the darkness, I could only catch a hint of movement before it slammed shut. Then the door swung open.

That’s when I first saw Sickle.

Sickle was huge.

I know, I had described her that way from our prior encounter. That time, however, it had been dark, lit only by a swinging PipBuck screen. It had left as much to my imagination as it had shown.

This time, I saw her in the light of day, however overcast it might have been. She stood there without her armor, glaring out at us, as I realized that my imagination might have been lacking.

She wasn’t just big. She was easily the largest pony I had ever seen.

Now, admittedly, I had never seen any of the princesses with my own eyes, but that wouldn’t have changed that statement. I’m reasonably certain that only Celestia would have stood taller, but even she wouldn’t have come close to matching Sickle in size. The closest I could think of was some old stallion who had retired in Appleloosa; in his prime, he had stood nearly as tall as my queen, and was strongly built. Even then, I suspect Sickle surpassed him.

She was large, and she was thick, and she looked like the strongest pony ever.

A bit of a clarification: when I say she looked like the strongest pony ever, I imagine it conjures up different images to different ponies. I’m still getting used to how perceptions have changed since the megaspells, but I know that during my stay in war-time Equestria, many ponies asked to picture an extremely strong pony would think of bodybuilders. They think of ponies with ultra-low body fat to highlight the contours of muscles, with focused exercises that lead to big, bulky shoulders and narrow hips and legs. Personally, as something of a professional in the arts of body alteration and morphology, it’s a look that always struck me as profoundly unnatural.

Sickle didn’t look like that. She didn’t have some perfectly sculpted body. She just looked thick. Her hooves were the size of my head, her legs as thick as my chest. Her body was strong and thick all the way through. Some might have looked at the soft definition and the roundness of her belly and concluded that she was fat, but I knew quite well how fat distributes around a pony’s body, and that wasn’t what I saw on her; what I saw was a healthy bit of padding over an immense, powerful frame. She looked like she might be more bear than pony.

The rest of her appearance was thoroughly rough and rugged. Her coat was a faded pink, wild and unkempt. It was also worn thin around her withers, hips, and a few other places, lingering signs of the heavy armor I had first seen her in. Her mane and tail, both in slightly darker shades of pink, were scraggly, thin, and short. And just for good measure, all of it was dirty and frayed, with the kind of worn-in grime that made me think she didn’t even understand the concept of bathing, much less had ever done so.

Her neck was almost as thick around as her head, and her face… well, she showed the signs of wounds all across her body, but it was her neck and head that bore the most impressive. Old scars left her features jagged and uneven. The left side of her jaw was so scarred up that a fair section was bare skin. She was missing half of her right ear. Her muzzle was lumpy and ever so slightly askew, as if it had been broken multiple times in the past.

Suffice to say, she wouldn’t win any beauty competitions, save by threatening to crush the judges.

I also noted that she was an earth pony. Apparently, the horn on her helmet hadn’t been to protect a horn underneath.

At least her cutie mark seemed relatively benign: a single, large horseshoe.

The whole powerful, rugged, chewed-up appearance combined to make the glare of pure death she was giving Dusty even more menacing. When she spoke, her voice was deep and rumbling.

“What the fuck do you want, Dirt?”

“It’s Dusty. I—”

“I know what your fucking name is!” She snapped, taking a step forward; Dusty took two steps back, and covered the same distance. “I asked you what… what…”

She looked right at me. I could see now that she swayed slightly when she moved, as if off-balance. Her eyes were dilated, with only a faint ring of blue barely visible, and I could see them trying to focus on me as she blinked. Then her expression hardened, and my gut dropped. “You! I remember you, you little cunt! And you!” She looked at Starlight, swaying slightly with the motion. “I told you two bitches what I’d do to you if you ever showed your fucking face around here again!”

Her head dropped, her legs tensed, and my heart started pounding at the inside of my chest. “What the fuck is this, Dirt?”

“It’s a job offer!” Dusty quickly answered, holding up his hooves. “That’s it!”

She looked square at him, blinking several more times as she refocused. “...What the fuck would I want with a job?”

“Not… not that kind of job,” Dusty said; he was doing a good job of keeping his voice calm and conversational without devolving into patronization. Given how hard my heart was beating and the copious amounts of adrenaline burning in my veins, even I might have had trouble remaining so level-headed.

Memories of being held helpless under those giant hooves didn’t help.

“A job killing raiders.”

Sickle’s ears—that is, ear and a half—perked up, and her murderous glare vanished. “The fuck are you talking about?”

“I got a job. Problem is, there’s a bunch of raiders where I need to do that job. Raiders got a nice bounty on them. I figure you kill all the raiders and collect their bounty, we do our job, and everypony makes an assload of caps.”

She stared at him for a couple seconds, blinking. Then she smiled. It was a cold smile, so predatory that I would have been only slightly surprised to see sharp teeth. “Go fuck yourself, Dirt.”

Dusty took a half-step back. “It’s a lot of caps, Sickle.”

“Yeah, right,” she growled, advancing a step and ducking her head to glare straight into Dusty’s eyes. “You want me to kill a bunch of ponies for you? You’re going to give me a cut of whatever you’re getting for this ‘job’.”

“We’ll let you have all the bounties,” Dusty said. “That’s a lot of caps.”

“Fuck you! I can kill any raider for a fucking bounty.” Her grin returned. “You want me to go out of my way to kill these raiders, then you’re going to have to make it worth my while.”

Dusty considered that a moment, doing his best to meet her glare without flinching away, though I could see the tension in his limbs. “Fine; you get a share of the pay, and we all split the bounties.”

“No. I’m going to be doing most of the killing. You little shits sure aren’t.” She waved a giant, dirty hoof toward Starlight and myself. “So I get a full share, and all the bounties for the raiders you’re bringing me along to kill, or you can all fuck off.”

Dusty stared back at her, his brows furrowing. She met the look with a sneer that made her scarred face crinkle up in strange ways.

After a moment of their silent stare-off, Dusty looked over to us. “What do you two think?”

Starlight grunted unintelligibly.

I gave a slightly more vocal reply. “If you think it’s a good idea, I would accept that.”

He sighed and looked back to Sickle. “Okay. Deal.”

Her chuckle rumbled so deeply I could practically feel it. “All right. So where are we going, and when?”

“Some compound south of here,” Dusty said, gesturing a hoof in that direction. “About forty miles. And I’d like to set out as soon as possible.”

Sickle nodded, her eyes blinking several more times as she looked south. “Okay… yeah, okay. Let me get my shit.”

She turned around, staggering a little, and disappeared into the shack again, slamming the door behind her.

“Charming,” Starlight said, and Dusty grunted in agreement.

It was several minutes, and quite a few thumps and bangs from inside the shack, before the door opened again. Sickle stepped out, to the clinking and scraping of metal. She looked more like I remembered her from our first encounter, but the lighting gave me a much better view. I could tell now just how thick her armor was, and the only places I could see her coat were a few bits of her face and the tip of one ear. That thickness made the dents and dings even more impressive, just to imagine how much force had been applied to it. The armor was as battle-worn as she was.

There were also a set of metal boxes hanging at her sides, like armored saddlebags. It looked as if someone had attached straps to a pair of large ammunition boxes, and then welded medical boxes to those. A few faded flecks of yellow still clung to the metal, despite the many scrapes, dents, and even a crudely patched bullet hole.

The thick-barred muzzle hung from one side of her helm, the other clasp dangling free. She was chewing on something, and her muzzle was wet and dripping; she’d apparently went to drink something and missed. She swallowed whatever it was she was chewing, then shoved the muzzle into place over her snout, latching it in place. “Okay, Dirt,” she said, voice slightly muffled. “Lead the way.”

With a weary shake of his head, Dusty started walking.

Much to my growing sense of dread, Sickle hung back, right next to me. I tried to ignore how I could feel her hoofsteps through the earth. Then her huge, armored head swung around in my direction, the spear-like horn looming dangerously in my direction. In the deep shadows of her helmet’s eye-slits, I saw tiny twin reflections of light. “What’s your name?”

My voice faltered slightly as I spoke. “Whisper.”

“Whimper. Got it.” Her head swung over toward Starlight. “And you?”

Starlight looked back with an unrestrained, hateful glare. “It’s Starlight.”

“Starlight. Star… whatever.” Sickle shook her head; her armor clanked noisily with the motion, and she stumbled a little. “Both of you, listen good. When I threaten to do something to a pony, I follow through. Period.” I started considering escape routes before she continued. “Only reason I’m not stomping your fucking heads in is because I know Dirt dragged you out here. So I’m letting you two bitches off on a techno-whatsit.”

I was wary of speaking at all, but I cautiously replied, “Thank you.”

That head swung my way again, a sneer showing behind that muzzle. “You want to thank me, you can stick your snout between my legs and show it. Otherwise, you can fuck off.”

Her pace quickened to catch up with Dusty, while I happily lagged behind, having no desire to stay too close to the angry goliath of a mare. Hanging back also revealed that her armor, despite covering almost every inch of her, left her groin bare. I suppose it made sense, as it meant one wouldn’t have to remove the armor to relieve themselves. Unfortunately, the observation combined unpleasantly with her prior statement.

Starlight broke the following silence. “I hate her.”

I winced, even as Sickle let out a quiet chuckle.

☢

Somehow, we managed to go through the rest of that long and tense day without incident. Little was said. Even Starlight was quiet. She responded to my inquiries with little more than “I’m fine,” before continuing on in silence.

When she looked anywhere but where she was setting her hooves, it was over to our newest traveling companion. Unsurprisingly, Sickle was the focus of my attention as well.

Sickle didn’t seem to think much of us, most of the time. She rarely turned her attention away from where she was walking, and on the few occasions she looked at one of us, I could just barely see the corner of her mouth quirk upwards in a smirk under that metal muzzle she wore. At first, those looks were accompanied by a few moments of wavering and focusing, and even the occasional stumble. Those diminished as we traveled, and within a couple hours, whatever impairment she had inflicted upon herself had faded away.

It was around then that I got the impression those glances had changed. While I couldn’t clearly see her eyes in the shadows that pooled behind those narrow slits, the little glimpses I could catch suggested a sharp, focused look to my mind. The impaired look of amusement and contempt had been replaced with a more critical expression. I worried whether that was better or worse.

Dusty called a halt as night fell, leading us to a narrow draw on a dry and dusty ridge, where a few dead trees and dry bushes gave a bit of concealment. I was happy to slip off my saddlebags, and we began to unpack our sleeping gear. Sickle was the exception; she simply rolled to her side and collapsed with a tremendous crash of metal. She ended sprawled out, propped up against the stump of a dead tree with her legs splayed in either direction. If it were some other pony, I might have considered the pose silly, or a simple expression of exhaustion. Sickle just made it look lewd.

I hid my attention by busying my hooves with setting out my bedroll, while observing her in the corner of my vision. After getting comfortable, Sickle reached up to undo one of the clasps of her muzzle, letting it swing free to hang from the side of her helm. She dug awkwardly—due to angle, rather than lack of coordination—at her saddlebag cases with her hooves. Eventually she retrieved a large bottle and some jerky. She pried the bottle’s cap off with her teeth, spitting it back into the case she had retrieved the bottle from, and took several deep swallows from it. Then she bit off a large piece of jerky.

She chewed for several seconds before her head lazily rolled to the side to stare at Starlight. She spoke while chewing, spraying a few little bits of half-chewed meat as she sneered. “You got a problem, little bitch?”

Looking over at Starlight, I saw that she wore an irritated expression, though she quickly looked away from Sickle. “You’re disgusting,” she said, keeping her glare focused on her own bags as she unpacked.

Sickle gave a dry chuckle, and followed up by gratuitously scratching an armored hoof at her crotch. “Yeah. And?”

Starlight’s ears pinned back, her blanket freezing in midair. I quickly stepped in to. “Hey, Starlight? Do you—”

Sickle’s hoof shot out, pointing straight at me; even with plenty of distance between us, I flinched back. “Fuck off, Whimper,” she said with a sneer. “We’re talking.”

When she turned her look back to Starlight, the smaller unicorn met her with an unflinching glare. “I saw what you did at the depot.”

Sickle’s head tilted to the side as she continued to chew on her jerky for several seconds. “Uh-huh. What depot?”

“That army depot,” Starlight clarified. “The one where you butchered all those ponies.”

After a moment more of thinking, Sickle shrugged. “I dunno. That doesn’t really narrow it down, much, does it?”

“What, you butcher that many ponies?” Starlight said, her voice rising. “It was a week ago, a warehouse in the middle of the desert with a bunch of—”

“Oh, yeah!” Sickle said, breaking out in a big grin. “Hell, that was fun.” She took another bite of her jerky. “So, what about it? You got a problem with killing raiders?”

Starlight recoiled a bit, but continued on. “I’m fine with killing raiders,” she said. “I’m not so fine with somepony sticking their bodies on a pole like some sort of fucked-up flag.”

Despite the criticism, Sickle was chuckling. “Oh, you saw what I did to Pike, huh? Yeah, she was a fun little bitch.” Her chuckles ended as she tilted her head, smirking at Starlight. “Guess you didn’t see her cutie mark, then? I know I left one of her hind legs laying around there.”

Starlight glared for a couple seconds before replying through clenched teeth. “There wasn’t enough left of them to see it.”

I paused in my unpacking, a package of food in my hooves. I wasn’t sure if wanted to eat with the topic at hoof.

“Ah, too bad,” Sickle said with a rumbling chuckle. “You’d recognize it. Just a gutted pony’s body on a spike. She liked to do that to ponies. I thought it’d be all ironic-like to do that to her.” She made a quick, thrusting gesture with her hoof. “So I stuck her own spear up her cunt and left her on display.”

I grimaced, placed the food back in my pack, and closed it.

“That’s fucking disgusting,” Starlight said, trembling, which just made Sickle smile more.

“Yeah. And?” She gave a deep, rumbling laugh, ending when she turned up her bottle and chugged the rest of its contents. She sent the bottle flying through the air to crash to the ground behind her, and continued. “Ain’t like she was some fucking saint or some shit. She’d put up whole caravans like that, just to show others what she did when they didn’t pay her toll. Hell, sometimes she’d do it even if they could.” She sneered once more. “Bet you’d change your mind if you saw a whole bunch ‘a little blank-flank colts and fillies on display, with poles jammed up their asses and out their mouths, all because ma and pa didn’t have enough caps.”

I shuddered, unable to hold back a whimper at the vileness she conjured up—which, naturally, appeared to amuse Sickle, given the moniker she had chosen for me. Even the horrors I had seen did little to take the sting out of what she described. I like to think that I avoid poetic license when possible, but I felt like it hurt something deep inside me to hear such an atrocity spoken of so plainly. The many levels of wrongness required to reach that state were the sort of thing that could drive a thinking person to despair.

Starlight’s voice drew me out of my inward focus. She trembled, looking faintly queasy, but managed to fix Sickle with a glare once again. “I saw the colt you killed.”

“Huh?” Sickle said, helmet tilting again. “What colt?”

“At the depot,” Starlight said, the tremble fading from her voice. “The one you kicked through a—”

“Oh!” Again, Sickle grinned in recognition. “I remember that little shit now! Hah, yeah, that’s a good one. I was thrashing the place, and some pony charges me from behind. I gave him a quick kick, only it sends the fucker straight through the wall! So of course, I’ve got to check it out, just to see, you know, what the fuck? Yeah, he was dead. One kick. But it gets even better! Ends up this little fucker came at me with a knife. A tiny fucking knife!” She broke out laughing, thumping a hoof against the ground.

When her laughter finally died down, Starlight spoke up again, though quietly. “It’s still disgusting.”

“Heh. Kid was a raider. He deserved it.”

“Aren’t you a raider, too?”

Any hint of amusement Sickle had was gone in an instant. Even her chewing stopped. When she spoke, her voice was low and quiet. “I ain’t a fucking raider,” she said. “Not any more.”

“Were a raider, then,” Starlight clarified; despite the sudden change in tone that had set me on full alert, she didn’t waver at all as she met the monstrous mare’s glare. “Does that mean you’d deserve it if I killed you?”

Her bags still floated in her magic, but just behind her, I noticed that her Lancer was wrapped in the same magical glow, half obscured by her body. My heart hammered inside my chest, as I moved my shoulder forward. A quick twist would bring my rifle to where I could hold it; the question was whether I could possibly do so in time to matter.

After a couple seconds of silence, a grin slowly spread across Sickle’s scarred muzzle. “Yeah, I guess I would. You going to try it?”

Another stretch of silence.

Finally, Starlight relaxed ever so slightly. The Lancer slid down, resting on the ground behind her. “Not today.”

“Then quit your bitching,” Sickle said, still grinning as she laid her head back against the tree.

On the opposite side of our small camp, Dusty resumed laying out his own bedding.

I sat next to Starlight as she finished unpacking. She grumbled a little, and I tried to be comforting just by being there. I couldn’t think of anything useful to say, at least not with Sickle lying right there. Her bad mood faded a bit as she ate. After a while, I was even able to stomach a bit of food, and shared one of the snack cakes I had stashed away during our celebratory dinner. By the time we were done eating, she gave me a weak but appreciative smile.

Meanwhile, Sickle ate a bit, drained and tossed another bottle, and downed a couple pills. After latching her muzzle back in place, she settled in to sleep. By the time we were done eating and ready to sleep, her head was lolled to the side, drooling as she snored.

While Dusty sat vigilant to take the first watch, Starlight and I tucked into our simple beds.

Minutes later, when I had almost drifted off to sleep, I heard her quiet whisper, barely audible.

“Whisper?”

I cracked open an eye to see her, lying on her side and looking at me, worry etched into her expression.

“Yeah?”

She swallowed, eyes wandering before returning to me. “...I’m not really comfortable with where this is going.”

“Yeah. Me neither.”

She gave a ghost of a smile, as if appreciating that I felt the same way, but it faded as quick as it came. “Do you think she’s going to cause a problem?”

I had to consider that. There was so much I didn’t know, and Sickle was throwing in all-new complications. Despite that, after a moment of thinking, I answered honestly. “No. I think she’s just having fun riling us up. I don’t think she’ll cause any real problems. And if things do take a turn for the worse, we’ll get out of it together.”

I smiled, gently and comforting, and she eventually did as well.

“...Thanks, Whisper.”

I gave a tiny nod, and she tucked her blanket in around her, her eyes closing.

I settled in to sleep once more. We still had a long couple of days ahead of us.

Chapter Nine: Paradise

Do raiders love?

It seems such a bizarre question on its face. From everything I had seen and heard, raiders are barbaric beyond all belief. These are ponies who rape, torment, torture, and kill, all for their own amusement. Such acts even became something of a social dynamic among them; the more depraved and vicious you were, the more respect you commanded from other raiders, and the higher your status. It was little wonder that those who led their own bands, like Pike, were the most horrible of the lot. In their vile social structure, it was how they gained standing.

So they had social dynamics and concepts of respect. They obviously enjoyed certain things, as horrible as those things often were. It seemed reasonable that they would have a degree of interest in their companions for them to have banded together. But did that extend to the kind of appreciation that would place that other pony on a similar level as themselves, or was it entirely selfish? Were raiders capable of loving anything but their own self-interest?

These were the kind of thoughts I had as I peered through Dusty’s binoculars at a watchtower, while the pair of raiders within grew increasingly frisky.

We all lay on a low ridge, several hundred yards from the tower in question; all except Sickle and her heavy, noisy armor, whom we had left another hundred yards back. In the growing darkness of twilight, we would have been practically invisible, even if the raiders had been looking our way. It gave us plenty of time to observe, and I looked on with interest.

I was hungry.

The day had been long and quiet. Despite the friendship I had fostered in Starlight, she had been so focused on Sickle that she had spared hardly a moment of thought toward me. Even when we had halted in the early evening a couple miles from our destination, to wait for nightfall, I had hardly gotten a nibble out of her. So, I watched the pair of young stallions in the tower, and silently contemplated whether I might be able to get any love if I impersonated one of them.

Not that I thought I’d have any chance of doing so, or that I would dare try, should the opportunity have presented itself. Sneaking off from my group without arousing suspicion would be difficult enough. Infiltrating theirs would be even more difficult, especially done blind. I could maybe catch one alone and forcibly feed upon them, but even that posed significant risk of discovery. I didn’t plan on doing any of these things, but when one is hungry and walking by a buffet, one can hardly be blamed for looking. So I looked, and thought.

Was there any love to be had, there? Some might have looked at the way one of the ponies roughly handled the other, pinning him in place and biting, and concluded that there was only self-interest, but I knew things weren’t always so simple. Both were clearly enjoying themselves, but that didn’t answer whether that enjoyment was entirely self-centered or not. Did they care at all for the other pony, or were they simply using each other for their own personal pleasure?

“Enjoying the show?” Dusty quietly whispered from beside me.

“Thinking,” I replied, and presented a different reason for my interest. “If all of their guards show a similar lack of discipline, we might be able to pull off a silent infiltration.”

I lowered the binoculars to pass them back to Dusty, and looked over the compound as a whole.

Paradise Beach made a mockery of both parts of its name.

Five office buildings, multi-story structures of crumbling concrete and broken glass, formed a semicircle around a large, muddy pond. The sandy desert earth around the pond was dotted with debris, with the occasional picnic table and the tattered skeletons of old beach umbrellas. The rusting remains of a skywagon lay half-submerged in the pond, and a large neighborhood of ruined houses were set across from the offices. A few service buildings were set on the pond-side of that neighborhood; I saw what looked to have been a restaurant, a store, and a few other buildings I couldn’t immediately identify.

Circling the compound was a concrete wall, worn and cracked by the years. Automated defenses had long since broken down or been stripped for salvage, leaving skeletal frames and scorched craters where they had once topped the walls. A pair of crude towers had been erected to take up the task of watching over the facility, one over each of the two opposing gates. The gates themselves bore the name “Paradise Beach” in letters that had once been bright and colorful, but were now faded and chipped.

Other than the two broken-down guard shacks by each gate, the only building outside of the wall was a small loading facility to service the rail line that led up to the place. A train lay crumpled and broken past the end of the rails, having plowed through the barrier at their end and gone crashing into the barren field beyond.

While the pair of ponies entertaining themselves in one of the towers were the only raiders we saw, there were plentiful signs of their presence. Long metal poles outside the entry gate were decorated with bones, lashed in place with wire. The decayed corpse of a pony hung from another pole that protruded from what had once been a store. The flickering firelight from within that and the neighboring restaurant were the only lights to be seen, and seemed to suggest that the raiders had holed up there. No lights came from across the compound, near the dark and silent office buildings.

The whole place was set in a shallow bowl between a few sandy hills, one of which was currently host to us.

Dusty was sweeping his binoculars slowly over the rolling terrain to our right, looking for an ideal approach. “It’s a lot of ground to cross, and the cover could be better, but we’ll have the darkness on our side. Say… fifteen minutes to get there? Probably more, if we’re darting from cover to cover.”

“I’m not sure if they’ll be busy that long,” I said. “They hadn’t gotten properly started yet, so I’d say they’ll be busy for at least five minutes. How much longer, I couldn’t say. Fifteen minutes may be pushing it.”

“And it’d be longer because we would need to get Sickle, too.” He sighed, lowering his binoculars again. “Okay, salvage experts. How long do you think it’ll take to locate, break into, and download the entire server in five separate research offices?”

Starlight shrugged, still peering through the sight of her Lancer. “I don’t know, probably a few minutes each? Plus getting into the place and moving. Maybe an hour?”

“And worst case?” I asked.

She lowered her Lancer, considering that for a moment. “An hour each?”

“Shit,” Dusty muttered. “Would have liked to wait a few hours for their guards to get bored and sloppy, but that would be cutting things a bit close for comfort. Scoot back; we’re getting Sickle and moving in.”

We slid back on our bellies until we were behind the crest, then rose to trot down the slope. Sickle was sitting, waiting for us. “You done sightseeing yet?”

“Yep,” Dusty said. “Scouted out a route that should get us there. Let’s go.”

“About fucking time,” Sickle said as she stood.

As she walked with us, her armor clattering and clacking with each step, Dusty talked us through the plan.

We made our way around the next hill, reaching a shallow draw several minutes later. We slowed, crouching low as we moved. It felt silly to do so when Sickle’s crouched shuffle was about as tall as I stood normally, but we did so anyway. The quietness of our advance and the young night made Sickle’s armor sound all the louder in my ears.

Eventually, we reached a point where the draw faded away into the slope of the hill. We stopped at a pair of scraggly bushes Dusty had spotted before, while he pulled out his binoculars.

While we were much closer to the wall, and therefore the tower, I couldn’t make it out well in the darkness. I saw what looked to be one of the stallions’ heads, but I couldn’t be certain. We were below its level, and couldn’t see what lay below those walls.

Dusty lowered the binoculars again, trading it for his rifle. “I only see one of them, but his back’s to us. Star, you’re up.”

As he lay beside the bush, peering down the sights of his rifle at the tower, Starlight grinned. “Got it,” she said, and crouching low, scurried up to another bush, a third of the way to the wall. By the time she got there, she was just a silhouette in the darkness. That silhouette dropped to the ground, lying halfway behind the bush. A faint glow of magic brought her Lancer forward as she sighted on the tower, winking out a moment later.

“She’s in place,” I whispered.

“Good,” Dusty replied around his bit. “Whisper, go.”

As planned, I moved quick and low, my rifle’s grip held in my teeth. I passed right behind Starlight, who remained focused down her sight, and continued on. My eyes were locked on the tower, ready to throw myself prone the moment I saw any movement. None came, and finally the broken top of the wall blocked it from view. I sat beside the wall, looked back, and gave a little wave.

Sickle was uncomfortably conspicuous. Her metal armor stood out against the sandy ground, if only a little; a ghostly image when compared to the silhouettes of Dusty and Starlight blending seamlessly into the ground around them. As she moved, I could already hear the quiet jingling of her armor, though only faintly. It made for an agonizing wait as I sat there, worried that the raider would notice us at any moment.

Slowly, she drew closer, and closer, and I finally let out a sigh of relief as she reached the shadow of the wall behind me. Her armor rattled one more time as she made a rude gesture Dusty’s way. It wasn’t the wave Dusty had suggested, but it got the message across.

Dusty didn’t move. After several seconds, I gave a wave, but there was still no motion. I was starting to get very worried when his silhouette finally drew back and rose, shuffling quickly toward us.

When he arrived, he gave a quick wave to Starlight before whispering, “Damnit, Sickle, I said to stop and hide if he looked your way!”

“Fuck off, Dirt,” she rumbled, rather less quietly. “I didn’t see him do shit.”

“Quiet!” Dusty hissed. “Anyway, we’re lucky. I don’t think he saw anything, and he lost interest pretty quick. We should still be good.”

“Then quit your bitching and let’s go.”

Dusty’s jaw tightened, but I assume he recognized how arguing about it would only make things worse. He remained silent for a couple of seconds, until Starlight slipped in next to us, and then motioned for us to follow him.

We crept along the wall for a couple of minutes, until we reached a point Dusty had scouted out. Beside a pillar that had once housed an automated turret, the wall was cracked and partially crumbled. While most of the wall stretched a good ten feet over our heads, the crumbling gouge was only about five.

Starlight was up once more. With a nod from Dusty, she slung her Lancer and rushed forward; her hooves clattered only faintly against the wall as she sprung up along it, hooking her forehooves over the rim. She hauled herself up until her chest rested against it, and then went still, her hind legs dangling. She remained there for several long seconds before scrambling up all the way, perching atop the wall, and motioning for us to follow. Then she disappeared over the top.

Sickle grumbled a bit as she sat beside the wall, giving Dusty the opportunity to climb up atop her shoulders on his way up the wall. I followed as soon as he was over. I felt incredibly uncomfortable stepping on Sickle, my hooves clunking against the metal plate over her shoulder; that discomfort edged toward outright fear when I heard her growl beneath her breath. My scramble over the wall top was quick and not terribly graceful. Fortunately, I landed on my hooves.

Sickle merely rose up on her hind legs, grabbed the top of the gap, and hauled herself over. Her armor scraped noisily against the concrete and clattered loudly as she dropped to the dirt beyond. I heard a sharp, wincing exhale from Starlight at the sound.

The space beyond the wall was mostly dirt and dead vegetation, save for the large plazas behind each of the office buildings with their assortment of benches, fountains, and barren planters. We quickly followed Dusty to a mass of dead vegetation lying at the rear of one of the plazas and settled in, waiting. Dusty looked forward, scanning across the back lots, while Starlight watched back along the wall.

Satisfied that nopony was coming yet, Dusty scooted back. “Okay, from here on, we move in buddy teams. Star, Whisper, you two are basically inseparable anyway, keep that up. Sickle, you and I stick together. Never split up, watch out for your buddy, that sort of thing. Okay?”

We agreed, and he nodded. “Good. I’m thinking we hit the offices in order, unless anyone thinks differently?”

I leaned in, whispering. “Stable-Tec should be our first target. We need access to computers for this, and they did a lot of computer research. If we’re going to find anything that makes our job easier, it’ll be there.”

He nodded. “Sounds good. Which one is the Stable-Tec office?”

Starlight lowered her gaze to her PipBuck, flipping to the map. After a moment of searching, she raised a hoof. “That one, the second building.”

“Good,” Dusty nodded. “We move from cover to cover, short bounds. Move around the back of the plaza, then to the rear door of the building. Star, Whisper, lead us out.”

Adrenaline started to tickle at my hooves again as we rose, darting forward almost silently to another set of dead bushes. This time, though, it was more familiar. More exciting. I felt like I was in my element, sneaking about behind everyone’s back, searching for hidden information to steal without anypony being the wiser. It wasn’t too different from how it was during the war.

I tried to ignore the fact that it would probably be just as bad if I were caught, too. Maybe even worse.

We stopped at the bushes, looking out across the plazas. Still nothing.

Another quick bound, and we passed the first office’s plaza entirely, continuing on until we could hide behind a planter at the back corner of the next. We waited as Dusty and Sickle moved up to the corner we had just left. Dusty set up there, his rifle resting across a bench; he’d have a clear line of sight across the entire courtyard.

With him set, we moved again. Our advance wasn’t quite as silent as we moved across the paved square, our hooves clacking quietly on the cracked and uneven concrete. We moved from planter to fountain to bench, pausing as Dusty and Sickle moved up to the corner of the plaza, keeping the distance close.

Slowly, the dark, empty pits of the building’s broken windows drew closer.

Starlight and I halted at a low concrete wall just outside the rearmost doorways. The broad, full-length windows and glass doors had long since been smashed out, leaving a gaping dark chasm inside the building.

Behind us, I heard the clacking of Sickle’s spiked shoes on the concrete as they moved up.

Then I heard a sharp clatter from between the two offices.

I lurched and quickly gestured with a hoof. I don’t know if Dusty reacted to my gesture or if he heard the sound himself, but he immediately dropped down beside a planter, and a moment later Sickle crouched as well.

Silence filled the air. Then it was broken by the clacking of hooves on concrete; the sound of a slow, walking gait.

A couple seconds later there was a missed hoofbeat, then another, and the sound stopped.

I glanced Dusty’s way. I could barely make him out in the shadows, but I saw him raise a hoof to gesture downward. I assumed he meant to stay put, and gave a tiny nod.

We crouched and waited, and soon I heard the faint sound of the dry earth crunching under-hoof; there was a pony drawing closer. The hoofsteps clacked louder as he stepped onto a paved walkway again. A moment later, I heard the pony, a stallion, start to hum a tune.

Moving slowly and smoothly, I lowered my rifle until it hung on its sling, released the bit, and drew my pistol; I took my time silently slipping off the safety, and leveled it at the edge of the wall.

The hoofsteps drew closer. Starlight edged backward, toward the far corner of our cover, as it became apparent the incoming pony was going to walk right between Dusty’s position and our own.

The raider came around the end of the wall, and I aligned my sights over the center of his chest.

I never fired. A loud clatter of metal on concrete interrupted us; the raider had just enough time to let out a startled, “Huh?” before Sickle slammed into him, her head lowered. Her armor’s horn jutted out of the raider’s side as she bore him back against the wall. I scrambled back as she reared up, lifting him atop her head, and then threw him down, his body slamming meatily into the concrete right in front of me.

He managed a single, wet gasp before one of her hooves pressed down on his throat. It was an almost gentle gesture, but that didn’t help the raider. I watched in horror as his hooves grappled and pressed at Sickle, clattering against her armor, while the sucking wound in his chest gurgled with his attempts to breathe.

Sickle lifted her other hoof, and he tried to shove it away as she lowered the leg-mounted blades to his chest. His efforts made no impact on the hoof’s slow descent, even as she slowly pressed the twin blades into him. He flailed and struggled, landing a couple good kicks against her chest, but she didn’t even flinch. It took only moments before his struggles started to lose coordination, ending with a few weak fumbles before his hooves stilled, slowly sliding down her legs.

Sickle lifted her hoof, and the raider gave a faint sigh as the last of his breath left him. One foreleg shifted a little, as if to curl up over his chest, but it never made it.

Sickle turned to me, flecks of blood glistening on her helm. “See?” she rumbled. “I can be quiet.”

I stared at the fresh corpse, breathing as hard as if I had been a part of that struggle myself. I recognized him: one of the raiders who had been in the watchtower. He was skinny and ragged, with a few scraps of leather worn as a crude vest. Fresh bite-marks adorned his neck and shoulder.

Mind you, my shocked reaction had nothing to do with the pony being dead. I had been fully prepared to end his life myself. What I had not been prepared for was the sheer violence of his demise.

Dusty hurried up beside us, his expression tight. “Get inside before someone comes looking!” he whispered. “And bring the body, we need to hide it!”

Sickle chuckled as she picked up the raider, throwing him limply across her back. I reengaged my pistol’s safety and slid it back into its holster, and we hurried toward the darkness of the building.

“Watch for glass,” Starlight hissed as we approached the doors, and we slowed, stepping carefully and nudging glass out of the way before putting any weight down; nopony wanted to catch a shard of glass in the frog. The exception was, naturally, Sickle, who simply walked right in, glass crunching harmlessly under her spiked shoes.

I could barely make out the details of the dark chamber. Several tables with attached benches filled the space, scattered about. A few were knocked askew or broken. Ceiling panels had fallen, leaving debris scattered across the floor and revealing the even darker void beyond the false ceiling. Sickle walked deeper into the room, to a long counter; the room must have been a cafeteria.

We approached the counter, ducking behind it as Starlight floated up her PipBuck and turned the screen on again; while its light could give us away, we also needed it to see. It faintly illuminated the space, and gave just enough light to see the bits of paint that still remained on the walls. It looked like the walls had once held a woodland motif. Now, the cracked and faded remnants among the long expanses of worn gray seemed to mimic the wasteland that Equestria had become.

Sickle dumped the dead raider behind the counter, then paused, looking down at him. “Hey, I know this little fucktoy,” she rumbled, giving him a firm poke with her hoof. “Well, shit! This must be Gutrip’s gang. This little bitch was always sucking on Gut’s hooves.”

Starlight looked up from her PipBuck. “Gutrip? Well he sounds pleasant.”

“It’s just a stupid name,” Sickle said with a rumbling chuckle. “He’s just a big dumbass with a big gun. Some giant drum-fed piece of shit he calls “Chomper”. Something about the bolt; I don’t know. He’s way into that gun. Hell, I’m pretty sure he’s fucked the damn thing. About the only other thing that gets him up is gutting ponies.” She shrugged. “He likes to think he’s big and strong and nasty, but he’s just a little bitch. Lousy fuck, too.”

“This isn’t going to be a problem, is it?” Dusty asked.

I could only barely see the wicked grin Sickle gave under her muzzle. “Naw,” she said, raising a hoof to show off the bloodied blades. “I think I’ll have fun gutting him, just to see how much he likes it.”

“Great,” Dusty dryly replied. “Okay, let’s move. Somepony’s going to come looking for this guy eventually. We need to find their server. And be careful with that light, we don’t want to draw attention.”

“If speed is the issue, we need a map,” Starlight said, turning her PipBuck’s screen down until it gave only the faintest of glows. “Best bet would be a lobby or the like. Otherwise we might have to hunt around and check everywhere to find those servers.”

“Lobby it is, then,” Dusty said. “Lead on.”

The going was slow. Despite the spacious design of the building, it was pitch-black once we were away from the outer windows, forcing us to rely on the faint glow of Starlight’s PipBuck to pick our way through the debris and rubble.

Fortunately, the hall leading out from the cafeteria led straight to the main lobby. It was a towering open space ringed by the balconies of each level. During the day, before it had fallen into decay, it would have been a warm, pleasant space, with its glass wall and roof. Right then, it just felt exposed. We could see the flickering lights of the buildings across the central park.

We waited while Starlight slipped out to the cluster of counters and information displays. It was a couple of minutes of silence, with only the occasional clopping of hooves and rattle of debris being moved.

When she returned, she was carrying a thin object, a placard pried from one of the information displays. She led us back into a small interior room and turned up her light.

It was one of those typical “you are here” maps, with a directory listing what each room was. Starlight’s hoof ran down the list, eyes darting back and forth. “Security office is right across the hall, should definitely check that out first. And I’m seeing two computer-related sections. There’s ‘R&D’ on the top floor, and ‘Data Services’ here on the first.”

“Data Services sounds like the server area,” I said, looking at the map. After a moment, I placed the tip of a hoof down on the first-floor diagram. “In fact, that looks like it’s probably the server room itself.” I moved my hoof to the fifth floor. “But I’d like to check out that R&D, too.”

“I don’t want to get bogged down with side-trips,” Dusty said. “How long will it take to get what you need in R&D?”

“I’d be looking for hardware, mostly,” I replied. “An access tool would be ideal. Barring that, a portable terminal, debug cables, stuff like that. Should be pretty obvious. Maybe a couple minutes to do a quick sweep, plus however long it takes to get in there.”

Dusty cocked his head to the side, giving me a funny, questioning look. “You do a lot of hacking on your farm, huh?”

“Just an old terminal my mom found. Mostly I read a lot of computer science books.” After a moment of consideration, I quietly added, “And maybe a few spy novels, too.”

After all, looking competent was good; looking too competent was suspicious.

“There’s a stairway just around the corner,” Starlight said. “I’m more concerned about power, though. You can’t do anything with a server if it doesn’t have power.”

Dusty blinked in the darkness. “Shit.”

I looked to Starlight. “Do you think a server would have a backup power source?”

I already knew the answer, of course. She slowly nodded, thinking. “Yeah, I guess they usually do. Those kinds of things tend to last well, too. Okay! Security room, up to R&D, and back down for the server?”

We agreed—Sickle merely grunted—and stepped out of the room.

Our quest for the security room ended almost immediately. Starlight pulled on the handle, but it refused to budge. The keypad beside it was dark, and made no response to its buttons being pressed. The cracked dome of a security camera hung silently above it, reflecting the light of Starlight’s PipBuck.

“I could cut it open,” Starlight said, “but that’s not exactly subtle.”

Sickle snorted, clopping a hoof against the floor and grinding a small piece of fallen concrete into dust. “Or I could just kick it open.”

“Maybe it’ll power up with the server,” Dusty said. “Leave it, we can come back later.”

Starlight muttered under her breath, but led us back down the hallway. The stairway door was just before the cafeteria, and opened much more readily than the security office, impeded only by a small heap of debris on the floor.

Hoofsteps echoed throughout the stairway as we slowly made our way up, dominated by the deep, metallic clacking of Sickle’s shoes. There was less debris here, just bits of grit that had fallen from the bare and cracking concrete walls. There was also less light; no windows shone into this interior space, and even though Starlight turned her PipBuck up, it still left half the space cloaked in shadows.

Starlight turned down the light again once we reached the top level, and cautiously cracked open the door. We followed her out into the hall, decorated with crumbling murals of grassy fields and happy ponies. Another camera, minus its dome, hung from the ceiling.

The door to R&D had the same kind of keypad the security room had, but it didn’t matter; the door itself lay askew, hanging from a single hinge, with deep dents all around the handle where someone had rammed it. I followed Starlight through, while Dusty and Sickle remained outside. “Make it quick,” he said, crouching beside the wall and sighting down his rifle in the direction we had come.

Once we were inside, Starlight turned up the light again. I scanned across several desks. The grassland motif continued here as well, cracked and peeling. Dust covered everything. Four vending machines lay torn open against one wall, their cracked signs advertising Sparkle-Cola and Sunrise Sarsaparilla. Bottles lay discarded around the room.

A quick look over the desks revealed nothing interesting. Even the terminals were mostly smashed, save for one in the back corner. Without power, it was just as useless.

We moved on through the opposite door to sweep through the rest of the section, moving from room to room.

The place was trashed. Two hundred years of constant decay and sporadic scavenging had left the darkened offices in shambles. Desks and tables lay scattered about the rooms, many of them damaged or broken. The debris littering the floor was different; less broken ceiling panels and crumbling bits of concrete, more discarded electrical components and prototyping breadboards. If I spent a few hours collecting various bits and pieces and sorting out the ones that still work, I might be able to make something out of it; a crude radio or clock, for instance. Nothing worth the time spent in hostile territory.

A rack of cables, bolted to the wall under a chipped painting of a pair of ponies frolicking in a meadow, drew my attention. A few seconds of sorting through them left me disappointed. They were all standard terminal connectors, nothing special. I still tucked a set into my bags, just in case.

Shadows swept along the walls as we moved, industrial-grade blank gemstones and other electrical components crunching under-hoof. The sickly green light glinted off broken terminal screens as it struggled to illuminate the dark, cluttered spaces. In the poor light, I almost missed our first good find. I had to call Starlight back to shine her PipBuck under the broken desk to find what I had glimpsed.

Lying half-buried under a set of prototyped circuits and half an office chair was a thick case. It was a fair bit larger than the medical box I carried in my bags, and much heavier, but infinitely more valuable: a portable terminal, one of the old models that was crude in comparison to the later PipBuck portable terminals, but which still carried sufficient functionality for basic diagnostics. It would serve my purposes.

The case was badly cracked and dented, but not warped to the point I would expect internal damage. I wiped the dust off and opened the top panel to reveal its keyboard and a small screen, with a thin crack running through the top right corner.

I flipped the power switch. Nothing happened.

“Battery probably died,” Starlight whispered, her horn lighting up as she rooted around in her bag. “Pop open the case, let’s see what it uses.”

I closed the lid and turned it over to pry open the battery access panel. Once I had, Starlight pulled out the large battery. “Heck of a spark-pack on this thing,” she said, lifting it up to squint at the writing along its side. “Ah, good. This should work.”

She floated over a fresh battery to slide into its place, and I sealed up the panel again. I flipped it right-side up again, opened the screen, and flipped the switch.

This time, I was rewarded by the quiet whirring and clicking of the computer starting up, and characters started scrolling across the screen.

I set it atop the desk to finish booting and rooted through the debris below. After a few moments of searching, my hooves found a strap among the trash. Pulling on it rewarded me with a torn and ratty satchel, but it wasn’t the bag itself that interested me. What interested me was the contents, including a full set of debug cables and a small toolset specialized for computers and electronics. Sadly, the data-store inside the bag was badly damaged, with its case broken in half and bent. I doubted it would still work, but I kept it, just in case I was wrong.

The portable terminal had finished booting up. A quick check revealed what I had suspected; it was a very, very simple device, with practically no storage capacity and a spell-matrix gemset that was bordering on antiquated well before the megaspells dropped. Still, it was sufficient for my purposes. I turned it off again, closed the screen, and took its carrying handle in my teeth.

We continued on, quickly scanning through the rest of the place for anything obvious, but not wasting much time at it. Every minute we spent here was another minute spent in raider territory, and I for one did not want to drag it out longer than absolutely necessary.

The one place we did pause to search was a small PipBuck research office, but our hopes were low of finding anything useful. It was even more ransacked than the rest of the offices, to the point where the tool cabinet had been pried from the wall and carried away, leaving a blank spot of bare concrete in the crumbling imagery of sunny fields. Still, the PipBucks were one of the most advanced pieces of arcano-tech ever developed, so we spent a minute to scour the place.

We found nothing. No abandoned PipBucks, no diagnostic or access tools, nothing. Not even the specialized keys needed to unlock them.

When we slipped out of the office again, Dusty glanced my way, keeping his rifle fixed down the hallway. Seeing the case I was carrying, he asked, “Find what you were looking for?”

“Yes,” I said. “I should be able to get past any security the servers might have with this and a bit of time.”

“Good. Let’s get to it, then.”

We returned to the stairway, and by it, to the ground floor. From there, Starlight led us slowly through a couple halls, until we arrived at a door labeled “Data Services”.

Stepping through, we found ourselves in what looked to be a secretary’s office. Beyond that were more offices, and a single heavy, keypad-locked door labeled “Server Room”, watched over by another camera.

Dusty frowned before turning to me. “Any way you can use that thing to hack the lock, or whatever?”

“That’s not really the kind of electronic device that you ‘hack’,” I replied around the portable terminal’s handle. “Especially not without power.”

“Just shut the door to the hall,” Starlight said, pulling out her cutting torch and goggles. “It’s an interior space, no windows for anypony to see this.”

Dusty nodded, moving back to shut the door leading out to the rest of the offices.

We sat and waited while the cutting torch cast the place into sharp relief of light and shadow, and seared flashes of the room into our vision. When she finished, she slipped her implements back into her bag before pulling out a pry bar. “Hey, um… Sickle? Could you help catch this so it doesn’t make a bunch of noise? Please?”

Sickle gave a sharp snort within her muzzle. “Yeah, whatever.”

Once she had moved into place, Starlight wrenched on the pry bar. A moment later the door’s cut hinges slipped apart, and the bottom of the door settled to the ground with a thud. Sickle caught the top edge easily, and lowered it to the ground. Even dropped from just an inch above the ground, the door produced a deep thump on landing.

Sickle’s hoof clanked noisily atop the door. “You know, I don’t get nearly as much caps if this stays all quiet-like.”

Frowning, Starlight slid the pry bar back into her bags. “You don’t have to fight if it stays quiet, either.”

“Yeah,” Sickle replied, chuckling darkly. “‘Have to’. That’s a good one.”

Dusty stepped in. “You want to be paid for the job, you have to do the job. Right now, the job is staying quiet. Got it?”

The huge, armored head slowly turned toward him—he backed up half a step—and fixed him with a stare that lasted a couple seconds. “Yeah. I got it, Dirt.”

She turned away again, leading the way into the server room.

The place was filled with a half-dozen large arrays. Arcano-tech gemstones glittered in the green light, nearly hidden behind the circuitry and mess of wires. The servers looked intact, if horribly dusty.

“This looks like what we want,” Starlight said, trotting to the back corner of the room. An array of spark batteries were mounted to the wall, just above a tiny spark generator. She searched around for a bit, finding the power switch for the generator. She reached for it, then paused. “I don’t know how obvious it will be, once I flip this. This thing shouldn’t put out much power, but it might turn on a few lights.”

I set down my newfound portable terminal, opening the screen and turning it on. “I’ll be as quick as I can, then we can shut the power down again.” Pulling out the collection of cables I had gathered, and looking over the ports of the server, I selected the correct one and plugged it in.

Dusty set Lady Amber’s data-store beside me, then returned to the doorway. He crouched, leveling his rifle down the hallway and out of my sight. Sickle sat behind him, unreadable beneath that helm.

When my terminal finished booting up, I nodded to Starlight. “Ready.”

She nodded back.

“Here we go.”

The spark generator whirred as she pressed the button. Red lights appeared above the spark batteries mounted above it, rapidly switching to green. The servers thrummed, crystals lighting up, and the servers’ boot-up text started scrolling across my terminal’s screen.

A small screen beside the spark-battery array lit up, as well. It was small, but the text was large enough for me to read.

Server Power Management System V1.32

Alert: operating on backup power

Primary power system offline

Attempting reset…

A deep thump sounded faintly beneath us, and a vibration ran through the floor. A loud beep sounded, followed by the clunk of electrical switches engaging, and the the room was suddenly bathed in light.

The small power-management screen blinked out a new message.

Reset complete

Primary power system online

Dusty drew back from the doorway, blinking against the sudden brightness. “Every damn light in the building just turned on!” he hissed. “How long is that going to take, Whisper?”

“Unknown,” I said, squinting at the screen as the messages continued to scroll. Somewhere, in another room, a shrill tone sounded for a couple seconds, likely some form of alarm about the electrical system. “The servers are still booting, and I have no idea how much data we’ll need to transfer.”

Music had started playing from nearby, filling the air with energetic beats and electronic sound. It sounded much like the kinds of music DJ Pon3 had made; it was another flash of nostalgia for a world dead for centuries, even if I didn’t recognize the song itself. Not that I spent much time focusing on the tune, even before Starlight hurried over to turn off the player. I kept my focus on the screen of my terminal, waiting as the servers went through their laborious startup procedure.

The boot-up finished.

With another keypress, I attempted to connect to the server. A password request appeared on my screen. I hit another key, and watched over the flood of data that flowed through the servers’ spell matrix.

I was hunting through that data when the gunfire started. It was distant, faint pops echoing through the many hallways to barely reach our ears. A muffled explosion rumbled like distant thunder. I cast a glance to the doorway; Dusty was still crouched there, silent and unmoving as he peered down his sights. Sickle was still sitting beside the doorway. I caught her grin before she latched her muzzle back in place, slipping a pill bottle back into one of her armored saddlebags.

Dusty must have noticed my glance. “How much longer?”

“Just getting the login,” I said, eyes returning to my screen as I selected the relevant piece of data from within the spell matrix.

“Make it quick,” he said. “We’re backed into a corner, here.”

“Maybe not!” Starlight called out from the back corner of the room. I looked her way to see her standing by an open floor hatch, grinning. “Looks like this goes down to a service level. We might have another way out.”

“Good,” Dusty said, and I flashed her a smile before turning back to my screen. The servers had accepted my meddling and allowed me to log on.

I plugged the data-store in and typed a quick command. “Files are transferring.”

“How long?” Dusty quietly asked.

The gunfire had stopped

I looked at the list of files rapidly scrolling across my screen. “Hard to say,” I said, keeping my voice low. “It’s thousands of files.” I watched the text continuing to scroll again before I felt like hazarding a guess. “Should be only a couple minutes.”

Path and file names started to slowly climb upwards through the alphabet as we waited.

We were nearing the end when, without a single word or sound of warning, Dusty opened fire.

I cringed, ducking halfway behind one of the server assemblies as he fired most of the magazine in a long string, before slowing and firing in shorter bursts. He ducked back, and I glanced down to my screen. I couldn’t be sure exactly how many more files were left, but it had to be getting close.

I looked up in time to see Dusty chuck something around the corner before calling out, “Down!”

The moment after I tucked myself against the base of the server, the grenade he had thrown went off. It wasn’t a deep, rumbling boom like in the radio plays. It was as sharp and sudden as a lightning bolt. I felt it in the floor, in the air. The lights all blinked and flickered, making my gut wrench with adrenaline, but a quick glance at my screen showed that the servers had continued on just fine.

“We’re running out of time!” Dusty shouted back as he slammed a new magazine home, cycled the weapon, and took up a firing stance once more; the hallway beyond him was much dimmer now.

“Almost there!” I replied, my words feeling mushy in my ears as I clutched my terminal.

The scrolling list of files stopped, leaving me at a command prompt.

“It’s done!” I called out, pulling the cable and data-store free to toss into my bags.

Dusty stepped back from the doorway. “Move!”

Starlight disappeared down the hole as I shut the screen of my portable terminal and picked it up in my teeth. When I got to the hatch, I cast a glance back at Dusty. He had stuck his muzzle into a large pouch. A moment later he pulled back, a metal disk clenched in his teeth. He hit something on the top with a hoof, then chucked it beside the door.

That’s a mine, I realized, and hurried down the open hatch.

I nearly fell in my haste, slipping on the short ladder, but made my way safely to the small, subterranean room. A single orange light dimly lit the space, with its bare pipes and electrical conduits. A door was set into one wall.

Dusty followed moments behind me, and finally Sickle squeezed her bulk down the hole, grumbling the whole way.

“Shoulda just fought them,” she growled as she reached the bottom, with all of her sharp metal protrusions making the small space seem even more claustrophobic. “Instead of all this chicken-shit running.”

“Patience,” Dusty said. “For now, we need to keep moving.”

“One sec,” Starlight said, somehow squeezing past Sickle and climbing up the ladder. She pulled the hatch shut—Sickle hadn’t bothered closing it—and jammed a piece of metal into the latch on the bottom.

She slid back down, hopping past Sickle. “Okay, now we can go,” she said, and took the lead once again. She opened the door and stepped out, while Dusty trailed close on her heels, rifle at the ready.

The pipes and conduits continued down the tunnel beyond the door. We walked, bits of rubble crunching under-hoof. The hum of generators grew louder.

We were halfway down the tunnel when a deep, muffled explosion shook the ground, casting down a soft hail of dust and dirt from the ceiling. Most of us stayed silent. Sickle gave a single dry chuckle.

The tunnel eventually ended with another heavy door. It opened onto a platform overlooking a much larger access tunnel, which stretched off to either side. Four spark generators were set in a row across from us, three of which were humming along happily. The sound of machinery thrummed from all directions. Most of the sound came from a door labeled “Utilities”, just beside the path we had emerged from.

When we reached the edge of the platform and the metal stairs leading down, we saw that the main tunnel was flooded.

Starlight halted and grimaced. “That’s… really not good.”

Dusty halted at the top of the stairs. “What? What’s wrong?”

“That,” she said, pointing to the water. “The water. You can’t see where you’re stepping.”

“We’ll just have to be careful, then,” he replied, but she gave a sharp shake of her head.

“Very careful,” Starlight said. “That’s got ‘infection’ written all over it. And who knows what you could step on under there. You know what tetanus does to a pony?”

“Oh for fuck’s sake,” Sickle growled as she shoved past Dusty and made her way down the stairs. “Move your asses already, I’m ready to be done with this shit.” She waded out, unconcerned about underwater obstacles with her heavy shoes. Then she paused. “...The fuck way are we going, anyway?”

“That way,” Starlight said, sighing as she gestured to our left, and reluctantly followed. She dipped her hoof gingerly into the water, only to jerk it back as if bit. “Holy shit this is cold,” she said as she slowly slid it in again. The water reached up to her knees.

I took a moment to fully power down my portable terminal before entering, and craned my head back to keep it lifted well clear of the water. Starlight was right; the water was icy. The dank, stagnant smell suggested it wasn’t very healthy, either.

Starlight muttered as we went. “We’re in the middle of a desert. Where did all this water come from?” She snorted, and immediately answered her own question. “It’s probably rainwater. At least that should mean there’s a way out.”

We waded through the muck, while the few working lights struggled to illuminate our path. The splashing of our movements echoed down the damp tunnel. I winced every time my hooves bumped into something with my shuffling steps. Some were rocks or other hard objects. Occasionally, it was squishy.

After a hundred yards of wading through the muck, we came to another set of stairs, leading up to another platform. We happily made our way to dry land, shaking off the cold water and stomping our hooves to shake off the muck that clung to them. I felt foul, and made a note to not touch my face until I’d gotten the chance to wash my hooves thoroughly. I idly wondered if Emerald stocked soap.

One door led out from the platform, locked with a keypad and festooned with warning signs. The most prominent declared the space beyond as property of Equestrian Robotics, warning that all unauthorized personnel would face not just potential prosecution for trespassing and possible espionage during a time of war, but also the lethal security systems intended to protect the facility, its workers, and the nation they served.

All in all, a fairly standard warning in wartime Equestria, as depressing as that is.

Unlike the keypads we had encountered before, this one was now powered. Starlight stepped up, her tools already floating before her. “Give me a minute, I got this.”

As she pried off the keypad’s case, Dusty looked to me. “Cover the rear. They might follow us, and if we can catch them knee-deep in water, all the better.”

I nodded, moving back to the top of the stairs to lie down, my rifle pointed off down the dimly lit tunnel. I stared off into the gloom, listening to the thrum of machinery and the clicking of Starlight’s tools.

A faint buzz sounded from the door. “Got it!” Starlight declared, followed by grinding as she pulled the door open.

In the next instant, there was an angry beep, a sharp yelp of surprise from Starlight, a clatter of hooves, and an ear-hammering blast of gunfire. I spun around to see chips of concrete flying as bullets sailed through the open doorway to blast chunks out of the concrete pad beyond.

“Turret!” Starlight called out as she scrambled away from the doorway and turned around. Her hind-leg nearly went out, and she turned again to look back at her flank. “Oh shit,” she said, her voice oddly calm. “It hit me.”

My heart lurched, blood running cold.

She turned in a circle, trying to get a better look at her flank, staggering when her right hind leg barely supported her. I scrambled up as her flank came back into view. At first, she looked uninjured. It took me a moment to notice the wound, a tiny blemish just in front of her cutie mark. She lifted her hoof to continue the turn, the muscles of her thigh flexed, and blood flowed from the wound in a thick surge. “Oh shit,” she repeated, her hoof stepping down again, and she staggered again; this time, her leg gave out and she toppled over.

“I got shot,” she said, eyes wide and staring as Dusty and I hurried over to her. “It shot me. Oh shit, it shot me!”

The moment Dusty’s hoof touched her side, she jerked away. “Don’t touch it!” she shouted, horn lighting up to shove Dusty back; I had to give her credit, she could put a good amount of force into it. The shove sent him staggering back to fall on his rump. “You’ll get it infected! Oh shit, shit, shit…”

He was immediately up, hurrying back over, though he didn’t put a hoof on her just yet. “You’re bleeding,” he said, as I came skidding to a halt by Starlight’s head. She had rolled onto her side, wounded flank up; the wound was still for a moment, but then the blood flowed again, pulsing with her heartbeat. “You’re bleeding bad,” Dusty corrected. “Bleeding first, then infection.”

Starlight was already pulling open her bags, digging out medical supplies. “I can fix this. D-don’t touch it, you’ll get that m-muck in there.”

“Settle down,” Dusty said, pulling out a pouch of his own. “Calm down, stay still—”

“No, I need—fuck!” Starlight yelped and jerked as she tried to move her leg. Dusty placed a hoof on her thigh, below the injury, and she seemed too distracted by the pain to object.

“Settle down!” Dusty said. “You know the deal: combat time means listen to me. Now settle down.”

Starlight breathed through gritted teeth. Lacking anything more productive, I placed a hoof comfortingly on the side of her neck.

“We need to stop this bleeding,” Dusty said. “It’s bad enough I’m not going to trust anything short of a healing potion. You could take one now, but that’ll heal the bullet inside you; you’ll need surgery to get it out, and it won’t be pleasant. Or, I can try to get it out now. Which will it be?”

Starlight’s leg jerked again, making her cringe, and Dusty moved a hoof to put pressure directly on the wound, adding, “Make it quick, or I’m deciding for you.” Her response was a choked whine, and after a moment, her horn lit again, digging through her medical supplies to pull out a set of forceps, which trembled in her magic. Dusty caught its handle in his teeth and turned to her wound, while she pulled out a familiar pair of bottles, setting them beside her head, ready to use.

“Okay,” Dusty said around the forceps. “This is going to hurt, but I need you to stay as still as you can.”

He lowered his head, bringing the forceps toward the wound and moving his hoof away. Blood covered the underside of his hoof, flowing down the curve of Starlight’s thigh. She tensed beneath my hoof. Then she yelled out. “Wait!”

Dusty jerked, pulling back and placing his hoof over the wound again. He looked her way as her magic grabbed at her medical supplies again. This time she produced a sealed hypodermic needle. She pried the cap off the needle, the tip wavering as she brought it to her thigh.

“Let Whisper do that,” Dusty said around the forceps, his hoof still pressed to the wound.

The needle halted as she looked up to me. I didn’t need any more prompting; I leaned in, gripping the body of the needle in my teeth, then brought it to her thigh, several inches up from the wound. “Is here good?” I asked around it, and when she grunted and nodded, I leaned in further. The exposed inch of thin metal brushed past her fur and slid easily into her flesh, and I pressed a hoof to the thin plunger to deliver the dose. She hissed faintly, but otherwise remained still.

Finished, I slid the needle back out, taking the time to replace the cap before setting it aside.

Starlight sucked in several deep breaths while Dusty waited patiently. Finally, she nodded. “Okay. Do it.”

The hoof pulled back again, and Dusty lined up the forceps. She tensed, and I gave a gentle squeeze. Then the tip of the forceps slid into the wound, and she hissed, gritting her teeth. As they slid in further, that hiss turned into a low growl.

There was a sharp clunk of metal on concrete behind me, and Sickle snorted. I turned my head her way, momentarily losing any common sense as I shot a harsh glare at the brutish mare that could kill me with casual ease, but she wasn’t even looking at us. Instead, she was turning away and walking toward the door.

Just before she got there, she lowered her head, and her steel-shod hooves cracked against the concrete floor as she sprang into a full gallop, charging down the hall and out of sight.

The same angry beep sounded, followed immediately by the sound of gunfire. I jerked in surprise; somehow, Dusty did not. The gunfire was matched with the deep thunks and pings of bullets striking thick metal, until it was replaced with the tortured sound of metal tearing and a ratcheting sound, like gears grinding. That lasted only a second before there was a loud pop, and Sickle shouted, “Fuck!”

Dusty kept the forceps remarkably stable as he called out, “If you just got yourself shot, you’re going to have to wait your turn.”

Sickle’s reply echoed down the hall. “Fuck you too, Dirt.”

Focusing on his work, Dusty slid the forceps in deep enough that his muzzle was almost touching Starlight’s thigh. He bit down on the grips, and I actually heard metal scrap faintly on metal as Starlight cringed. He had to back out a bit, parting the grips once more, and tried again; this time, it clamped down on something.

Starlight growled louder as he pulled, finally blurting out, “That’s not the bullet!”

“It is,” Dusty assured her.

“It’s not—Gah!”

Dusty pulled free. Starlight’s growl of pain faded to deep breathing as she looked up at him.

Clasped in the forceps was the remains of a bullet. The front of it had been completely smashed in and flared out wider than the base, looking more like a mushroom than a bullet. It was also smeared in blood.

Dusty set the forceps down beside the other medical supplies, then pulled a small, sturdy vial from a pouch; a healing potion.

“Wait,” Starlight said, her attention finally pulling away from the bullet. Her magic grabbed one of her bottles, floating it in a shaky grip. “Gotta sterilize. Clean. No infection.”

Dusty took the bottle, then frowned. “You shouldn’t use this on open wounds,” he said, and after checking the other bottle, quickly swapped them. “This will do.”

He popped open the cap, squirting the fluid into the wound. Starlight hissed a little, but remained still. The fluid washed away most of the blood, and Dusty used a bit of gauze to wipe around the wound. Then he brought the healing potion out and removed the stopper. He poured a little of it into the wound, then passed it to me. “Have her drink that,” he said as he grabbed a magic-laced bandage, pressing it to the wound with a bloody hoof.

Starlight blinked a few times, having difficulty focusing on the potion I held out to her. I hoped it was the painkillers dulling her senses, rather than blood loss. Her horn lit, taking the vial, and she downed it.

After a minute of waiting, Dusty peeled back the bandage, washing away a little more blood to get a better look at the wound before pressing it back into place. “Okay. Bleeding’s stopped, or close to it.” He retrieved a roll of gauze before turning to me. “Lift her hind leg so I can wrap it.”

Starlight spoke up. “I can lift—ow!” She gritted her teeth again, her leg dropping again.

“And that’s why I asked Whisper to do it,” Dusty said, keeping his hoof on the bandage. Starlight grumbled something under her breath as I scooted down, gently sliding my forehooves under her thigh and knee to lift the leg up. I was met with the wet feeling of blood.

There was a lot of blood. Not an excessive amount, mind you. There was no spreading pool of it beneath her. It wasn’t enough that I worried for her life. Still, it was enough to be concerning. The entire front of her thigh was slick with blood, and it had run down her lower belly to her other leg. It seemed like so much blood for such a tiny hole.

I was relieved to see the corner of her mouth quirk upwards, despite all that. “Hey, Dusty?”

“Yeah?”

“Your bedside manner sucks.”

He paused in his wrapping. Then he laughed softly, his hooves resuming their task. “Hey, I thought I was being nice. I even gave you a say in your treatment. Medics don’t usually do that, you know.”

She chuckled a little, while he finished up. I gently set her leg down again, then wiped my bloody hooves against the ground. It didn’t do much good.

Sickle returned, grumbling as she wiped at her muzzle. I reflected that, with her blades washed clean by the flooded tunnel, the violent “ex raider” was possibly the least bloody of the group.

And we had only just started.

Dusty noted her return as well. “You okay over there?”

“No,” Sickle grumbled, snorting. “I’m going to be smelling burned hair for the rest of the day. Fucking spark battery blew up in my face.”

“Yeah,” Starlight murmured. “You got it so hard over there.”

Sickle snorted again, and I honestly couldn’t tell if it was annoyed or amused. “Fuck you. At least I’m not lying down to take a nap.”

“No taunting my patient,” Dusty chided, retrieving a bottle of water from his bags. He splashed a little of it on Starlight’s legs and belly before wiping at her coat, crudely cleaning her.

“Hey, watch the hooves,” Starlight mumbled, then blinking and refocusing on the water bottle as he set it in front of her.

“Drink the rest of that,” he said. “You’ll need to stay well hydrated, even with the healing magic doing its work.”

Once she had downed the remains of the bottle, he crouched beside her, moving in close. “Okay, let’s see if we can get you upright.”

It took surprisingly little effort to get Starlight on her hooves again. She was able to rise on her own, wobbling only slightly against Dusty’s side. Putting weight on her leg made her wince, but she weathered it. Her speech came slowly, as if she were thinking out each word. “Yeah... yeah, I think I’m good now.”

“You sure?” Dusty asked. “You’re sounding a little out of it.”

“Yeah,” she said, blinking several times. She gave an abrupt shake of her head, followed by a little stumble. “Those painkillers are really good. I’m fine, just… a little slow.”

Dusty frowned, but nodded. “And you can walk?”

Starlight took a deep breath, then moved one hoof forward. One after another, she walked, wincing only slightly when she stepped with the wounded leg. “Yeah. Yeah, I can walk. I’d just rather not go very fast.”

Dusty was frowning again. “We may not have that option. Can you hustle if needed?”

Starlight lifted her leg, slowly moving it back and forth, flexing it, and finally setting the hoof back on the ground. “I should be good, yeah. Might just be a little cranky afterwards.”

“Good enough,” Dusty said. “Keep a healing potion handy, and down it if the bleeding starts up again, or if you’re having trouble keeping up.”

She nodded.

Dusty slowly looked around at us, then nodded as well. “Okay, enough drama. We need to get moving. Keep an eye out for the raiders and any other turrets. Let’s get this done.”

The turret had been a ceiling-mounted model. After its encounter with Sickle, it had been reduced to torn shards of metal and scattered ammunition, and the air was filled with the smell of burnt electronics. Though they looked like the same caliber of round that my pistol fired, we didn’t pause to collect it.

Past the turret was a set of stairs, leading up to another door. Our little subterranean excursion had brought us to ground level again.

Dusty cracked open the door to peek out into the sparsely lit hall beyond. We could hear something sparking in the distance, and a once-pleasant tune echoed quietly through the halls, warped into something sinister by damaged speakers.

Once Dusty opened the door enough for me to see out, I found myself even more concerned. The place looked like a warzone. Most of the false ceiling had collapsed, with sections of the frame hanging at odd angles. Only a few of the ceiling lights still worked, often hanging in the partially collapsed frame and struggling to light the ruined spaces. Bullet holes and scorch marks riddled the walls. A broken robot, one of those creepy models with a biological brain, sparked and smouldered a short distance away. The scent of cordite and ozone hung thick in the air.

Somewhere, far in the distance, I could hear a short bout of shouting. I hoped that meant their attention would be elsewhere. It sounded like it came from a different building, though I couldn’t be sure.

Dusty pulled back. “We can’t go into the lobby to swipe another map. If it’s anything like Stable-Tec’s, they’d see us easy. We’re going to have to move quietly and search for the servers. Make sure you can’t be seen from any windows; we’re going to be pretty lit up here.”

We—Starlight and I, that is—nodded in agreement. Sickle merely grunted again.

Slipping out of the door, we moved slowly down the ruined hall, looking in every door. Every room we found was trashed. Desks were overturned or broken. Papers were scattered and burnt. In one office, the ceiling had completely given way, with twisted rebar barely holding the collapsed concrete together to form a crude, steep slope leading upstairs, and a heap of ruined desks and office dividers piled at its base. We passed it by, though I made note of it, just in case.

The hall led to a common area. Once, it might have been a pretty and restful location, with several benches and tables, all made of metal and concrete. The lone working light instead cast a gloom over the dust and debris-covered furniture.

We were halfway through the space when gunfire erupted, a series of sounds so rapid that they seemed to blend into one. I caught the light of the muzzle flash down a hall to our side as I threw myself to the ground behind a bench. My world became incredibly small for a moment. I was barely aware of Starlight dropping beside me. The gunshots hammered at my ears, echoing off the walls of the chamber. Chips of concrete flew through the air, peppering me.

The gunfire paused. My awareness expanded enough to become aware of Dusty behind the next bench, rising to bring his rifle up. Another burst of gunfire sent him ducking again as bullets tore chunks out of the concrete benches we hid behind, throwing dust and fragments through the air.

The instant the burst finished, Dusty rose, snapping off a short burst in reply, the sound pounding at my head. He immediately ducked down again as another blast of gunfire peppered our cover.

I had only just shaken off the shock and recognized that I was a part of the fight when my ears finally picked up the sound of an angry yell. A moment later the yell was above me; in the dim light, a silhouette loomed above me in mid-leap, a long piece of metal glinting as it came down at me.

Sickle surged forward, and the raider’s leap crashed to a halt in mid-air as his chest met her waiting blades. She swung him up, over her head, and threw him to the ground hard enough that he bounced, his body gone completely limp with the impact. Another burst of gunfire erupted from down the hall, producing deep thunks as it impacted Sickle’s armor; there were no sparks, as I had half expected, but even in the dim light I could make out a couple puffs as the bullets shattered on the metal plates. I felt something slap against my shoulder, jarring my attention back toward the fight.

I grabbed the bit of my rifle as Dusty fired another short burst. I rose just enough to get the weapon over the back of the bench when the return fire came; I saw the flash from down the hall, and suddenly all I could see was a spray of gray dust and flying bits of concrete. I jerked back, dropping behind cover again. The bullet had struck right in front of my face! If not for that bench, I would have died!

Something light slapped against my side again, and I looked back to see Sickle fastening her muzzle again. I looked down to see what had hit me. An old, faded inhaler lay on the ground beside me.

I had seen that sort of thing in Appleloosa, so long ago. The smuggling of zebra drugs through the town had been one of the more interesting aspects of my work, and had led to a fairly casual understanding of contraband pharmaceuticals. While at the time I couldn’t be certain exactly what the inhaler had contained, the most immediately obvious assumption was Dash.

As Starlight raised her Recharger to send wild shots in the general direction of the shooter, Dusty yelled back, his voice sounding oddly mushy in my ears. “Sickle! We need your help, here!”

“I am helping!” she bellowed in reply, while repeatedly stabbing the dead raider in the neck with her leg-blades and emitting a disturbingly un-ponylike snarl of gleeful rage.

With adrenaline coursing through my veins, I rose again. This time, I twisted to get my rifle over the back of the bench while exposing as little as possible. Aiming was impossible, but I reasoned that hardly made a difference; I’m not a terribly good shot to begin with. I made up for it by simply holding the trigger down, answering the incoming fire with the roar of my own.

The instant the bolt slammed shut on an empty chamber, another blast of gunfire peppered our position. Dusty fired off a short burst of his own, momentarily drowning out everything else, but was forced behind cover as a new gun opened up; the sound was deeper and slower, and the impacts chewed chunks out of the concrete bench, rapidly tearing away at Dusty’s cover.

I was halfway through swapping out magazines when Sickle stepped over me. “Fucking catch!” she roared, throwing the severed head of the dead raider, while bullets smacked into her armor.

I was informed later that she hit one of the shooters square in the face.

Then she leaped over the bench and charged, snarling like a wild animal.

And she sounded happy.

Dusty was up immediately, and Starlight and I followed his example. I was up just in time to see Sickle lunge through a doorway. There was a flash of light from within, a short, rapid burst of gunfire, and the gun fell silent. Dusty quickly moved forward with his smooth, gliding walk, rifle leveled unerringly down the hall.

A deeper gunshot sounded from around the next corner, the muzzle-flash bright in the dim space. It was answered with a bellow from Sickle. “Motherfucker!” The gun fired again, this time a long burst as the pony held the trigger down. The muzzle-flashes cast a strobe-light over the scene as Sickle barreled out past the end of the hallway to charge the shooter.

We reached the corner just two seconds later. Dusty snapped to a halt, aiming his rifle around the corner while hardly exposing himself. Myself, I skidded on the scattered grit and rubble, sliding out a bit further before halting my progress. I was just in time to see Sickle throw her head to the side, flinging a stallion off of her armor’s horn and into a wall.

Flashes lit up the hall past her as more ponies opened fire, and several more moved around. It was all a vague blur as I scrambled back behind cover. Behind the fusillade of fire, I could only barely hear Sickle’s answering roar.

Dusty pulled back. “Star! Take this corner, fall back if they push you. Whisper! On me!”

With that, he bolted back down the hall we had just come down, and I rushed after him.

The gallop slowed to a brisk trot as we entered the common room again and turned right. I understood his intention, then; he was moving around behind the group we had just seen.

A silhouette came running around the next corner of the dark hall, something long clasped in their teeth. Dusty’s rifle barked twice, and the pony’s run turned into a tumble. Dusty continued on, slowing for only a moment as he neared to point the muzzle at the scrawny mare’s head and fire once more, the muzzle-flash searing the image of her dazed expression into my eyes.

He slowed again as he reached the corner, dropping into that smooth, gliding walk as he turned into the next hall.

I heard the distinct pop of Starlight’s Lancer, and a red glow lit up the wall at the end of the hallway, slowly fading as whatever she hit burned away. It was followed by several quieter pops and flashes of blue.

Dusty broke out into a trot again, dodging around a broken table and another fallen robot. He halted at the corner, casting a glance back to make sure I was right behind him. Around the corner we could hear more sporadic gunfire, and another sharp Lancer discharge.

With just a nod for warning, Dusty raised his rifle and rounded the corner, and I followed.

He was firing before I had cleared the corner. Sharp, single shots rang out in rapid succession. I only got a vague impression of the space when I stepped out. Wide, tall, dimly lit, with many obstacles. Dusty had continued moving out, mostly perpendicular to the direction he was shooting, which left me with a clear line of fire.

I was not nearly as controlled and professional as Dusty. I saw a cluster of ponies, tongued the trigger, and didn’t release until the hammering retort of my rifle fell silent. For two seconds, the entire world was thunder and blinding light.

When the magazine ran dry, nearly sending me staggering as the pounding pressure suddenly ceased, I blinked against the spots in my vision. Past my dazzled vision, I could see Dusty advancing through the upturned tables the raiders had been hiding behind, pausing to put another round into one of the fallen ponies.

I numbly fumbled my way through reloading. I was on my last magazine.

The room looked to be another cafeteria, littered with broken tables and buffet lines. Several ponies lay scattered around the closest tables, near where the halls led into the open space. They might have been good cover from the direction Starlight had been, but it had left them completely unprotected from our attack.

A deep, powerful gunshot echoed from another room, louder than any gunshot I had heard before. It was immediately followed by loud crashes of metal. Dusty’s head snapped around, back toward where Starlight watched from a corner, and we quickly moved that way.

It wasn’t hard to tell which way Sickle had gone. Even through the devastation that gripped the entire building, the wake of fresh destruction was clear. A door lead into a surprisingly well-lit kitchen, revealing another raider lying broken atop an old, crushed oven. Bones jutted out from a mangled leg, his muzzle flattened and bloody, his back and neck twisted at unnatural angles. Another raider lay beside a bent rebar spear, her hooves clutching her neck as she tried to stem the flow of blood pouring past her hooves and into the spreading puddle beneath her.

Dusty leveled his rifle at her head and fired. The mare’s whole body jerked, and her head seemed to deform in the most disturbing way as the round pulverized her skull.

Over the growing ringing in my ears, I heard Sickle bellow again, followed by another loud crash of metal.

We hurried to the far side of the kitchen and out the broken metal door to find Sickle grappling with a large white stallion. He wore a metal breastplate and a battle saddle with a huge, bulky gun on it, though I couldn’t make out many details as they rolled around.

As big as he was, it was clear he was no match for Sickle. She rolled over and smashed him into the side of a table, then rolled over on top of him to pin him to the ground. Her hoof raised up, slamming down into his face. He reeled, hooves punching at her side. She hit him again, smashing his muzzle in and slamming his head against the floor. Blood splattered across his pale coat, and his struggles subsided to merely clutching her in his weakening grip.

Evidently deciding she had things under control, Dusty moved past her to another table, setting up to look past it. We were at the edge of the building now, by a set of wide windows, and he aimed out of those. Lacking any better idea of what I should do, I figured I should follow his example.

The gurgling, angry cry from the stallion drew my attention back moments later. He was struggling again, but it wasn’t until I saw Sickle pull her hoof back that I saw why; blood dripped from her blades as they rose from his belly, entrails glistening from within the long, ragged gash.

She looked like a true horror, a monster. She stared face-to-face with him, blood smeared across and steadily dribbling from her helm as his struggles slowly weakened, hooves sliding on blood-slicked metal plates. His eyes fluttered as his head sank down again, legs slowly going limp as consciousness faded.

I simply stared, too numb to act.

The crunch of grit under hoof snapped my attention back to the world, and I spun around, only to halt myself as I saw Starlight approaching. She wobbled a little as she looked at Sickle, who sat panting over the downed raider, then back to us. “Did we get them all?”

Dusty spoke without turning from his position. “Star, smash those lights behind us, then set up watching toward those other buildings. If there are any others, they’re going to come running.” I turned back to the windows, squinting in the darkness. I could only just make out the silhouette of the Stable-Tec offices next door.

A moment later, the light behind us popped, lighting the area with a small shower of sparks before plunging us into darkness. Absent the surrounding light, I quickly started to pick out more details of the grounds outside. The hulk of a giant sentinel bot sat a short distance away. One of its legs was entirely removed from its hull, lying a short distance away.

“Holy fuck,” Starlight said behind us. “What the hell did you do to him?”

I cast a glance back to see Sickle wobbling as she rose; the raider beneath her was clearly dead now, his entrails slopped out of his thoroughly mauled belly. “I had some fun with him,” she said, her voice thick and wet. She coughed several times, and spit up a wad of bloody phlegm, which struck the bars of her muzzle and clung to them, dangling there. Blood continued to dribble from her chin. “Besides, serves him right. Fucker tried to shoot me in the ass.”

In the gloom, I caught the glint of light as Starlight’s eyes changed focus. “Uh, it kinda looks like he did shoot you in the ass.”

Sickle craned her head around, turning around as she tried unsuccessfully to look at her own rear. I got a much better view as she turned, seeing the blood glistening on the metal plate covering the inside of her thigh.

Unlike when Starlight was injured, I found myself completely unconcerned.

Sickle staggered, and flopped down on her side with a crash of metal. Sprawling out on her back, she finally got a better view. Her response was to laugh again. “Shit, he did. Hah! He shot me in the ass!”

Starlight frowned down at her, blinking. “There is something deeply wrong with you.”

“Shut up,” Dusty hissed. “There’s two more coming.”

We quickly took our places, peering out into the darkness. On the walking path that ran along the front of the towering offices, two dark shapes moved, bobbing in a slow trot. They were perhaps a hundred yards away.

Dusty took only a moment to appraise the situation. “I have the lead pony. Star, you have the second one. Whisper, keep an eye out for anypony else, suppress them if they try to engage us. Star, take the shot when you’re ready.”

The silence that followed lingered, dragging on. Then there was a flash, momentarily blinding me as the Lancer’s crimson beam tore through the air. The ponies were illuminated for an instant as the second one flared red, his chest burning away. Dusty fired on the other, the sharp gunshots echoing across the compound and off the walls of the other buildings in a rolling din as he put out five shots out at the lead pony. By the time he was done, the area was dark again; the pony’s silhouette lay unmoving on the dark path.

“Star, put a shot into that guy, just to be sure.”

She looked to him, a look of concern flashing across her face, but she turned back, raising her Lancer’s sight before her eyes once more. Several seconds later, there was another hissing pop and flash of red, and a spray of red embers rose from the fallen pony, burning away in the night.

There was a deep thump behind me, and I turned to see that Sickle had removed her helmet. Her face was bloodied, with a fresh gash covering her cheek; the blood that still dribbled from her chin was her own. She poked at the cut with a hoof, then chuckled. “Woo! Now that was fun,” she said, before choking and coughing again. This time, she spat up a much larger wad of congealing blood, and her hoof moved to press at the side of her armored but blood-smeared neck. “Shit, I think one of those fuckers got me in the throat.”

She didn’t engender the greatest show of sympathy or concern from any of us.

Starlight gave a questioning look. “So… do you need first aid or something?”

“Nah,” Sickle wetly rasped as she clumsily dug at one of her armored saddlebags. “It’ll take a lot more than getting shot in the neck to put me down. Just need to stop the bleeding.” She produced a vial, pulling the stopper out with her teeth and spitting it out—at Starlight, no less. Then she tipped her head back, downing the contents. I saw the words “extra strength” beneath a Ministry of Peace logo. As soon as she finished the vial, she tossed it aside, where it clattered and skidded under a table. The gash across her cheek narrowed as the flesh within knitted together.

Starlight stared at her, mouth opening to say something, but she stopped herself. She shook her head, turning away.

We remained there for a couple minutes, clustered together in the dark corner of the ruined cafeteria. Other than the quiet clanking any time Sickle moved, it remained silent.

Finally, Dusty drew back. “Okay, we may be good. Let’s check these bodies for valuables and make sure they’re dead, then get back to searching for the server.”

We slunk back into the shadows, with Sickle lingering behind, having donned her helm once again. She was a fair bit more sluggish than before, but it didn’t seem to hamper her mood.

If anything, the carnage of the fight had improved it. She seemed quite happy as she flipped the dead stallion over, cutting the straps that held his battle saddle in place and prying away his weapon. “Anyone want a big dumb gun?” she asked, hefting it up. The thing was thick and stubby, with a huge barrel. The bore looked bigger than a shotgun’s, and it was fed from a giant drum. The name “Chomper” was painted on the side, with teeth painted on either side of the large port, as if the massive bolt itself were a jaw.

“What the hell is that?” Dusty asked, which impressed upon me just how unusual the weapon must have been.

“I don’t know, some shitty fucking homemade shotgun.” Sickle shrugged, tossing it aside. “Didn’t help this fucker much!”

She then raised her hoof and jammed her leg-blades into his neck, sawing back and forth as she sliced through the flesh. I turned away, feeling sickened. It didn’t spare me from the wet sounds of flesh tearing and spine separating.

“There,” she said, followed by another cough and a spit. “Ugh. There. Just need something to carry the heads in.”

Dusty sighed, shook his head, and walked off. He kept his gun up and ready. Starlight followed him.

“Why do you even want his head?” I asked, even as I realized I may not want to know.

“‘Cause I want the bounty on these raiders, dumbass.”

“You only need the ear for that.”

“Oh, sure,” Sickle said, sneering. “Except Steel Shot’s being a little bitch and whining that some of them are the wrong ear, so he isn’t going to pay me for them. So fuck him, I’ll just bring the whole damn head, and he can have both.”

“Wouldn’t it just be simpler, and easier, to just bring the correct ear?”

“Sure,” she said, shrugging. “But I don’t know which one he wants.”

“He wants the right ear.”

“I know that,” she said, and something about her posture suggested she had just rolled her eyes. “I just don’t know which one that is.”

I had to stop and process that for a moment. The natural conclusion seemed absolutely ludicrous to me. “Do you mean to tell me you’re going to decapitate more than a dozen ponies and haul their heads around, all because you can’t tell your right hoof from your left?”

“Yeah,” she said, a growl entering her voice. “What of it?”

I had to resist the urge to sigh and walk away. Instead, I raised a hoof and pointed to the crumpled table beside her. “Could you hit that table with one of your forehooves, as hard as you possibly can?”

The bloodied helm tilted to the side. “What the fuck for?”

“Just humor me, please.”

She stared at me for a moment, then turned, reared up, and slammed her hoof into the table with a tremendous crash, flattening it against the ground.

When she looked back at me, no doubt glaring within her helmet, I nodded. “That’s your right hoof.” She looked down to her hoof, frowning, and I added, “Apparently, your right hoof is the right one for hitting things.”

She considered that for a moment, then dropped Gut’s head beside his body. She slowly placed her left forehoof on his armored chest, then raised her right hoof to press the blades into his torn belly, simply holding them there for a moment. Then she slowly smiled, drawing back. “That might actually work,” she mused.

Then she looked back down to the severed head lying on the ground, facing up at her. She gripped the head with one hoof as she raised the other to his ear. His left ear.

She had just started to cut in when she stopped. Then she turned his head around to face the same way as her. “Right,” she said, and cut away the correct ear. She smiled as she lifted it away, looking absolutely pleased with herself. After tossing it into the armored box at her side, she turned back to the severed head. “Guess I don’t need your ugly mug any more.”

With that, she stepped back and gave it a solid kick, sending the head sailing across the room to smack meatily into the opposite wall. While I winced and looked away, trying to ignore the grotesque absurdity of the whole scene, she merely chuckled.

She walked by me, pausing to give me a very solid pat on the back with her bloody, spiked hoof. “Thanks, Whimper.”

“Don’t mention it,” I mumbled.

☢

We finished our excursion in Equestrian Robotics without further incident.

While looting the dead seemed like a stark reminder of how things had changed with the megaspells, I didn’t find it especially troubling. Sickle’s gleeful attitude as she handled the bodies was more unnerving, especially the ones she had killed. She was proud of the carnage she had caused, and I heard her chuckling a few times as she looted the corpses of the ponies she had killed.

Myself, I tried to avoid paying them too much attention. I hadn’t had the time to get a good look at any of them during the frantic moments of the fight. I preferred to keep it that way.

But there was one that caught my attention. I almost wish she hadn’t.

I had made my way to the room Sickle had first charged into when I found her. The raider mare lay there, the crude metal plates of her barding shifting quietly with her short, labored breaths. Her side was soaked with blood, flowing from the pair of deep gashes across her chest; Sickle’s blades had torn right through the road signs and serving trays that made up her armor, leaving ribs bare.

A foreleg twitched, and I kept my rifle leveled at her chest. A submachine gun lay beside her hoof, loaded with a large drum. Her half-lidded eyes wavered, not quite looking at me. She was too weak to do anything.

I stared down at her: crippled, barely conscious, slowly bleeding to death.

I was hungry.

A quick glance out the door showed that everypony else was still gathered around the entrance of the cafeteria. Nopony would witness me.

I moved around behind the mare. Her eyes wandered roughly in my direction, and she made a weak, gurgling moan as her hoof shifted, brushing against her dropped weapon. I moved up behind her, placing a hoof on her neck, pressing just enough to keep her pinned there. Her moan grew choked, quiet and angry. Her hooves moved more, trying to clutch her weapon, but I swatted it away.

I loomed over her, reached deep inside her, and pulled.

Nothing.

I pulled harder as she choked and squirmed weakly beneath my hooves, and I finally felt a trickle of life-sustaining energy leaking out of her. I fed, drawing for all I was worth.

The raider mare writhed, her scream of rage and anguish choked into a weak gurgle by my hoof and her own injury.

The trickle of energy suddenly ceased, her limbs going still as she succumbed to her injuries. Her contorted expression slowly softened, and I staggered back, shaken.

I had gotten so little from her. A nibble, at best, and I had to dig deep for even that.

This wasn’t a pony. She might look like it, but she was no more a pony than I was. Less, even. She was something else. Something wrong.

No pony could be so devoid of love.

With shaking hooves, I quickly grabbed what I could and left her.

Our looting turned up a good deal of crude barding, which we all ignored, and a wide variety of weapons. Roughly half were melee weapons, which we also ignored. Most of the rest were pipe guns of various types: a couple pistols, some automatic rifles, and a single bolt-action long-rifle. None interested us. It did offer some replacement ammunition for my rifle, though, and several more magazines. I numbly picked those up, hoping to have Dusty check over them for quality when we were done there.

There were only a couple of more professionally made guns, with that raider mare’s submachine gun being the most notable. It fired the same caliber of ammunition as my pistol, and the pair of drums I had grabbed explained how she had been able to lay out such a constant stream of fire. Sadly, she had fired almost all of her ammunition, but we collected that and the gun. I considered keeping one of the drums for my pistol, as ridiculous as it would probably be; it looked like the two weapons were designed to use the same magazines.

There was also a pistol, in rather poor shape, and a bolt-action rifle with a sawn-off barrel. Neither were likely to be worth that much, but we took them anyway.

We also found a fair number of pharmaceuticals, which Sickle claimed, and a total of four unused healing potions which we split evenly. A hoofful of caps and some questionable-looking and immediately discarded meat rounded out our findings.

I felt like a vulture, picking over the remains of the dead. As much as I tried to focus on my training, to remain clear-minded and unemotional, I still felt distinctly uncomfortable. It was a scenario well beyond any I had expected to find myself in just a couple weeks earlier. Though I tried to avoid focusing on it, the carnage was still shocking.

That was also the first time I saw what Starlight’s Lancer could do to a pony.

She must have hit him in the head or neck. There was no trace of either, and most of his chest had been burnt away, severing one of his forelegs. A bit of spine and ribs had survived, scorched black by the heat. The flesh inside the gaping crater of a wound was charred to a crisp. Some parts still smouldered faintly, filling the air with the scent of burnt meat and hair.

The corpse lay near the others Dusty and I had come up behind. Curiously, there were two dead raiders lying against the wall several yards away, one of which was absolutely riddled with bullet holes. Both had been dragged there some time before our arrival, judging by the trail of blood leading up to them.

Once our looting was complete, we crept through the dim hallways until we found the server room. Without the time pressure I had faced in Stable-Tec, it was a much calmer and easier process, and a few minutes later, a full copy of the server’s contents resided on the supplied data-store.

As we exited the building to continue on, we saw another raider in front of the Stable-Tec building, lit by the light of the lobby. He was hobbling slowly away, back toward the buildings across the pond, and dragging one of his hind legs.

Dusty leveled his rifle, and after a couple seconds of aim, the deep crack of his shot echoed off the nearby buildings. The pony in the distance lurched to the side and fell to the ground. Then we were moving again.

Our path took us past the fallen raider. Once again, Dusty paused, putting a single round into his head before continuing on. Starlight looked sick to her stomach.

We found no more raiders. No more living ones, anyway; we went through the Stable-Tec building again to check on the security office, now that the keypad was powered, and swung by the server room to check on the raiders Dusty had fired on there. Two lay dead outside the server room, and another two lay among the ruined servers, killed when the mine had detonated. As had become the norm, we checked them over for loot, but the only thing of interest was a ridiculously short pump shotgun, with no stock and hardly any barrel. Dusty tucked it away, as well as a bandolier of shells.

Sadly, the security office was disappointing. Rather than the armory we had envisioned, it was instead merely a room for monitoring the security cameras around the building. Half of them were nonfunctional, their screens showing only static, and the ones that functioned showed nothing of interest. There were no racks of weapons, ammunition, and barding.

But there was the skeleton of a pony, clad in the tattered remains of a Stable-Tec Security uniform and lying crumpled in the one chair of the office. I wondered what circumstances had led to him dying there in a locked room, far from the balefire that had devastated Equestria.

Without opposition, the rest of our search went smoothly, even if it was still tense. We remained on-guard, worried that, at any moment, we’d run into some straggler, some raider who had avoided the earlier fighting. It never happened.

One by one, we cleared through the remaining buildings, finding their servers and pilfering their data. Our digital loot was the only prize to be found within those halls. The Ironshod Firearms office had been thoroughly stripped, leaving nothing of value; we even found places where heavy machinery had once been bolted to the floor, but those too had fallen prey to earlier scavengers. The Canterlot Medical Research Group and Crystal Life Technologies buildings were mostly research labs rather than practical medical facilities, and what little supplies they had held had been looted long ago, leaving only a few empty medical boxes and overturned carts.

Feeling shaken and filthy did lead to one course of looting that I likely wouldn’t have considered otherwise, as I checked the soap dispensers in each restroom we went by. By the time we finished, I had a good dozen bottles of antibacterial soap. As odd as it might have been, it was a comforting touch of normality. Luxury, even.

The only remaining item that drew any interest, at least from myself, was a white, egg-shaped pod in the CLT offices. Even then, it was simply mild curiosity. I was not as interested in their suspended animation technology as I was in how my hive had made use of that. If that information was there, it would be within their servers.

It took about an hour to thoroughly scour the ancient buildings. As we stepped out of the last office, we cast our eyes toward the buildings across the pond. Most of the lights had gone out, but a few remained. After a moment of consideration, Dusty spoke up. “We should probably check those out. They might have some loot worth hauling back.”

“Of course we should check it out,” Sickle said, trudging along behind us. “Dibs on the chems.”

We slowly circled around the pond, moving carefully among the picnic tables. Our eyes remained locked on the lit windows of the buildings ahead, our weapons ready. I tried my best to mimic Dusty’s gliding walk, keeping my rifle sighted in on the nearest building, but met with only limited success.

The closest building was the store, with the decaying pony hung from a pole like some profane raider flag. We cautiously circled around to approach from a side with few windows.

We shuffled quietly up to the wall, Dusty moved up to prepare to make entry, and Sickle simply ignored all of us to stroll in the front door.

When her entrance wasn’t immediately answered with angry yells and gunfire, we followed her in.

The store had been turned into some grisly shrine to death. All the shelves had been knocked over and shoved into the back to make way for the giant heap of bones that had taken their place. There must have been hundreds of skeletons there.

I understood then why we hadn’t found any bodies elsewhere within those old, dead offices. They had all been collected here.

More concerning, while I am by no means an expert in forensic science, some of those bones appeared to be quite fresh. A few still had bits of meat clinging to them, and the air was laced with a faint undercurrent of rot.

Behind the giant mound of bones, atop the piled up shelves, was a crude living space. A large mattress dominated the uneven platform, while a wide variety of melee weapons lined the back wall. A few dozen pony skulls were scattered around on either side of the platform, and a few ice chests were set along the back edge. A single electric lantern hung over the space, casting shadows around the room.

It seemed extravagantly grotesque, yet I found myself unsurprised. I had encountered too much carnage, suffering, and vileness in too short of a time; this seemed merely more of the same. I could even appreciate the logic of how such a display could be a sign of power and accomplishment among such monstrous creatures.

The chests contained a large amount of chems, which Sickle took, and a large variety of snack cakes, which prompted a bit of a smile from Starlight, even if short lived. The bag of caps, probably about a pound, got tucked away in Dusty’s bags; we agreed to work out the exact split of everything once we were well away from that place.

I did snag one thing that seemed to escape my companion’s attention: a small, ragged notebook, well-used. A quick flip through the pages showed all manner of scribbled notes, with no coherent organization. I tucked it away for later consideration.

We looted the place quickly and moved on.

The windows of the restaurant were mostly boarded up, with only a faint, guttering light seeping through the gaps. We stepped in to see the meager remains of a cooking fire, struggling to light the space. The restaurant looked to have been converted to a dormitory, or perhaps a barracks. Many of the booths had been torn out, their benches cluttered with rough blankets and pillows. Boxes and chests of all sorts were scattered about.

The once-bright decor had long since faded, and the walls were covered with various forms of crude graffiti, most of which was pornographic, violent, or both.

The moment we stepped inside, I could hear a faint banging, echoing from the back of the restaurant. They were slow and irregular. Then, at the edge of my hearing, I caught a sob.

We followed the sound. What we found… troubles me.

In what had once been a walk-in freezer were two earth pony mares. One looked to be about Starlight’s age, if that. The other was probably around fifteen or twenty years older. Both had silvery gray coats and dark manes. They were dirty and bruised, their cheeks matted with dried tears.

The older mare was locked in a small, thick-barred cage that offered barely enough room to lie down. The banging we had heard was her kicking at the inside of the lock. She froze in the middle of winding up for another kick. I remember the look of horror as we stepped into the room, and the way it had turned to fearful, wary interest as she realized we were not her captors.

The younger mare was bound atop a sawhorse, with one hoof tied to each leg. A bit and bridle had been strapped onto her. Her tail had been cut down to a nub, and traces of dried blood and other substances stained the inside of her thighs.

“Oh, shit,” Starlight uttered under her breath, her eyes wide.

From the cage, the older mare spoke up, her voice trembling and cautious, but I couldn’t help but sense a bit of hope in there. “Who are you?”

Dusty was looking around, blinking. “We… we’re here to help.” He swallowed, then looked back. “Star, get that cage open.”

Star nodded, quickly digging out her cutter to work on the cage’s padlock. Dusty pulled out a knife, crouching down beside the younger mare to cut at the bindings around her hooves.

I stood back, feeling a bit useless.

Sickle stepped up, sticking her head through the doorway into the crowded room. The older mare jerked back in her cage with a gasp. I glanced back at Sickle, and it was only after a moment of consideration that I felt somewhat ashamed and uncomfortable that I did not share her reaction. Her armored, brutish head was slathered in dried blood, making her look every bit as vile as the raiders we had just killed. The same raiders that had held these two ponies captive.

Under the bloodstained muzzle of her helm, Sickle’s lips curled up in a grin as she snorted in amusement. “Ah, fun. I see we found their rec room.”

The padlock clattered to the ground behind me, and an instant later a dark-blue leg shot past me, a hoof striking Sickle in the face. Her helmeted head rocked to the side, though I think it was more from surprise than the force of the blow. It turned back, that sharp-horned, bloodstained, muzzled helm facing the pony that had just struck her.

Starlight seethed, glaring up at the monstrous mare. “Get! The fuck! Out!”

I looked between the two, eyes wide, and pulled the stock of my rifle in tight against my shoulder.

Sickle stared back at her, as if incredulous that this other pony had just struck her.

A slow, deep rumble built up within her, until her blood-flecked lips pulled up in a savage grin. She laughed. Then she raised a hoof. Starlight raised her own hoof to fend it off, but it did her no good. Sickle shoved her; the gesture looked completely casual on Sickle’s part, but it sent Starlight crashing back against the wall. Starlight staggered with the impact, her wounded leg wobbling, but she regained her footing. She stood firm, hooves spread, eyes narrowed.

Sickle laughed again, sneering down at the much smaller pony that stood against her. “Yeah, whatever you say, runt.” Her head drew back from the doorway, armor clattering against ancient kitchen appliances as she turned around to leave. “And learn how to fucking hit.”

The door of the cage clanged, and I looked back as the older mare scrambled over to the younger, practically falling onto her. “I’m here, baby,” she cooed, wrapping the other pony in a tight embrace. “It’s okay. It’s over. We’re safe now.”

The younger pony trembled, choking back a sob as she shakily raised her freed forelegs to clutch onto the other mare. Still clutching her tight, the older mare brought her hooves up to undo the bridle’s straps, sliding the assembly off and tossing it away.

The final binding parted under Dusty’s knife. The younger mare whimpered as she slid to the side, eased to the ground by the older one. She trembled, curling up in the older mare’s embrace, and finally broke down completely. Her whole body shook as she sobbed into the other mare’s chest.

Dusty rose, leaning down near the older mare’s head to whisper, “We’ll wait out front.”

The mare nodded, continuing to quietly murmur as she held the younger pony, rocking gently.

We shuffled out, leaving the two alone for the moment.

When we returned to the main room of the restaurant, we found Sickle sprawled out on her back across one of the empty booths, managing to occupy both benches at once. She was looking down at the wound she had received, right at the edge of her unarmored groin. The whole area was caked in dried blood. It seemed unfair to me; it looked to be about the same size of a wound as the one that had caused Starlight so much trouble, but Sickle seemed to regard the injury as a curiosity.

When we entered, Sickle looked up, leveling an unpleasant grin at Starlight before looking to Dusty. “Well, this was fun. We done here?”

“We’re going to wait for them,” he replied. “I’d like to talk with them before we head out, make sure they get home safe.”

“Uh-huh,” Sickle said, having already lost interest, and went back to prodding an armored hoof at her injury. “Let me know when you bitches are ready to get going.”

Starlight huffed and walked off, muttering something about salvage. I immediately followed her.

As soon as we stepped out of the room, I moved up close to her. “Are you okay?” I asked.

“I’m fine,” she replied, jaw tense as she continued on.

“Starlight,” I said, giving a pleading tone to my voice, and she hesitated mid-step. For a moment, her expression tightened. Then she sighed, her hoof lowering to the ground, her ears drooping.

“I’m tired, I’ve been shot, and my brain’s all fuzzy on painkillers. I got to see Sickle gut that stallion because she thought it was fun, and Dusty straight-up executed a wounded pony. And then there’s that,” she said, gesturing in the rough direction the raiders had held their captives. “And if all that weren’t enough, Sickle’s determined to be as nasty as she possibly can. It’s just annoying when she does it to us, but doing it in front of those two? After what they must have been through? That’s just fucking wrong.”

I nodded sympathetically.

“And I really want to kill her for it. I just want to take all that nasty shit she’s been saying and doing and turn it all on her. I think I’d be happy about it, even. All ‘ironic like’, right?” She sighed, her head slumping. “And that scares me. Like… is that how raiders get started? Is that how she started?”

“I don’t know,” I said. “Maybe. But you’re not like that.”

“No, I’m not,” she replied, giving a quiet snort. “I just helped kill, what, fifteen? Twenty ponies? I’m not even bothered that I did. They’re raiders. They need to be put down. But I helped Sickle do all that nasty shit she did. And now I’m scared she’s going to keep doing that nasty shit to some ponies that have already gone through so much, and I don’t know what I might do if she does.”

“I was scared, too,” I said. “When you hit Sickle, I thought she was going to be pissed. I was scared she was going to try to kill you right in front of me, and that there wasn’t anything I could do about it. But instead… she backed down and did what you told her to do.”

Starlight blinked at me, then looked back the way we had come.

“And I was scared when you were shot. For a second, I thought you were going to die, and then there was all the blood.” I shuddered, shaking my head.

She looked back at me, a flash of worry crossing her expression before offering a weak smile; I could feel the sense of affection grow stronger as her attention turned to me. “Hey, don’t worry. It’s going to take a lot more than a bullet in the leg to stop me.”

Her expression held for about a second before suddenly falling flat. “Aw, shit. I just copied Sickle, didn’t I?”

I gave a weak, momentary smile. “Maybe a little.”

Starlight threw back her head, groaning loudly. “Fuuuuck.”

Dusty called out from the front of the restaurant. “What?”

“Nothing!” Starlight quickly replied. I’m pretty sure I heard Sickle snickering.

As Starlight huffed out a grumbling sigh, I reached out a hoof to lightly nudge her, and when I got her attention again, offered a soft smile. “Don’t worry too much about it,” I said, trying to sound gentle but confident. “You know you’re a good pony. You’re trying to protect ponies. That’s good. That’s why we’re here, right?”

She wavered, looking away. “...No. We just came here for money.”

“And if it were anypony other than raiders here, we wouldn’t have come,” I said, and met her eyes as she looked back to me. “We were willing to accept the job because, if it came down to a fight, we’d be fighting raiders that prey on other ponies. We made the Wasteland a little safer, today. And you know, even if I’d hoped to do this sneakily, without them ever knowing we were here…” I tilted my head, gesturing in the direction of the kitchen and the freezer beyond. “...I’m glad it turned out the way it did.”

She glanced that way, and sighed. “Yeah, I guess so.”

I reached up again, and this time she leaned in, wrapping her hooves around me as we hugged.

As her foreleg pressed against my left shoulder, I winced.

She quickly released her grip, looking alarmed. “You okay?” she asked, and followed my gaze to my own shoulder. “Oh, shit. You’re hurt!”

It looked like my coat was roughed up in a tiny patch, with bits of dried blood crusted into the hairs. Starlight brushed at it with a hoof, making me wince as she pushed back the hairs to look at the wound itself, and in the process, blocked my own view. “Shit, why didn’t you say anything, Whisper?”

“It didn’t hurt until somepony started jabbing their hoof in it!” I said, gritting my teeth as she prodded at my shoulder.

“It’s not a bullet wound,” she said, giving another press that made me hiss through my teeth. “Something stuck you, though, and it feels like there’s still something just under your skin. We should get this cleaned out.”

She quickly led me back to the main room of the restaurant, and right into an interesting conversation.

Sickle was still kicked back, but her helm’s muzzle hung freely, revealing her leering grin, an expression made even more disturbing by the dried blood matting her coat and the long, partially healed gash across her cheek. “Ah, it’d be just like good old times. Well, would have been even better an hour ago. Post-fight fucking is the best fucking.” She snickered, taking a deep swig from a bottle.

Dusty, meanwhile, had been glaring out the window, as if to ignore her. He noticed our arrival, wincing a little before replying to her. “There were no ‘old times’, Sickle. It was once. And I wouldn’t call it good, either.”

Sickle snorted and coughed, lowering her bottle as she started to laugh. “Hah! Damn, Dirt, that almost hurts! Also, that’s brahminshit. I remember you getting really into it.”

Starlight was looking back and forth between them, and finally leveled a flat, disapproving look at Dusty. “Seriously? You slept with that?”

Dusty scowled, continuing to look away from everypony. “I’d been stuck putting up with her shit all day, so I got drunk as hell that night. I don’t remember anything after that. I just remember waking up with her lying on top of me.”

Sickle waved her bottle toward him. “Well shit, if all you need is some booze, I’ve got a few more in here. Want one?”

“No,” Dusty grumbled. “And can we not talk about this right now, with those two right in the next room?”

Sickle snickered and turned to us. “So, you two done fucking, already?”

Starlight leveled an unamused glare her way. “We weren’t having sex,” she said before turning away, seeming intent on ignoring Sickle as she pulled out her medical supplies.

As she started to clean my wound, Sickle snickered. “Oh! Star likes to play rough, does she?”

Through grit teeth, Starlight replied, “We weren’t playing at all.”

“We were talking,” I said, hoping to help, but it didn’t seem to dissuade Sickle at all.

“Yeah, sure. Two marefriends slip off in—”

“We’re not marefriends!” Starlight snapped, glaring at Sickle again. “Why the fuck does everypony think I’m a lesbian?”

“I don’t think you’re a lesbian,” Sickle said. “I bet you like getting cock just as much.”

“Oh for fuck’s sake,” Starlight grumbled, turning back to my shoulder. After a moment, she added, “And just for reference, if you start talking about anything even remotely like this around either of those mares, I’m going to shoot you.”

“Yeah, sure thing, runt.”

Starlight flinched as Sickle reached out, only to stare in confusion at the bottle the huge mare was holding out. After a moment of silence, Sickle gave the bottle a little wiggle, to which Starlight hesitantly replied. “No thank you…”

“Suit yourself,” Sickle said, bringing the bottle back to her lips and downing the rest of the contents. The spent bottle ended up tossed back, clattering off a couple empty booths before hitting the ground and rolling to a stop.

Starlight continued to stare incredulously at Sickle, only to finally shake her head and return her attention to my injury.

The distraction had given me a better opportunity to look it over, myself. It was just a shallow cut, not even an inch long, but a gentle touch along the back edge of the cut had returned a sharp stab of pain.

After a few prods of her own, and accompanying winces of pain, the forceps came out again. I braced myself, but to my surprise, it wasn’t as painful as I expected. It still hurt, of course, but mostly, it just felt weird. I don’t know if I’ll ever get truly used to wearing a fleshy form. Feeling my outsides stretching and wiggling around can be nauseating if I focus on it too much.

In this particular case, however, I had to admit some advantage to it. Sure, my carapace might have protected me from the injury, but if it had failed to completely protect, it would have made the effort to extract the foreign object lodged inside me much more difficult. At least the flesh stretched to allow the object passage instead of trapping it in place.

I suppose there are some advantages to being a pony.

It took Starlight only a few moments, with only a mild jab of pain, and the forceps floated before me, clasped around a curved, jagged shard of metal.

“Bullet fragment,” Starlight said, dropping the piece into my hoof. It was so tiny.

She dribbled some liquid from one of her bottles over the cut, making me wince once more, and wrapped a non-magical bandage around my shoulder to keep it clean. I’m not even sure if it was necessary at that point; it was already feeling better.

It probably helped that I got a fair bit of affection from Starlight, finally taking a bit of the edge off my hunger.

With that, it was down to waiting. After a couple minutes, Starlight and I set out again to search the place, though we stayed away from the open freezer to leave the two mares some privacy. It wasn’t a terribly big place, and our search soon turned up their stockpile: a huge assortment of two-century-old food, all packaged up safely in cans and boxes, as well as several fuel-cans of water. It took us several trips to ferry all of it back to the main room, leaving us with a pile of food that probably weighed twice as much as I did. To the raiders, it probably represented a couple weeks worth of food. To our small group, it might last a couple months.

We started rooting through the various chests and boxes the raiders had kept their own belongings in. There were all sorts of things in them: a few crude melee weapons and pipe guns, spare ammo, loose caps, knick-knacks ranging from cards and pornography to bones and body parts, and a fair collection of drugs that Sickle promptly claimed. We even turned up a single super restoration potion, which ended up tucked into Starlight’s supplies.

What we were really looking for, however, were the various sacks, bags, and packs they had tucked away. Once we’d dug out enough bags, we started loading the food and loot into them.

We were almost done with that when Dusty, who was keeping a lookout, brought up his binoculars to peer at something that had caught his attention. I hardly even noticed, just some action on the periphery of my vision, of no particular importance.

What I did notice was him suddenly ducking down below the window, eyes wide as he stared off into space at the blank wall. “Oh shit.”

Naturally, that caught the attention of all of us. “What?” Starlight asked, being the quickest to voice the question that rose to all of our minds.

“Oh shit,” Dusty repeated. “We need to go.”

The last of Starlight’s cans lifted up in the glow of her magic to be dumped unceremoniously into a bag before hurrying over to Dusty. “What is it?” she said, drawing his attention barely in time for him to reach up and stop her from getting to the window.

“Stay down!” he hissed. “Don’t let it see you!”

“What is ‘it’?”

“There’s a fucking alicorn out there.”

“What?” Starlight asked, then shook free of his grip to slide up to the window, levitating her Lancer.

“Don’t shoot at it! You’ll just piss it off and tell it where we are!”

“I’m not going to shoot it,” Starlight said. “I just want to get a look at it.”

After a momentary pause, she asked, “Where is it?”

Dusty grunted out a short grumble, peeking up just enough to look out again before ducking down. “That little glow way out there, in the saddle.”

Starlight blinked and looked down at him. “Saddle?”

“The… the lower ridge between the two hilltops! It’s skylined there.”

“Oh,” Starlight said, turning back and aiming her Lancer that way. Having finished cramming the last of my own supply of cans into the waiting bags, I moved up to peer over her shoulder. The hills were probably a quarter mile away, and I could only just make out a faint purple light. Starlight hummed softly before speaking. “I wonder if that’s the same alicorn we ran into before?”

“You two ran into—” Dusty cut himself off, his hoof returning to rub at the bridge of his nose as he sighed. “Of course you ran into an alicorn. You two are fucking cursed or something.”

Starlight floated up the Lancer so I could look down the sight. I had to nudge it a bit to get it onto the correct point on the horizon again, but soon found what I was looking for.

She stood still on the ridgeline, faintly illuminated by the purple glow of her horn. The alicorn looked almost like a ghost, her coat barely standing out from the darkness around her. Her wings were spread beside her, her tail and mane slowly drifting in the still air.

I couldn’t tell if she was the same being we had encountered before, only that she had a similar coloration.

When I slid back, Dusty lowered his hoof. “You two done sightseeing, yet?”

“Yeah,” Starlight said, sliding back. “I’m done.”

“Good.” He moved over to one of the empty booths, grabbing at the bedding there. “Sickle, grab as many of those food bags as you can carry.”

“I ain’t your fucking pack mule,” she replied, though she rolled onto her hooves and lazily grabbed some bags as she said it.

“Whisper, go get those two mares. Get them up and moving, we need to get out of here.”

“On it,” I replied, and turned to head their way.

While I was confident in my abilities, it was not a conversation I was looking forward to. To tell the truth, I’d rather not be in that situation at all. But, I was there, and probably the best suited to get the job done, so I headed back to the walk-in freezer.

They were still sitting where we had left them, but now they sat there silently. The younger one was no longer crying, though she shook faintly with her long, deep breaths. The older one remained silent, slowly rocking, her forelegs wrapped protectively around the younger.

I hesitated only a moment before slowly approaching. The older mare twitched when she heard me, looking my way, and I did my best to put on a gentle, sympathetic expression. “I’m sorry, I don’t want to rush you, but we can’t stay here any longer. We need to go.”

She continued to look at me for a couple seconds with a look of mixed fear and determination. She finally swallowed, her voice slightly hoarse as she asked, “How soon?”

I gave a soft sigh, as if to show reluctance. “Now.”

Her ears drooped a bit, but she nodded, and turned back to the other mare. I stepped back to the door to wait.

“Honey?” she quietly murmured. “We need to go.”

She was met with a soft whimper, and leaned in to whisper quietly. After a few moments, the whimper stopped. The younger mare looked up, wavering a moment before a hint of the older mare’s determination was echoed in her expression, and she nodded.

“Let’s get you up, then. Easy, there.” Slowly, and with a good deal of help, the younger mare rose on shaky hooves. Her jaw was tight and breath shaky as she took her first step. She nearly fell, leaning heavily against the other mare for balance as her legs wobbled. Despite that, she forced herself onward.

“You’re doing fine,” the older mare cooed. She smiled, even as fresh tears started to roll down her cheek. “We’re getting out of here.”

Watching the poor mare’s slow and painful progress, I had to speak up. “We have a few spare healing potions, if you’d like a couple.”

The older mare blinked against the tears, and the look she gave me was full of caution. “...How much?”

I remember that one line more than anything else. After all the violence, all the carnage, all the vileness I had witnessed and learned of, I think that moment of simple, perfunctory cynicism hit the hardest. My eyes widened on hearing it, ears perking up. I stammered, entirely without intent. “N-no. For free. I couldn’t…”

She considered me for a moment before relaxing slightly, nodding. “Sorry. I’m just a little… wary of ponies, right now.”

“I understand,” I said, then opened my pack to produce the healing potion I had just recently acquired. She took it, giving a quiet murmur of thanks before turning to the pony resting against her.

“Here, baby,” she said, removing the stopper and offering the bottle to the other mare. “Drink this. You’ll feel better.”

She did, and after a few moments, was ready to move again. By the time we reached the main room of the restaurant, her pace was more sure, less laborious, though her head still hung low.

Sickle was heaving the last large bag of food onto her back as we returned. Both mares faltered upon seeing her. Fortunately, Dusty approached, a couple new bundles strapped to his back. “I’m very sorry for having to rush you like this, ma’am, but we need to hurry out of here while we still can. My name’s Dusty Trails. What can I call you two?”

While Starlight quirked an eyebrow questioningly at me and silently mouthed Dusty’s full name, the older mare answered. “Silverline. And this is my daughter, Quicksilver.”

“Glad to meet you,” Dusty said. “The rest of the meet-and-greet will have to wait, I’m afraid. We’ve got something dangerous coming in, and I’d like to get out of here before it arrives. Are you good to move?”

Silverline swallowed, but nodded. “We are.”

“Good. Stay close, and we’ll get out of here. If there’s anything you need, if you need help with anything, just speak up and somepony will take care of it. Everypony else, don’t be afraid to ditch those bags if we have to move quickly; our lives are worth more than a few days of food. Now let’s go.”

We moved to the back door of the building, slipping out where the other buildings would mask our movement. Silverline kept glancing over at us. We’d crept by three houses before she quietly spoke up. “One of the raiders. A big one, white, with a big gun on—”

“He’s dead,” Sickle rumbled, her helm turning as she looked down at the smaller mare. She paused mid-step to lift a foreleg, brandishing the pair of bloodstained blades mounted there. “Gutted him myself.”

Silverline stared at Sickle for a long moment before giving a nod. She seemed satisfied with the answer, and continued on without any more sideways glances.

Our progress was slow, and not terribly quiet. The clinking and scraping of Sickle’s armor was matched by the collection of cans we carried, but slowly and surely, we made our way toward the wall of the compound, and the gate leading out, with its vague promise of uncertain safety.

Dusty covered from the edge of a house as we moved up, waiting until Starlight and I had gotten the gate open and had set ourselves in position to cover him before hurrying after us.

He was almost to the gate when the alicorn glided in over the pond. My heart lurched as Starlight and I both tracked this unknown threat. Fortunately, for whatever reason, she didn’t look our way, and Dusty scrambled behind me for cover.

We stayed very still, not daring to move any more than was required to keep the alicorn in our sights. She back-winged once, her hooves gracefully touching down to the ground as she transitioned into a walk. She moved slowly, with a casual confidence. From that distance, in that poor lighting, I couldn’t make out her expression, but her posture and movement gave the impression of a haughty disdain for the world around her.

It made me think of the most prideful of nobility or Queens.

More concerningly, Starlight’s stories and Dusty’s fearful reaction made me worry that such a display of casual superiority might not be unfounded.

She came to a halt beside the body of a raider, the last one Dusty had shot in front of the Stable-Tec offices. Her horn lit, and a soft purple glow wrapped around the body, lifting it up to eye level as she peered down her snout at it. She slowly turned it over, looking at the bloody corpse. Then her magic twisted around it, and the dead raider’s torso tore open.

After all I’d seen that day, the gory display no longer drew the sense of revulsion it might have before. Despite that, I found myself very concerned about the motivation behind the alicorn’s actions, and very afraid of what might happen if she got her hooves on us. I stayed perfectly still, barely breathing despite the heartbeat hammering in my ears.

Organs pulled away, floating before the alicorn in a grotesque swarm of flesh. A leg tore open, as if the muscles burst within it, and then the head twisted until the skull cracked and split. A faint trace of revulsion started to rise in my gut. I’m thankful that I was far enough away to not hear the sounds that must have accompanied such a gruesome display.

The alicorn regarded her work impassively, occasionally floating a part closer for better inspection. One by one, parts were replaced within the cavities they had been removed from. Once they were all back in place, the wounds closed, knitting together in what struck me as an impressive display of magic. The torso closed up, the torn-open head sealed itself, and before long, the only sign of the raider’s injuries was the copious amount of blood staining his coat.

The alicorn’s magic turned and posed the raider’s corpse, slowly lowering it until the hooves touched the ground. Supported in her magic, it looked like the raider was simply standing there, as if Dusty had never shot him.

Then her magic winked out, and the corpse collapsed, limp and lifeless.

She stared down her snout at it for a second before looking away, toward the Equestrian Robotics offices. She resumed her slow, confident walk, stepping over the corpse as if it was once again beneath her notice.

As the alicorn walked further away, Starlight slid up beside me. “Can we go now?”

I nodded, and we crept back from the open gate. As we got further away, we picked up the pace, determined to put as much distance between us and that place as we could.

I silently followed along as we slipped away into the darkness, hoping I would never see Paradise Beach again.

Chapter Twelve: Covert Methods

Two weeks.

That’s how long it had been since the whole “Sunshine and Rainbows” event. That’s also exactly how long it had been since I had woken up from my centuries-long slumber. The day I had met Starlight, and the day one of the weather-control towers had exploded upon activation. That explosion had sent debris across the countryside, including to a certain C.L.T. facility. A facility that had coincidentally suffered a failure of its power systems at that very moment, prompting an emergency evacuation for the one surviving being within: me.

It was a sobering thought. By everything I knew, I had survived through pure chance, and a fairly slim one at that. Had that precise chain of events not occurred, how long might I have remained in that chrysalis? Would I have ever woken up? Or would I have met the same fate as my sisters?

Mostly, I tried to ignore those thoughts. They were depressing, and at that moment, I needed to participate in the festivities.

The ponies in Cinder Block’s Inn were in high spirits with the news of Celestia’s survival. Sure, she was somehow bound to the S.P.P hub, however that worked, but she was alive, and those ponies were quite happy to celebrate that fact.

Myself, I was quite happy to join in, share in their happiness, and siphon off a tiny bit of the camaraderie and friendship that filled the air. I did my best to ignore how utterly strange the whole situation was. Two weeks in the Equestrian Wasteland had done wonders to further develop my ability to simply accept things I didn’t understand. The whole world had gone crazy, and I had no option but to roll with it.

Starlight joined in, too, dancing to the music in a way that left much to be desired in form, but certainly wasn’t lacking for energy. Dusty kicked back with a few ponies he knew, swapping stories. Even Sickle shed her armor to join in, to rather mixed results. I stayed well clear, especially as she soon had a small gathering of the rowdier ponies, as well as an excess of alcohol and a general lack of common decency. Fortunately, she headed out with them before she got us all got kicked out.

Despite getting a fairly good meal out of the gathering, I turned in a little early. I had plans for that night, and I needed my rest.

I napped, waking only as ponies returned to our shared room. Starlight was the first, returning shortly after I had arrived. Sickle was the last, returning well after dark. Her hoof-falls came unevenly as she staggered back to her cot and collapsed with a groan. The smell hit me almost immediately, with the stench of alcohol nearly masking the musky scent lingering behind it.

She was snoring only moments later. I suppose I should mention that her snoring is much like everything else she does, excessively loud and grating, and it seemed to be made even worse for the amount of alcohol she had consumed that night.

If there was one small upside to Sickle’s presence, it was that her snoring perfectly concealed what little sound I made as I slipped out of the room.

☢

Some ponies would think that the best time to sneak into a place would be in the middle of the night.

That couldn’t be further from the truth.

The best time to sneak into a place is in the middle of the day, when things are at their busiest. When ponies are coming and going constantly, and something is always going on. When they expect ponies, rather than their presence being unexpected. When a disguised changeling is simply one more face in the crowd, rather than the only pony around.

So while I made my move at night, I did so out of necessity, rather than desirability. Fortunately, I had one very notable advantage; unlike the ponies living in Mareford, I could fly.

I skimmed low over the roof-tops in my temporary guise: a navy-blue pegasus stallion, light and lean. I had only a small amount of gear weighing me down: my portable terminal, tucked into a bag that had previously carried our loot, the holster holding my pistol and spare magazines, and my binoculars.

The first step of any infiltration is gathering intelligence. I already saw a little of the internal layout of the town hall, enough to know the basic layout of the first two floors. While that included my objective, I had plenty of time to scope the place out. There was no rush.

I landed atop the tallest building, an old five-story office building that appeared to be converted to stores and apartments. From there, I had a good view of the town hall building through the lenses of my binoculars.

That included the window to Big Gun’s office, which was lit. Though the worn blinds were closed, I could see the occasional shadow of movement.

After a couple minutes, I decided it was time to get closer.

I stepped off the edge of the building, the wind rushing past me as I fell, and pulled out of the dive to skim low over the neighboring buildings. The last stretch was straight across the street, and then I landed atop the town hall. I peeked back over the edge; nopony was around to have seen me.

Again, I slipped over the edge of the roof, but this time my wings beat to keep my descent slow, until I hovered just beside the window. While I couldn’t very well sneak in while the room was occupied, I could always eavesdrop. Though muffled through the old glass and worn blinds, I could hear Wild Runner’s voice.

“...ain’t selling as well as they used to. Said he’s getting more and more ponies trying to haggle or scrape up more caps to get rifling, and the old ones aren’t moving.”

Big Gun’s voice sounded quite pleased, perhaps even smug. “That would be market saturation, my dear. The old smooth-bores have become common, so ponies looking for a hoof up on their neighbor are looking towards something better. I’ll pass word on to Good Deal to reduce the price for the smooth-bores, and bump up the price for rifled pipes. And I think it’ll be time for Forge to put more focus on the production of proper weapons. If the trend continues, demand should be increasing soon enough.”

“I’m still glad you like all this business management stuff. I think I’d have to slit my own throat if I had to listen to Deal rambling on about margins and sales incentives.” There was a short pause, followed by a muted laugh. “Nah, I’d probably just slit his throat.”

“Now, now,” Big Gun said, suppressing a chuckle. “Don’t be too hard on the help. They’re hard to replace, and there are plenty of other ponies that deserve it more.”

“Yeah, I know,” Wild Runner said, her tone sharp and bitter. “Except you’re keeping me here instead of letting me deal with them. I’m bored. I liked it more before we had Fireline working for us.”

“This again?” A chair squeaked against the floor, followed by the faint sounds of hooves, which stopped a moment later. “There are a lot more skulls in need of cracking, my dear. I can’t expect you to cover every aspect of our growing little empire.”

“How about any?”

“Patience. You’ll have plenty of opportunity for fun, soon enough. As I’ve said so many times tonight, let Fireline earn his keep by disposing of this annoying little moral crusader. If you must know, I’ve got something much more entertaining in store for you, if you’re willing to be just a little patient.”

There was a moment of silence. When Wild Runner spoke again, there was a hint of eager amusement to her voice. “Oh, entertaining, now? Well, come on, spill it!”

“And ruin the surprise, my dear?” Big Gun chuckled. “I think not.”

“Yeah, you and your surprises. A hint, then.”

I heard Big Gun hum softly. “...No, I’m afraid not. Wouldn’t want to go spoiling your birthday present, after all.”

There was a thump and rattle, as if somepony had just bumped firmly against the desk. Wild Runner practically cooed, barely audible through the window. “Oh, a birthday present, hmm?”

“Indeed. And that’s all you’re getting out of me until then.”

A moment of silence followed, followed by a louder rattle from the desk. “Jackass,” Wild Runner said, though she nearly laughed as she did so. “This better be a damn good surprise.”

“I’m sure you’ll have more fun than I’ll want to know about.”

“Tease.” More hoofsteps. “And you better wrap up all your business shit nice and quick. I’ll be waiting for you.”

A door opened and shut. There were a few more hoofsteps, then the sound of the chair squeaking again.

I took that as my cue to leave. As satisfying as it would have been to wait until he left and break into his terminal, it was no longer necessary. While I didn’t have any specifics, there were a fairly limited number of ways to “dispose” of a pony.

I skimmed the roof-tops, returning to the inn.

☢

I woke to the soft morning light, feeling remarkably relaxed and rested. The aching in my legs had slipped off into the background, and for the moment, I felt content.

The peace was eventually broken by Sickle’s groan and the loud rattling of bottles clinking against each other. She muttered in barely audible and mostly incoherent fragments. “Fucking… where… dumb bottle…”

I cracked an eye open to see her leaned over the edge of her cot, fumbling at a bag with one hoof. Her eyes were thin slits, barely opened, and her ears were laid back against her skull. The side of her face was wet, probably with drool.

On my opposite side, Starlight stirred and groaned. “Ugh… what’s going on now?”

“Need a drink,” Sickle muttered, finally extracting a bottle from the bag and sending a few more rolling across the floor. She flopped back in her cot, sprawling out on her back in a way made especially lewd by way her coat was matted in certain places. She pried the bottle cap off with her teeth, spit it out, and proceeded to start chugging the bottle. She even managed to do it without spilling too much of her drink.

“And now you’re getting drunk again,” Starlight said, grumbling a little as she sat up and rubbed the sleep from her eyes. “And history repeats.”

“Hey, fuck you,” Sickle muttered as she lowered the bottle, squinting against the light. “Drinking fixes hangovers. ‘Sides, I had a great fucking night, unlike you lame-asses.”

“I had plenty of fun,” Starlight said, stretching. “And unlike a certain somepony, I did it without a massive headache in the morning.”

Sickle, however, had stopped paying attention. She was looking off into the distance, eyes opening a little more as she steadily blinked. Then she cracked a smile. “Hah, shit. I just made a pun. That was a pun, right? Great fucking night?” She broke down in snickering, which soon devolved into a groan as she laid her head back.

“Clever,” Starlight dryly intoned before hopping off her cot, landing on the floor with a sharp clatter of hooves and drawing a small wince from Sickle.

“Well I thought it was funny,” Sickle grumbled, though a moment later she started to smile. “Been way too fucking long since I’ve had a good rut.” She tipped back the bottle again, draining the last of the contents, and then dropped it beside her cot. “Shit, almost makes me miss my old crew. ‘Course, it took most of them to do a half decent job of it.”

“Really don’t need to be hearing all of this!” Starlight said, which just made Sickle snicker more.

“What, jealous?” Sickle grinned, spreading her hind legs wider. “I’m up for another round or two if you’re that desperate.”

I turned so I wasn’t looking at Sickle any more, and started slowly gathering my things. On the far end of the room, Dusty was already up, casting the occasional disapproving look down the room as he finished reassembling his rifle. He already had his gear ready to go.

Starlight grunted. “Ugh, no.” She glanced past me toward Sickle, grimaced, and looked away again. “And if you’re going to keep that up, the least you could do is clean up. That’s disgusting.”

“See?” Sickle grunted. “You’re all a bunch of lame-asses.” She groaned a bit more, and from the creaking of her cot, I could tell she had sat up. “Urgh… how hard is it to find ponies that like to fuck as much as they like to fight?”

Starlight turned back to her. “Hey! I don’t like to fight. It’s just a job.”

I looked back to see Sickle wincing, rubbing a hoof against an ear. “Yeah, sure you don’t,” she rumbled. “You just really like your job, huh?”

“I don’t—”

Dusty cut in. “Children. That’s enough. We’ve only got an hour before we’re meeting with Fireline, so why don’t you all get some breakfast before we head out. And Sickle, go clean up. Right now somepony could shoot you by scent.”

“Eat a dick,” Sickle muttered.

“Uh-huh. Better make it quick if you don’t want to miss the ‘fun’.”

While she grumbled and rubbed at her eyes, Dusty slung his freshly assembled rifle and stood to leave. It seemed the best time to speak up.

“Oh, Dusty? Just so you know, this is absolutely a trap. Big Gun intends Fireline to ‘dispose’ of us. Well, no, he specified you, but I’m assuming it’s a package deal.”

Dusty hesitated, giving me a questioning look. “And how, exactly, would you know that?”

I shrugged as nonchalantly as possible. “Because while you were all preoccupied last night, I sneaked out and eavesdropped on Big Gun and Wild Runner as they discussed various aspects of their business, including how to deal with us.”

He stared, eyes widening for a moment before blurting, “You what?”

“Also, I get the impression Wild Runner isn’t exactly the most pleasant of ponies.”

“Yeah, she’s not,” Dusty said, turning to face me with an angry narrowing of his eyes. “She’s the kind of pony who likes stomping in the heads of ponies she catches eavesdropping on her. What the hell were you thinking? Do you have any idea how dangerous that is?”

“Yes,” I replied. “I wasn’t acting impulsively or incautiously, if that’s what you’re thinking. I carefully considered every aspect of potential risk and my own abilities, and took a course of action that I was certain was safe for all of us. I could also point out that it went precisely as I expected it to.”

“This time, maybe!” Dusty shot back. “But if you keep trying to play at being a spy like in some ancient book you read, you’re going to get yourself and all of us into trouble.”

“I’m not playing at anything, Dusty. We all have our own skills.” I pointed a hoof at him. “You’re a soldier.” I set my hoof down again, and gave a little smile. “I’m not.”

He glared at me, mulling over my statement for several seconds before replying. “Fine. But you’re also a part of a team right now, and that means you don’t go running off to do your own thing. The fallout from anything you do is going to land on all of us, so don’t you ever go cutting us all out of it again. Got it?”

“As long as you don’t dismiss us out-of-hoof and give actual consideration toward our skills and expertise?” I held out a hoof. “Deal.”

He had to consider it for a few more moments before taking my hoof and giving it a quick shake. “So long as your idea of your own skills match reality. Considering the risk you took for nothing, I’m not terribly impressed, so far.”

My smile grew a bit more as I picked up my saddlebags, slinging them over my back. “Oh, it wasn’t for nothing. In fact, I think what we’ve gotten out of it will be quite valuable.”

“What, that this is a trap? We already knew that.”

“No, we didn’t. We suspected. Strongly suspected, but still only suspected.” I slipped the sling of my rifle over my neck, then paused to look square at him. “What we’ve gotten out of it is complete freedom from any lingering concerns that we might be about to aggressively interrogate an innocent and uninvolved pony.”

He frowned, eventually shaking his head. “I don’t know if that’s worth the risk you took. We’d find out soon enough, anyway.”

“And I think everypony will be considerably more comfortable with the plan with this knowledge.”

Sickle grumbled from nearby, a hoof still lying across her eyes. “I don’t actually give a shit one way or the other.”

“Everypony other than Sickle, then.”

Dusty sighed, shaking his head again. “Fine. No point complaining about it now, since you already went and did it anyway.”

“Indeed,” I said, smiling again. “Now is the time for more productive things. Like breakfast.”

☢

Dusty was still a little grumpy by the time we arrived at Mareford’s south gate, passing through the thin morning crowd. The sight that met us didn’t improve his mood any.

Fireline was there, sitting back against the wall. What we hadn’t expected was the four armed ponies gathered around him, decked out with saddlebags and weapons. Good weapons, too, like the Militia used.

“Well, shit,” Dusty grumbled under his breath as we continued to walk toward them.

Starlight leaned in. “Change of plans?”

Dusty thought on it for a moment before shaking his head and murmuring back. “Plan stays. As long as we draw first, we’re good.”

“I don’t know,” Starlight said, and I had to agree.

“Weren’t you just talking about unnecessary risks?” I asked, keeping my voice low; while we were still a good ways away, we didn’t want one of the occasional ponies passing by to overhear our plans to abduct one of their employed mercenaries.

Dusty shook his head slightly. “We’ll be starting with Sickle in close quarters with all of them.” He glanced back to her, speaking up just loud enough for her to hear. “I’ll get your attention just before it all goes down, and you can lay out whichever one is closest to you. Okay?”

Sickle was, naturally, in her armor once again. I wouldn’t describe her appearance at the time as “clean” so much as “cleaner”, or at least cleaned up to the point where it was no longer blatantly obvious what she had been doing the night before. “Sounds fun,” she rumbled, all signs of her hangover having passed some time ago. “I’ll take the closest three. You cunts should be able to finish off the leftovers, right?”

“Just don’t kill Fireline,” Dusty said. “Don’t maim him, either. In fact, I’d prefer if you didn’t kill anypony at all.”

“Yeah,” Sickle said, snorting out a quiet chuckle. “‘Cause I give two shits what you’d ‘prefer’.”

Starlight rolled her eyes. “Yeah, this isn’t going to go wrong or anything.”

“Yeah, fuck you too, runt.” Sickle snickered, and added, “‘Sides, we outnumber them.”

“There are five of them,” Starlight said, staring flatly up at Sickle. “There are only four of us.”

“Yeah, but I’m worth at least three of them,” Sickle replied, grinning behind her muzzle.

“That’s not how outnumbering works,” Starlight grumbled.

“Okay, quiet down,” Dusty said. We were getting close, and the ponies we were approaching had taken note of us.

Fireline was geared up like his companions, having donned armored barding, and with an assault rifle slung across his chest. He stood as we approached.

“Good morning,” he said, eying over each of us in turn. It was a calculating look, I thought. He was sizing us up.

“Good morning,” Dusty said, and he even sounded moderately pleasant about it.

The furthest mercenary, a green stallion, leaned over to his nearest companion, and spoke in a hushed but clearly audible voice. “Holy shit, that’s one big bitch.”

Sickle focused on him like a laser. “You better watch out, shrimp. Tiny little thing like you might get stepped on.”

He sneered back. “Yeah, you just—”

“That’s enough,” Fireline said, shooting the mercenary a harsh glare. “Save the comments for later.”

It was Sickle’s turn to sneer. “Yeah, listen to your boss, little bitch.”

Fireline shot her the same glare, but said nothing before turning back to Dusty. “You’re ready to go, then?”

“We are,” Dusty said, nodding and giving a little smile. “Lead the way.”

I caught a moment of hesitation from Fireline before he nodded. I don’t think he liked the idea of any of us being behind him. “Okay. Let’s go.”

With a wave from Fireline, the gates slowly opened. Dusty took the opportunity to chamber a round and ensure his rifle was ready to go. I did the same, acting as casual as I could as I locked my rifle’s bolt back.

Starlight merely smirked. Her Lancer was still slung loosely across her back, but her holstered Recharger was only a momentary thought away.

Fireline looked back, glancing down to our rifles before speaking. “No need to worry about that. If anything does come up, my team can keep us safe.”

Dusty just shrugged. “Better safe than sorry.”

I did my best to seem disarming. “We wouldn’t want to be freeloaders when we can help.”

“Uh-huh,” Fireline said, frowning just a tiny bit before hiding the expression. “Just be careful where you point those things.”

Once the gates had opened enough, we set out, hooves slowly beating against the cracked pavement and dry earth.

It wasn’t the most conversational traveling group I had ever encountered. That was hardly surprising, I suppose, when both sides intended violence upon the other. If anything, it was surprising that there wasn’t more tension there.

On the plus side, this gave me plenty of time to evaluate the ponies we were traveling with. While Fireline led the way, the four ponies with him had fanned out, taking up the sides of our little formation. It had the simple effect of making it look like they were protecting us, while in fact surrounding us.

On the left, closest to myself, was a violet mare. She was wrapped up in thick cloth over her barding, which left very little of her visible. She was also the only one of the formation who kept her attention entirely focused outward, rather than glancing in to check on us.

In front of her, by Dusty, was a lean young buck, the only unicorn other than Fireline. His gear was clean and neat. From the hints of dirt ground into his off-white coat, I got the impression that his gear was new, rather than fastidiously maintained. He was also quite alert. Possibly too alert, with his ears constantly flicking back and forth, and he would regularly glance into the group before immediately looking outward once again.

To the right, beside Sickle, was the largest of the mercenaries, a dark-brown stallion who would have looked moderately big and strong beside anypony else in our group. He looked almost bored as he walked along. Though his gear was worn and scratched up in places, there were a few additions that caught my attention. Instead of a pistol, he had a small shotgun holstered at his side. A few bulging pouches held what looked to be drum magazines for his rifle, but he didn’t have any of them loaded. Instead, he had a regular magazine in it, although one with with a thin band of red ribbon tied around it. My immediate suspicion was that it indicated the magazine was loaded with a special kind of ammo.

Behind him was the green stallion who had spoken up earlier. Of the entire group, he was the only one who acted completely casual. He hummed to himself on occasion, and was often smiling. It wasn’t a good smile, though; it was the smug kind of smile a pony gets when he knows something nopony else does.

His smile slipped a bit only minutes into our journey as he sniffed at the air. He sniffed a few more times before leaning a little closer to Sickle’s flanks and sniffing again.

Sickle didn’t even look back as she growled. “Unless you’re about to eat me out, you better back the fuck off before you get your face broken.”

He gave an amused snort as he returned to his place, wearing that smug smile once again.

Rather than heading back the way we had come to the city, our course took us east, first along Mareford’s walls, under the protective eyes of the Militia guards, and then out into the crumbling suburban ruins on the outskirts of Dodge City. Few buildings still stood near Mareford, having likely been torn down for materials long ago, but the skeletal remains of the old city grew more prominent as we got further from town.

We walked down the cracked remains of a wide paved street, some old thoroughfare that had run through the ruined neighborhood. Even close to a mile away, we could still see Mareford’s walls behind us, but that was soon to change. As we passed more and more buildings, we were quickly approaching the point where we would pass out of sight. That knowledge came with an acidic twinge in my gut, a hint of adrenaline at what was soon to come.

Dusty made no attempt to hide his wary glances around at the buildings we passed, eventually taking the bit of his rifle between his teeth. “How much trouble have you guys been having with the manticores, lately?”

“Not a bit,” Fireline said, glancing back. His eyes dipped down to Dusty’s rifle before adding, “Relax. We drove the last of them off last year, and we sweep through every month or two to make sure it’s still clear. Got to keep the roads safe for traders, right?”

“Right,” Dusty agreed, giving a little sigh and visibly relaxing, though he kept the bit in his mouth. “I’m glad to hear it. I never did like this stretch.”

I had to give Dusty credit. He was a decent actor at times.

The silence returned as we continued on, passing an old, burnt-out restaurant. The road curved along its front before opening into an old city square. It might have been beautiful once, but now the benches were broken, the plants withered, and the grand statue at its center was reduced to four hooves surrounded by rubble.

The curve also led us out of sight of the distant Mareford walls. That led me to look to our “escort” once more. As I was walking behind Dusty, the easiest to look at was the young unicorn beside him. That’s the only reason I caught the simple action that initiated everything.

While his rifle was slung across his chest, his horn was lit, his magic holding the weapon’s grips. With the jostling of his equipment, I would have never picked out the sound of him disengaging his safety, nor would I have seen it if I had not been looking right at it.

Dusty spoke. “Oh, hey, Sickle?”

Her head turned toward him. “What?”

Rather than answering, his head immediately turned away. His rifle swung around toward the young unicorn, and all hell broke loose.

Even expecting a confrontation, the loudness of his rifle made me jerk back. To my side, Sickle was already moving, throwing herself into the fight before I had even taken up my own weapon.

Dusty’s rifle swung around on the violet mare beside me, before I could bring mine to bear. He yelled. She moved. Another assault of sound hammered at my ears as Dusty’s rifle blared. She twisted and fell.

I staggered back, turning the other way. Fireline staggered sideways toward us, blood falling from his snout. Starlight had her repeater out, aimed in the air at nopony. The green stallion lay several yards past her, writhing and holding his blood-soaked face. The final mercenary was mostly hidden behind Sickle’s bulk; I could only see his hind-legs, jerking and twitching as Sickle turned, one of her spiked hooves rising up, dripping with blood.

I didn’t notice Fireline’s rifle lying on the ground, likely having fallen there at the same moment his nose had been bloodied, until his magic grabbed it again. I swung my rifle back toward him, yelling out what I had intended as a warning, but which came out as an incoherent shout of raw noise. Dusty also shouted, likely much more coherently than myself, though in the heat of the moment I missed whatever he said.

Sickle moved quicker than all of us. She reared around, smashing one hoof down on the rifle. The other, bloodied hoof caught Fireline on the top of the head, and shoved his face into the pavement. “Sit the fuck down!” she bellowed, loud enough that I remembered it clearly even over the jarring amount of adrenaline pumping through me.

The whole fight couldn’t have lasted more than a couple seconds.

Starlight muttered a string of profanity as she quickly looked around, turning her Repeater toward the green stallion, who did little more than moan and curl up. I didn’t get a good look at his face, between his legs obscuring it and my lack of desire to see what a buck from Sickle could do to a pony’s snout. All I saw was blood.

As Sickle leaned over Fireline, chuckling, Starlight finally broke her quiet tirade of curses to look towards Dusty. “What happened to not kill—”

She was interrupted by the most terrifying sound I have ever heard.

The sound was loud and sharp, yet seemingly without end. It wasn’t a single gunshot, or even the rapid cracking of automatic fire. It was less a string of distinct sounds and more of a tone, a horrible, tremendous sound that tore through the air just as a hundred bullets tore into the area around Sickle, throwing up sprays of dirt, shattered pavement, and blood.

Sickle fell.

I scrambled back, unable to hear whatever I saw Dusty shouting. He, Starlight, and myself threw ourselves to the ground beside the wall of the old restaurant. Old, long-vacant windows gave a good view over the street, but we huddled behind the low brick wall beneath them, taking what protection we could get.

The tone paused for a split second, echoing in the distance, and then resumed, louder and angrier, as the tide of bullets tore into the wall we hid behind. Bricks shattered and fell, peppering us in fragments and filling the air with dust. I could have been screaming and not have even known.

Dusty shoved me forward, and I crawled frantically in the direction he had pushed me, too terrified to do anything but follow his direction.

A quick glance back caught sight of Sickle scrambling to her hooves and lurching in our direction. Her armor, ever impressive, had saved her life from the terrible assault. The same could not be said of Fireline or that smug green stallion, both of which were quite clearly deceased.

I made it to the rear of the restaurant, past the edge of the windows and to the relative safety of having most of a building between us and the source of that tremendous fusillade of fire. The sound tore through the air again as another volley ripped up the edge of the restaurant and smashed into the side of Sickle’s armor. Cans of food poured from one of the shredded bags on her back as the assault sent her stumbling and falling; this time, however, she fell behind the partially destroyed wall, giving her a little relief from the fire.

The bullets still struck out, but most now hit the wall, with relatively few puffs of bullets shattering on the plates of her armor as she scrambled forward again, and moments later she made it to us. The terrifying gunfire stopped.

I can’t overstate just how relieved I felt when Sickle made it to us. While I certainly had my reasons to dislike her, this was precisely the sort of situation where having a heavily armored and psychotically vicious killer at my side was likely a good thing.

That, and I was burdened with the concern that, if someone or something were able to take down a mare like Sickle, what chance would I have?

That relief was diminished a moment later when Sickle staggered and nearly fell. Her head weaved from side to side, as if she were about to collapse. It was only then that I noticed the blood streaming from her. It was practically pouring from behind the plates over her right shoulder and side, as well as dribbling from her chin. Behind the thick bars of her muzzle, all I could see was blood and teeth.

Dusty was up beside us, his words finally registering with me. “Next building! Move!”

He rammed his shoulder against Sickle’s as she teetered, and she leaned against him without protest, while I looked in the way Dusty had indicated. Across the small back lot was a two-story building of some sort, likely a store. I hesitated, looking to my right, but the line of old buildings looked to give good cover from whoever had been shooting at us.

I obediently rushed forward, leaping through a vacant window. Safely in cover, I sat, trying to catch my breath. My heart hammered hard in my ears, beating away everything else.

Starlight arrived moments after me, followed several seconds later by Sickle and Dusty. Sickle shoved her way awkwardly through the nearby doorway, then collapsed. She uttered a few barely recognizable curse words as she awkwardly fumbled with her armored saddlebags.

Despite the unexpected chaos, Dusty took charge of the situation. “Whisper! Cover that way!” He pointed a hoof further down the back lot we had crossed, while aiming his own rifle out the window the way we had come. “Starlight! Help Sickle! Get a couple healing potions in her as quick as you can. We need to move fast.”

Starlight drew back from the window and moved further into the room, while I crouched by the doorway. I resisted the urge to look back and check on her, keeping my eye down the sight of my rifle. I ignored the clattering and rustling behind me as seconds sped by. I focused on the corner of the far building, where an alley led back into the lot, ready to pull the trigger the moment a head poked out.

I almost squeezed off a shot by accident when Dusty fired off a burst, the sound hammering at my head and kicking up dust in the confined space. He immediately followed up by shouting, “Fall back, now!”

I didn’t need any more encouragement, turning and running back into the building. I passed Starlight and Sickle, who was climbing awkwardly to her hooves.

“She’s hurt bad,” Starlight said as Dusty entered the room.

“I’m fine,” Sickle growled, her words slurred as she staggered forward.

Dusty pulled his snout out of a pouch, a mine clutched between his teeth. “Keep moving!” he said as he armed it, and tossed the device to the rubble-strewn floor behind us. I put on a bit more speed, running outside.

It was maybe ten yards to the next building, and every inch of it left me terrified that I was about to be shot by some unseen assailant.

One corner of the building had collapsed, and Dusty and I once again took covering positions over the remains of a wall, while Sickle collapsed onto the rubble-strewn floor behind us.

As soon as she had, Dusty spoke again. “Sickle, take whatever you need to get moving again.”

She grunted, and I heard the clatter of her armor and metal cases, followed by a couple loud, angry, pained growls. Those sounds continued in turns, second by second, while I focused on the corner of the building we had come from.

A powerful, almost impossibly deep bang shook the air, as a wave of dust and smoke burst from every opening of the building we had just vacated.

Dusty chanced a glance back before speaking to me. “Whisper, peel back to the next building, then set up to cover for everypony else.”

“Got it,” I blurted, spinning to run back. I caught only a quick glimpse of Sickle—her metal muzzle hung open, giving me a quick glimpse of her mangled snout—before I was past them, moving as quick as I could across the rubbled, uneven terrain. Then I darted out the doorway on the far side of the building, and out into the alley beyond.

The next building had no windows facing our direction, but halfway down the side wall was a recessed doorway. I took position there, aiming back past the building I had just emerged from, and casting wary glances toward the windows and alleyway looming beside me.

I crouched there, waiting in silence with nopony around. After the tremendous, frantic madness, the quiet was unnerving.

I’m quite glad that, despite the humming tone that had returned to my ears, I heard Sickle’s armored hooves as she approached. With how tense I was, I can’t be certain I wouldn’t have accidentally shot her if she just appeared around the corner.

She lumbered by, with Starlight tagging along beside her. Starlight gave me a quick, concerned glance before passing by me. Her Lancer was out, floating just beside her head, ready to shoot.

The sound of their hooves rapidly faded behind me as I waited, covering their retreat.

Dusty’s rifle fired again, the sound loud and distinct. There was a long burst of automatic fire, followed by several shorter bursts before the weapon went silent. I heard no return fire.

Several seconds later, Dusty came running around the corner. He slowed as he came along beside me. “Wait ten seconds, then bound past me.”

With that, he was gone again, hurrying down the alley in the same direction Sickle and Starlight had gone. I understood his intent, then. We would move alternately, one covering while the other fell back.

And at that moment, I was the one in front. It was my turn to lay down a wall of fire against those who pursued us. Adrenaline built with every moment, as the seemingly inevitable clash drew closer. I counted down the seconds, hoping that my allotted time would expire without the arrival of any hostile ponies.

It was with a wave of relief that I finally reached “ten”. I turned, hooves shifting to gallop away.

The first sighting of the ponies pursuing us came not from the corner I had been covering, but the alley leading off to my side. A pony—the instant was too quick to pick out any details of their appearance—galloped around the corner of the neighboring building and toward me. A weight dropped in my gut; that pony had run around to catch us in the flank, and the path of my retreat lay open and exposed to him.

Instead, I continued my turn, lunged forward through the doorway I had stood in, and threw myself to the side. I landed hard on the rubble-strewn floor at the same instant gunfire erupted behind me, throwing shards of plaster and brick from the wall behind me.

I immediately scrambled to my hooves and down the dark passage I found myself in. I managed to keep my footing despite the cluttered bits of fallen plaster, rushing past doorways that led even further from my companions. The dark hallway turned one way, then the other, and finally opened into an old storage room. Shelves lay askew, and shards of broken crates lay scattered about. I rushed through the room, leaping over a fallen shelf. I was so consumed with my frantic escape that I hadn’t even consider the possibility of nails among those broken remains, and likely escaped that hazard through pure chance.

I burst through the door on the far side of the room and into a completely looted store, and the much-welcome sight of muted sunlight. Unfortunately, the same floor-to-ceiling windows that brought in the sunlight also brought the much less-welcomed sight of three heavily armed ponies galloping down the street, one of whom was already looking in my direction.

I threw myself behind the counter, keeping low as I ran along it. Gunfire erupted once again, throwing more clouds of pulverized plaster into the air as bullets tore into the wall behind me—and to my horror, blasted shards of wood from the counter that stood between me and the shooter, as the bullets tore straight through the flimsy barrier. The only protection it offered was to obscure my position, but enough bullets would eventually find their mark.

I rushed forward as more bullets punched more holes, and leaped through the window at the far end. I landed in the small gap between that building and the next, and leaped again, diving through the much smaller window facing me.

It was another hall. The gunfire died off behind me as I galloped in the growing darkness of the building. I passed by the closed doors, unwilling to take the time to open them, and the hall quickly ended in a set of stairs. I bounded up them, finding myself in another hall. I could already hear the hoofsteps and shouts behind me.

Thinking of Dusty’s earlier tactics, I stopped at the top of the stairs, turned, and fired a short burst down the way I had come. Then I was running again. I knew I wasn’t going to hit any of my pursuers with the random shots, but it might give them a moment of pause, and right then, every second was precious.

I galloped down the hall, catching bits of light where the crumbling building let in the sun. A pile of debris from a collapsed section of ceiling forced me to run through an open doorway. The room beyond, originally an apartment, was strewn with ruined furniture, and I leaped over a sagging couch before rushing through the back door and into a bedroom.

The building had suffered a fire at some point in the past, leaving the bed a gutted mess of springs and the floor and walls blackened, but its misfortune turned into my good fortune; the wall of the bedroom had burnt badly enough to partially collapse, and I leaped through the gap into the adjacent room.

I passed through room after room, weaving back into the hall, slipping through fallen sections of wall, or leaping through narrow holes. The burnt floor crunched under-hoof, and at one point I had to shoulder my way through the remains of a wall, the old, charred wood practically falling apart and smearing me in black dust.

The building ended abruptly, the outer wall having collapsed to open up into the narrow alleyway. The building across the way had also been burnt away, its upper story almost entirely opened up. The gap couldn’t have been even ten feet across; an easy jump. I didn’t hesitate, galloping on and leaping the gap.

I really shouldn’t have been surprised to discover that the fire had weakened the building. In my defense, I had much more pressing matters at hoof than the state of the building I was fleeing through—or at least, I did until the floor I landed on smashed in under hoof. The entire floor caved in under my sudden weight, and I fell.

I immediately called up my magic. There wasn’t any time for fancy magics or calculated transformations. I simply stripped away my disguise, my wings buzzing. Then I slammed into the ground, my poor and tired legs collapsing as I tumbled. I came to a halt when I smashed into something hard. My right shoulder bore the brunt of the impact, sending a shock of pain through me, but I was intact. Between the bit of deceleration I had managed and the protection of my carapace, I seemed mostly unharmed, sore shoulder aside.

I quickly shoved myself up, appraising the situation. The object I had run into was a counter, and the broken remains of tables and stools littered the room. It had been a restaurant, it seemed, or perhaps a tavern. Though partially blocked by rubble, the windows gave me a good view of the street outside. Two doors on opposite sides of the room led deeper into the building.

I heard Dusty’s rifle, three rapid shots echoing around the buildings. It sounded so distant.

Unfortunately, my unexpected trip downstairs had cost me time. My lead was shrinking, and though my shoulder only felt sore, I feared it might slow me down. I could hear the hoof-beats of ponies drawing closer.

It was time to change tactics.

The front door of the restaurant smashed open as a well-armed stallion rushed in, but he didn’t find a changeling, or even a gray-coated, silver-maned mare. Instead, he found an off-white unicorn buck.

I was already calling out before the stallion had taken in the scene. “The back door!” I wheezed, holding my right foreleg tight against my chest as I leaned against the counter, and waved the other in the direction of the back door. “She went out the back door!”

He took one look at the apparently wounded pony, then rushed off in the direction I had indicated. I remained where I was, wheezing and panting. More ponies ran by, most on the street, with only a couple more following through the building. They paid me no more than a passing glance, too caught up in the moment to question the young unicorn’s survival. I’m not even sure if they recognized him, specifically, or if they had accepted my apparent help as proof that I was on their side.

I waited only about ten seconds before hauling myself up to my hooves and limping over to the window. There’s an important lesson in deception and consistency, there; if you’re going to fake something, keep faking it, even when you think you won’t be observed. It not only prevents you from being discovered by accident, but it’s a good way to keep yourself “in character”.

While I still heard hooves clattering on the cracked street and through broken buildings, they were all heading away. I had time to think and plan. Unfortunately, I wasn’t terribly happy with my situation.

I had escaped the immediate threat, but it left me in a troublesome position. While disguising myself as one of the mercenaries might give me a degree of freedom among them, it would also lead to my own companions mistaking me for an enemy. While I could move past the mercenaries with relatively little difficulty, it would do me no good if I were then shot by the very ponies I was trying to reach. It would also do me little good if all these mercenaries killed my companions anyway. While I had every respect for their fighting ability, they were three ponies against many, and I had no doubt that these ponies would be of higher skill than the raiders we had faced before.

So I was faced with a problem, and I needed to figure out a solution, quickly.

As always, the first step was information.

Peering out the windows, I looked around the buildings nearby. It wasn’t hard to find what I was looking for; all I had to do was look up and see what building rose the highest. The answer was an old bell tower atop a building just half a block away. I stepped out, heading there in a limping trot.

A couple more ponies were trotting down the street past me, but after a quick glance, ignored me, and I stepped into what I assumed had once been a government building. Despite the many offices and decaying decor, it wasn’t hard to find the stairs to the bell tower.

The bell was long gone, and the tower’s roof was likely one good gust from finally collapsing, but it served my purposes perfectly. While only slightly taller than some of the other buildings around it, it gave me a clear vantage of what lay ahead.

I raised my binoculars with my magic, keeping myself barely exposed. Starlight was out there somewhere, with her powerful and long-ranged weapon, and I had no desire for her to mistake me for one of the ponies attacking us.

And there were a lot of them. I could see almost a dozen moving down streets and through buildings, and by the rising sound of gunfire, there were many more of them. Past the gunfire, I could hear the occasional crack of Dusty’s rifle, and even more occasionally, the sharp pop of Starlight’s Lancer tearing the air apart in its wake. It made them easy to locate, though my hopes dwindled when I had; their retreat had led them down a long line of buildings, eventually ending in an old skywagon charging station a few hundred yards away. Ponies were taking up positions in several buildings across the street from it, and the paved lot behind the station offered no cover. Dusty’s fighting retreat had gone as far as it could.

I was taking in the scene when I heard hooves on the stairs below me. I suppressed the urge to run and hide—especially since my only escape would be onto the slanted roof beside the tower—and remained where I was, exactly as if I was supposed to be there.

I was still looking out the binoculars, and doing my best to keep my breathing in check, when the pony arrived. She was a blue earth pony, with light barding, a brown cloak draped across her back, and a long rifle held in her teeth. She dropped into a crouch beside the wall, swinging her rifle up to rest it across the edge. “Hey,” she said, glancing my way. “You see where they’re at?”

“Yeah, you can see them perfectly from here” I said, lowering the binoculars and raising a hoof to point. She raised her rifle, peering down the scope. “See that street one over? Follow it up to the intersection and you’ll see a service station. They’re in there. Watch the left—”

The sharp clack of my pistol echoed within the confined space, and the mare collapsed, her head smacking against the wall as she fell.

“—window,” I finished, lowering myself beside her. Aside from the faint thump of her fall and the huff of air leaving her body, the only other sound was the faint pinging of the casing clattering on the roof.

In the back of my mind, I noted that this was the first pony I knew I had killed. It’s possible I had killed one before, with the copious amounts of ammunition I had spent in our previous engagements, but I honestly doubted it. In any case, this was the first one I could be sure of.

I don’t note that because of any particularly strong feelings on the matter. There wasn’t any internal debate over the morality of having done so. At best, these were soldiers employed to pursue goals that ran contrary to those of myself and, as its only known agent, my hive. At worst, they were knowing accessories to rape and murder. I felt no particular remorse for killing her.

It simply felt like something noteworthy, significant only as something new. A milestone, in a way.

It was a first for me. The first of what I expected would soon be many.

I floated her rifle over to my side, removed her cloak, and rolled her onto her back. It took a surprising amount of effort. Though she naturally didn’t resist, it’s easy to forget just how heavy a pony can be, and how awkward a limp body can be. Once I had her on her back, I took a few moments to examine her, quickly taking in the details of her appearance. She was lean, with a thin frame and fine features, but reasonably fit. No visible injuries, aside from the obvious, nor any notable blemishes. She had a very short blue-green mane and a short tail, both straight and simple. Lifting the flanks of her light barding revealed her cutie mark to be a single bullet, long and narrow.

Nodding in satisfaction, I called up my magic, and in a flash, mimicked her appearance.

Next I opened her small bags, dumping out the contents. Food and water were pushed aside, while a single healing potion and a ragged first-aid kit were quickly tucked into my own bags. The only item I examined was a small notepad, but it disappointed me; she wasn’t so thoughtful as to have written her own name in it, and I had no time to pore through it. It, too, was added to my bags.

I did notice a word etched into the stock of her rifle, however. “Thunder”. I had no idea whether it was her name, or one she had given the rifle, but I remembered it in case anypony addressed me by it.

As for the rifle itself, it was a long, bolt-action weapon, with a large scope. It was of wartime make, worn by the years, but well cared for. The pouch resting across the mare’s chest contained a few dozen rounds for it, looking very much like the kind of round Dusty’s rifle used. I took that, as well.

With my quick check complete, I swept the cloak over my back, and returned to the edge of the bell tower. I lifted the binoculars, sweeping around the area again. The shooting was slow but steady, and I could see several puffs of bullet impacts from the walls of the service station. Fortunately, the structure had been built along practical, industrial lines rather than for aesthetics; the building was thick and blocky, and even the centuries of wear hadn’t worn down its concrete walls. Even if they had been forced to a dead end, Dusty had led them to what was possibly the most fortified building in the area.

The front of the service station was a wide but short window, like a long slit in the concrete wall. Deep within it, I saw a subtle flash. A second later I heard the sound of Dusty’s rifle echoing across the ruined buildings. Dozens of gunshots answered, peppering the area, but thankfully, none of the mercenaries were trying to move up.

That made sense to me. They had their targets trapped. Why risk moving in when they could simply pepper them at range? I just hoped they wouldn’t tire of the situation before I did something about it.

Not that I had any clue what that would be.

It looked like the mercenaries had taken position within three buildings. On the right was a long, narrow motel, two stories tall, of which the back half had long ago collapsed. To the left was what looked to be a small grocery store. Directly across from the service station was a convenience store, its colorful post-topping sign—”Shop ‘n Dash”—having long ago faded and fallen across the street beside it.

I could see several ponies in them, peeking out of windows or moving around, far more concerned with staying in cover from the ponies to their front than some unseen changeling behind them.

How convenient of this mare to have given me what appeared to be a long-range, high-accuracy rifle.

If only I were a decent enough of a shot to make good use of it. No, I needed another approach.

I continued scanning before something caught my eye. A pony, one of the mercenaries, was hauling a wagon up the street behind the motel. There were a few boxes and a barrel, but also several ammo containers and a few weapons, including a heavy machine gun. There was even a small basket full of grenades.

It seemed like a good place to start.

I drew back, slinging the scoped rifle across my back, while my own rested against my chest. I hurried down the stairs, past the long-abandoned offices, and out the back door of the building to canter after him and that wagon. I took care to always keep something solid between myself and the service station.

By the time I had caught up with the wagon, it was parked by the fence behind the motel. The pony who had been hauling it, a large stallion with a holstered pistol and a shotgun at his side, was pulling the heavy machine gun from the wagon, and grunting under the effort. I trotted up to him, imitating the blue mare’s tone. “Hey, you need any help?”

“I got this,” he grunted as he hauled the tripod-mounted weapon across his back, and took a step toward the edge of the fence. “You can grab some ammo for it, though.”

“Sure thing,” I said, walking behind him to get to the wagon.

Rather than getting the ammo, I used the opportunity to grab the bit of my pistol in my teeth, draw it, and bring it around on him.

For whatever reason, he started to glance back just as I fired. The shot caught him off-center at the back of his head, and he toppled over. The gun fell to the ground with a metal-on-concrete crack, and he rolled onto his back, groaning something made incoherent by the likely mortal, but not immediately fatal wound.

I had much more time to line up my second shot. His head fell back against the street, his body jerking, and then he slumped onto his side, dead.

I holstered my pistol again, clambered up into the wagon, and started rooting through their supplies.

I was not disappointed.

Amidst the food, water, medical supplies, and miscellaneous equipment, there were ammo cases containing hundreds of rounds of several different types, a good number of grenades, a few spare pipe rifles, and one case that particularly excited me. Inside were the sort of thing that could make a destruction-minded changeling weep for joy: a pair of large demolition charges, old Equestrian Army models complete with blasting caps and a radio detonator.

And to think, I had once considered my short course on demolitions and improvised explosives to be completely useless. Contingency planning wins again.

I wasted no time in making use of them. The radio detonator was a simple model, and I soon had each charge prepped, ready to go. I switched the detonator to “Arm”, and a small red light appeared. After that, it was a simple matter of getting them to where they would do the most good.

They were much too heavy to haul both at once. I turned the detonator back to “Safe” and engaged the physical safety, then tucked it into my bags. After that, I pulled out one of the demolition charges, closing the case over the other. I hauled my chosen charge around, swinging it onto my back. I grunted a little at the weight; it must have been about fifty pounds.

I carried it to the edge of the fence and peered around. I could see the roof of the service station, and while the yard and murky swimming pool behind the crumbling motel were wide open, the burnt-out husk of a skywagon provided enough concealment to get to the ruined building.

The gunfire had faded to background noise, a slow but steady cacophony. As I rushed toward the rear of the motel, crouched low, the nearby gunshots came to the forefront of my attention. They were coming from the front of the building, naturally, and I quickly picked my way through the rubble toward them.

I heard another shot from Dusty. They were so close, but the difference in the volume of fire was concerning. I had no idea how much longer his ammo would last.

Only the last three rooms of the ground floor were still standing, and the partially collapsed roof had rendered all but the last room upstairs impassable. I climbed over the mountain of debris until I could enter the back of what still stood, making my way steadily toward the nearby sounds of gunfire.

I crawled through a half-collapsed wall, into a debris-strewn bathroom, and then into a bedroom. The door between units had been battered down at some point. I peeked through it, finding myself right next to a closet, while a pony at the far end of the room crouched behind a couch, his rifle aiming out the window.

The pop of Starlight’s Lancer firing echoed across the street, and the pony across from me started firing again, putting a half-dozen rounds downrange. More guns blazed nearby, both in a neighboring room and from the floor above.

I took advantage of the noise to set the demolition charge inside the open closet and back out.

The canter back to the wagon was much easier without the extra weight. I hopped over the dead pony and retrieved the final charge, returning to the edge of the fence.

The convenience store was much more open. While there was still the occasional bit of broken skywagon or wall that had not yet fallen, there were enough gaps to make the prospect of crossing the distance twice look very unappealing. From there to the neighboring grocery store was much easier.

I decided I wouldn’t be returning to the wagon after that, so I set the charge down and loaded as many of the grenades as I could into my ammo pouch. Then I retrieved the explosive, took a deep breath, and galloped to the first piece of cover.

I practically slammed against the hulk of the skywagon as I arrived. I paused there for only a moment, taking another couple deep breaths before darting forward again to a low wall. Then a toppled dumpster, filled with debris. I was making the short gallop between the dumpster and an old delivery wagon when a terrifyingly loud snap nearly sent me stumbling. I threw myself to the ground behind it as the hail of return fire answered Dusty’s shot.

I quickly got to my hooves, taking advantage of the return fire to run the final gap, finding myself in the strange position of hoping their fire kept Dusty’s head down for just that moment.

The convenience store was small. I slipped in the back door, entering a tiny office that led into the store itself. Several ponies were in the front area, taking cover behind the edge of the window and the counter. One lay dead beside the front door, and another was nursing a bleeding leg.

One of the ponies noticed the movement and looked my way. He saw me, then immediately turned back to the window. After all, that’s where the danger was.

I set the demo charge against the front wall of the office, closest to them, and slipped out the back.

There was only one building left, and I was out of bombs.

I galloped across the narrow gap into the grocery store’s back lot, coming to a halt once I was in safety once again. The lot itself was cluttered with debris, broken crates, and old equipment. To my surprise, I wasn’t alone. A single pony crouched at the back of the lot, behind a refrigerator. Unlike the others, he was facing away from the service station, scanning over the buildings everypony had just come through.

A quick glance around confirmed that we were alone, so I moved toward him.

“Hey,” I called out as I neared. “How come you’re out here?”

He glanced my way, then looked out again. “Covering our asses. That gray mare got away, so Storm’s got me watching our rear in case she shows up.”

“So they stuck you out here all on your own?”

“Yeah,” he replied, a hint of bitterness to his tone. “Not that I don’t mind not being shot at, but I’d rather be up front with—”

I recognized a certain measure of irony as my bullet smashed through the back of his skull. The sharp clack of my pistol echoed faintly across the lot, almost certainly inaudible past the occasional gunshots from within the building. He fell against the fridge and slid down into an awkward heap on the ground.

Pausing behind an old food crate, I retrieved the detonator, arming it once more. I didn’t trigger it just yet, though. Instead, I hung it on the strap of my ammo pouch, close to hoof in case I could make use of such a dramatic distraction.

The back door of the store lay fallen on the ground, giving me access to the storage room at its rear. I picked my way through the room to the door leading into the store, and peeked in.

Rows of battered shelves left most of the store hidden to me, though the scattered gunshots from the front told me there were plenty of ponies there. I could only see two of the occupants, both sitting behind a battered freezer cabinet at the rear of an aisle. One was a large mare, who wore no barding, but made up for it with her weapon; she wore a battle saddle sporting a minigun, with a chute leading to a large ammo drum opposite it.

Surprisingly, it was the other mare that caught my attention. She wasn’t like the other mercenaries I had seen. She looked like a member of the Mareford Militia. My eyes immediately dropped to her foreleg, spotting the cloth-covered bulge of a PipBuck, and the adrenaline mounted once more. I had no doubts that fancy little arcano-tech device would consider me to be hostile, destroying any benefit my disguise could provide.

I considered my options for a few seconds, then began to pull out all the grenades I had acquired, setting them all on the floor beside the door. As I did so, the ponies outside continued talking.

“Because ammo’s expensive. It ain’t like we’re on a time crunch, here.”

“Some civilians might investigate the gunfire. We’re not supposed to arrive until after the fight’s over.”

“So you arrived when it’s still going on, big deal. I’m sure Shard knows what she’s doing.”

“After seeing your ambush, I’m not so certain of that.”

The other mare snorted. “Hey, nopony expected them to just stomp in Fireline’s head and kill his team. None of this shit makes any sense.”

I missed whatever came next. I had taken a grenade with each hoof, pulled their pins with my teeth—which is not nearly as easy as you might think—and after a quick glance around the edge of the doorway, threw one, then the other. As soon as the second one had left my hoof, I threw myself down against the wall, flipped the safety on the detonator, and smashed my hoof against the trigger.

It was as if I’d been bucked in the chest.

The explosion transcended sound, a terrible, angry wall of presence that smashed into me, even behind the intervening bulk of the building. The world felt disjointed afterwards, almost as if I couldn’t tell which way was up or down, and dust filled the air with a dense haze. I never even heard the grenades go off. It was a few seconds before I could pick myself up, detangle myself from my cloak, and look through the doorway again.

The two ponies I had spied upon lay motionless in the smoke and haze. The entire far wall of the store, closest to the convenience store and its bomb, had collapsed, a whole section of the roof coming down with it and giving a view of the sky. Dust choked the air, billowing away from the collapsed area. Past the dust and broken shelves, I could see a few more ponies inside the front of the grocery store, moving away from the destruction.

One by one, I picked up a grenade, pulled its pin, and threw it across the store. I could feel every explosion, though the sharp bangs felt somewhat muted and muffled after the tremendous detonation that had preceded them.

When the last grenade was thrown, I rushed over to the two dead ponies. Green fire erupted from my forehead as I added a horn to my disguise, then used my magic to quickly unbuckle the minigun-equipped battle saddle.

I think my reasoning at the time had been that anything which had survived two demolition charges and a dozen grenades would need something truly excessive to put down.

I had just pulled the battle saddle free when a dust-caked stallion came staggering out of one of the aisles, barely twenty feet away.

Maybe I could have bluffed my way further on. Maybe he would have missed that one of the many ponies there had grown a horn, especially with how dazed he looked. Maybe I could have talked my way into a better position and silently removed a few more ponies before things turned loud.

But the adrenaline was flowing strong, and I had a minigun. I swung the battle saddle around, shoved my shoulder against the back of the frame to brace it, and squeezed my magic around the bit.

The sound that had been so terrifying to be on the receiving end of was so amazingly empowering from the other side of the weapon. The battle saddle jerked and bucked back against me as the minigun roared, tearing into everything before it.

I didn’t aim so much as point it in the general direction and set it loose to do its own thing. I let off the trigger just a second after squeezing it. Amidst the dust that the minigun had kicked up, I could see the motionless form of the stallion, his side shredded by a dozen bullet wounds.

Sharp cracks of gunfire tore through the air, striking shelves in front of me. I dove back behind the freezer cabinet; someone in the front of the store was firing blindly through the shelves in my direction. I brought the battle saddle around, and answered with a much bigger gun. A single second of fire put out a tremendous volume of fire, shredding the vacant display before me. A couple aisles’ shelves finally gave in and collapsed

I let off the trigger, bringing the bucking battle saddle back into control just as a grenade bounced off the remains of the next aisle’s shelves and onto the ground.

I skittered around the cabinet and galloped down the aisle. I was halfway down it when the grenade went off, well behind me.

The adrenaline had taken complete control by then. I rushed forward, intending to get to the end of the aisle, turn the corner, and hose down any remaining mercenaries.

Instead, I got to the corner at the same moment another pony did. We were only feet apart, too close for me to bring my stolen weapon to bear, or for him to aim the assault rifle he held in his teeth.

Lacking any better options, and with the fury of adrenaline pumping through me, I dropped my shoulder and rammed him.

It went about as well as you’d expect.

My disguised form was light and lean, and though he staggered with the impact, he quickly looped a foreleg around me, twisted, and slammed me down atop a section of fallen roof.

I remember having just enough time to be surprised at suddenly looking at clouds before his weight landed atop me; I had just managed to catch my hoof in the sling of his rifle and pull him down with me. He responded with a swift hoof to the side, knocking the wind out of me. When that didn’t get his rifle free, he lowered his head to his chest, drawing back a moment later with a knife clutched in his teeth.

I threw my hooves up at his chest, halting his attack for only a moment. He immediately swiped with a hoof, shoving one of my much weaker legs away, then moved to do the same with the next. The knife loomed above me.

Fortunately, I had two things going for me. One: I’m a changeling. And two: fire tends to provoke very visceral reactions.

Green fire flashed over me as I tore away my disguise, and the stallion flinched back from my sudden and unexpected immolation. It delayed my imminent stabbing by only a moment, but that was all I needed as I snapped my head forward, firing a blast of magic from my horn that sent him stumbling and falling backwards. As he fell, I grabbed my rifle in my magic and emptied the magazine at him. At least one round hit, as he didn’t get up again.

I scrambled up to my hooves, grabbing the fallen battle saddle with my magic once more. I saw then that several ponies lay scattered along the front wall of the store, twisted and limp in death. At least two wore Mareford Militia barding. The store itself, already decayed through the centuries of neglect, had been devastated by my assault. Shelves lay twisted and crumpled in the aisles, and the ceiling was drooping and crumbling, as if it might give in and collapse at any moment. It was hard to believe that anything had survived.

Another pony stepped out around the counter at the end of the next aisle. He looked at me in wide-eyed horror, though whether it was my insectoid appearance or the minigun held in the green fire of my magic, I could only guess. I brought the battle saddle around, and he dove back behind the counter as I opened up, shredding what remained of the shelving and tearing apart the counter in a barrage of sound and bullets. So emboldened was I with my newfound weapons, I pushed harder against the back of the battle saddle’s frame, advancing toward the counter while firing short bursts of a few dozen rounds each.

A grenade arced up, bounced off the remains of the countertop, and landed at my hooves.

I leaped back, my wings buzzing frantically as I shot upward. The grenade went off, hammering at me with the blast. After all the chaos, all the explosions, all the adrenaline, I felt numb.

The pony rose up over the counter, a submachine gun held in his teeth. It would have been the perfect follow-up, except for one fatal flaw.

He hadn’t expected an opponent who could fly.

He was just looking up when I pressed the battle saddle’s frame against my chest and squeezed the firing bit.

With enough bullets, even I can hit what I’m shooting at.

I kept firing until the minigun ran dry a with a jolt, the barrels still spinning as I held the trigger. I floated down, landing in the street just before the grocery store. My right front leg almost gave out as I landed. A quick glance revealed a thin trickle of blood leaking out from a crack in my carapace. I ignored the wound. I couldn’t feel it, so clearly it couldn’t be important. Instead, I looked back to the store, panting. Nothing stirred within it.

To my left, the demolition charge had completed what the apocalypse and two centuries of decay had started, having finally flattened what was left of the motel.

Closer by, the convenience store had ceased to exist, with chunks of wall and ceiling scattered liberally about the lot it had once occupied.

And across the street from it, three faces stared out from behind the service station’s counter.

I was an unfamiliar face, an alien creature of unknown intent. My final armor was stripped away. I stood looking back at the wide-eyed, wary expressions of Dusty and Starlight, and the psychotic, blood-caked grin of Sickle. I was completely exposed, and out of tricks.

My magic flickered out, letting the battle saddle drop noisily to the pavement. I wavered on my hooves.

Lacking any better options, I gave a weak and uncertain smile, my voice rather small after all the storm I had just passed through.

“Hey, guys.”

Chapter Sixteen: Homecoming

We passed the chain link fence that marked the southern edge of the Pale Sands territory exactly two days after passing its twin to the north. Other than Ponytown, the entire expanse between those two points had been barren, empty desert.

The low mountains at the edge of the badlands drew near.

For the most part, we had recovered from the “incident” near Ponytown. Starlight’s splint had been removed, and after a bit of ginger testing and a warning to go easy on it, she was walking normally once again. Healing potions are truly remarkable things. Both she and Dusty still felt a little sore from their injuries, but it was nothing significant. I just hoped Starlight was actually healed, rather than stubbornly refusing to acknowledge her injuries.

As for Sickle, she had taken up wagon duties once more, allowing me to retake my normal, less exhausting disguise. She was unhappy with it, though possibly not for the reason you would think.

“Fucking wasted potential,” she grumbled as she pulled the cart. “I mean, come on. You give yourself a fuckstick like that and you don’t even use it? Dumb cunt.”

We did our best to ignore her.

By mid-day, we were approaching the settlement on Starlight’s map, a place nestled between Pale Sands and the Badlands, cheerfully named “World’s End”.

When we laid eyes on the place, I recognized it. Not the settlement, of course, as it hadn’t been there before the megaspells. The terrain, however, I recognized. World’s End was built between a pair of rock formations that jutted up higher than the rest of the rocky hills around them. It was a distinctive landmark, one that could be used by returning changelings to orient themselves on their way home.

We were close.

The cliffs between the two formations were now adorned with several structures, some of which were even suspended over open space, with rope bridges criss-crossing the gap. The only presence on the ground was a fortified structure, with what looked to be a large winch-lift hanging down from above. The lowest level of cliff-hanging structures had metal scrap strapped to them, and looked to give excellent firing positions over the lone access point. A few more structures were set around the tops of the rock formations, though it seemed most of the space up there had, somehow, been converted to crops. I found myself pondering how difficult irrigation must have been.

The distant tones of a bell rung out across the distance, almost as soon as we were in sight. We could see movement along the rope bridges as the inhabitants moved to take up defensive positions.

We continued on. Dusty gave a wave when we were were still a few hundred yards out. “It’s good to look friendly,” he quietly said. Starlight and I waved, as well.

As we drew near to the fortified lift-house I could see clearly that not all of the residents were ponies. I saw the hulking forms of a few buffalo among their numbers, and to my surprise, the stripes and exotic stylings of a pair of zebras. There was even a pony whose face looked like it had been skinned and left to rot for a week. I figured she had to be one of those ghouls Dusty had told me about. Either that, or one of the most unfortunate ponies of all time. Possibly both. Even from the distance, the sight provoked simultaneous feelings of sympathy and nausea.

We were only a hundred feet away when a heavily armored mare atop the lower fortification called out. “Hold up, there. We saw you coming in. You came through the Pale.”

It seemed more like an accusation than a question, but Dusty answered anyway. “We did.”

She glanced to her side, to a buffalo who had what could only be described as a cannon strapped to his side. He stepped forward and spoke, his deep words echoing clearly without raising his voice. “The pale ponies reign over that land. They are the harbingers of death itself. No one passes through their domain.” He gave a short pause, as if for drama. “How did you escape their influence?”

“We ran,” Dusty said. “Very fast.”

The buffalo continued to stare at him for several seconds. I was starting to grow worried, when his shoulders suddenly shook, and he let out a deep laugh. “You must have run very fast indeed, pony, to outrun death itself.” He turned back to the mare, giving a nod.

She nodded back and turned to us. “Okay, what’s your business here.”

“We’re traveling south,” Dusty replied. “Our wagon’s damaged from our trip through the Pale, so we were hoping to get some repairs. Maybe a safe bed for the night. That’s it.”

“There ain’t anything to the south of here. What’s your interest there?”

Dusty cast a quick glance my way before answering. “It’s personal business I’d rather not shout out across the whole town, if that’s okay with you.”

She mulled that over for a moment before nodding. “Fair enough. Any trade in there?”

“We’ve got some supplies we might be convinced to part with, if the caps are right.”

The mare considered us for a few seconds, tapping her hoof on the edge of the wall, and finally nodded once more. “Okay. Leave the wagon in the bunker, along with your weapons, and you can come up.” She turned and called out. “Open the gate!”

A minute later, we were riding the lift on the short journey up. We were just lifting up through a hole in the floor of the winch room when a set of massive claws reached out to grab the edge of the lift. Starlight yelled out in surprise and slammed into the opposite rail of the lift. I turned toward the threat, and my veins ran cold as I laid eyes on my first hellhound, mere feet from my face.

He loomed over us, towering over even Sickle. His claws were nearly as long as my foreleg, and sharp fangs protruded past his lips. A coat of dark fur covered his muscular body, thick and ragged.

“Chickenshit,” Sickle muttered at Starlight, as the hellhound held the lift stable and opened the gate. Then Sickle turned to the hound. “What the fuck are you doing here, Spot?”

The hellhound frowned down at her. His voice rumbled deep enough that I could have sworn I felt his words as much as heard them. “Ain’t my name, Peenk.”

She glared back at him for several long seconds, before finally breaking into a grin. “Shit, it’s been a long time. Didn’t think I’d find you out in the ass end of Equestria.”

My heart-rate slowly returned to normal as it became clear that the hulking, heavily clawed monstrosity wasn’t about to reduce us to bloody chunks. I only then noticed that there were a few other townsponies there, including the pair that had greeted us at the walls. Starlight still looked quite pale, backed up against the far side of the lift. Dusty just looked a little more wary than usual.

“Yeah, been uh long time,” the hellhound said in a stilted, awkward accent, and flashed a grin full of vicious teeth. He reached out, flicking a claw against Sickle’s breastplate. “You must be doeen well. Didn’t theenk I’d see you in dis.” His head tilted. “You the new boss, huh?”

“Nah,” Sickle said, shrugging. “I’m done with that shit.”

The hellhound nodded. “Good,” he said. “Change ees good.”

The mare who had addressed us before cut in. “If you’re done terrifying our guests,” she said with a teasing tone and a smile, which earned a chuckle from the hellhound. Then she looked to Dusty. “My name’s Granite. I’m the mayor of our nice little town. So who might you be?”

We introduced ourselves, and she nodded along as she listened.

“Good, good. Now then, we’re not shouting across the whole town any more. What brings four well-armed ponies way down here?”

I had a moment of concerned reflection on how I had come to be a well-armed pony despite my best intentions. It was certainly an accurate description. I had been carrying two firearms, a pair of grenades, and more than two hundred rounds of ammunition, and that wasn’t counting the pipe rifle with another hundred rounds I had packed away, or the significant arsenal contained within our wagon. I quickly shook off the feeling of distress and refocused on the conversation.

Fortunately, it seems Dusty had used the short delay of our ride up to plan a response that didn’t involve looking for an ancient changeling hive. “We were looking for a pony, and heard he headed out into the Badlands.”

The townsponies exchanged wary glances. Granite frowned slightly before continuing. “So you’re bounty hunters, then?”

Dusty shook his head. “No. We’re not after him for money. We’re just trying to bring a bad pony to justice.”

She mulled it over for a few moments, her frown deepening. “I see. And who is this pony you’re looking for?”

“His name is Banger. I’m afraid the name is all I have to go on. He sold out a bunch of ponies to be raped and murdered.”

“Never heard of him,” Granite said, but finally nodded. “Ain’t our business what you do out there. Just keep it out there. We won’t be having any of that in our town. Got it?”

“Got it,” Dusty said.

“Good.” She turned, gesturing a hoof to the stallion beside her. “Sundown can show you to the lower berths. Anypony that wants to trade will meet you there, and there are beds in the back if you’re spending the night. A hundred caps, and the place is yours for the day.” She fixed Dusty with a firm stare. “I’d suggest not staying too long. Once word gets out that you’re hunting somepony, you ain’t going to find many friendly faces.”

“We’re just passing through,” Dusty said. “We’re not here for anypony in your town, just—”

“Ain’t anypony going to care who you’re after,” the mare shot back. “And we ain’t going to care about why you’re after them. Just that you are after them. Now, we’re going to be gracious hosts and let you rest for the night, but I expect you to be on your kindest behavior.” She looked around at us. “And I expect you to be gone in the morning. You got that?”

Dusty hesitated, but finally nodded. “Yes, ma’am.”

“Good,” she said with a sharp nod. “And if you ever have to come around again for another pony, I suggest you steer clear of here. We don’t take kindly to that sort of thing.”

Dusty nodded again.

Sundown led us along a series of walkways and rope bridges, until we descended to a low-hanging structure a short distance away. Wide windows gave a good view over the crevice between the two giant pillars of rock, while inside were a few tables, a half dozen chairs, and a few simple cots.

On the way, Dusty also filled me in on hellhounds, and how the diamond dogs, ever on the bottom end of Equestrian society, had somehow won the magical-radiation-mutation lottery to become the most dangerous creatures in the Wasteland.

Once we had arrived at our lodgings, Sundown informed us that we were to remain in the lower town, between the ‘berth’ we were in and the lift down. The rest of the town was off-limits.

As soon as he had left, Dusty started grumbling. “So. Apparently tracking down an accessory to rape and murder is a bad thing, now.”

“Well, I thought it was a good story,” I said.

He flashed a wry smile, which died as quickly as it came. “And I can’t help but note that they stuck us in the lowest part of their town, with only a single, easily defended route back into the rest.”

I looked back. The stairs leading up from our current residence ended on an open platform, connected to the rest of the lower town by a long rope bridge. One of the defensive positions overlooked the entire length of it, and I couldn’t help but notice that it was occupied. The earth pony with a double-barrel shotgun was the most obvious, but it was the zebra that really caught my attention. She was almost entirely hidden under her cloak, but it didn’t hide the long, slender rifle she had braced on the frame of the window. While the earth pony was relaxed and laid back, though with the shotgun within easy reach, the zebra appeared completely focused, as if expecting trouble.

“Well that’s comforting,” Starlight said. “And our guns are all down on the ground.”

“You dumb fucks and your guns,” Sickle grumbled as she dug around in her armored bags. She eventually retrieved another pill bottle, popping it open and slapping a pill back between the bars of her muzzle.

Dusty scowled. “Seriously? After what happened yesterday?”

“Fuck off,” Sickle snarled, turning to head back the way we came.

“Hey, wait!” Dusty called out after her. “Where are you going?”

She halted, turning to look over her shoulder. “Me? I just spent half a day staring at the ass-end of a big beefy stallion and thinking of all the fun I could have with somepony I don’t have to worry about breaking in half. Except Whimper’s a fucking pussy. So I’m going to go find Spot again, pin that mutt to the first flat surface I can find, and fuck his dumb little brains out.”

“You’re going to… with a hellhound?” Starlight blurted, looking at Sickle in shock.

“Fuck yeah, with a hellhound,” Sickle said. “Spot’s about the only one who’s ever matched me in wrestling, and he’s a lot better at fucking than most stallions.” She grinned. “‘Sides, hellhounds are a lot more interesting. Ponies, they’re all just smooth and boring, but hellhound cocks are—”

“Oh, goddesses, I don’t care!” Starlight replied, bringing both forehooves over her ears.

“Then why the fuck did you ask?” Sickle said, her grin taking on an increasingly sadistic twist. “Or are you jealous?” She hiked her scraggly tail, leaving her bare and unarmored rear fully exposed. “Come on, then! Stick your face right up in there and put that mouth of yours to use for once!”

“You’re revolting,” Starlight said, turning away, her eyes narrowed in an angry glare and color tinting her cheeks.

Sickle laughed. “Nah, I just know how to have some fucking fun instead of being a little bitch all the time.” Her tail lowered again. “And if you cunts are going to be so damn uptight, then I’ll just have to find someone that does know how to relax.”

She climbed the stairs and left.

Dusty sighed. “I really hope she isn’t about to get us all into trouble.”

“When does she not?” Starlight asked with a grumble, tossing her saddlebags onto one of the cots. “Maybe we should just go. We’re obviously not welcome here.”

“Tempting,” Dusty said. “But I’d still like to see if we can get our wagon fixed. The terrain ahead is a lot more rough. Even if the wagon holds up, it’s going to be a pain in the ass to haul with a broken wheel.”

Starlight flopped out on one of the cots, burying her face in an old straw pillow that muffled her voice. “Yeah, well, that’d be Sickle’s problem.”

“Except I’m sure it’d make her even more irritable, and then she’d make it our problem. ‘Sides, all our stuff is in the wagon.”

She sighed. “Yeah, fine.”

Dusty and I sat at one of the tables. Lacking anything better to do, I dug out one of the packages of ancient, pre-cooked food from my saddlebags. I was halfway through it when Sundown returned with a couple of the townsponies to discuss trade.

One was the ghoul I had spotted before, giving me a good look at her. Or at least, as good as I could get without being obvious in my attention. It was, to my surprise, less concerning up close. Yes, it gave me a clear view of the decay the poor pony had suffered, to the point that I could see bare skull in a couple places, but it also let me see that her condition appeared relatively stable. I had imagined the decay as active, festering rot, but it was actually fairly clean.

If not for the difference in appearance, I probably wouldn’t have even noted her. She participated in the negotiations with the same cautiously friendly attitude of her companions, showing no sign of burden over her condition.

In the end, Dusty managed to get lodging for the night and repairs to the wagons for the exorbitant price of two of our spare assault rifles and ten loaded magazines. We could afford it, though; after looting most of a mercenary company and seizing their supply wagon, it was a small portion of what we owned. We were, apparently, moderately wealthy by Wasteland standards.

We returned to our accommodations for the evening while the other ponies worked on our cart. Dusty took a chair and dragged it to the edge of the structure, and spent his time leaning against the window frame. It gave him the perfect vantage point to watch over our wagon.

I rested my forelegs on the windowsill beside him and looked down. A buffalo had shoved his shoulder under the edge of the wagon, lifting it up while a pony used a length of wood to brace it in place.

“You’re worried,” I said, keeping my voice low.

“You’re not?”

“I’m always a little paranoid,” I said. “Comes with the profession.”

He gave a short huff, and the corner of his mouth twitched upwards. “I guess we’ve got that in common.”

“I guess we do,” I agreed.

He slowly nodded, his voice quieting to a whisper. “So, I know the soldier’s take of the situation. What’s the spy’s take?”

“Concerned,” I said. “There are few reasons to react that poorly to the story of bringing a pony to justice.”

“Yeah,” Dusty said. “That’s what I was thinking. Shit. And here I thought it made a good story.”

“No, it was good,” I said, giving him a smile. “The creative use of true events is one of the best ways to fabricate a cover story. Consistency is one of the most important factors when constructing a long-term falsehood, and it’s much easier to be consistent when you’re using real-world facts.”

He cast a sideways glance my way before looking back to our wagon. “Thanks, I guess. Still backfired.”

“It’s a rare lie that doesn’t have the chance to backfire,” I said. “And since I’d really rather not advertise to everyone that we’re looking for a specific place instead of a specific pony, I’d have likely come up with a similar story, myself. They might draw the wrong conclusions about what’s out there, and I’d really rather not have a bunch of treasure hunting ponies digging around my hive. I appreciate the discretion.”

He gave another little huff, a shadow of a laugh. “Thanks.” Then he shook his head. “Not that it seems to have helped our situation.”

I nodded. “True. Fortunately, whatever their reasons to dislike us, the town as a group doesn’t seem intent on harming us. I’m concerned that individuals in the town might not share that thinking, however. I think we’ll be safe during the day, while their guards are watching us, but I’m not sure if—”

“We’re not staying the night,” Dusty said. “I’d been thinking the same thing. We’ll head out as soon as they get that wagon fixed.” He looked back to me. “Get some rest. Just be ready to do your thing if somepony starts something.”

I hesitated, but nodded. I’m not sure what he expected “my thing” to be. I suppose I’d have to improvise.

The rest of the evening was uneventful, despite the constant low-level tension. It was a familiar feeling. From Dusty’s relaxed posture and perceptive eyes, it seemed one he was quite familiar with, as well.

The sun was getting low when Dusty stood up. “Looks like they finished. Let’s get going. Where’s Sickle?”

Sickle wasn’t in the small portion of the town that we were told to stay in, to absolutely nobody’s surprise. A few armed ponies, as well as the cannon-armed buffalo, met us when we made our way to the lift, and one of the ponies headed off to track her down. Several minutes later, Sickle and her hulking hellhound friend made their way down to us along the ramps and walkways.

Sickle wore a very satisfied smirk as she walked up. “Hey, bitches. The fuck’s up, now?”

“We’re leaving,” Dusty said, and Sickle halted, scowling.

“Seriously? We just fucking got here!”

“The wagon’s fixed,” Dusty said. “We can get a few more hours in before it gets dark, so we’re heading out.”

Sickle groaned. “Wonderful. We finally get to a place we can relax and have fun, and you dumb cunts are trying to drag me off already. Could have spent the whole night fucking like mad, but no…”

The hellhound gave a quick wince, ears folding back, and he cast a quick glance at the couple of townsponies nearby. None of them seemed to notice. Their attention was focused on Sickle.

“Isn’t like you have to come with us,” Starlight grumbled.

Sickle gave an angry snort, but then grinned. “Nah, I ain’t going to miss out on this shit.” Then she lifted a hoof to point at Dusty. “But you’re hauling the cart. I’m done for the day.”

“Fine,” Dusty said.

The hellhound reached out, placing his huge claws across Sickle’s shoulders. “You shud stay, Peenk. This is uh good place.”

She looked back to him, pausing only a moment before letting out a snort. “If it’s a good place, you really don’t want me here. ‘Sides, I’d get bored. Not enough fighting.” She chuckled a little, flashing a grin up at the hellhound. “Might have to swing by and visit every now and then. It’s been way too fucking long.”

The hellhound chuckled in reply, though his sideways glance toward the other ponies made it seem slightly awkward to me.

We loaded into the lift, and the hellhound unlatched it, letting us descend. Granite watched us from the nearest guard post. So did several other ponies, and I caught at least a couple disapproving glares.

We retrieved our gear, and Dusty strapped himself into the restored harness. While we strapped on pouches and guns, Sickle climbed up into the wagon, flopping back heavily with a satisfied grunt.

Soon the cart was rolling along, down the slight slope leading away from the town.

The sound of glass bottles clinking together rose from the wagon as Sickle rooted around in her bags, finally pulling out a couple bottles of antique beer. “Shit, it’s been a long time since I saw Spot,” she said, dropping all but one of the bottles beside her. “Met him when I was still with my old gang. He hit the same caravan we were setting up to jump.” She popped open the bottle and took a long swig. Then she snickered. “He popped out of the ground right under their brahmin. Fuck, you should have seen it. It was like the damn thing just exploded! Meat and guts everywhere!”

She laughed, while beside me, Starlight scowled and muttered. “Must have been love at first sight.”

“Hah! Fuck no. That was our caravan, not his.‘Course, most of those pussies didn’t want anything to do with a hellhound, but I went down there and butted heads with him.” She tapped the lip of the bottle against the cheek of her helm, then traced down along her neck to her shoulder. “Can still kinda see the scar where he caught me, damn near took my head off. Heh, I remember him grinning all smug like until I planted a hoof right in his gut. Should have seen his dumb expression when he looked up and realized he just got pinned by a pony!”

“You have such a charming way of making friends.”

Sickle shrugged and took another swig of her drink before continuing. “Eh, I almost wanted to kill him for clawing my face up, but I was so high I couldn’t even feel it. ‘Sides, it was fun. We kinda just wrestled and beat on each other until we were both exhausted. Then we kicked back and shared some beers.” She grinned over her bottle. “And then we fucked.”

“Of course you did,” Starlight muttered. “Because the first thing you think when you see some monstrous creature tearing an animal to pieces is, ‘Hey, I wonder if I can have sex with it?’”

Sickle snickered. “Pretty sure you’d think it, too, if you ever gave it a chance.” She waved her bottle our way. “Should get your marefriend to turn into a hellhound and give you a good hard fucking. You’ll see.”

Starlight’s ears laid back as she grimaced, color rising in her cheeks. “I’ll pass, thanks.”

“Come on,” Sickle teased. “I thought you liked the cock? And two-leggers just let it all hang out in the open. You can’t tell me you didn’t get a good eyeful of that sheath.” She took another draw from her bottle before tossing it out behind us. “I ain’t kidding, though, you should try it. I’ve fucked lots of things: buffalo, zebras, donkeys, even a pair of griffons this one time. And lots of ponies. Hellhounds got them all beat, easy.”

Starlight shot her a glare. “Seriously, how do you not have, like, every disease ever?”

Sickle stared at her for a few seconds before shrugging. “Health potions?”

“They don’t…” Starlight stopped herself, shook her head, and simply continued walking.

Sickle just chuckled quietly and laid back, relaxing. There were several seconds of silence before she muttered. “Fuck. Now I’m horny again.”

We ignored her, of course. We even continued to ignore her when she unstrapped one of her spiked hoof-boots. The side-walls of the wagon helped, concealing most of the contents of the wagon from us, but they did little to block sound. Sickle was, as with all things she did, extremely unsubtle.

Dusty continued on with equal measures of disgust and determination, with his ears laid back against the sound and his scowling gaze fixed straight ahead. Starlight and I drifted a little further from the cart. I did my best to not dwell on the situation.

None of us said anything about it, naturally.

We were almost a mile away from the town when I noticed Dusty’s head dip down to reach into the folds of his cloth barding, drawing out the pistol he had concealed there, and returning it to its holster.

☢

If there’s one thing the Badlands have going for them, it’s the desolation.

I can’t imagine how much worse my reaction to the Equestrian Wasteland would have been if I hadn’t grown up in the Badlands. Admittedly, I had spent most of my time there in the hive, rather than on the barren and largely lifeless surface, and after that, I had lived in Equestria for several years. Still, it made the transition less jarring than if I had lived in the northern parts of Equestria, with their rolling, grassy fields and sprawling forests, all teeming with life.

That desolation was ideal for changelings seeking to remain hidden. With the surface devoid of food and water, and the ground split into a maze of canyons and hills, it was rare for anyone of any sense to wander out that way.

It also meant that the land was almost entirely unchanging. I had no need of Starlight’s PipBuck and its map to guide us. When we set out that morning, I knew exactly where we were. By mid-day, the pale slice of sky ahead of us had stretched over half the sky, as we passed under the ragged edge of the Enclave’s cloud cover. Looking ahead, it was as if I had stepped back in time. The bare sun beat down on bleached rocks, the air growing hotter and drier by the moment, just as I remembered it. The rugged canyons and valleys we followed led up between sheer cliffs, leaving plateaus and spires of rock decorating the land.

I know not many outside my hive would share the opinion, but I always found the Badlands to be beautiful.

We walked on, pebbles and dry earth crunching under our hooves and the wagon’s wheels. I even sprouted wings, taking to the air to get the same perspective I would have had on my return trips to the hive.

Everything was exactly as I remembered it. Even in the few places where the centuries had worn down a slope or rocky formation, they were still immediately recognizable.

The heat was certainly unchanged. Starlight and Dusty’s almost awed attention to the sun was quickly stifled. Without the protective layer of the clouds, it beat down on us, unrelenting. Sickle had it the hardest. Between muscling the heavy wagon over the broken and hilly terrain, the ever increasing altitude, and the heavy armor she wore, it wasn’t long before she was panting in exhaustion.

I’m not sure how long she would have stubbornly pressed on if Dusty hadn’t called for a break. We sheltered beside one of the many rocky columns that stretched up from the ground, which had always looked to me as if someone had stacked rocks atop each other. It gave us a little shade.

Sickle unharnessed herself and tore her helmet off. It banged down against the rocks as she flopped down, moving only enough to retrieve the pair of bottles that she chugged, one after the other.

“How far is it to your hive?” Dusty asked.

“Probably about thirty miles,” I said. “Sorry, I think my estimate of our travel time was a little low. I always flew. I hadn’t expected how much slower it would be to walk, especially with a wagon in tow.”

Even Sickle’s abrasiveness was worn down by her exhaustion, though she still huffed out a retort between pants. “You’re welcome to haul it yourself if you think I’m too fucking slow.”

Ignoring her, Dusty asked me, “Is the terrain like this the whole way?”

“Worse.”

“Then I’m thinking we leave the wagon here. It’ll be a lot easier to carry a few days of food and water than it will to drag that thing with us.”

“Sounds good to me,” Sickle mumbled as she pulled out another bottle.

“And drink some water,” Dusty said, looking to her. “Alcohol isn’t going to help.”

“Alcohol always helps,” Sickle grumbled as she popped open the bottle. “Stop being such a cunt.”

Dusty frowned at her, silent for several seconds before replying. “You know, I might find that more insulting if you didn’t throw it around every other word.”

“Like I give two shits what you think,” Sickle said before tipping back the bottle and chugging it all in one go. When it ran dry, she threw it back the way we came. The sunlight twinkled off the final drops streaming from the bottle as it spun through the air, remarkably vivid and strangely beautiful after the dullness below the constant cloud-cover.

An hour later, we had each packed five days’ worth of food and water in our saddlebags. As we prepared to set out, I laid out the course for the rest of the day. “There’s an outpost along the way to the hive,” I said. “A way station and hideout for returning Infiltrators, among other things. It’ll be a good place to stop for the night.”

The moon and stars were shining overhead by the time we reached the familiar rocky formation, and the narrow gap in the rocks below it. I paused before the opening to tug at my magic, unwinding my disguise. This was a changeling place; it felt appropriate to return in my natural form.

I stepped into the passage, pushing just enough magic into my horn to cast a faint light. The rocky ground was covered in dry earth and grit, entirely undisturbed. We crept forward in the dimly lit space, following the tunnel almost fifty feet before it ended in a metal door. It was unlocked. I pushed it open, and stepped into the small bunker beyond.

It wasn’t an impressive space, but it was immediately familiar. Many times I had stopped in this place. It was a single room, with a small alcove at one end. The main part of the room held boxes that had once held supplies for passing changelings, a large table that doubled as both a dining surface and a map table, and a tiny kitchen. The alcove at its end held two sets of bunks set into the smooth rock walls, stacked three high, and at the back was a toilet and shower.

Without a thought, I reached out with my magic. The switch beside the door clicked loudly in the silent space, and to my surprise and relief, the lights flickered and struggled to life. I let out a shuddering sigh. A soft rattle sounded from the tiny vent at the back of the room, the stale air stirring as it mixed with the fresh air being drawn in.

While the outpost was coated with dust, it was intact. I simply stood there, marveling at it. That small part of my hive had survived. This one place that I had been so familiar with was still there, unchanged. With a little bit of sweeping, it would have been indistinguishable from my last visit, two hundred years ago.

Dusty eventually stepped up beside me. “Should we look around?”

I pulled myself away from my nostalgic thoughts and nodded. “Of course.”

As he checked over the stack of boxes, Starlight followed me to the table at the center of the room. There was a substantial amount of papers spread across it, with a box of neatly arranged writing implements set to the side. Some were maps, others were printed reports. My attention was immediately drawn to the small stack of papers near the center of the table. I gently slid them over with my magic, brushing away the dust.

The top paper was a printout of a simple grid of letters. I gave a soft huff of amusement, which caught Starlight’s attention.

“What’s that?”

“A vigeneigh cipher table,” I said, sliding the paper over to her. “One of the low-security methods used for—”

The page below was covered in writing that formed the familiar jumble of nonsense of a ciphertext. “...encoded messages.” I drew the paper over, scanning over the words.

“Like a code?” Starlight asked, peering at the new paper as well. “What’s it say?”

I gave a soft chuckle and smiled. “I may be good with cryptography, but not that good. I’ll have to take some time to decode it.”

“Oh,” Starlight said, her ears drawing back as if she had just said something very stupid. That lasted only about a second before perking forward again. “So how long will that take?”

“When it comes to cryptography, I’m afraid the key is patience. Complex ciphers can take a lot of work to decrypt.” I picked up the cipher table before her, setting it down with the encoded message. “But if it was left here, it was probably meant for any changeling from our hive to read. We’ll see.”

The next paper had only eight words written on it.

Siphon. Bulwark. Scatter. Umbra. Shale. Flitter. Cinder. Desire.

My throat had already tightened as I started to read, but as I reached the last one, it felt like a weight had dropped in my gut.

Starlight stepped in close beside me, her voice soft and concerned. “What is it?”

“They’re names.” I swallowed around the lump in my throat. “My sisters.”

Starlight’s ears drooped in sympathy.

Somewhere behind us, Sickle rumbled quietly.

“Desire was an Infiltrator, too,” I finally said. “We trained together. We were close.”

A thin, neat line crossed through her name, as well as Scatter’s and Umbra’s.

Starlight reached over my shoulder, giving me a comforting squeeze. I leaned into it for a moment before drawing in a deep breath and refocusing.

I returned to the stack of papers, but there was nothing more to find. All that remained were supply requests and the final reports destined for analysts in the hive, left undelivered for two centuries. I even recognized one of my own reports on strategic supplies shipped through Appleloosa in the week before the end, as well as records of what smuggling activity I had been able to track. I felt an unreasonable urge to take that report, to scour it for anything I might have missed, as if I might have somehow prevented what had happened.

I set it aside with the rest of the reports, to be ignored.

Dusty had finished searching through the supply boxes. Every single one had been emptied long ago and neatly stacked back in place.

As we sat and ate a late dinner, I started working to decrypt the message left so many years ago.

My suspicions turned out to be correct. The message used a simple cipher, one that would never be used for high-security traffic, but which served the purpose of quickly protecting a message from casual observation. Even without the key, I could have likely broken it in a few hours at most. But it really was intended for any changeling in our hive to read, and as such, it used a common and well-known key. It took only a couple minutes to transcribe the entire message to plaintext.

I sat back, reading the message as I held it, floating, before me. Then I read it again.

I was starting on a third read-through when Starlight finally spoke up. “What’s it say?”

I had to force myself to speak. “The changelings who came here all received substantial amounts of magical radiation,” I said. “The ones who survived headed north into Equestria.” I folded the paper, which crackled dryly. “They were looking for C.L.T. facilities.”

“What, any of them?” Starlight asked.

I tucked the folded paper into my saddlebags. “It seems that way. Maybe not all, but… it does appear to have been a widespread project.”

A hint of concern touched Starlight’s expression, as if sensing something was wrong. “That’s… good, right?”

I huffed out a short breath, and nodded. I even managed a weak smile. “Yes. It means there may still be some of my sisters out there, waiting.”

I settled in with my own as-yet untouched food.

Starlight finished eating well before I did. She sat awkwardly for almost a minute before speaking up again. “You keep using the word ‘sister’ a lot. How many sisters did you have?”

I shrugged weakly and spoke around a soggy bite of limp, canned hay. “Almost the whole hive.” When her eyes widened in surprise, I added, “The queen laid all our eggs. It’s just how changelings are. Even the few that weren’t laid by her were treated as sisters.”

Dusty had a questioning look, but remained silent. I suspect Starlight’s next question was the same on on his mind. “No brothers?”

“No,” I said. “We don’t really have any use for males.”

Dusty’s expression had turned skeptical, but he only managed a cautious “Um...” before I continued.

“That isn’t an expression of bigotry,” I said. “It’s biology. Ponies have only small differences between the sexes, but male changelings are very limited compared to females. Different biological castes. The only reason male changelings are even a thing is to ensure the queen can be fertilized.” I shrugged. “But seeing as female changelings can shapeshift to change sex, there isn’t any reason for a healthy hive to produce males.”

That just seemed to make Dusty even more uneasy. “So… what do you do with male, um… hatchlings?”

“Nymphs,” I corrected. “And we just don’t have any. Fertilized eggs are always female.”

Sickle cut in with a chuckle. “Oh, sure, and you all get bitchy whenever I start talking about sex.”

“I’m not talking about sex,” I said, casting a flat glare her way. “I’m talking about reproduction. Of all the ponies in the room, I would think you would be particularly clear on the distinction between the two.”

“Oh, ouch,” Sickle said, chuckling some more. “Whimper grew a bit of spine under that shell.” Then she stopped and blinked. “Wait, do bugs even have spines?”

I looked away from her, returning to the previous conversation. “Anyway, yes, pretty much any changeling in the hive could be considered my sister, even if it isn’t quite biologically true. It’s not quite like a pony family, but…” I trailed off, remaining silent for several seconds. They all waited patiently, until I spoke again. “But I guess it kind of is. At least, it was in my hive. We’d do anything for our sisters, even if we’d never met before.”

There were a few silent nods, and after a short moment of contemplation, I returned to my food.

We were about ready to settle in for the night when Starlight looked to the back of the alcove. “Do you think those showers work?”

I shrugged. “The outpost still has power, so maybe.” A thought struck me, and I frowned. “But the catchment hasn’t been cleaned or maintained in two hundred years. I doubt it’s safe to drink.”

“As long as it’s not radioactive, that should be just fine,” Starlight said as she walked over. “I don’t need a drink. I just want to feel clean for a change.”

She stood to the side, reaching out with her magic to turn the faucet handle. A deep, rattling groan sounded from somewhere below, and she quickly turned the handle back. “Well, that’s—”

“That’s normal,” I said, smiling at the knowledge that the outpost was largely functional. “This place wouldn’t get used for weeks at a time, and the water always drained from the pipes. You have to let it run for a bit.”

She nodded and turned the handle again. Again, the rattling groan started up, growing louder. Starlight jumped back when the first explosive sputter of water burst from the shower head, followed a second later by another, and rapidly grew into a steady spray marred by only the occasional hiccuping sputter. The water was murky and brown with the first few sprays, but was already lightening by the time the flow had stabilized.

As it ran clear, Starlight grinned, murmuring a quiet thanks to Luna and stripping off her belongings. She dove into the water, and let out a sharp gasp. “Damn that’s cold!” Despite that, she closed her eyes and plunged her head under the flowing water, grinning happily.

She opened her eyes to see an unusual luxury floating before her in my magic: one of the bottles of soap I had salvaged from Paradise Beach. She laughed and snatched it, and soon was lathering up. She arched her back and turned this way and that, practically dancing under the steady stream of water, her hooves splashing in the water that swirled around the floor drain.

The rest of us sat back, unable to help smiling at the simple pleasure and enthusiasm of something that had once been so mundane.

Starlight was halfway between panting and shivering when she finished, but grinned as wide as I had ever seen as she walked away from the shower, dripping wet and clean. As she fetched a towel to dry off, I took my own turn at the shower.

The water was icy cold, but it still felt amazingly good as it flowed over my carapace. I fetched an old, faded washcloth set beside the shower and scrubbed all over, removing the weeks of grime and oil and gunk that had remained even after multiple transformations. It felt liberating.

And I have to admit to a moment of narcissism as I admired the glossy luster of my shell, shining as the water flowed over me.

I was interrupted by a grind of metal on concrete, and looked back in alarm. Sickle was partly wedged into one of the lower bunks, her armor scraping and screeching against the top edge of the nook as she tried to force herself into a space that was far too small for her. “Oh, this is brahminshit!” she finally growled as she gave up, and then spent a couple seconds wrenching on the cot mounted within before it tore away with a crack of sheared-off bolts. She threw the frame to the ground and flopped down atop it.

I was tempted to object, but I let it go.

When I finally finished with my showering, I was met by Dusty, who smiled and inclined his head to the bottle of soap. “Mind if I use a little of that?”

I smiled back, floating it over. “Not at all.”

As he started to shower, I quickly toweled off. I shook out my wings, casting off the final drops of water, and lifted into the air. I floated up to hook my forelegs over the edge of the top bunk, hovering beside it; Starlight was already lying there, grooming her coat with an old brush.

I met her smile with my own, and spoke. “Hey, do you mind if I take this one?”

Her smile turned to curiosity. “Sure. Why?”

I suddenly felt very silly, my ears folding back. “Oh, uh… it’s just that every time I came here, I always slept in this bunk…”

She stared back blankly for a couple seconds, as my concern grew. Then a smirk crept across her face. Her shoulders shook in barely constrained laughter as she lifted a hoof to point at me. “Holy crap, that’s not fair. No! Creepy bug monsters shouldn’t look that cute and pitiable!”

I blinked in surprised and, I’ll admit, confusion. After a few moments of laughter, she finally controlled herself enough to speak again. “Yeah, you can have it,” she said between laughs.

She scooted to the side and slid out, a hoof holding onto the edge to neatly swing herself into the bunk below. I blinked again, and finally gave a chuckle of my own as I processed what had just happened. I floated up and dropped myself onto the cot, rolling over to my side.

Starlight’s hoof was still holding onto the edge of the alcove. Her laughter had stopped. A couple seconds later another hoof joined the first, and her head peeked up over the edge. “Hey, Whisper…”

“It’s okay,” I said, giving her a smile. “Even if I’m most certainly not ‘cute’.”

She chuckled, flashing a smile. The expression quickly faded away again. “That’s good, but… I mean, are you okay? With…” she glanced around, her eyes lingering on the table and its stack of papers before returning to me. “...all this?”

My smile withered away. After a moment, I nodded. “I’ll be fine.”

She hesitated, as if deciding what to make of my reply. Finally, she hauled herself up to sit beside me. Her eyes were full of worry. “You want to talk about it?” she asked, her voice gentle and full of caring.

I remained silent for several seconds, but slowly relaxed. “If you want,” I said, a faint smile returning. “I’m sure this whole expedition of ours is going to be an emotional rollercoaster for me, but… we’re doing something good. I think I’ll be just fine.”

She stared back into my eyes for several seconds before her concern slowly melted away, and she leaned comfortingly into my side, mirroring my own soft smile. We sat there, quiet and relaxed.

Eventually, she spoke again. “I never had much of a family. Never knew my dad, no brothers or sisters. It was just my mom and me.” She heaved out a sigh before continuing. “What were they like? The ones you were close to, like Desire.”

My throat threatened to tighten again. “Desire was… energetic. Active. Enthusiastic.” I found myself smiling again, just a little. “And very social and friendly. She liked people.”

Starlight gave a soft chuckle. “Sounds a little like me.”

“A little,” I said, nodding. “But she was a lot more… flirtatious.” I gave a chuckle of my own. “Which she cultivated into a fine skill set as an Infiltrator. She enjoyed her work, and I’m sure she left a long line of mares and stallions longing after her alter-egos.”

I told her about more of my sisters, but mostly about the rest of our small group, Infiltrators who had bonded during our time in training. There was Shadow, gentle and kind, and so quiet that you might mistake her for being shy, but always so clever, especially when it came to avoiding attention. There was Dagger, always bold and playful, yet probably the most aggressively calculating of us. And then there was Ripple, amazingly brilliant in many fields, but particularly in understanding how others thought; a natural manipulator.

The stories didn’t last long; we were both quite tired and relaxed by then. I was still smiling as I drifted off to sleep, with the warmth of Starlight’s body, and her friendly affection, right beside me on the slightly-too-small cot.

☢

We set out shortly after sunrise the next morning. I felt remarkably refreshed. I was clean, well-rested, and comfortably fed. Despite all that, I was troubled. The happy memories recalled the previous night made way for worry and doubt.

“I don’t know what we’ll find at the hive,” I said as we buckled on saddlebags and slung our weapons. “I don’t even know if… if there will be a hive left. The message mentioned magical radiation, and I know at least one balefire bomb was detonated in the Badlands. I saw the flash.”

That news had a chilling effect on Starlight and Dusty; if Sickle felt anything at the news, her reaction was hidden under her helm.

“Why?” Dusty asked. “Balefire was zebras, right? Why would they bomb a wasteland?”

“To kill the changelings who were helping Equestria, perhaps,” I said, darkly. “Or perhaps one queen wanted to remove a rival, and was able to acquire a megaspell through some scheme.”

“Well there’s a terrifying thought,” Starlight said. “Stealing a megaspell.”

I shrugged. “Why not? My hive did.”

She gawked at me.

“Or so the rumors went,” I said. “It’s quite likely we had something to do with Equestria getting information on zebra megaspells. We might have even been the reason they had balefire bombs to test. I don’t know for sure. Not my field.”

We traveled throughout the morning and early afternoon, winding our way through narrow canyons as we drew closer. With every step, the tension in my gut grew, as if chewing at my insides. Our progress was agonizingly slow in the rough terrain as our path twisted this way and that, and we were forced to climb over obstacles or navigate steep slopes. Several times, my wings buzzed anxiously, ready to draw me up into the sky, to cover the last miles in an aerial sprint, but my hooves felt as heavy as lead. The whole time we traveled, I remained silent, save for the most basic of directions.

A terrible sense of dread dug at the back of my mind as we ascended toward one more ridge. Part of me wanted to turn back and never return, but I couldn’t stop.

We climbed higher, and the shattered spires of rock that had stood on the barren slopes above my hive came into view. Many had fallen, and unfamiliar cracks ran through some of the cliffs, but the land above the hive, though battered, remained. Off to one side, the familiarity of the terrain abruptly ended. Just a mile from my hive, the rocky ridges had been torn away, ancient canyons opening abruptly into a deep crater that had been carved into the rugged terrain. Even in the daylight, wisps of green were faintly visible, flickering and rippling in the depths of the crater even after all these years.

The balefire bomb had detonated frighteningly close to my hive, but it had missed its mark. A mile away, and nestled deep below the rocky surface, my hive waited.

We pressed on with a renewed pace. The path to the main entrance was so broken, twisting, and narrow that it was easily overlooked, and wound through difficult terrain, intended to make any ground assault near impossible. A sheer wall of rock lined one side, while the opposite was a straight drop to the canyon floor, hundreds of feet below. Fallen rocks and crumbling cliff faces made the path even more difficult, forcing my companions to climb over or squeeze around several obstacles. Many sections were passed with me hovering anxiously beside the narrow path, offering a little more support for the rougher sections.

Starlight jerked when her PipBuck clicked, quickly snatching it up. A couple more clicks followed a few seconds later.

“What’s that?” Dusty asked, ears perking up alertly.

“Radiation,” she said, and let the PipBuck hang on its strap again. It let out another lonely click.

Dusty frowned, his expression tense. “How bad?”

“We’re fine,” she said, giving a playful smirk. “Unless you plan on camping out here for the next few months.

Finally, we reached a large split in the cliff face, looking like any of the hundreds of other gaps and crevices filling the landscape. The crack was wide with a relatively flat bottom as it led back into the cliff face. Unlike the other crevices, which ended after just tens of feet, this one snaked its way back, eventually turning into a tunnel that pierced deep into the stone. The brilliant sunlight quickly faded behind us, leaving us once again navigating by the light of Starlight’s PipBuck. The air was chilly, a sharp contrast from the Badlands outside.

The tunnel turned sharply to the side, then doubled back, before abruptly opening into a smooth-walled chamber. The ground simply ended, falling away in a pit that extended far beyond the weak light of the PipBuck, and about thirty feet across. Narrow metal-grate stairs were bolted to the walls, descending into the darkness in a steep spiral. The small lights that ran along them, normally casting off barely enough light to navigate by, lay dark.

We made our way down, the sound of hooves on metal echoing in the stillness. The powerful clanging of Sickle’s spiked shoes drowned out the groaning of metal caused by her passage, and the occasional click of Starlight’s PipBuck.

“How deep is this?” Starlight asked, a couple of minutes later.

“Four hundred feet,” I replied. “We should be most of the way there.”

Finally, we reached the bottom of the shaft. A single, wide tunnel led out, and as we stepped into it, Starlight’s light illuminated the giant steel-cog door.

“Huh,” Dusty said, a much more subdued reaction than Starlight’s.

“Holy shit,” she said. “That looks like a Stable door.”

“It should,” I said, smiling for the first time that day. “It was stolen from Stable-Tec themselves, with the theft disguised as war profiteering from a corrupt official. I wish I could claim credit for it. I did manage to re-route an entire shipment of concrete and rebar, and pin it on a smuggler who had just died in a firefight with the authorities.”

I stepped up to the blast door, reaching out to touch the metal surface. It was covered in a thick layer of dust. “We already lived underground. It wouldn’t take much to turn the hive into a fully functional Stable.” My hoof slid down, leaving a streak in the dust before settling on the ground again. “We were less than a year from completing the project.”

I turned away, moving to the access panel beside the door. I lifted the protective cover. Thankfully, the “ready” light lit up. Beside it, another blinked red, indicating that the door was operating on backup power only. I started pressing keys, typing in a long sequence of numbers. My hoof moved to the large red button at the side, hovered over it for a long moment, and with a deep, steadying breath, I pressed it.

An electric buzz hummed out from the wall, stretching on for several seconds. My stomach did a flip at the loud, mechanical thump that emanated from the door, and then, with a shriek of metal scraping against concrete that filled the cavern with a wall of sound, the great door ground its way open.

I glanced over to my companions. Sickle had bared her teeth, and pawed at the ground, the sound lost behind the scrape of the door. Starlight glanced my way, giving a cautious but reassuring smile.

Beyond the door, everything was dark. As it rolled open, the PipBuck’s light spilled across the entryway of the hive, with several overturned trolleys and crates lying scattered about. I caught quick glimpses of the security station, the door machinery, all the regular sights of the entryway. My attention, however, was immediately drawn to the hall beyond where, just at the edge of the light, movement drew my eye, and I froze. Stepping out from around the corner was the one thing I hadn’t dared to hope for: a changeling.

She stopped, head turned to stare at us, one pale eye reflecting the green light. To my sinking horror, I realized the other eye was nothing but a vacant pit. The changeling’s jaw hung askew, the entire plate of her cheek shattered and caved in. Her wings lifted, revealing the tattered ribbons that remained. Her carapace was dull and pitted.

The blast door thumped loudly as it came to rest, followed immediately by the walking husk’s clicking, rattling cry—and the dozens, hundreds of cries that answered it.

There was a shout. A hoof shoved against my chest. I stumbled and staggered back. My hind legs gave out, and I fell to my haunches.

Then the sound of gunfire tore through the air, echoing through the halls of my dead hive.

Chapter Seventeen: Goodbye

I’ve never been one for assigning intellect or personality to things that don’t have those qualities. Such things are simple lies to make the unknown seem less misunderstood. Similarly, “fate” is a simple way of pretending that all things happen for a reason; that there is no such thing as misfortune or chance, merely actors living out a play.

I’ve always found that level of self-deception to be incredibly unhealthy in the long-run, but I knew enough of psychology to understand its reasoning. People like order. They like things to happen for a reason, preferably an intelligently driven reason. While in reality an event might be an extremely long chain of independent events all contributing to a single outcome, to the point where it can be incredibly hard or impossible to declare one single action to have been the one responsible for the ultimate outcome, it can be much more comfortable to decide some complex event happens because of a single entity or force of nature deciding it will happen.

This becomes even more tempting when there are plainly existent entities who are actually capable of doing such things. The princesses Luna and Celestia were vastly powerful beings. Now they are revered as goddesses, and their influence is perceived—almost certainly incorrectly—in a great number of events. Ponies offer up pleas and prayers to these princesses-turned-goddesses, and expect events to be altered in their favor. There are even a number of spirits out there who exert various degrees of influence over the world. It is quite true that events could be influenced by these entities.

The problem comes when individuals start seeing all events as being under their influence. It’s a self-centered conceit, where individuals perceive themselves as somehow more important than the individual beside them, and therefore, what happens to them must also be more important. Realistically speaking, almost everything that happens is a natural result of the course of events, with no outside intelligence steering the results.

There is no such thing as fate.

But for a brief moment, I entertained the idea that some malevolent entity had set its intentions upon me.

It was just too much for me. I’d seen so many horrible things in such a brief span of time. My queen, a decayed and empty husk. The remains of my sisters, some still floating in the murk of their own decay. The vileness of raiders, mutilating, raping, and killing ponies that should have been their kin. Another pony, one who should be a benevolent leader, instead selling out the ponies he was responsible for to those same raiders, all for a few pieces of metal.

The whole way to my hive, I had tried to prepare myself for the worst. I had expected to either find a glowing crater where my hive had been, or a cold tomb for those who had died centuries ago.

I’d even learned of ghouls. I’d seen a pony ghoul just two days before. And yet, I had refused to consider the possibility that such a thing could happen to my own kind. I must have pushed it away, as a possibility too painful to consider. I allowed emotion to blind me to a threat, and left myself vulnerable as a result.

Then I had encountered them, face-to-face and impossible to deny. It was too much, so in my desperation and horror, I imagined that some foul intellect had decided I hadn’t suffered enough already. I imagined that it had animated the dead of my hive, all so I would have to face down the corpses of my own sisters as they tried to kill me.

All that was missing was a spoken accusation. “Why you?”

But it was all a lie.

There was no malevolent force determined to make me miserable. The world didn’t have it out for me. It wasn’t even unfair. It simply was. Complaining about my misfortune, or trying to seek out some imagined enemy, was pointless. I had to deal with the situation I found myself in, rather than imagine some completely different problem.

I’ll admit, all of this is considerably more clear-minded than I was at the time. I was on the verge of breaking down. Maybe I did. I’m not entirely clear on what happened. I remember being pushed back, and gunfire. The next clear memory was being held in Starlight’s forelegs, my face buried in the soft fuzz of her neck, her coat damp with my tears.

I pulled back, wiping at my eyes. Starlight stayed there, a hoof resting on my shoulder as I struggled to recover. I caught sight of Dusty and Sickle at the open blast door, though my gaze immediately dropped back to my own hooves. I couldn’t meet their eyes.

Starlight remained silent and supporting. In the background, I heard Dusty and Sickle exchange a few words. Sickle was spitting and griping about something, but I didn’t catch what. The first words I clearly remember were Dusty’s. “We should leave.”

“No,” I croaked, quickly wiping at my eyes again. “N-no. We came this far. We can’t… I can’t just leave now.”

Starlight wore an expression of concern, but she helped me stand. I wobbled, but managed to keep my hooves. If I had been a bit more clear-minded, I might have worried over how weak I felt, even with the supportive emotions flowing from Starlight.

The entrance to my hive was a scene of carnage. The choke-point formed by the blast door was perfectly tailored for Sickle’s abilities. She stood there, heaving deep breaths, over the shattered remains of a terrible number of long-dead changelings. They were piled three or four deep around the entrance, crushed and mangled by her hooves and blades, and blending into a single gray, jagged mass in the monotone light. The broken shells leaked murky fluids, which filled the air with a powerful stench of rot and decay. The smell dug up horrible memories of my first day in the Wasteland; a slight tremble passed through my legs before I could stop myself.

Sickle was practically drenched in the fluids, dripping from her muzzle and chest. She grimaced and spit again, though strangely, she went still and quiet when she saw me looking at her.

I approached the scene with trepidation, stepping past the scattered shell casings from Dusty’s rifle. He stepped in front of me, looking as concerned as Starlight did. “Whisper… there’s probably going to be more.”

I nodded, almost stumbling as I did so. I had to stop and steady myself, taking a deep breath; it met with mixed results, given the nauseating scent in the air. “...I know.”

“And if we go in there,” he continued, “we could get surrounded. If we’re attacked from multiple directions, we’ll need every gun.”

“I’ll be fine,” I said, though I’m sure it wasn’t a terribly convincing statement. “...It was a shock. Unexpected. Surprises are… more psychologically impacting. Now I… have time to mentally process and prepare.” I swallowed. “I’ll be fine.”

He frowned at me for several seconds before speaking again, and my ears drooped. “You’re not fine,” he said. “I get that this is important to you, so I’m willing to go in there, but you’re not in good shape. If I decide we’re leaving, then we leave, no arguing. We can always come back later. Got it?”

I nodded again. “Of course.”

“We’re also on limited supplies,” he said. “I spent a lot of ammo keeping the ferals—” I winced “—from piling onto Sickle and weighing her down with their numbers. I know it’s going to be hard, but we need you contributing to the fight.”

Sickle grunted quietly, but said nothing.

“I will,” I said. He continued to stare at me for a moment before nodding, though I could tell it was with a great deal of reluctance.

We entered the hive. I flew up and over the short wall of bodies, holding my breath as I went. I refused to watch as the others made their way across; their grunts and the crunching of broken exoskeletons was more than enough for me. I shuddered at the sound.

The bodies trailed off rapidly past the entrance, the few who had been gunned down before piling into the melee. There was plenty of room to walk around them in the wide hallway.

I tried to ignore the bodies and instead focus on the hive itself. Apart from a few new bullet holes, it seemed this part of it was in good condition. The concrete walls were cracked in a few places, leaving a bit of dust and debris scattered on the floor, but the damage was minor. The maintenance panels spaced regularly along the floor were still in place, and the lights built into the ceiling, while dark, were intact. Even the paint, a cool gray, was almost entirely intact, with only a little chipping and peeling.

Seeing the place lit only by the green light of the PipBuck screen gave it an eerie appearance. The subtle difference made the familiar space seem alien and sinister. It was wrong.

I shook off the feeling of unease, refocused on the task at hoof, and led us into the hive.

The hallway split, leading to different places. I took the hall that led deeper into the hive, which immediately led into a wide atrium, extending two stories both above and below our entrance. The open center stretched well outside of the PipBuck’s light, dark and cavernous. Balconies overlooked the open space, and above, massive arches of reinforced concrete crossed over the vaulted ceiling, the nearest two just barely within the light’s glow.

Beside me, Starlight let out a low whistle. “Wow. Except for being pitch black, this is a lot nicer than what I had pictured.”

I walked over to the edge of the balcony, hoofsteps echoing weakly across the empty space. “What were you expecting?”

In the corner of my vision, I could see her ears droop low. “I just… well, you know, the whole ‘bug’ thing, and you’re calling it a hive, so, I dunno, was thinking like bees or ants or...” She trailed off, scuffing a hoof against the floor. “Shit. Sorry.”

I looked down from the balcony. Below, the courtyard was cloaked in shadows. Green light glinted softly off the water below the still fountains. Once, it had been a common area, dotted with changelings relaxing and socializing. Now, the only signs of this were a few misshapen lumps lying scattered among the benches, tables, and open spaces, barely visible in the gloom.

I sighed. Then I blinked as Starlight’s words finally connected. “Huh? Oh, no. Some hives were like that.”

“Oh?” It’s surprising how desperately hopeful a single word could sound.

“Yes,” I said, looking back to her. “The Chrysalis hive was ancient, and many of the new hives kept that aesthetic. Tradition.” I gestured my muzzle out to the open space. “We were quite happy to distance ourselves from tradition. I suppose it was a mostly symbolic gesture, but… I guess sometimes that can be useful in itself.”

Dusty and Starlight walked up to the edge of the balcony, to look out over the courtyard. The PipBuck’s light spilled over the ground as she reached the edge, removing any uncertainty as to what the scattered shapes were.

On my other side, Sickle spat a couple more times, stopping when I looked her way.

It caught Dusty’s attention, too. “Is something wrong over there?”

Sickle snorted. “I had my mouth open when I squashed one of those fuckers. Now I can’t get the taste off my tongue.” She spat again, grimacing. “I hate fighting fucking ferals.”

Starlight muttered. “Gee, how horrible this must be for you.”

“Oh, get fucked, you little bitch,” Sickle said, baring her teeth before looking away from us.

I turned away from the edge to follow the balcony around the atrium, and after a moment, the others followed. It was an awkward silence that followed.

To my surprise, it was Sickle who spoke up first. “You know, you changelings are tougher than I thought. Couple of those ferals took blows that would have crushed a pony’s skull, and they just shook it off.”

Dusty and Starlight both groaned. “Sickle…”

“What?” she shot back. “I was giving a compliment!”

“You’re shit at giving compliments,” Dusty said, shaking his head.

“Yeah, well, I don’t do it very fucking often, now do I? Ass.”

The heavy mechanical door we needed to use was shut, forcing us to spend a minute as I opened the emergency access panel beside it, engaged the manual override, and cranked the door open.

As it started to open, another rattling cry echoed from the hallway beyond. I ignored it, focusing the entirety of my attention on the crank. I remained focused, even as a scramble of hooves struck the door, flailing through the small gap that had opened. Moments later the door was open enough for the dead changeling to squirm its way through the gap, only to be met by the carapace-shattering stomp of Sickle’s hooves. Something cold, wet, and sticky splashed against my hind leg.

I kept cranking, until the door stood open enough for us to easily pass through, and we continued on. I avoided looking down as I stepped over the shape on the floor.

The hallway led directly to the central hub, a series of high-vaulted chambers where the various residential areas met. On each floor, the connecting hallways opened into broad walkways that circled and crossed over the central open space, while huge support columns and arches reinforced the structure.

Most changelings in the hive would pass through the space each day, so it was designed to be as pleasant as possible. The entire space in the center was a multi-level park, combining a natural-stone underground aesthetic with a variety of surface plants. Water flowed from artificial springs, trickling and pouring down rock faces and along small streams to form crystal-clear pools. A soft, cool light filled the space, like an eternal twilight, perfectly balanced for a changeling’s natural eyes. Above, the roof of the chamber sloped steadily upward to a peak high above. And then there were the other changelings; always other changelings, coming and going, flying and walking, attending to business or relaxing on their time off.

Now that pleasant space lay dark, silent, and dead.

As the most heavily traveled place in the hive, it would have been foolish of me to expect it to be unoccupied. A changeling ghoul stood only thirty feet from us as we entered, and with an angry cry, threw itself at us.

Sickle caught its charge in her forehooves and smashed it to the ground with a sickening crunch. As more cries echoes through the grand chamber, we drew back to the connecting hallway; it reduced the angles we could be attacked from, but only just. It was a major path of traffic, and that meant it was built wide. Sickle stood in the middle, and we quickly arrayed on her flanks. Shadows danced as Starlight moved, casting the area into a confusing contrast of light and dark.

The first ghoul came hurtling at us through the air, flying on tattered wings that shouldn’t have supported it. An eye-searing flash of red tore out, and half of the ghoul vaporized in a cloud of embers, while the other half crashed to the ground. I quickly looked away as it tumbled to a stop, fairly certain I had seen parts thrown about from the motion. Several seconds later, two more ghouls came running down the walkway, rasping and hissing. Another flash of red sent one to the ground.

“That’s fucking bright!” Sickle snarled as she stopped the other ghoul with a double-hoof buck that sent the limp form flying into a supporting column.

I stood to the side, floating my rifle before me as I tried to control my trembling. The trickle of dead grew quickly, scrambling and stumbling over each other. By then, a dozen or more were coming down the walkway. The faces of my sisters twisted into grotesque snarls of rage as they bore down on me, fangs bared and eyes full of hatred. They lunged, and I squeezed the trigger.

My assault rifle chattered angrily, rattling in the grip of my magic as it spewed out bullets at a terrifying rate. The air filled with the head-pounding sound of gunfire in the tight space, the scene lit by the strobe of the muzzle flash.

I don’t know how much effect I had on the horde bearing down on us. I know the one I was looking at fell. Then the magazine ran empty. I got only a moment of horrified realization before one of the ghouls, one of my fallen sisters, plowed into me.

I staggered and almost fell from the jarring impact, my rifle clattering to the ground. A hoof slammed into my side, and suddenly I had a face-full of angry changeling, her dead eyes staring into mine as her mouth opened, broken fangs lunging at my face. Something tugged at the inside of me.

I might have screamed. I don’t know. I know for sure that I pushed a surge of magic into my horn and blasted it into her face. I was free. Flashes of blue tore through the air, and another ghoul I hadn’t seen fell beside me.

I stepped back, my rifle floating up in front of me. There were still ghouls everywhere. Sickle was roaring out, and nearby I saw Starlight firing away. I didn’t know where Dusty was, somewhere on the other side of Sickle. I wasn’t entirely sure what was happening. All I knew for sure was that none of the ghouls were attacking me at that precise moment. I focused, running step-by-step through the procedure Dusty had drilled me on just days earlier.

Magazine release. Remove magazine. Retrieve magazine. Insert firmly. Pull. Release. Aim. Squeeze.

My rifle roared again, and I swept the muzzle across the line of bodies trying to get at us. One lunged at me; I swung the rifle around, still firing, and put the last of the magazine into it. Another of my sisters fell at my hooves, dead for good.

I reloaded and fired again. There was no grace or control to my fire; I simply pointed in the direction of the crowd and held down the trigger until the magazine ran empty.

And then, I finished reloading and aimed to find there was nothing left to aim at.

It was only with the sudden stillness that I realized how fast my heart was pounding, or how hard I was panting. Starlight was panting as well, turning to give me a very concerned look, which turned to relief when I gave her a weary nod in reply. My head felt slightly funny when I moved it, as if a fog had descended on my thoughts.

A deep crunch made me wince as Sickle stomped down on a still-squirming ghoul. Then she looked back to me with a broad grin and a chuckle. Even past the buzzing in my ears, I could hear her rumbling voice clearly. “Hell yeah, Whisper. That’s how you do it. Fuck ‘em up.”

I winced and looked away.

Sickle let out a laugh. “Shit, maybe we should have brought that minigun. Just turn you loose on all of ‘em.”

I could barely hear Starlight’s reply between my own impaired hearing and her hushed tone. “Sickle, come on, lay off. This is her family.”

“No it ain’t,” Sickle shot back with a snort. “Her family died a long time ago.” She jammed a leg-blade into a corpse, cracking right through the shell. “These fuckers just look like them, that’s all. Ain’t like things are all what they look like when you bugs get involved, is it?”

The last part was said directly to me. I glanced her way, saw her smug smile behind that gore-drenched muzzle, and looked away again.

Starlight stepped up to my side, and I’m sure she cast Sickle a dirty look before speaking to me. “Whisper?”

I sighed, then shook my head. My voice came out a little shaky and off-tune in my ears. “Yeah. Changelings are well aware that... what something looks like and what something is are two very different things.” I cast a glance back to the scattered corpses. A shudder passed through me, but it faded away.

The closest corpse was contorted where she had fallen, her eyes relaxed and expressionless, her limbs twisted at awkward angles. Of all the signs of injury scattered across her ancient body, the only one that drew my attention was the jagged opening behind her shoulder, where a bullet had exited, tearing out a large hole from her carapace. I lifted a hoof, and tenderly placed it atop her head, brushing gently beside her horn. “...But we also know that a physical change doesn’t change who someone is, inside.”

Starlight’s hoof rested gently on my shoulder, comforting. Everyone was quiet, save for a rattle of metal as Sickle shrugged.

When I finally moved, it was sudden enough to make Starlight jerk in surprise. I simply crouched down, hooked a foreleg under my dead sister, and hefted her up. “Help me gather them,” I said as I dragged her toward the center of the loose cluster of bodies.

While Sickle went to work without a question, Starlight hesitated a moment before her horn lit up to carry another body over. She cast a concerned look my way, which I pretended not to notice. Instead, I spoke as if unprompted. “The magical radiation killed my sisters, and transformed their bodies into something monstrous. I won’t leave them like this.”

It took only a couple minutes to gather the bodies. We remained undisturbed; no more ghouls appeared.

When it was complete, everyone stood back from the mound. Starlight was just starting to say something, likely asking what was next, when my horn lit up. I pushed a good amount of magic out, and fire burst out around the bottom of the heap so abruptly that she jumped back. Green fire quickly crawled up over the bodies, turning them into a raging pyre.

Dusty and Starlight edged back, especially as the scent of burning meat and shell filled the air. Sickle remained sitting right next to me, staring silently into the flames.

“I’ll have to do this for the others,” I said, my voice quiet against the crackle of the flames.

“How many were there, in this hive?” Dusty asked, and I shook my head.

“Not all of them,” I said. “I’ll come back, when the future of my hive is certain, and make sure that all of my fallen sisters receive their final transformation. For now… I’ll at least give that freedom to those I come across.”

There were nods all around, even from Sickle.

The flames worked swiftly, light dancing across the chamber. Soon, the flames faded, guttered, and died away, leaving only a thick scattering of ash in their wake. The light of Starlight’s PipBuck seemed even weaker in the flame’s wake.

I stood. “We should move on.”

They followed me as we continued on, following the walkway the length of the central hub. Three times we paused by the still husk of a dead changeling who had died without being reanimated by the balefire’s magic. Each time, I bowed my head, lowering my horn close to them as I conjured more flames.

As we were walking away from the third, Starlight moved in close beside me. “How’s your magic doing? Do you have enough to keep that up?”

“I’ll manage,” I said, and gave her a weak smile that quickly faded away again. “Don’t worry. I have an important mission for the hive. I won’t endanger that.”

She nodded, though judging by her frown, she wasn’t entirely comforted by the answer.

The multiple levels of walkways closed in, arcing down to merge into a single path that entered a wide tunnel. Every now and then, another small group of ghouls came running at us, two or three at a time. Sickle and Starlight dispatched them with ease, letting Dusty and myself conserve our ammunition. The largest group came near the end of the tunnel, as the echoes of Starlight’s Lancer brought the attention of the ghouls gathered beyond. Again, the small trickle turned into a sudden flood of dead changelings. As the body of the group close in, I once again fired off a magazine in one long burst, reloaded, and fired again. The powerful crack of Dusty’s rifle and the brilliant red and blue flashes of Starlight’s weapons filled the air, as we formed a killing line. It was as if it had become routine already as the horde melted before us, especially once Sickle met the charge. I’m not sure how many I accounted for. Only a few were still standing after my second magazine, and Sickle easily dispatched them.

I finished reloading, and as I placed the empty magazine back into my pouch, I took inventory. The results were less than ideal. “I’m almost out of ammunition.”

“No shit, with how you’ve been shooting,” Dusty said, frowning across the carnage at me. “How many mags you got left?”

I glanced down to my pouch, then back to him. My ears were already hanging low. “One.”

He stared at me for an uncomfortable couple of seconds before speaking again. “I do hope you mean one spare magazine, in addition to the one in your weapon.”

“Oh! Yes.”

He nodded slowly. “Okay. You know how your rifle’s selector switch has a semi-automatic position?”

I nodded.

“Use it.”

Rather than replying, I twisted the small switch, letting the soft click answer for me.

Sickle snorted, already gathering the bodies up. “Shit, and here I was liking the whole changeling-berserker thing. Whisper’s more fun on full-auto.”

“Well Whisper is almost out of ammo. If she wants to do the whole full-auto thing, she needs to start carrying a lot more ammo.” He cast a glance my way. “Or better yet, learn to spend the ammo you do have better.”

“I’m not a good shot,” I meekly replied, occupying myself with the task of gathering the dead together.

“Volume of fire is a poor substitute for accuracy of aim,” Dusty said. “It’s certainly got its uses, but you need to learn control first. I can teach you how to shoot when we’re done here. Maybe even teach you a bit about being a proper soldier.”

“I…” I don’t need that, is what I intended to say. I was an Infiltrator. My tools were guile, deception, and stealth. I wasn’t a combatant.

But the last few weeks had put the lie to that idea. How many firefights had I gotten in? The same tools that had served me before were still my greatest strength, but things had changed. Appropriately, I had to change with them.

“...I think I’ll have to take you up on that.”

He nodded, satisfied.

With another pyre quickly burning down behind us, we stepped out into the next chamber. It towered as high as the previous chamber, but it wasn’t the wide-open space that one had been. A massive structure stood before us. In the dim light, we could only just make out the closest parts of it, including a couple of the great supporting arches that crossed above us between it and the outer wall. To either side of us, a plaza stretched out into the darkness, just a couple of feet lower than the walkway and dotted with more benches and pools. The broad walkway itself continued straight on, to a set of great doors, standing wide open.

“Wow,” Starlight murmured. Then, a little more clearly, she added, “Your hive keeps getting more and more impressive.”

“This is the Spire,” I said. “This is where the queen lives and rules, and below it are where the changelings who help run the hive work. Down there is where we’ll find the servers.”

The Spire loomed above us as we approached and entered through the main doors. Just inside, I started to turn to a side door, one which led into the back ways through the structure, but I halted myself. Instead, I turned back to the second set of main doors.

I was about to open the doors when my ears were assaulted with the near-simultaneous sound of Starlight’s yelp, a rattling hiss, and the near-deafening crack of the Lancer firing in an enclosed space, nearly blinding me with the red flash. I jerked to the side just as a black form crashed to the ground, and several more flashes of blue lit the chamber like a strobe light, ending when the dead changeling lit up blue, burning away under the Repeaters assault.

Starlight was already staggering back, her Repeater sweeping drunkenly through the air above her as she babbled loudly. “Holy shit! What the shitting fuck shit? I-it was crawling down the wall. The fucking wall!” She panted hard as she spun, sweeping her Repeater around again.

“Oh,” I said, trying to calm my own breathing. “Yeah.”

“What do you mean, ‘yeah’?” she snapped, stumbling around as she spun around again, searching the ceiling above us; the space was high enough that the rapidly bouncing light of her PipBuck left many dancing shadows above us as the blue embers died off. “It was just crawling down the wall at us! That was the creepiest thing I’ve ever seen!”

“Calm down,” Dusty said, while Sickle snorted something more derisive.

“It’s okay,” I said. “Changelings can do that.”

“What?” She glanced my way several times, torn between searching the darkness above and looking at me. “What do you mean changelings can do that? You don’t. Why don’t you?”

My cloak shifted back as I spread my wings, giving them a single flick. “Because I can fly?”

Her gaze stopped on me, blinking. “...Oh.” She looked back up, then slowly lowered her Repeater. Finally, she let out a shaky sigh before turning to me. “You think you could have shared that little bit of information before now? You know, before I nearly pissed myself because some creepy wall-crawling bug-zombie is trying to nibble on my ears?”

She immediately stopped, placing a hoof over the bridge of her nose as she groaned, her ears laid back. “Sorry,” she said; I assume I had made some obvious reaction to her description of my deceased hive-mate. “Sorry, just… that scared the shit out of me.”

“Pussy,” Sickle muttered.

Starlight responded by lashing out with a forehoof, connecting solidly with Sickle’s shoulder in a loud clop of hoof on metal. The armored mare barely budged with the blow, and followed it up with a quiet huff of amusement.

“It’s okay,” I said, swallowing uncomfortably. “And I didn’t mention it because, honestly, it just didn’t seem important.”

“Not… not important?” She let the question linger a moment before adding. “You didn’t think it might be important, like, tactically or whatever, that these things can walk on walls?”

“...They can fly.”

After a couple sputtered attempts to come up with a reply, Starlight finally sighed and sagged, a hoof returning to her face. “Fuck. My head hurts now.”

Dusty stepped in. “It still could have been useful information, but there’s no point in dwelling on it now. Let’s move on. And Whisper, if you can think of anything else unusual about you guys, let us know, okay?”

“I can’t think of anything,” I said. “But yeah, we should move on.”

I pushed on the door, and it opened a couple of inches before thumping against something and stopping. I pushed a bit more, but it refused to budge. I placed both forehooves against it and shoved, feeling it shift another inch before stopping again.

Defeated, I stepped away and looked back to Sickle. She was staring down at me, with her head inclined slightly to the side as if to say, “Really?”

I gave an awkward smile. “Do you think you could get it open?”

She responded with a short huff, then stepped past me. A crash of metal-on-metal filled the chamber as she slammed her shoulder against the door, jarring it a couple feet further open, then pushed. Her spiked shoes scraped against the floor in a way that sent a shiver through my shell, but the sounds of clattering and grinding from the far side of the door soon rose over it as she forced the doors open.

One final shove threw the door most of the way open. Most of the room beyond was in shadow, with Sickle blocking most of the light, but I could already see dozens of bodies lying just past the doors, as well as the broken remains of a couple of benches. A good number of both had been set against the doors to keep them shut.

Sickle stepped in, and I quickly followed. The room was mostly dark until Starlight passed the doors as well, her light spilling out across the room. I saw the dozens of desiccated corpses lying around us, some still clad in armor, but my attention was immediately drawn by a flash of green. I jerked, then froze, my eyes wide.

The flash of light had been the PipBuck’s light reflecting off a facet of a giant crystal at the center of the room, standing taller than even Sickle. One face of it was badly cracked, with a few shards scattered around the floor. The floor itself was cracked and crushed in where it had fallen, forming a small and shallow crater.

A rasping, clicking cry made me jerk back; one of the bodies near that crystal was a “living” ghoul, but my sudden sense of panic faded immediately. Her body ended with the crushed remains of what had been her hips. One foreleg lay twisted and shattered, the hoof missing entirely, while the other scraped at the floor, dragging her towards us a few inches at a time. Her face, lined with cracks, was twisted into an expression of rage, but I could only feel pity for her, crippled and trapped in this place for centuries.

Sickle crushed her head under hoof, the good leg spasming and scraping against the floor a few more times before going still.

I shuddered, turning my attention back to the giant crystal. While Sickle started gathering up the bodies, I simply stared.

I jerked when Starlight brushed up against me, then let out another deep sigh as I slowly relaxed again. She spoke quietly, though still clearly audible in the quiet room. “What is it?”

“A love crystal,” I said, voice almost choking. “We called it the Heart. As in, the Heart of the Hive. It hung here in the throne room, and… and it was always kept full of love, glowing with the energy inside it. It… it’s never been dark.”

She nodded silently. It was a few seconds before she asked, “Throne room?”

I lifted my snout, gesturing behind the crystal. She leaned to the side, shifting her PipBuck to light up the simple throne at the back of the room. The giant tapestries that hung behind it on either side remained surprisingly intact after all this time.

I turned away, moving to help gather the bodies of my fallen hive-mates.

They were dry, empty husks, rather than the crude semblance of living that the ghouls had been. As I bent over the first one, clad in the armor of a soldier, I saw the injury that had killed them; a single neat hole, almost hidden below the front edge of the helm, and right between the eyes. A pistol lay on the ground before her.

I slowly reached up, tenderly running a hoof along the side of her helm. Sickle grunted as she tossed a pair of husks onto the growing pile, and I could see both of them bore similar injuries. So did the others whose faces I could see. I turned back to the body I stood over. “They killed themselves.”

Dusty paused in dragging a body over. “The radiation would have been deadly, if it was strong enough to be turning them into ghouls.”

“Radiation poisoning is a nasty way to go,” Starlight said. “This way… well, at least it would be quick and painless.”

I slowly nodded. I could appreciate the reasoning, at least. I drew my hoof back, ready to drag the dead soldier to join the others, but I hesitated. Slowly, my hoof returned to the side of her head. I sat, another hoof joining the first, and as gently as I could, I lifted her head and slid off the helm.

Sitting back, I held the helmet before me, staring at its midnight-blue surface.

Starlight was watching me, curiously. “Whisper?”

I huffed out a slow breath, turned the helm around, and slid it on. My horn and ears slid neatly through the gaps designed for them, and the helm came to rest flush against my carapace, as if it had been made just for me.

I removed the rest of her armor, then shed my cloak and bags to don them myself. I slipped each piece on, slipping my wings through the gaps intended for them, and carefully tightened the straps until the segmented assembly fit snug and secure. Once it was all in place, it covered my body from chest to flank, leaving only the underside of my belly unprotected. A set of hoof-boots completed the set, covering the sides of my hooves while leaving the bottom exposed for grip.

With the last piece in place, I stood. The armor was surprisingly lightweight, and even more surprisingly, it didn’t restrict my movements. I wasn’t sure how much protection it might offer, given the light weight, but it had to be better than nothing.

Starlight was nodding when I had finished turning around to test the flexibility. “It looks good on you.”

“Thanks,” I said, though my feelings were a bit more mixed. I have to admit, the contrast of the dark blue on black was aesthetically pleasing. It was the significance of what it symbolized that concerned me. An Infiltrator shouldn’t need armor.

A hollow thump interrupted my thoughts, followed a moment later by Sickle’s voice. “That’s the last of ‘em.”

I looked down to the dead soldier at my hooves. Sighing, I hooked a hoof under her chest, dragging it to join the dozens of others nearby. I leaned her back against the heap, as if she were sitting. Then I stepped back, calling up my magic. Green flames erupted from the pile, rapidly consuming the dry husks.

I stared into the flames for several seconds before a loud crash of metal suddenly grabbed my full attention. The cold shock of adrenaline surged through my body as I bared my teeth and spun around, shouting in a loud snarl. “Get off of that!”

Sickle was sprawled out across the throne in her typically lewd fashion, her head held at an odd angle as she looked back at me in what I assume was surprise.

I took a step forward, wings flicking in agitation as I growled at her. “Get off! That is not yours! It was Ephema’s, and I’m not going to allow anyone but the next queen to sit there! Get off!”

As I huffed and growled, heart pounding, Sickle stared back at me. She gave an amused huff, the corners of her mouth starting to rise, but her expression froze, and slowly, they lowered again. After a couple of seconds, she nodded. “‘Kay.”

With that, she casually slid off and walked away.

A deep shudder passed through me as I fell back to my haunches, heaving deep breaths to calm myself. My legs trembled. To my side, I caught Starlight’s wide-eyed expression, as she silently mouthed, “Wow.”

I lowered my head to my hooves, eyes closed as I calmed down, letting the adrenaline burn away.

The pyre was almost burnt out by the time I stood again. Starlight was sitting nearby, looking awkward. Dusty was picking through the abandoned weapons, a couple of magical energy rifles poking out from under the flap of his saddlebags. Across the room, Sickle stood in the shadows, leaning against a wall.

I took my time recovering my equipment, strapping on bags, slinging my rifle, and donning my cloak once more. By the time I had finished, the last of the jitteriness had passed.

“Okay,” I said, drawing everypony’s attention. “Time to move on.”

I started to move to the back of the room and the doors there, but hesitated at the giant crystal. I stared at the Heart, dark and empty. Only a moment of consideration passed before I lowered my head, touching the tip of my horn to the crystal, and called up my magic. It was only a tiny amount, but it was enough to bring out a gentle glow from the depths of the crystal.

I caught Starlight’s questioning look when I stepped back. “I couldn’t just leave it dark like that.”

She gave a little nod.

I led us to one of the doors in the back of the throne room. Like the main doors, most of them were barricaded with the remains of chairs and benches. Dusty’s attention was immediately drawn to the center door, which did not.

“Why did they barricade these, but not that one?”

“That leads to the queen’s chambers,” I said, as I helped Starlight carry away one of the benches. “There’s no other entrance.”

“So they were keeping it safe?”

“I assume so.”

He nodded. “Did you want to check it out?”

I froze, almost dropping my end of the bench. Yes. “No.”

We finished removing the crude barricade and passed through, entering an access hall that led into the depths of the hive’s administration center.

As we walked down the hall, Sickle stepped up beside me. I resisted the urge to shrink away, especially when her head turned to stare at me. “So. Armor, huh?”

“Yes,” I said in a perfectly neutral tone.

She nodded. Then her hoof lifted and struck my side, giving a powerful shove. I slammed into the wall, my head cracking against the stone. The impact knocked my breath out, and I staggered for a couple steps before regaining my balance.

Starlight shouted, but Sickle ignored her. She continued to stare at me, her expression impossible to read behind that helmet of hers. “It any good?”

I glared up at her. “Yes,” I said, with a clear edge to my voice. Despite getting the wind knocked out of me, my unexpected encounter with the wall hadn’t actually hurt.

Sickle bared her teeth in a grin. “Good,” she said, and turned to look ahead of her again. I continued to glare for several seconds as we continued on.

You’d think being able to feel certain emotions might make it easier to understand ponies, but the fact that she had held some small level of positive feeling for me throughout the encounter just made things more confusing.

Fortunately, there were no more unexpected armor-checks along the way. We made it to the main stairway and headed down. We encountered only a single ghoul along the way, apparently trapped in the stairway.

Five levels down, I led us out. The halls there were much less impressive than the large public spaces from before, but they were still of comfortable size and cleanly cut into the rock. It had also apparently been abandoned. There were no bodies, reanimated or not.

Finally, we reached the doorway I was looking for. I stopped before it, huffing out a short sigh, and whispered quietly to myself. “Please, let things be simple, just this once.”

Dusty shot me a questioning look, but I just shook my head, pushed open the door, and stepped through.

As Starlight’s light flowed over the room, my ears and wings drooped at my side.

Past the technician stations, a broad window looked in on the server room, and the mangled lumps of metal and gemstones within.

Dusty muttered a curse under his breath, while Starlight trotted up to the window, lifting her PipBuck as she peered around the server room. “It’s all trashed. What happened? Ferals don’t normally care about property damage.”

“Security protocols,” I said, sitting down heavily to lean back against one of the technician’s desks. “The servers’ databanks get wiped, matrix disruption grenades are used to wipe any remaining information and collapse the spell matrices, and thermite charges destroy the hardware. Information security, in case the hive is lost. I’d hoped they hadn’t decided to do this.”

Dusty cursed again. “So we get nothing.”

“Not here,” I said, leaning my head back to thump against the desk. I repeated that a few times before grunting and forcing myself back to my hooves. “But not all information is digital, or stored on the servers. We should go to the command center.”

“Where’s that?” he asked.

“Four levels up,” I replied. “But first…”

I turned to the technician’s stations and started searching around. The results were swift and bountiful. Within a couple minutes, I had acquired an extensive toolkit for computer and electronic work, a smaller, more portable kit, various cables, six datastores, including one labeled “software toolkit”, and a pair of portable terminals that put my much larger one to shame. In the process of gathering them up, I also noticed that the “emergency destructive devices” locker still had contents, and we gathered them up, as well; four matrix disruption grenades and a pair of thermite charges. I had no idea if they’d ever be useful, but I took them all the same.

Once those were all tucked away, we headed up.

The command center occupied the entire level it was on. The two stairwells connected to the ends of a single hallway, and in the middle of that hallway was the entrance to the command center, flanked by fortified security positions. As expected, the door was locked.

This posed a problem, as there was no way Sickle was bucking that door down. It was a heavy blast door, a foot thick. On top of that, the locks were electronically powered, and required a constant supply of power to remain unlocked.

As soon as she heard that, Starlight went to work. After knocking around on the frame of the door, she brought out her cutter. We all retreated around the corner, waiting in the darkness as the sharp, powerful light flashed and danced.

Her first, exploratory cut opened just enough of the doorframe to peer inside the machinery and wiring there, and gave her a better idea where to cut. The second cut, lasting for a couple minutes, opened a foot-tall hole. Then it was a matter of digging at the internals and trying to get them to work.

It was a good half hour of work before she hooked up a spark battery to a couple of cables, and with a muffled buzz, the machinery spun to life.

“Come on, come on,” she muttered to herself, eying up inside the hole she had made. I could just make out the edge of some cylinder drawing away from the door. Then, with a loud thump, the cylinder stopped, and the door lurched. “Yes! Open it!”

Sickle stepped forward and shoved. Some mechanism squealed and ground in protest as the foot-thick door slowly swung open. Starlight removed the spark battery, the machinery producing a final thump as the buzz ceased, and repacked her tools.

The door thumped heavily against its stops, and with a sudden shriek, an armored ghoul dropped onto Sickle’s back.

Both Starlight and Dusty’s weapons snapped up, but neither fired as Sickle spun around. The ghoul flailed and bit uselessly at her armored back, until one spin sent it off-balance and it lost its grip. Sickle lashed out with both hind legs, smashing the ghoul against the open door with a sickening crunch.

More ghouls came, and Sickle charged forward to meet them. We followed behind her, stepping through the doorway and into the entry gallery. Blue lines cut through the air, taking down one of the three ghouls rushing towards us, while Sickle met their charge with her own, smashing both of them against the low wall of the gallery. Their struggles ended moments later.

We scanned around, weapons sweeping over the room. The entry gallery overlooked the central operations room, a large space with dozens of desks with terminals, all facing the trio of large projector screens. To the sides, hallways on both the main room’s level and our own led out to specialized offices, with chipped and faded lines of color leading the way to different sections. While I could see several bodies, there were no more ghouls.

Sickle took a step, wobbled, and toppled over on her side.

There was an assortment of startled replies as we rushed over to her side, but she was already getting back on her hooves.

Dusty was the closest to her head, though he gave the sharp horn a wide berth. “You okay, there?”

“I’m fine,” she muttered. “I just tripped.”

“Uh-huh,” Dusty replied, frowning.

“Fuck off,” she replied, a little louder. “I got ghoul gunk everywhere. It’s slippery. Ass.”

Dusty frowned, but didn’t press the matter.

With that more or less settled for the moment, I turned to the emergency supply cabinet beside the door. To my surprise, it was open and empty, except for some filter cases and spare batteries.

I turned back to the first changeling ghoul, clad in the same kind of armor I had just acquired. Sure enough, she wore a respirator mask, one of the supplies missing from the cabinet. She also wore a bandolier of pouches, carrying replacement spark packs for a magical energy weapon that was nowhere to be seen. Hanging from that bandolier was the item I had originally hoped to find in the cabinet: a flashlight.

I unclipped it, then turned and held it out to Dusty. “There’s a blue line on the wall in the hallway to our right. You and Sickle follow it. It’ll lead you to the computer security department, and the backup server. I expect they’ll have destroyed it as well, but it’s worth a check.”

Dusty accepted the flashlight with a nod.

“Starlight and I will be down in the pit,” I said, inclining my head toward the main chamber.

We parted ways, and I headed down the ramp to the main floor of the room. I headed straight to the rear-most desk, elevated to look over the stations in front of it. I figured, if there was important information to be found, Ops Lead was the place to start.

All the desks were covered with various folders and papers, as well as a thick layer of dust. Another body lay behind the desk. A respirator mask was strapped to her face, connected by a short hose to a bottle hung around her neck. Even past the centuries of decay, I could recognize Vigilance. This was—had been—her domain.

I tore my view away from her, throat tightening a bit. We hadn’t been close, or even spoken much, but this was a face I recognized. Instead, I turned to her desk. I pressed the power button on her terminal, just in case, and when it produced no result, looked to the papers lying on the desk.

“You need that on?” Starlight asked, already prying at the back panel of the terminal with a hoof.

“It would help,” I said. “Can you do that?”

She chuckled, floating out her compact electronics kit. “Oh yeah. I’ve done this a lot. It’s surprising how much stuff is tucked away behind terminal-operated locks. Powering stuff up is a useful skill for scavengers.” The back panel came off with a soft pop, and she got to work. “And you guys even use the same Stable-Tec terminals everyone else uses.”

She retrieved a spark battery from her bags, and after half a minute of tweaking and rewiring, leaned over the computer and stabbed a hoof at the power button. The terminal hummed and chirped as it sprang to life, the screen flickering awake with a soft green glow.

A few seconds later, it finished booting up, and the screen displayed a login prompt.

It was my turn to get to work. I retrieved one of the new, smaller portable terminals and turned it on. It sprang to life without complaint. To my satisfaction, I found that it had all the software tools I would need, and quite a few my older terminal had lacked. A few moments of digging produced the right debug cable from my bags. I plugged it into the exposed port inside the open back panel and rebooted Vigilance’s terminal.

This time, text representations of all the spell processes scrolled down the screen of the portable terminal. It was trivially easy to halt the spell matrix at the right point and convince it that, yes, I had entered a correct login.

There was very limited information stored locally. I started skimming through entries, which were mostly scheduling, along with a few back-and-forth messages about a game night. Starlight sat next to me, reading the messages that popped up.

Then I found a message log. It only held fifteen messages, but from the header, I could see they were all priority messages sent from the Ops Lead to Queen Ephema and her assistants during the final day of the hive’s life.

We read the entries together.

0832 — INFOP reports asset Manehattan 3138 has gone off-task for a priority investigation of Four Stars central offices. Multiple work teams dispatched without announced work orders. Site on elevated security, with activation of lethal measures. Zebra contacts in Four Stars may be higher placed than initially believed. Asset Manehattan 1284 reports elevated MoM traffic and arrival of Steel Ranger detachment; believes MoM is preparing a major raid. INFOP prioritizing infiltration of Four Stars to investigate possible mid- to high-level threat.

0955 — NIGHTFALL — INFOP reports asset Canterlot 6916 has discovered a Four Stars work skywagon parked near the castle. Presence in Canterlot is unexplained. Vehicle abandoned, no occupants or cargo. Possible Zebra ties concerning. Asset Canterlot 6916 tasked with immediate investigation—BROKEN MASK. INFOP declaring all further Four Stars traffic as NIGHTFALL.

“What does any of that mean?” Starlight asked. “The, um… ‘INFOP’ and the like.”

“INFOP is Infiltration Operations,” I said. “Basically, my boss’s boss. They’re in charge of all espionage operations. ‘Broken Mask’ means that task is top priority, and is to be pursued as aggressively as possible, even if that means the Infiltrator has to burn an alias or expose themselves. And ‘Nightfall’... that’s bad. It’s one of the reporting keywords to indicate the severity of the message contents.”

I glanced at the next entry, and hesitated before adding, “In fact, there’s only one keyword that’s more severe.”

1101 — ECLIPSE — SIGINT reports abrupt increase in communications traffic in Zebra strategic defense network; decryption pending. Possibility of lead-up to large-scale offensive actions.
ECLIPSE—ECLIPSE—ECLIPSE

1113 — ECLIPSE — SIGINT reports traffic indicating full activation of Zebra strategic assets. OPLEAD suggests enacting COCOON protocol.

1116 — ECLIPSE — INFOP reports inability to contact Zebra assets. No contacts made in past four hours. All assets presumed lost or ineffective. Assume large-scale strategic/megaspell attack imminent. Requests permission to declare BREAKOUT for all assets globally.

“And what does—”

“‘Breakout’ was the command I got on the day the megaspells hit,” I said, suppressing a shiver. “Drop everything and run away as fast as you can. It usually means the MoM is about to bust down your door, not...”

Starlight slowly nodded. “And ‘cocoon’?”

“That one’s new to me.”

1118 — ECLIPSE — Staging begun for COCOON protocol. Recommend Queen departs immediately for COCOON site 4. BREAKOUT command issued to all Infiltrators. Further instructions added when possible to comply with COCOON.

1122 — ECLIPSE — OPLEAD acknowledges, wishes best speed to Queen. Command is remaining in-place to continue operations. Will continue to update on situation.

1135 — ECLIPSE — All section leads reporting large-scale conventional missile attack on Canterlot. City-wide shield is holding against attack. Local Army mobilized to evacuate nearby civilian population.

1200 — ECLIPSE — Unconfirmed report of megaspell detonation, vicinity Cloudsdale.

1202 — ECLIPSE — SIGINT intercepted Equestrian PINNACLE - SPELLFLASH traffic confirming megaspell detonation in Cloudsdale.

1213 — ECLIPSE — Further megaspell detonations confirmed in Manehattan, Fillydelphia, and Maripony. More unconfirmed reports coming in. SIGINT reports zebra strategic communications are significantly degraded, but indicate retaliatory megaspell strikes.

1215 — ECLIPSE — Unknown megaspell event reported inside Canterlot shield. Shield holding.

1221 — ECLIPSE — Current count, eighty three megaspell detonations confirmed, more underway. SIGINT reports complete breakdown of both Equestrian and Zebra strategic communications.

1225 — ECLIPSE — Hive under attack. Megaspell detonation in close proximity. Hive intact. Damage assessment underway.

1238 — ECLIPSE — Balefire ingested by ventilation systems. Radiation levels rising to rapidly lethal levels throughout the hive. Oxygen levels critical. Declaring the hive lost. Enacting information security protocols and lockdown. Evacuation underway. Command remaining in-place to coordinate while secondary air supplies hold out. To anyling receiving this message: the hive lives on in you. Good luck.

I didn’t realize I was trembling until Starlight’s foreleg closed around my shoulders. I gave a weak, shuddering sigh, leaned my head gently against hers, and closed my eyes.

Hoofsteps drew closer, echoing strangely in the irregular room before halting a short distance away. “You found something,” Dusty said. It wasn’t a question.

I took a deep breath, slowly sitting more upright as I opened my eyes, looking to him. He stood a short distance away, the flashlight in his mouth pointed at the ground. Behind him, Sickle was already moving to gather the bodies.

“Messages,” I said, and weakly motioned a hoof at the terminal. “Sent while the hive was dying.”

“And that ‘cocoon’ stuff,” Starlight said, giving me a gentle squeeze. “That could be good. If that place you woke up was the fourth cocoon site, that means there’s at least three more places where some changelings might have survived. Maybe more.”

“Maybe less,” I said, looking down at my hooves. “It was common practice with sensitive data to start numbering at something other than one.”

“Anyway,” Dusty said, “you were right. We found the server you told us about, but it’s toast. What else should we look for?”

I looked up again, eyes glancing over the various desks. “...Anything referencing something called the ‘cocoon protocol’. It seems likely that’s the name for what the hive was doing with C.L.T..”

He went to one of the desks and started leafing through the papers. Starlight looked to me, worry in her eyes, but giving a soft smile. I managed to return it, and after giving me another squeeze, she moved to another desk to do the same. I remained sitting there for a couple more seconds before forcing myself to stand. Another flashlight lay beside Vigilance. I retrieved it, suppressing another tremble, and set into another desk worth of papers.

Sickle grunted as she dropped another couple of bodies in the growing pile. She was panting just a little as she turned my way. “Shit. You’ve got one huge fucking family, you know that?”

Off to my side, Starlight was glaring daggers at her. As for myself, I wavered on exactly how to reply to that. Eventually, I sighed, and quietly murmured, “It’s a lot smaller, now.”

Sickle gave a single chuckle before going silent again. After a moment, she turned and resumed gathering bodies.

I wasn’t surprised when our search turned up no more references to Cocoon. Information security was a serious concern, even in the hive itself.

The dead were all gathered by the time we had finished, with Sickle sitting back against the wall beside the pile. My throat tightened as I looked over them. There must have been forty or fifty changelings there. Vigilance lay along the side of the heap, her body twisted at an unnatural angle.

Dusty finished removing another respirator mask from one of the dead, adding it to the three he had already acquired. Another flashlight was given to Sickle, who dismissively tossed it into her bags. Then it was time for me to do my thing.

I focused my magic, and soon another funeral pyre was roaring, the green flames burning away the dead.

I silently led the way out, my pace lethargic. We were leaving the command center when Starlight spoke up. Her voice was quiet and surprisingly timid. “Whisper?”

I looked back over my shoulder. Her ears hung low as she tried to speak, starting and stopping several times before quietly asking, “What did you say the symptoms of, um… over-feeding were?”

My gaze fell to the floor again. “Fatigue. Headaches, dizziness, or disorientation. Magical exhaustion. Emotional suppression.”

“Yeah,” she said, slowly nodding. “Um… I think you might need to, you know… go easy on the magic.”

I nodded dully.

Then Dusty added, “I’m kind of feeling it, too.”

“Sorry,” I said. A moment later, his words fully processed. My head came up, turning to him. “Wait, you too? I wasn’t—”

I hesitated again. There was a small amount of affection—or perhaps compassion?—coming from him. “...I mean, I don’t think I was feeding on you, unless I did it without realizing it.”

“This place is fucking with our heads,” Sickle growled from my other side, and I looked over to see her flicking her tail in agitation. “Like the place ain’t right.” She glanced my way. “‘Cause yeah, I’m feeling it, too.”

I slowly nodded. “I’ll be careful. We’re pretty much done.”

Dusty nodded. “Where else are we going?”

Emotions warred inside me, but I spoke evenly. “Queen Ephema’s chambers. It’s the last place I can think of that’s likely to have any relevant information for us.”

Nopony said anything in reply, and we continued on. I led us silently back to the throne room, and then to the unbarricaded set of double doors. Broad stairs led us up to a wide landing, with another set of ornate double doors at the end.

The lock broke with a loud crack as Sickle bucked the doors open. We moved in, PipBuck light and flashlights illuminating the rooms as we went. The whole area had a sense of grandness to it; it was built to the scale of a changeling queen, and the hive had ensured that she had the most comfortable of living arrangements.

There was the grand entry chamber, ringed by a balcony above. A large office served as a workspace for both Queen Ephema and her assistants. Another huge room, larger even than her entry chamber, had numerous cushions and couches, with a few low tables. It was an ideal place to hold relaxed meetings. There was also a dining area, with a large table that could seat a few dozen changelings.

And then there were the more personal chambers, such as the sizable bathroom and, of course, her bedroom chamber. I had seen the more public portion of her chambers, but I had never been in these private areas. I had to force myself to continue walking. I felt like an intruder, a trespasser. It was a feeling both intimately familiar and alarmingly discomforting. I was able to take some small comfort that Ephema would surely not object to my intrusion. I was, after all, here to fulfil the mission she had entrusted in me.

I led the way through the rooms, my pace slow as I looked around. I could feel the tears slowly running down my cheeks, but I continued on, pretending they weren’t there.

The bedroom was the hardest part. There were several displays to hold the small number of necklaces and other jewelry she owned, mostly gifts from changelings returning from missions in other lands. The shelves set on the back wall contained an assortment of artistic works that had been given to her. But mostly, my eyes lingered on the huge bed, long-vacant and lightly coated in dust.

I swallowed a few times as we moved back to the offices, and felt confident enough to speak by the time we got there. As we neared the largest desk, I raised a hoof to gesture. “Starlight?”

She moved forward quickly, stepping up behind the terminal atop the desk. It took less than a minute, which I spent in a fruitless search through the desk’s single drawer, before the terminal flickered and whirred to life.

With the servers down, there was practically nothing to find. The local cache contained only a single file, a local copy of the last message the terminal had sent.

Thank you for your concern, Solace, but I must fly on my own power. My children are already sacrificing so much for their sisters and myself. We are being forced to leave far too many behind. It breaks my heart to know that, should the worst come to pass, I will never again see the many who remain here. Yet I am filled with pride for the bravery and resolve of all of my children, as they offer their own lives, with heads held high, to ensure a future for us.

I should do no less. I understand that the flight will be exhausting, but it is a small price to ask me compared to the sacrifices others have made. More importantly, the skywagons can carry a dozen eggs in the space I would occupy. I will not leave a single one behind, even if I have to carry them myself. They deserve to see the future that their sisters’ sacrifice has brought them.

Please, load the skywagons, and send them on their way the moment the eggs are secure. Tell them I shall depart shortly, and don’t let them wait for me. Have them fly without delay, and take the eggs to safety as swiftly as they can.

I will be speaking to the hive in a few moments, to those who are remaining behind. Vigilance is worried about the security issues if this turns out to be a false alarm, but I can’t leave without saying goodbye, expressing my shame in leaving, and offering my thanks for everything you have all given. Whatever the future of our hive may be, I hope we can live up to your example.

Thank you, Solace, for all you have done. Goodbye.

I shakily raised a hoof, pressing the terminal’s power switch. The screen flickered and died, the soft hum from within slowly winding down. I sniffled, blinking tears from my eyes. Starlight was beside me again, squeezing gently with a foreleg, her eyes watering up. It was several seconds before I was able to speak past the lump in my throat, my voice barely above a whisper. “...That’s it, then.”

“Sorry,” Starlight quietly murmured beside me, and I gave a deep, shuddering sigh. I leaned against her.

“At least we know there were other sites,” Dusty said. When I looked up at him, blinking away tears, he added, “There weren’t any eggs.”

I slowly nodded. “Yeah. There weren’t.”

Starlight gave another squeeze and a cautious smile, despite the thin trail of tears that had run down her cheeks..

Dusty stepped over, sitting on my other side. “So, hey, I know it isn’t quite as neat and simple as if we had a map telling us right where to go, but… well, I’ll be glad to help you look for them.”

“Me too,” Starlight said, full of determination.

Sickle merely grunted.

“Thanks,” I murmured, then raised a hoof to wipe at my eyes. A few second later, I spoke again, a little more surely. “Though… I can at least make sure we don’t leave empty-hooved.”

I looked up to Dusty’s questioning expression, and blinked away the last of the tears.

“I know where the armory is.”

☢

We stepped out through the giant blast door, the last funeral pyre rapidly burning down behind us. My head throbbed, and my magic reserves were nearly depleted. My body felt exhausted. I knew I shouldn’t have felt so drained, but it didn’t matter. Love starvation was no longer a concern with three ponies keeping me fed.

Then again, those three ponies looked as weary as I felt. The trip through the hive had been more draining than any of us had expected.

As I walked over to the control panel, Starlight walked beside me, her bags bulging. The muzzles of several weapons, both kinetic and magical, protruded from under the flaps. “You’re sure about us taking all of this stuff?” she asked. She’d been hovering close to my side the whole time, watching me in concern. “I mean, I know that’s a little stupid coming from the experienced scavenger, but… well, it’s your hive.”

I have to admit, it did feel a little wrong, like digging up a grave just to rob it of some trinkets. Despite that, I nodded. “Any changeling would give everything they had to help the hive. I think they’d be happy to know these went to finding their sisters, instead of just lying there, unused.”

She slowly smiled and nodded. “That’s a really nice way of looking at it,” she said.

I nodded a little, my mind slowly unwinding as I reached the door panel. She stepped up beside me. It was around then that I noticed her limp.

Starlight must have noticed my glance toward her leg. Given my downcast expression at the time, I suppose my concern must have been obvious. “It’s just a little sore again,” she said, giving a casual shrug for emphasis. “I’m more concerned about you, to be honest. How are you holding up?”

I stood silently for several seconds. The only response I could come up with was to shrug. Finally, I reached out, pressing the big red button.

A thump sounded from behind us, followed by a short screech as the giant door started to move once more. I looked over my shoulder, watching as the multi-ton slab of steel slowly rolled into place. The flickering green glow emanating from beyond steadily narrowed and faded.

I drew in a deep breath and let it out in a long, soft sigh. Then I spoke, my voice quiet and almost lost behind the grind of machinery. “The hive lives on in me.”

The blast door shut with a deep thud, the muffled sounds of machinery winding down. I turned back to Starlight. Her expression was concerned again, until I smiled. It was a small, weak smile, as if it struggled against everything I had just experienced, but it held.

As she smiled back, I gave a little nod. I turned again, looking ahead as we started to walk.

“I’ve got a lot of work ahead of me.”

Chapter Twenty Two: Sanguine

The light was just starting to fade as I crept up to the ridge of a low hill to peer out at the farmstead, only a quarter mile away. I lifted my binoculars, scanning over the remains of buildings. To my sides, Dusty and Starlight did the same.

The barn had collapsed, and many of its boards were blackened and charred. The house itself, a small, single-story affair, showed some fire damage along one side, and the door was broken down, but the building was still standing. An old, decaying fence surrounded the buildings. Only the outhouse appeared undamaged.

The fields themselves had been torched.

“Doesn’t look good,” Dusty murmured, lowering his binoculars.

I nodded, lowering mine as well. “It looks vacant,” I said. “I can’t imagine the farmers would have stayed with everything destroyed, and it seems like the raiders would have to be incredibly persistent to wait in hiding for so long.”

“Yep,” Dusty said with a nod, then looked back over his shoulder. “Okay, we’re going straight in. Keep your spacing wide, and your eyes out. There might be friendly ponies in there. If you’re absolutely certain you see a raider, lay on the fire while everypony else gets to ground. Otherwise, return fire only as a last resort. Got it?”

There were nods all around, followed by Sickle’s voice. “Sure thing, Dirt. I won’t shoot anypony.”

“Yeah, yeah,” Dusty said as he rose to his hooves. “Like you’d listen to what I say, anyway. Let’s move.”

We all stood, following after him. After a couple short commands, we spread out on either side of him. Dusty walked with a relaxed pose, and while he held the bit of his rifle in his mouth, he kept the barrel low. I tried to emulate him, loosening up my stance and holding my rifle lightly. I imagine the idea was to look as nonthreatening as possible, while ready for a fight at a moment’s notice. Those two goals worked against each other quite thoroughly, even without Sickle’s armored bulk clattering along beside us.

Striding across the barren earth and ashen fields, we were greeted only by silence.

When we reached the fence, Dusty came to a halt and crouched. The rest of us took up places along the fence spread out on either side.

Sickle remained standing, staring down at Dusty. “Seriously? What now?”

He ignored her, looking back and gesturing to Emerald. When she came up to him, he said, “Go ahead and call out, see if they’re in there.”

She looked over the house and stood tall, calling out in a clear voice. “Quartz? Flint? It’s Emerald.” She hesitated, chewing on her lip for a moment before adding, “Are you there?”

Only silence answered, and her ears drooped.

“Okay, we’re sweeping the house,” Dusty said. “Stick together, check every room, and stay alert until we’re sure we’ve cleared it all.”

Sickle immediately walked past him, stepping over a broken section of fence. We followed. Dusty held his gun up, tracking the nearest window. I raised my own rifle, seating the stock firmly against my shoulder, despite the awkwardness of doing so while walking.

Dusty had fallen into a slow, careful walk, keeping the window covered, while Sickle trotted casually up to the door.

I was just starting to pick up my pace when Sickle stepped into the doorway.

During the war, I had come up with a certain theory in regards to ponies, weapon development, and the psychological processes involved in such. The simple version was that ponies’ driving mentality during the war was emotion rather than logic. It explained the rapid rise of xenophobia in a culture that had always been so open to outsiders. It explained the fear and anger that arose in people unfamiliar with war. And it explained why some weapon designer had made a weapon that would warn its target, as if to avoid feeling guilt over making an “unfair” surprise attack.

But as the mine chirped below Sickle, my experience with raiders immediately produced a new theory: that whoever had designed the standard Equestrian anti-personnel land-mine had been a sadist, a sick and twisted individual who took immense pleasure from that one moment where you look upon her creation and realize there is absolutely nothing you can do to prevent what is about to happen.

I remember Sickle had raised her hoof right before it went off. Whether she intended to shield her face, or was merely trying to stomp the device that had just announced itself, I’m not sure, but it may well have saved her life. The entire world immediately turned into an incoherent daze, choked with dust and abruptly twisted beyond any attempt at comprehension. When reality started to congeal again, I found myself on my side, blinking against the dust-filled air as bits of dirt and debris fell to earth all around me. My chest felt tight, and the world reeled even as I lay there. It only occurred to me later that I didn’t hear anything.

I turned my head, and the whole world spun around me. Despite lying on the ground, my legs kicked out, instinct insisting that I was falling over. My brain still hadn’t processed the events leading up to that moment, leaving me confused as to why I was lying there.

Then I saw Starlight. Her movement had drawn my muddled brain’s attention. She had just rolled onto her back. Her hooves were at her neck, her mouth open. My mind immediately focused on the thick spurt of blood that surged out between her hooves.

I leaped to my hooves, or tried to. My hoof caught on the edge of my cloak, jerking me back down to the ground. I rolled to the side to disentangle myself, and tried again. The world lurched under me as I rose, sending me staggering one way, and when I tried to rebalance, my right foreleg simply gave out from under me. I collapsed to my side, and looked down at the limb that had betrayed me. I was met with the sight of blood and bone. My lower leg was bent where it had no business bending, and the bone that was supposed to remain on the inside of a pony was protruding out through the skin, joined by a jagged piece of metal.

But it didn’t hurt, so my attention immediately went back to Starlight. In just that brief moment of distraction, she was drenched from chin to chest in blood, her mouth flapping as if she were drowning.

I tried to get to her, but my body continued to betray me, always moving in any direction but the way I intended.

Then a hoof fell in front of my vision, and another gripped my side. A head moved over me. With my view of Starlight obstructed, I instead found my world focused on this other pony. It took a moment to recognize Dusty’s worried expression. His nose was bleeding, but he was otherwise well. He might have said something, but I’m really not sure. All I know was that he was the happiest sight in the world at that moment.

Then he moved past me, and I saw Starlight choking on her own blood again, and my world came crashing down.

Another set of hooves grabbed me, but I kept struggling to reach Starlight—which I’m sure consisted mostly of flailing my hooves in her general direction—until Emerald appeared before me. I know she tried to say something to me, as I remember her mouth moving, but I didn’t hear any of it. I wasn’t paying that much attention. I knew there was something important, something that I needed to do, but as she gently shifted me to lie flat, I couldn’t for the life of me remember what it was.

It was around then that the pain started to truly sink in. The tightness in my chest started to grow worse and worse, but what really set it off was when Emerald shifted my broken leg. It was bad enough to feel it twist and turn in ways it never should have, but I think what really did it was the sight of the bone slipping back inside the mangled wound, like some alien entity tucking itself away inside my body. Every instinctual fear and revulsion surged forward at once, and I screamed and kicked against the horror that was hiding inside me. Only Emerald’s firm grip and steady stroking of my side brought my panic under control, and I’m thankful that, in my struggles, I hadn’t thought to transform to a form without a theoretically internal skeleton; I have no desire to discover what a compound fracture of an internal bone would become for an exoskeleton.

The following moments were a blur. I squirmed and grit my teeth as Emerald tended to me. Every movement of my leg was like the stab of a knife, and every flinch and jerk I made in response merely worsened the pain. I choked back a scream as she pulled a shard of metal out of my leg, as sharp as a blade, but twisted and jagged. Her hooves were smeared with my blood. My own leg was coated in it.

A healing potion was shoved into my mouth. I tilted my head back, trying to grasp at it, but she kept my leg pinned down. The attempt sent another jolt of pain through me, and I nearly choked on the potion, but coughing and sputtering, I managed to down it.

Within moments, the pain receded, and the world reoriented, becoming more real. It felt as if my ears popped, and distant, muffled sounds soon drew closer until I could hear Emerald moving over me.

I also heard Starlight’s wet, sobbing coughs.

“Starlight!” I again attempted to get to her, only for a spike of pain to flare up from the leg Emerald was still keeping pinned down. Despite how much better I felt for having the healing potion, it seemed I was still injured.

“She’s okay,” Emerald reassured me. “She’s stable. Right now, we need to care for you. Where are your healing potions?”

I laid my head down again, finding myself increasingly tired. “Medical box,” I mumbled. “Left bag.”

She kept her hooves on my leg as she leaned in, opening my bags with her mouth and pulling out the misshapen medical box. She retrieved another healing potion and fed it to me. The remaining pain rapidly diminished. After a few more seconds, she slowly relaxed her grip on my leg. She gave it a few careful prods, asking me how it felt.

“Sore,” I answered, slowly relaxing. The pain had finally receded into a deep ache throughout my body, but my head felt relatively clear once more.

Emerald prodded a few more times to be sure. I did my best to minimize the tremble as the squishy flesh mushed against the hard bone that had, moments earlier, been stabbed through the very same flesh. I think she mistook my disturbed reaction as one of pain, but I assured her it was merely an ache.

“All the same,” she said, “you should go gentle on it. I’d prefer to immobilize your lower leg.”

She eventually produced a splint from her own medical supplies, a good one produced during the war, and went through the process of fixing my leg in place.

As Emerald worked, I got a good view of Starlight. She was lying on the ground, facing away from me, with her side rapidly rising and falling. Even facing away from me, her neck and shoulder were completely caked in blood and dirt. Dusty had rolled her to her side, facing away from the large puddle that was slowly seeping into the dry earth. It was a truly shocking amount of blood, enough to make me wonder how it could all come from one pony.

Dusty came over to us, snatching up the other healing potion. He returned to Starlight, cradling her head as he tilted her face upwards and carefully fed her another healing potion. She weakly grasped at it, and after a few gasps for air she started to relax, her rapid breathing slowing, but only a little.

I lay there as Emerald worked, feeling so utterly useless.

Sickle was sitting on the opposite side of Starlight, with a few empty healing potion bottles lying between them. Sickle’s muzzle hung open, but it and her face were dripping with blood. She just sat there, panting and occasionally spitting out a bit of blood.

As soon as the splint was in place, I struggled up to my hooves. The world wobbled and contracted around me, my heartbeat rushing in my ears, but it smoothed out as I took a few deep breaths. I was able to stand long enough to move over to Starlight. She looked up to me, still panting softly. Her cheeks were wet with tears.

I lay down with her, slipping my good foreleg around her to hug, ignoring the blood. She snuffled against my neck and held me tight, trembling.

“Watch over them,” Dusty said to Emerald, then turned to speak across us. “Sickle, you good to move?”

I heard a spit in reply, followed by a grunted and weary, “Yeah.”

They moved up to where the doorway had once been, now just a ragged gap in the wall. What floorboards remained were shattered and thrown about, and the roof sagged. They passed through the gap, slow and wary, while we waited outside.

A minute later, Sickle strolled out again, walking a few paces past us before flopping onto her side with a clatter of metal and a weary grunt. Dusty emerged after her, though he stopped to sit on the porch. He looked exhausted and downcast, eyes unfocused even as he pulled out and lit a cigarette.

Emerald stood. “...Are they in there?”

Dusty took a long drag of his cigarette, followed by a deep sigh. “Just the foals,” he said. “A colt and… I think it was a filly.”

Emerald’s ears drooped. I’m sure she had expected such bad news, but that hardly made it any better. She shook her head, then walked toward the door.

“Don’t,” Dusty said, holding up a hoof. “You… you don’t want to see that.”

She stopped, but slowly shook her head. “I can’t just leave them in there. They deserve a burial.”

“They’ll get one,” Dusty said. “Just… you don’t need to see what’s in there. At least let us get them down, first.”

Emerald’s expression wilted, and she sat again. Her eyes watered as she nodded.

We sat in silence until Dusty had finished his cigarette, dropping it to the dirt and grinding it under-hoof. “Okay,” he said, standing and walking up to Starlight and myself. He produced a water bottle and held it out. “Here, Star. You’re going to need plenty of fluids, so drink up. Try to eat something, if you can. It’ll help you recover.”

Starlight’s grip slowly relaxed around me, and she pulled her head away to look up at the bottle. Her eyes were red and puffy. Her horn eventually lit up, wrapping the bottle in her magic.

“Now let’s get you sitting up,” Dusty said, crouching down to wedge his muzzle in against her side. Between the two of us, we got her sitting upright, though she leaned heavily against me. She sniffled and wiped at her cheeks, only to stop and stare at her blood-covered hooves. A tremor passed through her, and she shut her eyes, taking a long drink from the bottle.

With that settled, Dusty took a step back. “Hey, Sickle. Help me out with… the stuff inside.”

“Why?” Sickle rumbled, not even moving. “Ain’t like they’re getting any less dead.”

I sighed and looked up to Dusty. “I’ll help.”

He frowned, contemplating me for a moment. I imagine he was thinking on whether I should be exposed to whatever was waiting inside, but he finally nodded.

Emerald sat beside Starlight, giving her another shoulder to lean on. “I’ll be right back,” I promised, and Starlight looked up to me with a weary, almost hopeless look. I gave a smile back, trying to be reassuring. She meekly nodded, her eyes closing again.

I stood and, forgetting about my own injury, winced as I put too much weight on my injured leg. A quick shuffle solved that, and I followed Dusty. He paused for a moment, casting a glance at my leg, but said nothing.

We went inside. The house had once been nice enough, but it had come across hard times lately. The mine had done a terrifying amount of damage to the old structure, completely obliterating most of the flooring in what had once been the entryway, and all the walls we could see were torn up, with holes ranging from barely visible to several inches wide. A few pieces of furniture lay nearby, upturned and scarred by the blast. The stench of smoke filled the air, but as we moved further into the house, another, fouler smell began to emerge.

The raiders had ransacked the place, overturning and smashing furniture as they rummaged through the place for loot. The kitchen was badly charred, but the fire hadn’t spread further. And then there was the final room we entered, one which looked to have once been a pleasant place for a family to relax, now turned into a showcase of brutality.

The room itself was wrecked, but it was the colt that I first focused on, or at least, what remained of him. He was hung from the rafters by a rope tied around his rear hooves. His head was missing, and his upper chest was so torn up that one of his forelegs had been severed and was lying on the ground several feet away. Between the carnage and a couple days of decay, it was hard to guess at his age. Ten, maybe twelve at the most.

The couch he was hanging beside was torn apart, and bits of debris covered the floor. In the dim light of the room, I first thought the debris was pieces of the cushions or other furniture. It was a couple of seconds before I focused on the pale, curved fragment of a skull. His head wasn’t missing; it was all right there, scattered about the room.

Another foal hung opposite him, suspended by a pair of ropes tied to their forehooves. I think it was a filly. She was at that age where it can be hard to tell from just the face, even before decay. More reliable methods of identification were impossible. Her body ended where her hips should have been, while much of what had once been her insides now lay in a shredded mess beneath her. Her hind-legs lay on the floor, with the curved shards of a destroyed pelvis still attached.

All of that was enough to make me feel a little queasy, but the worst was her face. Her head was lolled forward, mouth hanging agape and eyes open. The expression on what remained of her decaying face seemed one of dull shock and distress. It was disturbingly macabre, as if she were still aware of the horrors done there.

After that unnamed army depot and Paradise Beach, I had thought—hoped, at least—that I would never be surprised by the vileness that one pony could inflict upon another, but raiders continued to find new ways to horrify.

I nearly jumped when Dusty’s hoof gently patted my shoulder. “Take your time,” he said, his voice quiet. I focused on him as he looked around the room. His eyes lingered on details, giving the impression of an immense sadness. But I saw a little deeper. I could see the bit of hardness in his eyes as he looked over the scene.

We couldn’t save these ponies, but we could damn well make sure the ponies responsible could never do this again.

I steeled myself, standing tall and firm, and gave Dusty a nod. “Okay. I’m ready.”

Getting them down was a gruesome affair. Fortunately, Dusty had a knife, which we used to cut through the ropes. It was a far better alternative to untying them with our mouths. If not for the knife, I would have been tempted to transform and use my magic, even if it risked Emerald discovering what I was. She seemed like a reasonable mare; explaining my situation to her seemed preferable to putting my mouth on those ropes.

Plus, it seemed she was good at keeping secrets. Sadly, I had a more important task at hoof than to ponder that fact.

Dusty found a pair of blankets in the bedrooms. We bundled the foals up in them and brought them outside.

The burial was a brief affair, without ceremony. We managed to find a pair of shovels amidst the heap of farming tools the raiders had ignored, and we dug a pair of tiny graves. I’ll admit, the digging went much quicker when Sickle got tired of waiting, shoved me out of the way, and took up the shovel herself. Emerald claimed a couple of pieces of the broken fence to form simple grave markers, and borrowed Dusty’s knife to carve a name into each one: Sage and Pebble.

Starlight spent most of the time leaned back against the building, looking groggy as she alternated between downing a second bottle of water and eating a pack of crackers. With the burial done, Emerald drew some water from the hoof-pumped well and returned to Starlight’s side, dunking a washcloth in the old bucket. “Let’s get you cleaned up a little, hmm?”

Starlight grunted quietly, setting her food and water down to let Emerald work. Slowly, the worst of the blood was cleaned away.

I ended up doing the same thing Dusty was: keeping an eye out, in case the explosion had drawn any attention. Thankfully, it was quiet.

Starlight was mostly cleaned up when Sickle stepped up to her. “Let me see,” Sickle rumbled, shoving Emerald’s hoof out of the way, then nudging Starlight’s chin back. Sickle frowned, then pushed Starlight’s head to the side to look at the other side of her neck before releasing her again. “Well, shit. That sucks. Don’t even get a cool scar out of it or anything.”

Starlight huffed out a breath that might have been faintly amused, and I think the corner of her mouth might have twitched upwards.

Emerald resumed the cleaning, though she watched Sickle and her blood-stained snout. “You might want to clean up, too.”

“Right,” Sickle said, chuckling. “You ain’t seen me fight. Ain’t any point in me cleaning up yet.”

Rather than argue, Emerald merely shook her head and shrugged. “Suit yourself,” she said, returning to cleaning Starlight.

Some ten minutes later, we gathered around, with Starlight sat against the side of the house, as Dusty appraised the situation.

“Between the potions we’ve already used, and the bottles that broke from the explosion, this is all we have for arcane medical supplies.”

Set between us was a single healing potion and three magic-laced bandages.

“Got plenty of painkillers,” Sickle said with an armor-rattling shrug.

“Useful, sure,” Dusty said. “But they don’t stop bleeding like a potion does. The bandages are useful, but not nearly as good. Somepony takes a nasty hit, a potion might be the only way to keep them alive. Two someponies take a nasty hit, and one of them might not be making it home.”

“Right,” Sickle said. “Stop getting hurt, got it.”

“If only it were that simple,” Dusty muttered. “We haven’t even seen these raiders yet, and we’ve already gone through most of our medical supplies.”

I stared down at the small collection, feeling distinctly uncomfortable about the situation. I’d just downed two healing potions, and my leg still ached. “Are you suggesting that we go back?”

“We can’t go back,” Emerald said. “Quartz and Flint might still be out there! And besides, it isn’t as if more potions are going to magically appear in my store overnight. You cleaned out my stock already.”

“I’m not saying we have to turn around,” Dusty said. “Like you said, going back to Gemstone won’t do us any good. Maybe if a caravan comes in, but how often do you see healing potions turn up?”

Emerald thought a moment, then slowly shook her head. “Maybe a dozen or so over a whole year. Sometimes more. Ponies tend to hang onto them.”

“Maybe another settlement?” I asked.

“Like where?” Dusty asked. “We might luck out and find a couple in Rust, but that’s, what, a day or two there? Same back. Mareford would have plenty, but that’s out of the question.”

“Raiders will have some,” Sickle said, grinning. “Funny how many dead ponies you find with perfectly good healing potions on ‘em.”

“Got to live long enough to use them,” Dusty noted. “Anyway, this isn’t about some quick fall-back to refit and try again. There is no quick resupply. Right now, the question is whether we continue on with the mission, or we abort and spend the weeks or months we need to get adequate supplies for a second attempt.”

“Quartz and Flint won’t have weeks or months,” Emerald said, her ears hanging low. “They might still be alive.” She turned a desperate look toward Sickle. “Right?”

Sickle scowled, but her expression eventually mellowed as she shrugged. “Maybe. Depends on why they took ‘em. If they brought ‘em back to have fun torturing or putting on a show, they’re already dead. If they brought ‘em back to be fucktoys, they might still be alive. Probably not. Depends on how rough they like to play.” She followed that with a dry chuckle. “And from what they did to those foals, I’m guessing they like to play plenty rough.”

With a shiver, Emerald turned back to Dusty. “W-we can’t turn back. Those ponies are depending on us.”

“I’m not saying we’re turning back,” Dusty replied, a bit of an edge creeping into his voice. “I’m saying the situation just got more dangerous, and every one of you needs to consider that before we move on.”

We stared at the supplies in silence for a minute before Starlight spoke up, her voice quiet and tired. “I’m still going,” she said. “Least we can do is scout things out. Find the raiders. See if those ponies are alive. Heck, maybe Whisper could do her thing and sneak in, take a look…” She blinked, casting a glance my way, then shook her head. “No, bad idea. But we can still look.”

“Are you going to be able to make it?” Dusty asked.

“Of course I can make it,” Starlight said, her voice rising, though a moment later she sagged against the wall. “Shit, Dusty. I almost died. I-I…” She swallowed and took a deep breath. “Yeah, I can make it. I’m going.”

Dusty nodded solemnly, and looked to me.

I gave a wry smile in reply. “As if you have to ask?” I said, gesturing a hoof toward Starlight.

He looked to Sickle, who gave an exaggerated roll of her head. “Oh no, I might get hurt.” She drew in a deep snort and spit out a disgusting glob of mucus and blood. “Of course I’m going. Fuck, I ain’t killed a pony in weeks, and I need to murder the shit out of some motherfucker for that sneaky fucking trick.”

With a sigh, Dusty looked back at the supplies. “Okay. Emerald, you’ll be carrying those medical supplies. Keep them safe.” He looked back to Starlight. “Are you going to be able to travel?”

“Yeah,” she said, though I caught the hesitant tone to her voice. “I’ll manage.”

“Here,” Sickle rumbled, and something small and pale sailed through the air. Starlight yelped weakly as it bounced off her chest, then fumbled with her forehooves in a failed attempt to catch it.

Sickle glowered at her as Starlight bent over and picked up the object, blowing off the dirt, and looked at the thick, white tablet. “What’s this?”

“It’s Buck,” Sickle rumbled. “Should keep you going for an hour or two.”

Dusty’s mouth opened to protest, but he hesitated, and eventually shook his head. “Well, I can’t say it’s the worst idea I’ve heard.” To me, the statement seemed to have an implied “but it’s close.”

Starlight was frowning down at the tablet. “Uh… maybe I’ll just hold onto it. I can use it later if I need it.”

“Whatever,” Sickle said with a snort.

Starlight tucked the pill inside her bags. “...Thanks.”

We set out shortly after that. I expect we made for a rather pitiful sight. I was limping, not from pain, but from a desire to be gentle with my injured leg. Starlight tended to lag behind and weave a little, but every time, her head would snap back up, and she’d push on. Even Sickle seemed a little more lethargic than usual.

To everyone’s relief, we only traveled for an hour before Dusty decided we were far enough from the farmstead to be relatively safe. We took up a spot in a small recess of a rocky hill, sheltered by the rocks rising to either side, and settled in for the night.

After a quick meal, Starlight laid out her bedding right next to mine. We all settled in, except Dusty, who took the first watch.

It was hardly a minute before Starlight slipped over, pressing close against my side. She was trembling. I shifted more to my side, slipping my splinted foreleg over her and tucking the blanket over both of us. She, in turn, buried her muzzle against my neck, muffling the faint sobs that accompanied her shaking.

I held her close and tight, tucking my head in against hers, until she slowly relaxed.

☢

When morning came and ponies started to wake, I stayed close beside Starlight. “Are you okay?”

“Yeah,” she murmured, looking away as she rummaged through her bags. “I’m just really hungry.”

I kept my voice low, so the others were less likely to overhear us. “Are you sure?”

She paused, holding a package of mixed vegetables in her magic. “...I almost died last night,” she said, her voice quiet, and shook her head. “It’s… I don’t know. I almost died, and I couldn’t even do anything about it. I didn’t even try, just…”

I slipped a foreleg around her shoulders, and she sighed. “I just panicked.”

“I tried to run on a compound fracture,” I said. “I think we might have both been a little concussed.”

She gave a weak snort. “Yeah, sure. Still, I was just… useless.”

“You’re not useless,” I said, giving a squeeze, but she just rolled her eyes.

“I mean I felt useless,” she said. She opened her mouth to continue, then shut it. I waited as she tried a few more times before speaking again. “It reminded me of when my mom died.”

I gave another squeeze, but held it, and leaned my head against hers. She sat there, still for a few moments, before giving another huff and shrugging her shoulders, pushing me back just a bit. “Hey, I’m better now,” she said, giving a weak smile that was only partially convincing. “The sleep helped a lot.” Her smile slowly faded away, and after a moment of silence she added, “It just freaked me out is all. It’s the only time I’ve felt so… scared and helpless.”

She glanced warily my way. “...You know what I mean?”

I slowly nodded. “Yeah. I know what you mean.”

“Yeah.” She sighed, then tore open the bag of veggies and tipped the bag back, dumping several bite-size pieces of various vegetables into her mouth. “Ehhee huhhgy,” she said around the mouthful as she chewed. While I speculated at what she had intended to say—”Really hungry,” I think—she started scratching at her neck. “And my neck is itching like mad,” she said, once she had swallowed the mouthful.

I’m not surprised. Despite Emerald’s effort to clean her, Starlight’s scratching dislodged several flecks of red, blood that had dried under her coat. She eventually stopped, looking down at her hooves, speckled in dried blood, and blearily declared, “I need a shower.”

I looked down at my own hooves. I’d cleaned thoroughly with the well water, but I was sure I’d be imagining the feeling of dried blood under my coat until I’d had the chance to clean up in my natural form. “I think I could use one, too.”

She gave a dry chuckle, tipping back the bag of veggies again.

Soon everypony was gathering up their bedding and eating a quick breakfast. Starlight ate ravenously, and downed the entire package and a can of beans before washing it down with a bottle of water. Afterwards, she lay out with a groan, waiting for everypony else.

Dusty laid out a brief plan for the day: head toward the area Emerald had indicated, scout out any raider presence, and attempt to locate their base of operations. “And above all else,” he said, “stay alert. Keep an eye out for ambushes, booby traps, stuff like that. We already know they like to use mines, and we can’t afford to get surprised like that again.”

As we donned our packs and gear, I saw Starlight staring off toward the horizon and taking a few slow, deep breaths. On the final exhale, she murmured, “Okay.” This was followed by a grimace as she noticed I was watching her. “...Okay, so I’m a little nervous,” she said with a frown, “but I’m not going to let that stop me.”

I cautiously nodded, uncertain of what to say.

Since Sickle had merely flopped down in the dirt to sleep, she had no bedding to pack or equipment to re-don, and was ready to go as soon as she got up. As a result, she waited as impatiently as ever while we got ready, occasionally waving a spiked-and-bladed hoof at one of the flies buzzing around her head.

Emerald slung her magical energy weapon across her back and paused, looking over to Sickle. “You know, if you cleaned up that blood, you probably wouldn’t have all those flies bothering you.”

Sickle growled. “Oh, hey, yeah, keep poking at me, bitch.” She swatted at another fly. “Then in a couple minutes I can tell you how if you just kept your cunt mouth shut, you wouldn’t have a broken jaw. How’s that sound?”

I sighed quietly. Not that I was surprised by Sickle’s behavior. Just, maybe a little disappointed.

Emerald looked disappointed as well. “I’m sorry,” she said, her ears drooping. “I didn’t mean to offend you. I was just trying to offer some help.”

“Well don’t,” Sickle replied with a snort, and looked away.

Despite my hopes that Emerald would just leave things be, she spoke again. “You really don’t like me, do you?”

I started walking closer to the pair, hoping to intervene if Sickle replied too aggressively.

Sickle gave a short, dry chuckle. “‘Course not. You’re a fucking idiot.”

Emerald glanced over to me as I approached, giving a questioning look. When I shrugged, she looked back to Sickle. “I have to wonder why you think that.”

“Because you think you’re actually helping,” Sickle said, her head turning to fix on Emerald. “You’re not. You just hide behind your walls and your guns. It’s like you’re living in some fucking fantasy land, where you think happy thoughts and smile, and everything’s okay. ‘Cept right on the other side of those walls, you got a bunch of ponies getting raped to death by raiders. But hey, maybe if you think they’re actually good ponies for long enough, they’ll all stop with the raping and murdering and join in singing some happy song about friendship and rainbows and shit. Any decade now, right?”

Emerald’s ears hung low. “...The world isn’t going to get any better if we just keep killing ourselves,” she said, her voice quiet, but growing stronger with every word. “I know, some ponies need to be stopped, sometimes even killed, but we have to work towards something better, instead of just keeping what we have. You can kill off every single raider in existence, but it won’t make a difference if we don’t deal with the reason they exist.”

Sickle laughed, sharp, bitter, and without humor. “Like you know why raiders exist.”

“And anyway,” Emerald said, her head rising as she took up a more firm posture, “I’m not hiding behind those walls now. I’m out here, trying to do what’s right.”

“Brahminshit!” Sickle growled, rising to her hooves. “You’re out here because you’re a fucking coward and a liar.”

“Hey!” Dusty shouted, trotting in our direction, while adrenaline started to tease at my senses.

“Fuck off, Dirt!” Sickle took a step toward Emerald—I took a step in, as well—and snarled in her face. “You talk a lot of shit, but as soon as push came to shove, you pussied out and ran away. Don’t play like you’re out here to make the world a better place. You lied to everypony, pretending everything was good and happy, right before you turn around and abandon them. You’re nothing but a fucking coward that thinks she’s better than everypony else.”

The pained look on Emerald’s face was too much. I stepped in. “That’s enough, Sickle. She already explained why she needs to leave.”

Sickle turned her glare to me, staring for several seconds before finally snorting and turning away. “Yeah, sure. We going, yet?”

Dusty was glaring at Sickle, but slowly nodded. “Yeah, we’re going.”

I looked to Emerald. She stood still, eyes shimmering with tears. Her expression was like a hoof to the gut.

I stepped forward, gently placing a hoof on her shoulder. “It’s okay.”

She looked to me, her eyes full of sadness, and sighed. “No, it’s not.”

She slipped away from my hoof, slowly walking along behind Dusty, who cast a concerned look back our way before returning to keeping an eye on Sickle.

“I’ve helped a lot of ponies,” Emerald quietly said, her head hanging low as she walked. “I know I have. I’ve done what I can to make life better for as many as I can, but… I’m not a fighter.” She cast a quick glance Sickle’s way. “I’m not a coward, either. I’m a pony who’s willing to give up everything she has for a cause she believes in. I’m just not a fighter. And yeah, sometimes we need fighters. Sometimes, we need ponies who will stop the monsters that try to kill us. Heck, even the ponies who embodied the Elements themselves fought to protect Equestria.”

She paused, and a flicker of a smile crossed her face. “Well, maybe not Fluttershy, but she still helped those who did.” The faint smile faded away a moment later. “But I’m still not a fighter.”

The ground crunched quietly under-hoof as we continued on in silence. Eventually, I nodded. “I know what you mean.”

Emerald cast a glance my way. “Is that so?”

“Yeah.” I looked down at the rifle slung at my chest, which now felt so familiar there. “I had never fired a weapon in anger before a month ago. I had never been in a real fight before then, much less a firefight. Heck, it still seems weird when ponies see me as someone who can fight.”

Emerald considered me for a few long moments. “From the stories Dazzle told, I would have never guessed.”

I gave a wry smile. “Adversity seems to be a very efficient teacher.”

“For some things,” Emerald said.

“For some things,” I echoed with a nod.

She nodded thoughtfully, but that eventually ended with a slow shake of her head. “I hope you’re not trying to convince me to stay and fight.”

I considered my reply for a few seconds before speaking. “No, I’m just offering sympathy. If I were to make comment on the situation at hoof, it would be that there are fighters out there, sometimes in places you don’t expect it.”

“...Thanks.” She looked down at her hooves as she continued walking. “Except right now, they don’t even know they’re needed.”

I nodded. “All the more reason to share that information.”

“Yeah,” Emerald said, heaving a deep sigh. “And I will. It’s just… hoo. You have no idea how hard it is. You seem like good ponies, but I’m still not sure how you’ll take it. I’m not even sure if you’ll believe me.”

I had to smile at that. “And that’s something I can definitely sympathize with.”

She turned a questioning look my way. “Oh?”

“Yeah.” I smiled at her, looking at her expression of curiosity. I thought of all the things she had said and done, all the good she had tried to accomplish, all that she gave without expecting anything in return, and I came to a decision. “How about this: I’m pretty sure I can top whatever story you’ve got. These are some very understanding ponies we’re traveling with. And you, you seem like a good pony, and one who is very good at keeping secrets when they’re for a good reason. So, how about a deal?”

She blinked, her ears perking up. “What’s that?”

I inclined my head in the direction we were traveling. “We go out there, play the heroes, maybe save some ponies. Then, when that’s all done, you and I swap stories of our dark and mysterious pasts.”

Starlight’s ears had shot up in alarm, and she cast a concerned look my way, as if to say, “Are you sure?” I could certainly understand. She understood exactly what I was offering. Even I felt a little uncomfortable about sharing. A few weeks earlier, and I would have never considered it, but I had shared my secret with three of the ponies I was traveling with, even if it hadn’t been entirely by choice. Instead of leaving me more vulnerable, as I had feared, that shared secret left us all better off.

Emerald had caught Starlight’s look, and watched her curiously before looking back to me. I simply smiled back, and after a moment of wary hesitation, she smiled as well, slowly and cautiously. “Okay, then. It’s a deal.”

In hindsight, I could have pressed her right then. I was reluctant to share my own secrets, but I was convinced that she was a pony they would be safe with. What she had already shared was enough for that. I’m sure that revealing my own past, not to mention my hidden nature, would have been enough to convince her to share her own story, but I didn’t press the matter.

Maybe I should have.

☢

Neither Starlight nor Emerald’s PipBucks had a name for the tiny ghost town we found. The settlement had once had about twenty buildings, mostly simple two-story houses. Now more than half of them now lay in ruins, whether collapsed from the wear and tear of two centuries or torn down by scavengers for material. The ones that remained were in poor repair. Roofs sagged, walls had holes where boards had fallen away, and all of them were caked in two centuries of dust and dirt. Stretches of broken-down wire fence marked out several large patches of land between the surrounding low hills. Once, they might have been fields for crops. Now they were nothing but desolate patches of dry earth.

The center of the tiny town was a cluster of four buildings. One was still identifiable as a saloon, though one of the side walls had partially buckled. For the others, I could only make vague guesses as to their original purpose.

Between the buildings stood a tall pole, and lashed to that pole were the dry bones of a pony.

“They’ve certainly been here,” Dusty said as he peered through his binoculars. “Don’t see any sign of them right now.”

“Unless they’re inside,” I noted, slowly sweeping my own binoculars over the scene. Even in mid-day, the ever-present cloud-cover turned several windows into dark pits.

“Naturally,” Dusty said with a slow nod. He lowered his binoculars, though his eyes remained fixed on the town, just a quarter mile away. His hoof idly tapped the ground in front of where he lay, as he mulled over the scene.

“Wish we had broadcasters,” he muttered. “Could be a lot more flexible that way.” He shook his head, as if chasing away the thought, then spoke up. “Okay, plan of action. Left side of town, closest to us. You see that single-story building with the wide windows and stone foundation?”

As one, our heads turned to look at the building he had pointed out.

“Our first move is going to be toward there. It looks unoccupied, and if we do run into trouble, it should give better cover than one of the wood buildings. Stay spread out when we’re crossing the open, just like before. If we take fire, I want you all to lay on the return fire. Suppress the shit out of them and fight your way to that building. Move when your buddy is shooting, then stop and shoot so they can move. Once we’re enlodged there, we can move on to sweep the rest of the town. Got it?”

Nods and affirmations went around.

“Good,” he said with an authoritative nod, and stood. “Let’s move quick.”

He took his rifle’s bit in his mouth and led us out in a slow trot, and we spread out on either side.

We crossed over the fallen remains of a wire fence and into one of the old fields. Nothing but dust remained, kicked up by our hooves in tiny clouds to drift away in the gentle breeze.

My heart was beating a bit too hard for the mild pace, my breathing a bit too fast. I watched the slowly approaching windows, and checked once more that my safety was disengaged.

The distance steadily diminished. There were no signs of movements in the town, save for a few tattered scraps of cloth caught up in the displayed skeleton, fluttering gently.

We were less than a hundred yards from our destination when Starlight called out. “Hey! Uh…” Her head dipped down, then looked up at the saloon, directly across the street from where we were going. “I’ve got red marks over there.”

Dusty’s rifle was already swinging up and over before she had finished; I saw the puff from his muzzle an instant before the roar of incoming gunfire shattered the silence all around. I jumped, putting a round into the dirt in front of me, then quickly swung my weapon up in the direction Dusty was firing. My sights fell over the saloon. Muzzle-flashes blazed within the upper-story windows of the saloon, and I mashed the trigger as fast as I could. Puffs of dust and fragments of wood flew from the face of the building, followed by the brilliant flash and crack of Starlight’s Lancer putting a new hole in the wall. Snaps and cracks sounded all around me, but I only distantly recognized that the tiny puffs of dirt kicked up around us were incoming bullets.

My weapon jerked as I pulled the trigger on an empty chamber, my magazine already spent in what felt like a single instant. I glanced to to my left. Dusty had galloped ahead and had just thrown himself to the ground, his hooves moving swiftly as he reloaded his rifle. I followed his lead, breaking into a gallop, moving while he put out more fire, kicking up clouds of dust with every shot. A quick glance further to the left caught sight of Starlight and Emerald scrambling along, with the former helping the latter. The concern that stirred up had to wait; I had more pressing matters to attend to.

I had just passed Dusty when his rifle fell silent. I threw myself down in the dirt, sending up a small cloud of dust, and let my empty magazine fall to the ground as I fumbled a fresh one into place. Dusty was already galloping past behind me by the time I pulled the charging handle to chamber a round.

Flashes lit up the upstairs window again, matched with a frighteningly rapid chatter of gunfire. I swung my sights over the window and mashed the trigger again, answering it with my own shots. Dust flew up around me with each shot, obscuring my view, and more sprays of dust and wood fragments flew from the building as I put round after round into it. The incoming fire stopped almost immediately, but I didn’t stop until my weapon ran empty again.

I leaped up to my hooves, turned, and galloped again. Dusty had already halted, standing just a dozen yards from the safety of our destination, and started to steadily fire toward the building. Another burst of fire, slower and deeper, answered back, but fell silent almost immediately under Dusty’s steady, accurate fire.

As I galloped past Dusty, I saw the others had already made it inside. I dove in through the wide window, tumbling to a halt on the debris-strewn floor. I immediately saw Sickle, sitting there half exposed, her muzzle hanging to the side to reveal an enthusiastic grin.

I righted myself, disentangled from my cloak, and kicked out the empty magazine to reload again.

Dusty leaped across me and dropped neatly behind the edge of the window as he started to reload. “Star! Get on line, I need you shooting. Emerald! How bad is it?”

As I chambered another round, I glanced back. Starlight scrambled up to the edge of the window beside us, but I looked at Emerald, who was lying on her side and panting. She had pressed a hoof to her chest, and lifted it away, looking at it as if expecting blood.

“I’m okay,” she called back. “The barding stopped it!”

Dusty’s shout jerked me back to attention. “Whisper, get shooting!”

I snapped my head around, tugged on the bit to seat the stock against my body, and rose up. I saw flashes of white around the upper floor of the saloon, but in that frantic moment, I couldn’t be sure if they were the flashes of muzzles or the results of bullets striking the building. I simply pointed at wherever I saw movement and kept firing.

Then I saw a flicker of something dark arc from one of the windows.

Starlight’s Lancer swung upwards, and its near-blinding light was answered with a flash and the sharp blast of the grenade detonating in mid-air. I cringed, ducking down for an instant. I think Starlight laughed. S.A.T.S. is pretty amazing stuff.

I forced myself to rise again and resume shooting. I only got two more rounds out before I dropped down again, ejecting another spent magazine.

I was halfway through reloading when Sickle threw a pair of Dash inhalers to the ground. “Yeah, this is more like it!” she roared, slapping her muzzle back in place and latching it. She turned her manic grin our way. “Okay, you cunts! Let’s get this fucking party started!”

Then she leaped out the window, bellowing out an incoherent battle-cry of rage as she charged right across the open ground between the two buildings.

Dusty cursed, quickly snapping off several rounds into the upstairs windows, and as soon as I had finished reloading, I did the same. I heard only a short chatter of return fire, but saw no impacts; I assumed our suppressing fire had worked.

Sickle barreled straight through the half-broken doors of the saloon, disappearing into the darkness.

The windows flashed with light for an instant before the hammer-fall of an explosion hit me in the chest, throwing a billowing cloud of dust and fragments out of the lower-story windows. Everypony ducked. I heard debris striking the building, and kept my head down until the sound had stopped.

Dusty was already up and covering the upstairs windows by the time I had risen again. My heart was hammering. There was no sign of life within the building, even as the cloud of dust started to thin. Then I heard Sickle’s furious roar. I couldn’t make out what she yelled for sure, but if I had to guess, it would be, “You cheap-ass motherfuckers!”

Gunfire erupted from inside the upper floor of the saloon, that rapid chatter and slow boom mixing into a wild cacophony. Flashes of light lit up the windows, but they weren’t shooting at us.

Emerald moved up behind me. “Is everypony—”

A sharp crack interrupted her as she let out a pained yelp. My head snapped around to see her fall to the ground. I turned back to look for a shooter, only to have my vision filled by the suppressor of Dusty’s rifle as he swung it around to a new threat. I cringed back as an ejected casing slapped against my side, but the suppressor turned the rifle’s ear-shattering muzzle blast to sharp, echoing cracks. I recovered quickly, backing up and bringing my own weapon around.

I saw the flicker of bits of wood flying from the upper levels of a distant two-story house, probably two hundred yards away. I settled my sights over it and started to fire.

After a couple shots, Dusty yelled out. “Star! Far right, end of the road, two-story house. Follow my shots.” He fired off a couple more rounds, while Starlight scrambled over, sliding into place beside me and leveling her Lancer out the window.

“I see it!”

Dusty fired off a couple more rounds before shouting again. “Single upstairs window. There’s a shooter in there. He pops his head up again, you take it off!”

“Got it!” Starlight said, focusing down her scope.

My gun clicked, and I dropped down to reload again. I kicked out the magazine, which fell to the ground with a deep thunk. There were still rounds in it, but I didn’t take the time to contemplate that as I slid a fresh magazine in. I had to rack the bolt a few times to get it to finally close all the way.

As soon as I had, I brought my weapon up again, just in time to see the upstairs wall of the saloon explode outwards as Sickle plowed straight through it. She fell to the street, streaming dust and shattered boards like a descending meteor, her forelegs wrapped around a flailing pony.

It only occurred to me upon retelling the encounter that I had fired more than one hundred rounds of ammunition by then, and this was the first time I had directly seen one of the ponies we were fighting.

They crashed to the street with such an impact that I’m sure I felt it through the ground. Somehow, the other pony, a mare clad in metal barding and sporting a neon green mane, had survived Sickle tackling her through a wall and landing on her. Sickle solved that by bringing her head back and smashing her armored muzzle down on the pony’s head. I’m sure the first impact had finished the job, but I watched in morbid fascination and horror as Sickle repeated the action twice more, finally pulling her head back with blood and bits of brain dripping from the bars of her muzzle.

I tore my eyes away from the scene and focused on the distant house. Dusty had just finished off a magazine, dropping down a bit to reload once more. I carefully lined my sights up on the distant window, and as I started to put out carefully aimed shots into that dark void, Dusty spoke up.

“Emerald? You up? Can you shoot?”

I wanted to look back, but I kept focused on the building. Aim, squeeze, breath. Aim, squeeze, breath.

Emerald’s groan came as a welcome relief. “Yeah, I can do that.” She slid herself up beside me, and I saw she was holding a foreleg tight against her chest. She was clearly in pain, but I saw no blood, so I assumed her barding had again stopped the bullet.

Dusty slapped in the magazine. “I’m going to need you giving us covering fire. As soon as we move, I need you putting steady shots into that upstairs window. Star, you nail that shooter if he shows himself. The moment we get inside there, you two hold fire. I don’t want you shooting us on accident, got it?”

While they nodded, I had a sinking feeling as to who “we” were.

Dusty turned to call out toward the saloon. “Sickle!”

Sickle had risen to her hooves, and was limping in our direction, though she didn’t respond. She was giggling, interrupted as she staggered drunkenly. I could see now that blood was dripping heavily from her belly and running down her hind legs.

“Damnit,” Dusty muttered when he got no response from her, and he turned to me. “Whisper, you’re with me. Whatever happens, keep up!”

Despite my concerns, I gave a quick nod.

Dusty took a deep breath, then called out to Emerald. “Suppressing fire!”

Emerald had propped herself up enough to see out the window, and the gem of her rifle flashed as thin lines of light snapped in the air, sending out small clouds of cinders from the distant house. Dusty popped off several rounds, and then went up and over the windowsill, galloping away. My heart hammered with a fresh surge of adrenaline as I leaped after him, leaving the relative safety of the building behind.

We galloped across the street, my lungs already protesting at the dust-choked air. We passed the remains of the mare and her heavy, raider-styled armor, and moved to the wall of the saloon. Dusty led us down along the line of buildings, most of which were merely collapsed ruins. Rather than focusing on the house ahead of us, his attention was focused to our left, on the buildings we were passing. The ruins seemed to offer few places to hide, but he wasn’t taking chances. I mimicked him, looking for additional threats.

When the snaps of Emerald’s magical energy rifle fell silent, Dusty dropped down to a trot, firing off a couple rounds towards the house. I slowed and did the same. I was sure I had no chance of hitting anything like that, between the trotting and my panting. I just wanted to keep that pony’s head down.

A thin line of light flashed between the two buildings, and Dusty broke into a gallop once more. I followed, becoming increasingly aware of the weight of equipment bouncing and jostling around me. My leg was aching again, despite the magic I had spent in subtly altering and reinforcing the bone and muscles there.

We hooked around to the side of the house, closing the final gap from the side, where that upstairs window couldn’t see us. I nearly collapsed when we halted beside the house. I struggled to control my breathing. Dusty merely looked a little winded, his chest steadily expanding and contracting as he kept his rifle leveled, unwavering, at the corner before us.

He gave me about ten seconds before stepping back to crouch beside me. He lifted a forehoof to hold his rifle in place as he released the bit, and quietly spoke to me. “Load a fresh mag. When we go in, I want you to stay right on my tail. Just don’t shoot me in the flank, got it?”

“Yeah,” I said in what I hoped didn’t sound too much like a gasp. I swapped the magazine in my weapon with one from my pouch, which had grown considerably lighter than it had been just a few short minutes earlier.

Dusty reloaded as well, his motions slow and deliberate. He gave me a few more seconds, then he rose up and prowled forward like a predator, his body staying perfectly level as he moved.

I followed.

The snaps of Emerald’s rifle fell silent by the time we rounded the corner of the house. Dusty slowed as he approached a window, stepping up close to it, his rifle held low. Then he surged forward, his rifle coming up to point inside. He moved to the side, sweeping his view around, then moved past it, his rifle pointing toward the door we were approaching.

The whole way, I kept glancing down at the ground. I was certain that, at any moment, we would find another mine.

Inside the house, I could hear a stallion’s voice, muffled through the walls, but fast and urgent.

When we reached the door, Dusty paused, then surged forward again, his gun tracking the inside of the house as he moved from one side of the door to the other. The muzzle swept over everywhere he looked, including, I was thankful to see, the ground. Satisfied that we weren’t walking straight into a mine, he moved quickly and smoothly through the door. I followed right on his tail, rather less smoothly.

The stairs up were just inside the door, and Dusty led the way up, his rifle focused on the doorway at their top. The voice was coming from upstairs, and was much clearer.

“...fucking dumbass, they killed Chatter!” There was a pause as Dusty continued up, halting just below the level of the upper floor. “‘Cause she’s got a fucking army with her, that’s why! One of ‘em’s got power armor or some shit. We ain’t got nothin’ to deal with fucking power armor!”

Dusty glanced at me as I came to a halt beside him, my rifle leveled at the doorway. He gave a quick nod, and dipped his head down to one of the pouches on his barding.

“Yeah, no shit!” the voice angrily shouted. “I shot her in the head! It didn’t do a goddess-fucking thing except piss them all off, and they’re turning this building into fucking Swiss cheese! ...Yes, the one with the fucking holes you retarded shit-for-brains!”

Dusty’s head rose up, a grenade clutched in his teeth. He gripped it with his hooves, looking to the doorway, and pulled the pin.

I stared at it with mounting tension as he just held onto it. I wanted him to throw it. I willed him to throw it, for all the good it did.

“Brahminshit!” the stallion in the next room shouted; his was still the only voice we had heard. “What kind of shopkeeper runs around with a small army and a fucking Steel Ranger?”

Dusty’s ears pinned back, and he swung his hoof around, arcing the grenade through the door.

“Well you fucking tell Boomer if she wants that green bitch dead, she needs to get the whole fucking gang and every fucking bomb we’ve got before they kill every one of—FUCK—”

The building shook with the explosion, pounding at my head and chest, and sending a cascade of dust and grit falling over us. I realized Dusty was already moving, and I scrambled after him.

I passed through the doorway just in time to see Dusty put two rounds into the sprawled and dust-caked raider lying on the floor. The clack of his rifle echoed sharply in the small space, even over the sharp hum in my ears. The raider didn’t even twitch, and Dusty was already moving past him to another doorway. We swept through the room without pause, then another, before returning to the first.

“We’re clear up here,” Dusty said, returning to the downed raider. The floorboards just a couple feet away were shattered; the grenade had punched a small hole down to the floor below, and torn up everything around it, raider included.

The raider himself was clad in heavy metal armor that was wrapped in ragged bits of cloth, and sporting a good number of pouches. He was missing most of his face thanks to the bullets Dusty had put into his skull, but I could see goggles and a face-wrap tangled up in the remains. A banged-up bolt-action rifle lay beside him.

“Watch the stairs,” Dusty said as he stepped over the raider, staring down at him. I turned my attention back the way we came, pulling the stock of my rifle in tight again.

Several seconds passed before Dusty suddenly spoke. “There you are.” He dipped down, retrieving something, though I kept my attention focused on the stairs. In the corner of my vision, I saw him fiddling with whatever it was he had found. That lasted for several seconds before he grumbled. “Damn it.” He shoved the object into a pouch, then spoke up. “Let’s get back to the others.”

He led us down the stairs and out, heading across the open field at a steady trot.

As we were returning, I could see Sickle had made it back to our building, though she now lay on her side. Starlight was at her side, and looked to be speaking to her, though Sickle showed no sign of replying. As we drew nearer, I saw her reach out to shake Sickle’s shoulders, or at least try to. Still no response.

Emerald was staring down at the healing potion she held in her hooves, her expression sad. After several seconds, she caught Starlight’s attention, and held out the bottle. Starlight took it and managed to unlatch Sickle’s muzzle, shoving the bottle into her mouth.

I was climbing in through the window after Dusty when Sickle groaned, rolling onto her back. Emerald retrieved some of the magic-laced bandages and offered them to Starlight, who grabbed them in her magic and hurried to Sickle’s rear.

“You’re still bleeding,” Starlight noted as she went to work. Given the amount of blood coating her belly, legs, and groin, and the amount pooled on the floor, I had to wonder how much she had left to lose.

Sickle grunted, her head rolling drowsily to the side. Her words were slow and slurred. “Yeah. Had a mine go off under my ass. Cheap fucking trick…”

Dusty approached, quickly appraising the scene before stepping in. “Let me handle that,” he said, stepping in to take one of the bandages. “You’re the salvage expert, right? Think you can get this thing working?”

He’d fished out the object he had retrieved from the sniper-raider, and I immediately recognized it.

Starlight took it in her magic, peering at it. “A broadcaster? With… what, they wired a spark battery directly into it? What the hell did they do to this thing?”

“I don’t know,” Dusty said as he pressed the bandages into place; Sickle’s bare groin and rear were a mess of gashes, and while the healing potion had stopped most of the bleeding, some of the larger cuts were still leaking. “Just see if you can get it working. The raider who had it was talking to somepony. I want to listen in if they say anything else.”

“Oh, good idea,” Starlight said, sitting down and pulling out tools. “I’ll see what I can do.”

Dusty packed the magical bandages over the worst wounds, then used some mundane bandages to hold them in place. As he was tying the first one off, he noticed my attention. “Eyes out, Whisper. You’re our lookout right now.”

I nodded and turned away, scanning over the view outside those windows, while trying to ignore what was happening right behind me.

My concern was alleviated to a degree when Sickle started to giggle, and eventually mumbled, “You’re just looking for any excuse to get between my legs, ain’t ‘cha, Dusty?”

“Just keep telling yourself that,” Dusty quietly replied, earning a chuckle from both Sickle and Starlight.

There was a rattle of armor as Sickle moved, then the sound of her armored saddle-bags opening, followed by Dusty’s sigh. “Just don’t overdo it.”

“Yeah, yeah,” Sickle weakly replied over the sound of pills rattling in their bottles. A few seconds later there was a louder rattle as she struggled up to a sitting position. I saw Dusty was helping her.

“You okay?” he asked, once she was upright.

She groaned, leaning heavily on the window sill. “The buck and painkillers say yes. Woo…” I glanced over as she chuckled faintly, licking over her lips. A few bits of former-raider were still stuck to her snout.

While she giggled quietly to herself, Dusty moved up to the window as well. With a second set of eyes, I took a momentary break to look back to Emerald. She was lying down with her foreleg held against her chest. Her brows were furrowed as she panted shallowly, though her expression softened when she saw me looking. She coughed, swallowed, and spoke up. “I think I’ve changed my mind.”

Dusty looked back. “What’s that?”

“About going with you,” she said, then shook her head. “I mean, to fight the raiders. I… I think this was enough fighting for me.”

Dusty frowned, but nodded. “I understand. Afraid you’re kind of in the middle of it, though. If those two ponies are still alive, we don’t have time to head back and make another try at it.”

“Oh, no, no,” Emerald said, raising a hoof to wave off the comment, then wincing and tucking her leg back against her side. “You all go on without me, those ponies need you. I’ll just wait behind for you.”

“Can’t do that,” Dusty said. “We’re in raider territory.”

“I’ll go back to the farm,” she quickly said. “I can wait for you there.”

“You’re not safe anywhere outside of town,” Dusty said, then pointed to Starlight and the broadcaster she was working on. “Those raiders were gunning for you. Boomer wants you dead, and we’re not leaving you unguarded.”

Emerald’s expression went slack. “Me? But… why?”

“Don’t know,” Dusty said. “I intend to find out, but until we deal with them, they’re going to be looking for you, and I don’t intend to leave you unprotected.”

“Amber,” Emerald muttered. “She must have…” She shook her head. “Doesn’t matter. Look, I… I’ll go back to town and wait for you where we made the, uh, second deal. If the raiders come looking for me, I’ll run for the gates. I’ll probably be safer there than I will getting into another fight.”

Sickle rumbled quietly. “Chickenshit.”

“Yeah, I am,” Emerald quickly replied. “And I’m not going, but you all need to if you’re going to save those ponies.”

Her eyes glanced to me, and I realized I was frowning as I tried to piece together her reasoning. I had one thing absolutely correct: this was not a sudden bout of cowardice.

Dusty was shaking his head. “You’re talking about a day-long trip through raider territory, even if you weren’t cradling your leg like that.”

“This is nothing,” she said, giving a pained smile, and wiggled her PipBuck-clad hoof. “Just a bruised rib. I’ll be fine as soon as I catch my breath.”

Dusty’s frown deepened as he mulled it over, and I looked to him. While I didn’t like it, I was willing to go with whatever he decided.

Emerald continued to hold her smile.

Then she twitched, and Dusty’s ears perked up, his brows furrowing as he looked at her.

“I’m fine,” she reassured him. She swallowed, then twitched again, the faint, full-body convulsion of somepony trying to hide a cough.

Dusty stepped forward, his expression abruptly business-like. “What’s wrong?”

“Nothing,” Emerald said, though I could hear the rising fear in her voice. “Just really sore from—”

Her words were cut off as she clenched again, her body shaking several times before she couldn’t hold it back any more and let out a couple of coughs. They were short, weak, and wet.

Dusty moved to her side, fixing her with a stare. “Okay, now it’s an order. Tell me what’s wrong.”

“Nothing,” she repeated, choking back a couple more coughs. Tears were forming in the corners of her eyes. “Just go.”

“Damnit,” Dusty muttered as he sat in front of her, his hooves reaching for her side. “We had a deal, Emerald.”

“No!” Emerald’s legs kicked out, trying to swat his hooves away as he grabbed at the strap of her saddlebags. “I’ll be fine, just go without me! Stop!”

I wavered; hearing Emerald’s pained cries of protests as she struggled wildly against Dusty’s grip was deeply disconcerting, enough that I started to question what Dusty was doing.

Then he froze for a moment, his eyes widening. He tugged at the strap across her belly, working past her struggles, and as she cried out, pulled away the saddlebag with its tiny, overlooked bullet hole. The underside was soaked with blood.

“Shit!” Dusty snapped, and threw the bags out of the way to grab at the straps of her barding. “Damnit, Emerald, you don’t hide shit like this!”

“Please, don’t,” she sobbed, her panting growing ever faster, mixing with increasingly wet coughs. Her struggles had fallen off to weak gestures. “Just go. Leave me. Save Quartz and Flint.”

Dusty ignored her, and I found myself moving in to help him undo the buckles of her barding. A final strap came undone, and Dusty pulled back the side of her barding. It peeled away from her side.

The barding had done a good job of containing the blood. Her entire side was soaked in it, from shoulder to flank. She sobbed softly, and each cough produced a little surge of blood from the tiny hole in her side.

“Fuck,” Dusty blurted, then grabbed my hoof, pressing it over the hole, I almost drew back from the surge of warm blood that met me, but Dusty barked, “Pressure!”

While I pressed on the wound, trying fruitlessly to stem the flow of blood, he grabbed at her foreleg and the PipBuck clasped to it. “Let me see,” he said, his voice much softer, though his grip was firm when she tried to pull it away. “Easy,” he said, his other hoof moving to her neck. “We’ll take care of this.”

She whined and coughed under my hooves. “Please… just go…”

Dusty ignored her, except to give a reassuring stroke along her neck. His other hoof poked at the PipBuck, switching to its medical display. I was a bit too far away to make out what it said, but still close enough to see the several flashing warnings it was giving.

“It’s okay,” Emerald said, giving a weak smile. “You can’t save me. I know.” A short fit of coughing interrupted her. “But you can still save Quartz and Flint. Please, just go.”

Dusty ignored her. He stared at the PipBuck screen for a few more seconds, then turned to push my hoof away, taking my place. “Starlight! Sniper house. Whisper! Street and saloon. Search those raiders for medical supplies. Go!”

I turned and ran, leaving bloody hoof-prints in the dirt. I slid to a halt at the raider Sickle had killed, ignoring the pulped remains of what had once been her head to rifle through the few pockets and pouches her crude armor had. I found water, dried meat, and ammunition, but the closest she had to medical supplies was a bottle of mixed pills.

Leaving her, I ran to the saloon. I didn’t pause to take in the devastation of the ruined main room. I bound and scrambled up the torn-up stairs, having to haul myself up the last bit to the top floor, and made my way to the room the raiders had been shooting at us from.

The third raider was half embedded in the floor, in what I presume was a result of Sickle stomping him. He wore remarkably thick metal barding with spikes protruding from the back, for all the good it had done him. I searched through his pouches, and then the saddlebags I spotted near the window. The only medical supplies I found was a single magic-laced bandage. I grabbed it my my teeth, turned, and ran.

I vaulted down the stairs, ignoring the flash of pain in my leg upon landing, and burst out the front doors. I was panting hard when I finally got back inside, sliding to a halt in the loose grit scattered on the floor.

Dusty had our final magical bandage pressed against her side, but it was already completely soaked through. Sickle sat nearby, watching silently. The containers at her side were open, and a variety of drugs were set on the floor before her.

The moment Dusty saw the bandage in my mouth, he snatched it, pressing it to the wound.

“Don’t,” Emerald protested, tensing up for a moment before laying her head down again. She was still panting hard, but increasingly shallowly. “Save… save it. It’s not… it’s not going to work.”

She trailed off, and ten seconds later, the new bandage was just as soaked as the old one.

There was a clatter of hooves as Starlight returned, Dusty and I looked up, only to be met with her worried look and a quick shake of her head.

I sat beside Emerald’s head as Dusty tried to stem the bleeding. I could hear the wet, raspy sounds of her breath as she gasped for air, and I gently placed my hoof on the side of her neck to offer what meager comfort I could give. She blinked a few times, lifting her head, then coughing and setting it down again. It took her a few blinks to finally focus on me, and once she had, tears started to well up in her eyes. Tiny flecks of blood dotted her lips.

“Please,” she gasped, weakly lifting a hoof in my direction. “...Leave me. Leave me…”

It wasn’t until later that I realized I had misheard her. At the time, looking down on that expression of pain and fear, I had thought she was afraid we would leave her to die alone. The alternative made no sense. Not yet.

So I took the hoof she had raised in my own, giving it a squeeze, and attempted to reassure her. “We’re here,” I said, soothing. “We’re not going to leave you.”

The tears started to flow, her ears pinning back as she stared up at me. The look of pain in her eyes was far more than just physical. She looked terrified, sobbing to me, “Don’t… don’t tell them—”

She was interrupted by another fit of coughing, and ended with her head slumped to the ground, eyes half-lidded. “...Don’t tell them…”

I leaned in, stroking at her neck as I squeezed her hoof again. I wanted to keep her talking. “Don’t tell who what?”

She coughed again, only weakly. “A-about me,” she gasped. Another cough. “D-don’t… don’t tell…”

She trailed off, giving a few incoherent mumbles as her eyes shut. As she fell silent, the pace of her breathing changed. It was weak, and so shallow that her chest barely moved.

“What about you?” I asked, but she didn’t answer. Her hoof had gone limp in my grasp. I released it, my hooves cradling her head to angle her face up. My heart was hammering again. “Emerald, stay with me. Don’t tell them what about you?”

“Keep her talking,” Dusty called out.

“I’m trying!” I gripped her head, leaning in close. “Emerald? Emerald! Wake up. Don’t tell them what about you?”

“Shit,” Dusty muttered beside me. As I tried to get her to wake up, he looked over the PipBuck screen again. “Damnit… Whisper! Give her a hit of Dash.”

I set her head down, immediately following his order and snatching up one of the inhalers laid out before Sickle. “Are you sure that’s a good idea?” I asked, even as I popped off the cap and pressed the nozzle into her mouth.

“It’s a terrible idea,” Dusty said, glaring down at the PipBuck. “But it’s all we’ve got.”

I pressed down on the inhaler, sending a spray of the drug into her mouth. She twitched, then gave a phlegmy cough as her body jerked in response to the powerful stimulant. Her eyes fluttered open, but they didn’t focus. “N-no,” she wheezed. Her gaze weaved around, her eyes unseeing. “It w-was real… all… all real…”

Already, her eyes were closing again, her body going limp.

“See if you can get her to take some Buck,” Dusty said.

Though I figured it was said out of desperation, I turned back to the assortment of chems. I searched for a moment before Sickle lifted a hoof to indicate a bottle. Snatching it up, I retrieved one of the thick tablets.

Sickle spoke quietly. “She’s done.”

“No she’s not!” I reflexively replied, lifting Emerald’s head a bit to open her mouth and slid the tablet in. “Emerald, I need you to swallow this. It’ll help.”

Of course, she didn’t respond. She was completely limp again, her eyes half-shut and unresponsive. I glanced at the screen of her PipBuck. More warnings had shown up, and the vital signs were steadily diminishing.

I gave her a gentle shake. “Come on, Emerald. Talk to me.”

Nothing.

I looked back to Dusty. “What do we do?”

He just stared down at the PipBuck and slowly shook his head. His hooves lifted from the sodden bandages, and rested on softly on her side.

My ears fell. I wanted to protest, to do something, but I couldn’t. There wasn’t anything to be done. So I sat there, watching the PipBuck screen, knowing what was coming.

Time passed slowly, agonizingly. Numbers I didn’t quite understand slowly changed on the medical display; mostly, they marched steadily downward. Several words, mostly starting with hypo- or tachy-, flashed red on the screen.

Then a larger warning flashed, clear and dominant on the screen: respiratory arrest. Just a few seconds later, another warning joined the first: cardiac arrest. The eyes of the cute little cartoon pony on the medical screen turned to ‘x’s.

Dusty’s lowered his head. Starlight sniffled.

Myself, I stared down at Emerald, my ears hanging low. I just sat there, watching, and waiting, and dreading.

And seconds later, the green flames flashed across her form, revealing the glossy black beneath.

Chapter Twenty Five: Serenity

I murmured and rolled to my side, pulling my thick blankets in tight as I nestled into the plush softness of my bed. It was so warm and comfy that I just wanted to stay snuggled up there all day long.

I made a good attempt at it, but consciousness was unrelenting. Eventually, I pushed back the pile of blankets and slowly stretched, yawning as I met the day. I’d slept well past dawn, and the sun lit my cozy bedroom brightly. I must have been quite exhausted to have slept in so late, but for the life of me, I just couldn’t place what I might have been doing.

Maybe I had just stayed up late. That was probably it.

I rolled over to the edge of my bed, reflecting on how it was really too large for just a single pony. Maybe Starlight should be there? No, she had her own house. Still, it was quite large enough for a visit...

My hooves set down on the thick carpet, and I took a moment to enjoy the soft feeling, combined with the warmth of the sun flowing over my side. They were such simple pleasures, so easily available, yet I soaked them in as if it had been ages since I’d enjoyed their comfort.

With a smile, I turned and slowly walked past the end table and dresser, to approach the broad window. I stood my front hooves on the sill, soaking in the sun, and looked out at Serenity.

My home was situated on a loop, and from my second-story window, I could see all the houses that lined that loop, with their spacious yards and lush gardens. The street continued off from the loop, leading to the rest of our pleasant little town of some thirty homes and a hoofful of shops, surrounded by lush grassy hills and light forests.

I swung the window open, drawing in a deep breath of the fresh morning air. Yes, moving to Serenity was the best decision I had ever made.

I couldn’t really remember making that decision, but I must have done so to be there, and that was the important part.

Shutting the window, I turned back to my room. I looked over at the closet, and gave a cursory glance over the contents. I had a good collection of dresses and accessories, after all, and it kind of seemed like a shame to not use them. As I looked through them, I found myself coming up empty. I could have sworn I had a particular cloak, but I couldn’t find it. I know it wouldn’t have matched anything else I had, and it was far more practical than fashionable, but it was disappointing to not find it. I knew I had it. I must have simply misplaced it when unpacking.

Deciding against wearing anything, I made my way to the door. I was nearing the stairs when I heard quiet voices drifting up from below.

I had guests? I didn’t remember having guests, but I couldn’t imagine anyone sneaking in just to chat in my living room. They must be guests, after all. Still, I paused. Snooping in on conversations really is rude, but I couldn’t help it. There was something wonderfully mischievous about it that just seemed so appealing.

“...longer than usual, but it shouldn’t be a problem.” The voice was male, with a rich tone that struck me as handsome. I couldn’t picture that voice coming from anything but an incredibly attractive stallion.

Another voice sounded, this one female, with a delicate and clear tone that sounded equally pretty. “Control would say so. They’re not the ones who have to wait in here.”

“They’re waiting just like us,” the stallion said, with an inflection that seemed like the auditory equivalent of rolling his eyes. “It’s not like they’re able to just kick back and relax like we are. Someone has to monitor the data. They’re still not sure why she isn’t awake yet. Medical insists she’s fit.”

“Fit, except for sleeping for thirteen hours. I’m starting to wonder if she’s ever going to wake up. Control said the brain activity was weird. What if she’s got brain damage?”

There was a long pause before the stallion spoke again. “No, Control says they’re sure it’s not brain damage. They say the brain activity is weird, but familiar. They’ll figure it out.”

“Mmm, good for them,” the mare said with a sigh. “I’m bored of waiting. I’m going to see if they thought to stock any drinks. Care to join me?”

There was a huff of amusement from the stallion, but he agreed, and I heard them moving to the kitchen.

Had I taken a physical when I moved here? That must be it. It still seemed weird, but that made sense. I sighed and started down the stairs to join my guests. It seemed like the proper thing to do.

And yet…

I could easily avoid them. It seemed like such a sneaky thing to do, slipping out on guests that I must have invited, but I felt in far too good of a mood to bog things down with medical discussions.

But more importantly, it seemed so mischievous and exciting, like I’d be getting away with something I shouldn’t.

I stepped back to the landing, returning to my room. I could easily fly out from my bedroom window without them ever knowing I was up.

Oh, I wouldn’t let them wait too long. I had still invited them over—probably—and I didn’t want to be rude by completely neglecting them. I just wanted to get out and enjoy the morning a bit, first. A pleasant stroll through the lush park under those clear skies and warm sun seemed so…

The first word that came to mind was “rare”, but that wasn’t right. Serenity was scheduled for warm, clear weather most days. I settled on “pleasant”, even if the word seemed somehow insufficient.

I stepped up to the window, swinging it open, then hesitated. I wasn’t entirely sure why. Sure, I was a changeling, but Serenity was a place of friendship, love, and tolerance. They wouldn’t care if I was a changeling, or a griffin, or even a zebra. So why was I disguised? I must have had a good reason. I looked down at my chest, raising a leg to run a hoof through the thick fluff of my chest. Not only was I disguised, I was disguised in the wrong form! Why had I shortened my mane and tail, and thickened my coat? It was far too pleasant of a day to need that much insulation.

The weather must have been bad before. Yes, it had been cold and rainy, that was it. But not here. Serenity had been scheduled for sunny days with the rare shower. It must have been before I arrived, and I simply hadn’t bothered to change yet. Yes, that was it.

It was only as I went to remove my disguise that I realized I was dangerously low on love. It was far too little to squander on transformation. I was tempted to strip my current disguise to save energy, but I had kept myself disguised for a reason, and while I couldn’t remember what that reason was, I was certain it was a good one. No matter; I knew exactly where to go to get love.

With flying off the table, I instead climbed out the window, moving silently to the edge of the roof. It was just a short drop down to the soft grass below; I’d made more strenuous leaps before.

It did seem a little silly, sneaking out of my own home, but I couldn’t deny that it was exciting.

After a quick brush-down to ensure my thick coat was lying smoothly, I casually trotted off around the loop.

It really was a nice neighborhood. Willow and Rose’s garden was in full bloom, gracing their yard with a rainbow of colors. At the next house over, Ricochet, one of Serenity’s griffin residents, was maneuvering a small cloud to water her lawn. We exchanged a quick wave as she swooped around, and I had the sudden desire to fly up in the air, banking and looping around without a care in the world.

The next house was Strawberry’s. She was out in the yard, working on the fence. The old fence must have needed replacing, judging by the way she bucked one of the posts, snapping it off. She noticed me passing by, and called out to me.

“What the fuck are you smiling at? You enjoying this shit, you brain-dead little cunt? Or do you need someone to go over there and fuck-start your head?”

Strawberry has such a colorful way with words. I smiled and gave a little wave as I continued on.

She responded with a snarl as she bucked down the rest of the fence. “Pull your head out of your ass and get a clue, Whisper! You retarded little shit!”

I trotted on with a light step, thinking that I really should take the time to pay Strawberry a proper visit. Maybe I could do that after meeting with my guests. As mischievous as it was sneaking out on them, I couldn’t let them wait too long. That would just be mean.

Starlight’s house was just a few doors down. I was just passing the house of her neighbor, Flay, when her front door opened. I halted, turning to admire the lilac bush at the corner of Flay’s lawn. I wasn’t quite certain why I did that. It was unobtrusive, something that would be unlikely to be noticed, and it let me watch the earth pony couple that exited Starlight’s house without being obvious about watching them.

I wasn’t sure why I wanted to watch them, but it seemed like the right thing to do. It was certainly better than going up to a pair of strangers and asking them why they were leaving my friend’s house.

It was another mare and stallion pair. They gave cheerful goodbyes and waves as they exited. I could barely make out what the mare said after the door shut.

“She’s certainly the most promising of this lot.”

In the corner of my eye, I could see the stallion nod as they walked toward the street. “That she is. If she loves this ‘Whisper’ as much as she seems to, we should be…”

I waited, listening in for a couple more seconds before I realized they weren’t there. I blinked, looking around, but there was no sign of them. Even more strange, I couldn’t quite place what had happened. I’d been watching them in the corner of my eye, and listening to them talk. I had seen them at one point, then a couple of seconds later I realized I didn’t see them, but I had no memory of them actually leaving.

A creeping feeling ran through my spine. Something wasn’t quite right, and my mind spun as I focused on this new problem, attacking it like some new puzzle. I couldn’t just miss something like that while observing a pair of ponies. If one of them were a unicorn, I would have guessed they used some sort of magic on me. Instead, I was left with the possibility that my perception was compromised. I could recall how muddled my perceptions were after waking up from two hundred years in a cocoon, or the concerningly rising number of times I may have suffered a concussion.

Or maybe I was just more hungry than I thought.

I blinked. The creeping sense of wrongness grew even more as I tried to correlate these seemingly impossible flashes of memory. It was maybe twenty years since I hatched, not two hundred, and in any case, I’d never been in a cocoon. Strawberry would have never tried to kill me, and I absolutely, positively, under no circumstances, had ever been blown up. Not even a tiny bit. I’d had a nice peaceful life in Equestria, among friendly and loving ponies, and that had only gotten better once I had moved to Serenity.

I was losing my mind. That was the solution that came screaming to the forefront of my mind, until I shook the thoughts away. I’d just been sleeping for more than half a day. I must be remembering dreams. Yes, that’s it. The gray skies, the barren, dusty land, the flashes of blood; it was all just a nightmare, and now I was awake.

Suppressing a shiver, I walked up to Starlight’s door.

Moments after knocking, the door opened to reveal Starlight, and her expression lit up the moment she saw me. “Whisper!”

Her forelegs wrapped me in a crushing hug, and her mouth met mine, delivering an eager and energetic kiss that I, after a moment of surprise, happily returned.

It was a blissful moment, tempered only by a single flaw; while I could feel Starlight’s love, it seemed surprisingly distant. Not weak, mind you; it was nice and strong, but it felt as if I were trying to feed from across a room.

One more factoid pointing to possible brain trauma. I was starting to think I should really go meet with those guests of mine.

I must have given away some sign of my inner thoughts, as Starlight stepped back from the kiss, a brow cocked curiously. “You, uh…” Her eyes glanced downward, and she smirked. “Trying out a new look, huh?”

“Oh!” I looked down at myself again. “Right, that. I guess I forgot to change at some point, and now I’m a little low on love…”

She chuckled softly, stepping back. “Well, why don’t you come in instead of just standing in the doorway? I’m sure we can fix your little problem.”

I gave a weak chuckle as well, stepping in and turning to shut the door behind me. The moment I did so, Starlight pressed against me, sending me staggering and falling onto the couch. She was above me in an instant, giggling, then lowered her head to nuzzle firmly against my chest. “Mmm, so fluffy!”

“This look does have its advantages,” I said, raising a hoof to rub at her shoulder. “Though it may be a bit too warm for the current weather.”

“Well let’s get you some love before you overheat,” she said, smirking as she slid up, her mouth meeting mine again. Her hooves gripped at my side, her breath quickening as her body pressed and rubbed against mine. It was exciting, exhilarating, and it took a force of will to press my hoof against her chest, gently pressing her back a bit.

She drew her head back, blinking in confusion. That confusion immediately turned to concern as she saw the fear that had overtaken my expression. “Whisper? What’s wrong?”

“I… I think there’s something wrong with me.” I said, slowly shaking my head. “I can barely feed. It’s there, I just… I can’t get at it.” I shook my head, swallowing. “I’ve been getting flashes of memories that make no sense, and I can’t even tell they’re wrong, except they contradict everything else I remember. And then, just a few minutes ago, I… I must have zoned out. I was watching a couple of ponies, and I didn’t even realize they’d left until they were out of sight. I don’t even remember the time passing, I…”

“Woah, easy,” Starlight said, her hooves gripping at my shoulders. I was shivering. “Take it easy. Maybe… maybe we should get you to the clinic? You’ve taken a lot of blows to the head, maybe you’ve got a concussion. That would explain things, right?”

The shivering stopped as I looked wide-eyed up at her. “...I have? The blows to the head, I mean.”

“A bit more than I’d like, yeah,” she said, giving an awkward smile. “Heck, last time you kinda got…”

She trailed off, blinking, and a weight dropped in my gut.

“Were you about to say ‘blown up’?”

“Yeah,” she said, sitting back and staring off into space. “I don’t know why. You couldn’t have been blown up. I mean, I know you play with explosives a lot, but—” She blinked again. “Wait a minute, when the hell did you get explosives?”

“We found them,” I replied automatically.

She blinked a couple more times, then shook her head. “No, no. That’s not right. It must have been a—”

“Dream,” I finished for her, and she froze, mirroring my own look of concern.

I thought for a moment, scrambling for stray thoughts. My ears perked up. “A land mine. Do you remember a land mine?”

Her hoof moved to her neck, her eyes widening for a moment, but she quickly shook her head. “N-no. I remember a dream, but… no, where would we have ever ran into a land mine? But… but you remember it, too?” Her ears pinned back, and she looked around. “Oh, shit. Are we dreaming?” She looked back to me. “Wait, if I’m dreaming, are you even real?”

“We’re not dreaming,” I said, pushing myself up to a more upright position. “But something isn’t right. Something’s messing with our heads.”

“Oh, Luna,” Starlight murmured, her hoof moving to her head. “Am I going insane? What’s going on?”

“I don’t know, but we need to figure it out.” I sat up, reaching out to grip Starlight by the shoulders. “What do you remember? How did we get here?”

“Emerald’s PipBuck,” she answered. Then her ears drooped. “Oh, no. Emerald. Did she really…”

I swallowed around the lump that tried to form in my throat. My brain was telling me that what I remembered couldn’t be true, that I could have never witnessed another pony dying like that, but it was clear I couldn’t trust my own memories. My own mind was working against me.

That was a problem. I knew how good I was at telling a lie.

I shook off the thought. “And why did we come to Serenity?”

“Because it’s such a nice place,” Starlight said, shuddering. “And you thought you might find—”

She froze again, her eyes widening. “...Your family.” Her shoulders heaved as her breathing accelerated. “Changelings.”

I nodded. Yes, that sounded familiar.

“Changelings,” Starlight murmured. “Changelings make themselves look like something they’re not.” She looked around the room. “Oh, Luna, goddesses, is any of this—”

She jumped and yelped loudly at the knock on her door. As she clamped her hooves over her mouth, a smooth-spoken stallion’s voice called from outside.

“Miss Starlight? Are you okay?”

She lowered her hooves to shout back. “I’m fine!”

“Can we come in?”

Starlight scrambled to the window, peering out. “Just a second!” She leaned in close to me, quickly whispering. “It’s the welcoming committee, again. I don’t know why they’re back. Are they changelings, too?”

I looked around, quickly trying to form a plan. I could practically feel my grip on the situation slipping as my mind told me everything was fine. “I’m going to hide. Let them in, see what they want. Just don’t tell them I’m here.”

She trembled, staring at me as if she feared she’d never see me again. “W-why?”

Giving my best reassuring smile, I reached up, holding her by the shoulders once more. “Sneaky bug stuff.”

The look of fear cracked as she gave a timid smile, and she nodded.

She waited until I had slipped up the stairs and out of sight before opening the door.

“Hello.” She sounded nervous. “I wasn’t expecting to see you again so soon.”

The stallion answered her. “We heard you shout. Is everything okay?”

“Uh… yeah, yeah, I’m fine. I, uh… the knock just kind of surprised me, is all.”

“Is something wrong?” the stallion asked. I could faintly hear the sound of hooves as he stepped inside. “You know, we’re here to help you. Why don’t you tell us what’s bothering you and we can help out.”

“Oh. Yeah.” The nervousness had vanished from Starlight’s voice. “Sorry, I was just feeling a little freaked out.”

A mare’s voice spoke up. “Why don’t you tell us what’s bothering you? I’m sure we’ll be able to help.”

“I’m not really sure how to describe it,” Starlight said. “It’s like… I’m remembering things, but they don’t make sense. Like, guns and fighting, and… ruins. And there were explosions, and… a land mine. And I remember Whisper was there.”

I winced at my name, fearing what she might say next.

“And… and it all feels like a dream, but I know it wasn’t. It was too real, but how could it be real? It doesn’t—”

“It’s okay,” the stallion said, cutting her off. “You must be remembering your term in the Army. That’s what it is.”

“I… was in the Army?”

“For a very short while, yes. You were just given a medical discharge. It was nothing serious, but I guess you got knocked around a bit if you’re having trouble remembering. It’ll clear up on its own in a few days, but you might want to pay a visit to the clinic. A little medical magic will help speed up your recovery.”

There was a moment of silence, followed by a faint chuckle. “Oh, that… that makes a lot of sense, actually. Sorry about that.”

“No need to apologize,” the stallion replied. “Stress can have a tremendous impact on a pony, and especially our soldiers, but it’s something we’ve become quite adept at diagnosing and treating. A couple days of confusion is completely normal. You can ask your neighbors. Several of them came from similar backgrounds, and they’ve gone through the same thing you have.”

“That’s a bit of a relief, yeah,” Starlight said. “It’s still, you know, just a little freaky not remembering stuff like that, but… but yeah, it’s kinda coming back. Sorry. I feel a little silly now, freaking out like that.”

“Please, don’t worry about it. We’re here to help you. Was there anything else bothering you?”

“No, that was it. Thank you. I… I think I’ll head down to the clinic in a bit. Seriously, thank you.”

The mare answered, sounding pleased. “It’s what we’re here for.”

They said their goodbyes, and moments later the door shut again. I crept down the stairs, until I could see Starlight giving a slow, deep sigh. She turned and smiled as I made my way down.

“Are you okay?” I asked, and she grinned.

“Yeah. Sorry about all that. You know, you should have stayed. Ponies are going to think you’re weird if you keep hiding any time somepony comes by.”

She stepped in, nuzzling under my chin, but I leaned back. “I’d say we have more important things to worry about. We need to figure out what’s messing with our heads, and I’m pretty sure those ponies are in on it.”

“Don’t worry about it,” Starlight said with a chuckle. “Those two were with the welcoming committee, they were just here to help. And the whole ‘head’ thing was just stress messing with us.”

I froze as she gave back the story those ponies had fed her, and she slipped in again, nuzzling. “Starlight, this isn’t stress. Those memories, they’re real, but they don’t fit with everything else. Something is messing with our heads.”

“It’s just the stress,” Starlight repeated, and chuckled. “I can’t believe I’d forgotten we were in the Army, but that explains where all that shooting and explosions came from. It’s all coming back now.” She drew back, looking me in the eyes with a look of sudden realization. “That’s where we met, wasn’t it?”

I stared at her, heart hammering. The Army made so much sense; I could remember fighting alongside her. Dusty and Strawberry were there, too. Were they in uniform? Yes, Dusty was. But I couldn’t remember if the others were. Why else would we be fighting? The idea of serving, of following a mission, that sounded completely right. The Army was the only way that made sense.

With a shudder, I pushed away the thoughts. I already knew someone was messing with my mind. I couldn’t trust my own memories. I couldn’t trust my own mind.

To say that was a problem is quite the understatement. The mind is an Infiltrator’s best weapon.

An Infiltrator. I wasn’t a soldier. I was never in the Army. I did not serve Equestria. All of this was a lie.

I took a moment to evaluate my situation, to weigh my options. It was clear that something was messing with my mind. I seemed to be forcing past it, though it was still a muddled mess. Maybe, if I was lucky, I might be able to help Starlight get through it, but she seemed far too quick to latch onto those ponies’ story. It would be difficult. I had no idea if Dusty or Strawberry could be brought around, though from the behavior I had seen earlier, I doubted Strawberry would take much convincing.

But what then? It wasn’t just enough to know the truth. If they were messing with our minds, we were vulnerable. I had no idea what kind of troubles we might face outside of this lie. I was certain this place was a lie, but I had no idea how far that lie extended. I had no idea what to expect, and therefore, no ability to plan for it. Our captors—if that’s even what was going on—had every advantage. We couldn’t fight this.

And if I couldn’t fight it, the only way to get through was to go along with it.

I put on a reassuring smile, lifting a hoof to tenderly touch Starlight’s cheek. “Yes. Yes, that’s exactly right.”

Her expression brightened up, and she leaned in, giving me another kiss. I took a few moments to enjoy the sensation before gently drawing back. “I should get back home. I have a welcoming party of my own I need to talk to.”

Starlight put on a mock-pout. “Aww.”

“Don’t worry,” I said, still wearing that smile. “I’ll see you soon.”

The smile vanished the moment I had stepped outside. My heart hammered as I walked around the loop to my own house. Strawberry was nowhere to be seen, and a pair of ponies were floating a new fence into place where the old one had been. As I passed her house, I heard the clop of hooves trotting on the street. I looked back in time to see a pair of ponies, the same two I had first seen leaving Starlight’s house, now hurrying back to her door.

As I approached the door of my own house, I could hear the muffled sounds of the ponies inside. They sounded like they were arguing.

The argument stopped the moment I opened the front door. The mare quickly set down the hoof she had been gesturing wildly with, and called out to me. “Oh, thank goodness! There you are, Whisper! You gave us quite the scare, there. Where did you disappear to?”

“I snuck out,” I said. “But now I’m back, and I’d like to talk.”

“Well, that’s what we’re here for,” the stallion said. “But you know, there’s no need to sneak around, here. Serenity is a nice, peaceful place.”

“I’m sure,” I said in a dry tone. Adrenaline teased at my senses as I took a calculated gamble. “Are you changelings?”

The mare blinked. “What? No, no changelings here. Why do you ask?”

The stallion beside her, however, effectively torpedoed her words. He stared at me, his eyes widening in dawning realization. He opened his mouth, gasping a single word. “Disconnect.”

The mare’s head turned, drawing my attention for just an instant. In that instant, I realized the stallion had vanished.

A moment later, I realized the mare had vanished, too.

I twisted around, looking this way and that, until the entire world went away.

☢

Light and sound twisted around me in an incoherent jumble. The world turned, and hooves pressed against me. I tried to move my head against the pressure that tried to hold me as up turned to down, and something soft pressed against my side. Something tugged on my forelegs, and something warm wrapped around my hooves.

Among the jumbled colors, a pale-blue orb drew my attention, though my addled brain made no sense of it until it turned to me and narrowed, mirrored by a twin just beside it. My view focused rapidly on the glossy black around them, until I could make out the expression of an angry changeling.

I jerked, adrenaline flowing. I tried to lift my head, only to find myself restrained. I tried to call out, only to produce a muffled moan; I was muzzled. More hooves gripped and pressed at my sides, and I twisted my head to see several more changelings. I was lying down, strapped to a gurney, with my legs bound with goo. The changelings were working over me. The green light of PipBuck screens shone from their forelegs. The jumble of sounds I heard were words.

“She’s regaining focus,” the angry one near my head said.

“Tertiary leads disconnected. That’s the last of it.”

“No, hold the sedative. I want her lucid.”

“Get those legs restrained. Lay it on, she’s waking up!”

“Get those guards in here.”

I twisted my head the other way. I couldn’t see much past the changelings over me. I saw one of the guards stepping up, clad in armor while a magical energy weapon floated beside her head.

“Move her.”

The gurney rocked under me as it started to roll, surrounded by changelings. I looked around with wide eyes, producing more muffled sounds as I tried to call out to them. So many changelings, so close. They were right there!

As we moved, I got a parting glimpse of the room. I was being wheeled away from a white contraption that looked as if it had split open. It took me a moment to place it as the white eggshell of a suspended animation pod, just like the discarded remains in the lab I had woken up in. More pods filled the wide room. There were dozens of them, maybe sixty in total, and I could see faces inside them.

With a lurch, I tried to search out Starlight and the others, but the door shut behind us, cutting me off.

I was rolled down a hall and into a small room, bare except for a pair of plain benches. It looked like a jail cell.

The group of changelings hauling the gurney parked me by the back wall, engaging the wheel brakes. Most stepped back, while the angry-looking one returned to look me in the face. Her horn glowed brightly, grabbing my eyelids so I couldn’t blink, and shined a light in my eyes. A few seconds later, she stepped back, addressing the pair of guards who flanked her. “She’s fully responsive. Keep a close eye on her.”

One of the soldiers grunted in reply, then addressed me, her large magical energy weapon leveled straight at me. “If you attempt any magic, we will immediately shoot and kill you. Do you understand?”

The straps made nodding difficult, but I managed.

I was there for several long, silent minutes, with only the pair of wary and suspicious guards for company. Unable to attempt conversation, I remained still. I didn’t want to test their nerves, or their reflexes.

I found myself staring at one of the soldiers. A changeling, dressed in armor much like my own, with a PipBuck on her leg. I’d found changelings! But this changeling was standing ready to kill me at a moment’s notice. As excited as I was to find changelings, I was still in an incredibly dangerous and uncertain situation.

And there was a room nearby with several dozen ponies—and other species—held in suspended animation. While I could think of a few reasons to do so, one stood out as the most likely reason a group of changelings would organize something like this, and it was a troubling one.

It would also explain why I felt so drained of love.

I must have been in that room for about five minutes before several guards entered. To my shock, two Enclave soldiers entered with them. A moment later, I realized my error. The soldiers were clad in Enclave armor, certainly, but I could see the fanged, chitinous muzzle below the armor’s visor. They were changelings wearing Enclave armor, and I noticed then that the back-plate had been painted a dark, iridescent blue, as if to mimic a changeling’s coloration.

“Move her,” one of the power-armor soldiers ordered, and the guards rolled me out on the gurney.

This journey took quite a bit longer, leading me through many halls and an elevator. The construction was rugged but refined, with reinforced metal walls, hydraulic doors, and plentiful lighting. It looked like Stable-Tec construction.

Finally, we rolled into a large room. As we were coming to a halt, a beautiful voice, rich and melodious, called out. “Release her.”

My heart hammered, while the guards stepped in, undoing the straps that held me. Moments later I was floated off and set on the ground, and the goo that bound my legs dissolved away. I got a hoof under me to push myself up, and looked in the direction of that voice.

Some twenty feet away lay a large cushion, and lying atop it was a young changeling queen, her head held in a regal pose. Flanking her were a pair of soldiers in black-painted Steel Ranger armor, much larger and bulkier than the Enclave-armored soldiers I had seen before. They stood tall and proud like statues, sporting heavy magical weapons.

The queen’s slit-pupil eyes were fixed on me, half-lidded as if bored with me. Her fanged mouth opened as she spoke again. “Lose the disguise.”

I gulped, well aware of the many guards around me, and tugged at the strings of my magic. My flames stripped away my disguise, leaving me in my natural form—minus my armor, which I kept concealed for now.

The queen continued to stare at me for several long seconds, those bright green eyes silently judging me. Finally they twitched to the side, looking at the group that had brought me. “Leave us.”

They bowed and left without comment. The two armored hulks beside her remained still.

Once the doors had shut, the young queen stood, advancing toward me in a slow, graceful strut. Her long mane fell across her shoulders, while those beautiful green eyes remained fixated on me. I tried my best not to stare.

She halted a couple of yards away, looking down at me. “Who are you?”

I swallowed again. “My name is Whisper,” I said, then quickly bowed my head as an afterthought. “Your Highness.”

She hummed quietly to herself as she considered me. Her posture tightened, her head rising slightly, proudly, before speaking again.

“I am Queen Chrysalis.”

My gut dropped, and I completely failed to hide my reaction, eyes widening at those words. There was no possible good reason a changeling queen would adopt that name.

The situation had just gotten worse.

Her eyes narrowed, glaring down her snout at me. “Is there a problem?”

“S-sorry,” I stammered, allowing the fear to show for only a moment before tightly constraining my expression to one of confusion. “I’ve heard that name before, but… I’m not very well-versed in history, but I thought Queen Chrysalis lived before the Great War.”

Her lip twitched, baring her fangs a little more. She spoke again, her voice darkening with irritation. “I am Queen Chrysalis the Sixth.”

I forced my body language to relax. “Oh. My apologies. That makes much more sense.” I gave a little twitch, then bowed my head. “Your Highness.”

She gave a faint snort. “It doesn’t matter. Now tell me, Whisper. Why are you here?”

I looked up at those waiting eyes, watching me like a predator, ready to pounce. My mind raced, scrambling to piece together an appropriate story. “I… I’ve been looking for other changelings. I learned that there might be changelings around here, so I came looking.”

The queen’s voice was sharp and demanding. “Where did you learn that?”

“F-from another changeling!” I quickly replied, suppressing a shiver. “Except I didn’t know she was a changeling. It was a pony named Emerald. At least, I thought she was a pony, until a raider shot and killed her. She had a PipBuck, and after digging around on it, I found that she’d come from here. I thought I might find some other changelings here, or at least clues to where they were.” I looked around, putting on a slow, awed smile. “I didn’t think I’d find a whole hive!”

“And why were you looking for us?”

I flinched a little, bowing my head again. “M-my queen and my hive are… are dead. I’ve been on my own for so long, I…” I slowly sagged, bowing my head again. “I didn’t know what else to do. I didn’t want to be on my own any more. When I learned there might be more changelings—”

“How did your hive die?”

I looked up, blinking, my ears pinning back. I gulped, covering for the moment of thought. “I think they starved. I was in a cocoon because we lacked enough love for everyling. When I woke up, they were all dead.”

She slowly walked to the side, looking off in thought. “Another hive. Noling has heard of another hive in at least a century. You must have been very good at hiding.”

“We tried to stay low-key,” I said. “We didn’t even have a proper hive, certainly nothing as impressive as you have. We had to hide among ponies.”

“And yet, your hive failed.”

Wincing, I ducked my head. “It was always difficult finding enough love. Ponies can be… paranoid.”

She gave a slow nod, humming thoughtfully, then looked back to me. “So now you come here, hoping to… what? Join some other queen’s hive?”

My eyes widened slightly as I looked up at her. “If… if you’d have me.”

She frowned, and I prostrated myself, bowing my head until my nose touched the floor. “Please, Queen Chrysalis. I have nowhere else to go. I have no purpose on my own. I’ll do anything you ask of me, without hesitation, just to have a purpose again.”

Her head tilted as she looked down, towering over me. “You seem quite eager to cast aside your loyalty.”

I closed my eyes, ears hanging low. “I will never betray my hive,” I said, my tone firm despite the tremble in my voice. “But there is nothing remaining to be loyal to.”

“So you’re certain every member of your former hive is dead?”

I inhaled sharply, eyes opening to look up at those piercing eyes. “...My queen is dead, and my hive is shattered. I know most of them are dead. If any others did manage to survive… if they do not serve the same queen I do, then they are no longer of my hive.”

The corner of Queen Chrysalis’s mouth twitched upwards. “Hmm.” She turned, slowly pacing to my side as she thought. I remained still, keeping my head bowed. “Then I suppose I have one more question,” she said, turning to face me again. “What are your thoughts on ponies?”

I blinked in surprise. I hadn’t expected a question like that. Here I was trying to convince her that I would be a loyal and obedient subject, and she instead wants to know my opinions on something completely unrelated? It made no sense, and I had nothing ready.

I considered what a queen who would adopt that particular name might want to hear, and cautiously offered it. “Ponies are necessary, but… problematic. They’re the best source of love, but they can be dangerous and paranoid. And lately… since my hive fell, I’ve seen some of the worst ponies have to offer. I’ve seen what raiders do to other ponies, and they’re even worse with non-ponies…”

Noting that the corner of her mouth had risen in a faint, smug smile, I pushed just a little harder. “And I can’t help but note that it was ponies who created the megaspells that put us all where we are now.”

Queen Chrysalis smiled, revealing her sharp teeth. “Yes, it was, wasn’t it?”

I nodded silently.

“Tell me, how did your former queen deal with ponies?”

“We hid,” I said. “We stayed in the shadows, trying to steal what love we could find without drawing attention.”

“And because of this,” Queen Chrysalis said, “her hive now lies dead.”

I winced, then nodded. “Yes, Your Highness.”

She gave a pleased hum, turning to slowly strut back to her throne-like cushions. “You’re right, you know. Ponies are a problem. They’ve always been a problem. We’ve had to hide in the shadows for centuries because of them, living like thieves and vultures. They’ve already tried to murder our entire species. They turned the world into a wasteland, and even then, they manage to find new forms of barbarism. Petty warlords, slavers, raiders.”

I watched her, ears perked attentively; a good, eager, enraptured audience.

She turned and sat primly atop her cushion, her head held high and proud. “You have come to us at a great time, Whisper. The Grand Pegasus Enclave, the final bastion of the old world, is tearing itself apart. The great slaver army of the north has been shattered. The twisted Goddess behind the monstrous alicorns has been slain. Even the remnants of the Steel Rangers have turned on each other, decimating their numbers.

“Destroying the world wasn’t enough for them. Ponies have had every opportunity to change their ways, but even in this wasteland, they continue to spread death and destruction, and we suffer for it. The queens before me have allowed this to stand for too long, but I will do what they never had the ability or courage to do. It is time for a change.”

She looked down at me, seeing my smile. Her own grin grew, sharp-toothed and eager; I think she liked having an audience. “The ponies are divided, and their power is broken. A tremendous opportunity has presented itself to us. So, tell me, Whisper… what do you think we should do?”

I stared back, my heart hammering as I considered the question, knowing exactly what she had in mind. My eyes darted to the black-painted power armors flanking her, a small portion of what seemed to be a well-equipped fighting force, while I thought of the tremendous resources available to the hive. The expected answer was obvious. “We could rule.”

“The reign of ponies is over,” Queen Chrysalis said. She held her smug smile for a moment before turning to one of the motionless soldiers. “Call in Ocelli.”

The soldier nodded, the first time I had seen them move. Meanwhile, the queen turned back to me. “Answer all of her questions, and follow all of her directions. Do this, and you will be allowed to remain as a member of my hive.”

I grinned wide, and bowed my head, blinking as my eyes teared up. “Thank you! Thank you, my Queen!”

Ocelli was a small, lean changeling, but her body language was full of confidence, even as she bowed to her queen. She led me off to a side room, accompanied by a pair of guards. I followed, grinning like a loon and occasionally pausing to wipe away tears.

“Sit,” she said, indicating a chair beside a plain table, while she sat opposite it.

I followed her direction, giving a sniff and another wipe at my cheek, my wings fluttering a couple times before lying flat again. “Heh, sorry. I’m probably not making the best first impression, getting so emotional and all. It’s just… it’s been a long time.”

“So I gather,” Ocelli said with a faint smile, while she lay one foreleg across the table to view her PipBuck screen. “Which means we’re going to have a lot to talk about.”

She started in with the questions, which I answered dutifully. I told her of Queen Shadow, and how she had guided our nomadic hive around the edges of pony society, sneaking in to steal what love we could and scurrying off before any suspicion could be aroused. I told her of my incomplete training as a scout, cut off when I was placed in a cocoon to conserve my hive’s dwindling supply of love. I described my confused experience, waking up in the depths of a mine near Rust, surrounded by the remains of my dead hive, and wandering out to find the slaughtered raider camp above.

Then I described my time wandering the Wasteland. Meeting Starlight, Dusty, and Sickle. Our encounters with raiders and mercenaries while scouring for old-world ruins. And of course, though I was hesitant to mention it, my eventual uncovering.

“Wait,” Ocelli said, her expression skeptical. “They know you’re a changeling?”

I nodded. “I managed to hide it for a while, but I had no idea what I was doing. I guess it was probably inevitable, but… what could I do, really? I needed the food, and…” I slowly shook my head. “Hell, I was scared when they found out, but it worked out. Probably helps that they had no idea what a changeling was. I even managed to convince them to help me look for more of my own kind.”

“Interesting,” she said, tapping a couple buttons on her PipBuck. “Does anypony else know?”

“No!” I shuddered. “No, I was scared enough that they knew, and I think they were scared of other ponies finding out. I was more useful if nopony else knew what I could do.”

“I see. So, what does that make them to you? Friends?”

I stared off into space, considering that question for a moment. “More like… pets, I guess? They were good food and decent company, and I’d rather not see them harmed if it’s convenient, but I wouldn’t consider them friends, no.”

She hummed and nodded, reading something from her screen. “...That big one, Strawberry—”

“Sickle,” I said, then smiled awkwardly. “Sorry. She hates that other name, and I learned not to offend the huge, short-tempered pony who could casually crush my skull.” I raised a hoof, rubbing at the side of my head. “One concussion is more than enough, thanks.”

Ocelli nodded. “Sickle, then. We’ve been having difficulty with her.”

“I don’t doubt it,” I said with a soft snort.

A smile flickered for a moment on Ocelli’s face. “It sounds like you were able to keep her in line and get love from her. How?”

“Well… keeping her in line is more like knowing when to let her loose and what direction to point her. She loves to fight and kill, and the best I could do is make sure she fights and kills the right ponies. She gets bored when she can’t fight, too. Drugs and sex help, but she still tends to be pretty aggressive.”

“We obviously can’t have her killing others in the simulation,” Ocelli mused. “Sure, it won’t actually kill them, but I can’t imagine the extra work the simulation staff would have to put in to deal with the chaos that would cause. Drugs are out, too, unless she’d be content with a little alcohol and some cigarettes.”

“A lot of alcohol,” I said. “Though that only mellows her a little. Combine that with hard drugs or sex, and that could keep her pleasant.”

Ocelli pondered that, tapping a hoof to her chin. “Sex we could manage. Maybe the sim staff could steer one of the stallions to her. Or does she prefer mares?”

“I think she’s fine with either, but prefers stallions,” I said. Then I clarified. “Um, stallions plural. Unless you’ve got one just as big and aggressive as her, she’s not going to be satisfied by just one.”

Ocelli frowned thoughtfully, then slowly shook her head. “Sounds like she’s going to take more work than she’s worth. Pity. The raider types can be tricky. The staff was planning on euthanizing her and being done with it, but they hoped you might have some insight.”

“I’m afraid not,” I said with a slow shake of my head. “I think she’s too well-adapted to the Wasteland. I know the hive has employed raiders in the past, though. It’s part of how I found my way here. If she isn’t useful in that ‘simulation’, she might be useful as some sort of hired agent.”

Ocelli hummed. “I’m sure it’s under consideration. Now why don’t you tell me what happened after they discovered you were a changeling?”

I continued on to tell her how I convinced the others to help me look for any signs of other changelings. How we’d followed a clue about a possible changeling hive in the badlands, only to find a gaping crater in its place. How we’d scoured old-world offices, looking for clues. How after Emerald had been killed, we had realized Lady Amber was a changeling, and came looking for Serenity. How we had seen Stable-Tec and C.L.T. offices there, two of the companies she had sent us looking for at Paradise Beach.

The whole way, she kept slipping in quick questions, clarifying little details. We must have spent three hours at it before she finally called it quits. “I think that’s satisfactory. I’ll pass this information on, then we can get you situated. Come along.”

She led me out, and I followed her down a series of halls, while the guards remained behind.

The whole place was in excellent condition, well maintained, and full of changelings going this way and that. The hive was alive and thriving, and I grinned as I looked around. So many changelings, all carrying out their business, and I moved through them as if I truly belonged there.

I caught the faint smile Ocelli wore, and gave a sheepish smile of my own. “Sorry. I’d gotten so used to being alone.” I glanced to the side and quickly changed the subject. “Is this a Stable? I’ve seen pictures before, and the architecture seems pretty distinctive.”

“It is,” Ocelli said with a nod. “Ironic that the ponies should have become better than us at underground shelters, but thankfully, their wartime preparations could be repurposed to allow our hive to survive.”

We approached a door, flanked by a pair of chatting guards.

“...It’s still eight times I’ve killed you,” one of them was saying, grinning smugly.

“It’s random chance, could have happened to anyling,” the other guard said, giving a short snort, then cocking her head. “Wait, eight? The Thunderhead defense made seven.”

“I got you in the the convoy breakthrough, too.”

“The convoy—we were on the same side!”

The first guard’s grin grew a touch wider. “I shot, you died. It totally counts.”

The second guard started laughing. “That should count negative you—” She abruptly stopped on seeing our approach, straightening up and giving Ocelli a quick nod. “Ma’am.”

She didn’t so much as pause as she walked by them. “Friendly fire. I see your training is going well.”

The first guard’s grin had turned sheepish. “Ah, yes ma’am.”

We passed through the door the guards were flanking, and entered into a workspace. A few technicians were working over PipBucks, with at least thirty more PipBucks arrayed on shelves behind them. As we approached the technicians, I picked up the pace to move beside Ocelli and quietly ask, “What, are changelings immortal in this hive?”

“Oh, that?” She smirked, shaking her head. “They’re talking about combat simulations. It’s for training purposes, but many of the soldiers see them as nothing but a game.”

“Ah. I see.”

Ocelli had one of the technicians retrieve a PipBuck and make a few quick adjustments to its systems before presenting it to me.

“Every member of the hive gets one,” Ocelli said. “Don’t remove it unless absolutely necessary, and always keep it on you. This one is also heavily restricted at the moment. I’m sure you understand, it’s just a precaution. I’m sure the restriction will be relaxed once you’ve been here a while.”

It also gave them an easy way to track my movements, of course.

“Thank you!” I said, smiling as she clasped the device to my leg. Lights flickered before my eyes, quickly forming into the increasingly familiar E.F.S. readout. I wasn’t surprised to see that S.A.T.S. was disabled. Then I looked at the compass, and blinked. “Should I be concerned about that cluster of hostile contacts?”

“Hmm?” She turned her head, looking in the same direction I was, then relaxed, chuckling softly. “Oh. That’s the zoology department. They study Wasteland wildlife, and most of it is quite hostile. You learn to tune it out after a while.”

“Oh, good,” I said, relaxing with a soft sigh. “Sorry. First day here, and I thought I’d already offended someling.”

“Don’t worry about it,” she said, smiling. “Also, you might see the occasional hostile contact along the west side of the hive. Some of the food-ponies flash hostile every now and then. In fact, do you see a hostile over there right now?”

I looked over, then shook my head. “All green.”

“Hmm, well there’s something,” she said. “Your pink ‘pet’ has shown up as hostile to every other member of the hive.”

I frowned. “Considering the number of times she’s nearly killed or raped me, I question these things’ definition of ‘hostile’.”

Ocelli blinked in surprise, her head tilting. “I… guess so.” She slowly shook her head, and changed the subject. “Anyway, the equipment you and your companions had is also stored here. If there’s anything you need, or that you think would be useful to the hive, I can see about getting it returned to you eventually.”

“I think I’m good,” I said. “I can’t imagine needing any of my weapons in here.”

“No, I expect not,” Ocelli said. “Anyway, let’s get you a place to rest. You’ll be staying with me for now. Just a temporary thing, I’m sure.”

“Sounds good.”

Naturally, they’d want to keep an eye on the new ‘ling. The queen may have said I was accepted into her hive, but I knew that wasn’t quite true. I was allowed to stay and prove myself worthy of being a member of the hive, but they were going to keep a close eye on me until then. That, or they were hoping to get more information out of me. Either way, it was a sensible precaution.

She led me out and down new halls. “Speaking of equipment, that was quite the arsenal you walked in here with. You said you were a scout?”

“Training to be a scout,” I said. “I’d only gotten basic weapons training, but I’ve been learning quickly. Dusty, the yellow stallion, helped with that.” I gave a short chuckle. “A couple months ago, I’d have thought that gear I had was absurd overkill. After the experiences I had out there… well, overkill has a lot going for it.”

“Better than the alternative, I suppose,” Ocelli said with a momentary smile. “And the explosives?”

“That’s mostly new. I’m surprised how simple it is, though. Connect two wires to a blasting cap, put it in the explosive, hit the trigger when you’re far enough away, boom.” I shook my head. “Still a little unnerving carrying something that dangerous, though. Same for the grenades.”

“And the computer gear?”

“Basic computer intrusion training,” I said. “In case I ended up scouting out any old-world facilities. I was lucky enough to find some good equipment at Paradise Beach. Ended up making a lot of use out of that recently. Heck, it’s a surprisingly fun pass-time. Like… a puzzle, I guess?”

She nodded. “I guess I can see that.”

“Not that any of that helped us,” I noted. “I’m still not sure what happened, here. We went underground, hoping to follow some cables to a central server, and then everything just got… fuzzy. Was it gas?”

“It was,” she said, though she didn’t elaborate.

We exited the hallway, entering a public atrium. More changelings walked by, but others stood or sat around, talking or relaxing. As she led me along, she spoke again. “I know we just spent a lot of time with all the questions, but I’d kind of like to hear some more of your past. Maybe once we get back to my place, you could share some stories? It’s a good way to pass the time.”

Or in other words, maybe I could give her more useful information I hadn’t shared yet. “Sure,” I said, smiling, and she smiled back. It was a soft, pleasant smile. She turned back to watch where she was going, but I noted her head was turned ever so slightly, keeping me in her vision. Watching. Analyzing.

I avoided looking too close at her, letting her watch. Instead, I let my gaze wander over the changelings we passed. There were so many! Even the spacious Stable-Tec-designed atrium felt pleasantly crowded, filled with changelings traveling to and fro, relaxing on benches, chatting, and even snuggling up together. I caught bits and pieces of conversation as we passed.

“...for ten hours, but I’ve got the next two days off while we wait for the techs to do the final engine tests before…”

“...almost eight hundred yards, and with a carbine! I told you I’m a good shot!”

“Your team must have put a thousand rounds into those buildings. One of you were bound to get lucky. That’s not so…”

“...of the new armor. She ate dirt so hard! The whole requisition team was laughing their shells off, and she…”

“...cockpit is just weird. How do they even fly with their wings inside the vehicle?”

“I dunno. Magic?”

My mind raced as I fixated on a small group we were passing; most of the group was chatting happily, while two of them were cuddling up and nuzzling affectionately.

My gaze lingered just a little too long as we passed the group, and when I looked ahead again, I caught a glimpse of Ocelli’s sly smirk and look of amusement. My ears flicked back in embarrassment, and I quickly looked away again, rather obviously pretending to have not noticed.

As we continued down busy hallways and busy public rooms, I hunted down a few similar scenes among the hundreds of changelings. A pair nuzzling in affection. A couple of changelings curled up intimately, legs intertwined as they dozed on a bench. A trio lying sprawled over each other, chatting while hooves rubbed at sides and flanks before teasingly slipping between hindlegs.

It occurred to me that there were certain aspects of a changeling hive Sickle might appreciate. For one, the close quarters and enclosed spaces tended to result in greatly diminished expectations of privacy. There were certain advantages to that.

I soon noticed that Ocelli’s walk had changed, putting on a subtle but pleasant sway to her hips, her tail held a bit too high. I have to admit, she was rather pretty, with her near-perfect curves and uniform, glossy carapace. There was something very pleasant in the way her flanks shifted and flexed with every strutting step.

She noticed my lingering gaze, her eyes half-lidded as she looked my way. I quickly looked away again, tucking my tail down between my legs.

“So, you must have been on your own for a very long time,” Ocelli said, her eyes watching me closely. She had seen an opening, and she was taking it.

I nodded awkwardly. “It’s… been very lonely.”

“Mmm, I bet.” She smiled, taking advantage of the busy hallway to move closer and brush against my side. My ears perked up. She knew exactly what she was doing. “Well, you’re not alone any more, and I’m sure we can make you feel very welcome.”

I was breathing hard, and my tail crept up before quickly tucking down again. She merely smiled knowingly. I started to smile a little, then swallowed and looked away again.

A minute later, she purred beside me. “We’re here.”

A single guard stood by the door of her room, and gave us a nod as Ocelli opened it. “Come on in,” she said over her shoulder, her hips swaying so nicely. Even the guard cast a quick glance out of the corner of her eye before pretending she hadn’t noticed.

I followed Ocelli into a small room filled with a variety of furniture, adorned with various trinkets and pictures. The one detail that most immediately caught my attention was the single, decently sized bed. The heavy hydraulic door thumped shut behind her, and suddenly Ocelli was right in front of me, her muzzle so close I could feel her breath. I halted, ears perking up, alert and excited.

“This is my room,” she purred, moving in to gently brush the tip of her muzzle against mine. “I’m lucky enough to have a place of my own, so it’s just the two of us.”

My mouth parted, but the only sound that came out was a soft panting.

Her muzzle slipped to the side as she nuzzled along and under my jaw. “Mmm. You know, most changelings spend their whole lives in the hive. We’ve gotten very good at keeping ourselves entertained…” She gave a slow, teasing lick at my neck, and I responded with a shuddering huff of breath. “...But I’d absolutely love to hear about the outside world.”

“Y-yeah,” I huffed, her nuzzling working its way back up along my jaw, until her mouth was right by mine, lips parted just barely and so close to my own. Her eyes met mine with a sultry, half-lidded expression, sly and inviting.

I pressed forward, my mouth meeting hers, and she purred into the kiss. Soon I was gripping at her shoulders with my forehooves, ignoring the awkward balance as I pressed up to her. One of her hooves tucked around my shoulder, holding me close as she moved back, and a moment later we were on her bed.

I clutched at her sides, finally breaking the kiss to look down at her. We both panted softly for a few seconds before she smiled again, giving a soft, pleased hum.

That was sign enough for me. I pressed in again, kissing and nuzzling and licking with unrestrained eagerness, while her hooves teased along my sides and flanks. Moments later I was sliding down, giving only a few cursory licks and nuzzles across her underbelly before plunging my muzzle between her hind legs.

I played her like an instrument, every twist of my tongue producing a new melody, her voice rising to a crescendo and falling, again and again. Her hooves stroked across my head and horn, her hind legs wrapped around my shoulders.

We were both panting by the time I finally climbed over her again, muzzles brushing as our eyes met again. It lasted only a moment before her forelegs gripped around my shoulders, pulling me into another passionate kiss. When she finally broke the kiss again, she licked at her lips, purring. “Mmm. We really must get you taken care of,” she said, a hoof slipping from my shoulder to tease down along my side and under my belly. “Alone all this time, I can’t imagine how pent up you must be.”

As the hoof traveled lower, I shuddered, a faint moan escaping my lips. I drew back just a little, ears flicking back. “Would you, um… mind if I turned into a male for…?”

Her grin grew, sharp-toothed and eager. “You have no idea how much I’d like that,” she said, finishing up with a slow lick across her lips.

I slid back, calling up a quick transformation, then slipping a hoof under her flank, nudging upward. She hummed softly as she followed my direction, rising to her hooves, and gave a sultry smirk over her shoulder. Her tail was held high and inviting, and I eagerly climbed atop her. Moments later, she was moaning again, while I nuzzled and nipped at the back of her neck.

Her voice rose again, her head tilting back and eyes shutting. I tilted my own head back as well—then snapped it forward, slamming a stunning spell down into the back of her head.

She gave a single twitch and fell limp, collapsing to the bed while I caught my balance, panting, above her.

Immediate appraisal: complete and immediate unconsciousness. She had been sufficiently distracted to not see the attack coming. There was no opportunity to throw off or avoid my attack, and certainly no time to get out an alarm or even cry for help. It was as perfectly executed a takedown as could be managed.

Still panting, I sat beside her, trying to calm my pounding heart and the various emotions currently flooding my mind. I focused on simply breathing deep, calming breaths, then turned to analyzing my situation.

I was alone, trapped in a guarded room without any equipment except a partially disabled PipBuck, my hidden armor, and whatever I could scavenge. I was in a Stable, deep underground, with likely only a single way out. My friends were trapped in a simulated world, unaware that they were even prisoners, and held in a reasonably busy area. I had an unknown amount of time before Sickle would be killed in her sleep. Our confiscated equipment was under guard. And lying between us and freedom was an entire Stable packed full of a thousand or more changelings, following a Queen that had taken the name Chrysalis, and all equipped with arcano-tech devices that could detect hostile intent at a glance.

I frowned, looking down at the unconscious would-be interrogator, and came to a simple conclusion.

“We are so completely fucked.”

Chapter Twenty Eight: On The Road

Starlight was gone when I woke up.

She’d been lying right next to me the whole night, cuddled up close. Despite lying awake for most of the night, and sleeping fitfully even when I did drift off, I’d somehow missed her slip away.

I pushed myself up, looking blearily around in the dim morning light. Dusty was sitting a short distance away, drinking slowly from a cup and looking as weary as I felt. I didn’t get the chance to speak before he gestured with a hoof, already figuring what was on my mind.

I struggled to my hooves and slowly staggered my way in the direction he had indicated.

Starlight was sitting almost a hundred feet from camp when I found her. She was staring down at her PipBuck, her hoof resting gently atop it. She remained like that until she noticed my approach, her hoof slipping away as she looked back at me.

I drew up beside her. Despite my fatigue and the relentless worry that refused to leave my mind, I asked, “What’s wrong?”

“Nothing,” she said, looking back to her PipBuck. “Just thinking.”

I sat beside her with a quiet groan. “Oof… about what?”

“This,” she said, lifting her PipBuck a fraction before lowering it again. “And everything else I have, and us, and… yeah, pretty much everything.”

I grunted softly. “Sounds familiar,” I said, reaching up to habitually rub at my eyes. “I was so caught up thinking about everything that I hardly slept.”

“Yeah,” Starlight said, slowly nodding. “It’s just… we almost lost everything there. I mean, I’ve almost died a few times now, but this…”

I nodded and reached out a leg, gently looping a foreleg around her shoulders.

“Shit, we didn’t even know,” she continued. “We could have been stuck there the rest of our lives and not even known it. And…” She turned her PipBuck slightly, her hoof once again touching beside the screen. “And they took my PipBuck, and my Lancer, and… a-and I didn’t even remember them. I just… I forgot…”

Her breath caught, tears welling up in her eyes, but she fought them back. I gave a reassuring squeeze.

She sniffled, wiping at her eyes. “Just… the more I think on what those changelings did, the more… scared I am. These are all I’ve got from my mom, and I almost forgot them! It’s like I almost forgot her.” She shuddered, leaning into me, her eyes fixated on her PipBuck. My own concerns felt a little small at that moment.

“...Sorry,” she said, her voice raw. “It’s just, everything’s going to crap and I don’t have a clue what to do about it.” She paused, a frown touching her expression. “You know how when we met, I was working as a guard for that caravan?”

I nodded, thinking back to the ill-fated group.

“I was there because, you know… I wanted to protect ponies. I thought it was something my mom could be proud of.”

I could see where that thought was going, and gave another squeeze.

She let her forehooves fall, looking out across the rolling terrain. “How many ponies were in Serenity?”

My ears drooped. “Dozens. Some zebras and griffins, too.”

“Dozens,” she echoed. “Just as clueless as we were. And who even knows what Serenity is going to do next? How much worse...” She fell silent again, as if deep in thought. After several more seconds, she slowly drew in a deep breath and exhaled. “...I wish I was more like my mom. She always had a plan, knew exactly what to do. Hell, she recorded a message for me years before I was born. I don’t have that kind of… I dunno, foresight, whatever.”

“It’s a difficult situation,” I said, nodding. “Though to be fair, looking like you know what you’re doing in a difficult situation is often as simple as remaining calm and level headed when you have no idea what to do.”

Starlight was still and silent for several long seconds. I had just started to worry that I had offended her when the corner of her mouth crept up a hair, followed by the soft exhale of an almost-silent chuckle. “Okay, I know you’re trying to cheer me up in your weird buggy way, but did you seriously just say my mom had no idea what she was doing?”

I replied with a soft chuckle. “I’m saying that, from what I’ve heard from you, she knew exactly what she was doing.” I smiled. “Even when she didn’t.”

She gave a slightly more audible chuckle, and pushed my side lightly with her shoulder. “Thanks, I think.”

The smile slowly slipped away, until she was staring silently at her hooves.

“So… I guess the first part of that would be moving on instead of just sitting here moping, huh?”

I nodded again. “It’s a start, which is better than doing nothing. We’ve got a lot of traveling to do. That means a lot of time to think.”

“Wonderful,” she grunted, then heaved a deep sigh. “Sorry. Done moping. You think you’ll come up with something?”

I resisted the urge to grunt, myself. “Maybe. I’ll certainly be thinking about it the whole time.”

She stopped and looked at me, really looked at me, as if she had just realized that I had been a part of the conversation. “...Yeah, I guess you would be, huh?”

“Yeah.” I forced a wry, half-hearted smile. “Like I said, it’s a difficult situation.”

“Yeah,” she agreed. We stood in awkward silence for a few more seconds. “I guess we should get going.”

“Probably.”

We returned to our tiny camp. Minutes later, we climbed into the motorwagon. I had the back seat to myself. I strapped myself in, and Starlight started driving.

Despite the jostling, I fell asleep within minutes.

☢

The motorwagon tore across the wasteland.

I could easily fly faster than it, but I lacked the endurance of the tireless machine. As such, it traversed the barren land more swiftly than I could have done by wing, and far faster than my land-bound companions could have managed. Miles rolled by as the vehicle creaked and groaned and rattled, leaving a long trail of dust drifting away behind us.

After my nap, I spent most of the time sitting silently in the back seat, gazing out the narrow gap in the armor beside me. For most of the trip, I was far too lost in thought to register the landscape passing by.

For all my thinking, I had come up with nothing. I slumped against the side of the vehicle, continuing to stare without really seeing, thinking without reaching any conclusions. I know Dusty and Starlight had both tried to strike up conversations, though that information barely registered with me at the time. I think I might have offered a few half-hearted replies, but I couldn’t tell you now what they had been. It seemed so unimportant at the time.

The only thing that did register was information that had some significant importance. In this case, it was Starlight during our short stop for lunch, when she checked on the power in the motorwagon’s spark batteries. They’d been fully charged when we took it from Serenity, and according to Starlight, should hold enough charge for two more days of operation. The spark packs we had in the cargo bay would probably be enough for a full charge, perhaps with a bit spare. Dusty mentioned wishing for a spark generator.

Then we were driving again.

The evening proved no more productive than the morning. Ideas formed, only to be immediately discarded. By the time the skies started to darken with the onset of night, I was probably spending more time mentally grumbling than I was on anything useful.

I mostly tuned out what happened around me as we settled in for the night. I know Starlight laid out her bedroll beside mine. I also know Sickle sat on top of Dusty; her improved health seemed to have enlarged her already significant libido, and further cemented my desire to tune out everything around me.

As we settled in for the night, I tried to comfort myself that we were at least making progress towards finding the remains of my hive. My mood led me to note “if they are still alive” with an extra helping of cynicism.

It wasn’t the best note to go to sleep on.

☢

It was still dark when I woke, and Starlight was gone once again.

I could see the lump of Dusty and Sickle through the darkness, sleeping a few yards away, which meant Starlight must be on watch. Normally, that would have been the end of it. I would have closed my eyes and eventually drifted off again.

Instead, I heard the sound of her voice, barely carrying through the still night air. She was talking.

I lifted my head, looking to the nearby lump, just to make sure. Sure enough, that was Dusty half-hidden under Sickle’s foreleg and thoroughly dwarfed by the larger mare.

Which raised the question: who was Starlight talking to?

Thoughts of sleep were forgotten as I pushed aside my thin blanket. I quietly made my way toward the faint sounds of Starlight’s voice, my ears perked alertly to capture any sound, my eyes plucking details out of the darkness of night under the cloud cover.

I found Starlight kicked back atop a rock a short distance away, close enough to watch over our camp—at least, as much as pony eyes could do in that darkness—without disturbing our sleep. The soft glow of her PipBuck underlit her face with green. She was speaking into it.

“...was pretty impressive. But, well, it’s more than that. She’s helped me a lot. This last… what has it been, like, two months?” A pause as she pressed buttons. “Wow. Forty days. Heh, it’s been pretty crazy. But, yeah, I don’t think I would have gotten through it without her. I mean, she can be kinda weird at times, but, you know, ancient changeling super-spy. It’d be weird if it wasn’t weird. But she’s… she’s nice.”

I paused by a scraggly bush, watching and listening intently, and not daring to make a sound.

“It’s almost inspirational, you know? All these horrible things she has to deal with, but she’s still always there to help. She’s nice, and she’s smart, and she’s really good at what she does. She’s an amazing friend.” A long pause. “Yeah, I don’t know what other ponies will think of changelings, but Whisper’s a good one.”

Another pause. “...She’s also a nosy little sneak that likes to eavesdrop on ponies.” Her head turned, shooting a look of mock disapproval in my direction, though the look was spoiled by her smirk.

I winced, then slowly stepped out from behind the bush, giving an awkward and embarrassed smile, despite my concern over the situation.

Starlight held her smirk for a second before turning back to her PipBuck. “Anyway, I guess that’s a good start. I’ll have to record some more next time. So, until then… goodnight.”

She pressed a button on her PipBuck, a faint click sounding in the night. With that concluded, I spoke up.

“What was that?”

She gave a soft chuckle and shrugged. “I dunno. It’s silly.”

I continued to slowly approach, trying to force myself to relax. At least I kept my voice level. “Oh?”

“Yeah,” she said, leaning her head back. “...I was thinking of my mom, you know, because of all that stuff earlier. I got thinking about my PipBuck, and the recordings she made for me, and I just thought I should record something. You know, leave something of me there.”

She gently stroked a hoof along her PipBuck, then shrugged. “I tried doing like she did, but, I dunno, it didn’t feel right. Not like wrong, just… maybe a little cheesy, I guess? I couldn’t do it like she could. I couldn’t really figure out what to say, but I wanted to record something, so I figured, just start talking, see what happens. I guess it kinda turned into a diary pretty quickly.”

“A diary?” Of course that’s what she was doing. I let out a silent sigh, relaxing, though I did my best to hide my reaction.

“Yeah,” she said, setting her hoof down and leaning back. “Just kinda going over things, talking about what happened, you guys, stuff like that. I dunno, might just delete the whole thing later, or try recording it again a little more planned-out like, but…” She cracked a smile. “I think it helped. Like I feel better, just recording all that. Kinda like… I’m not my mom, but I’m doing my own thing, right?”

“I suppose that makes sense,” I said, stopping beside her rock. “And talking about things is a good way to deal with them.”

“Yeah,” she said again, then fell silent in thought. Eventually, she turned to me. Her expression had turned serious, maybe even concerned. “Maybe you should do that, too.”

“What?” I raised a brow questioningly. “A diary? I’ve never really seen the point. Besides, it’s kind of a bad idea for an Infiltrator to keep records of all their actions. Maybe in a secure location like the hive, but not a PipBuck anypony could take from me.”

She fidgeted a little, looking away for a moment before turning back. “I don’t really mean like that, just… I’ve been thinking…”

I frowned a little. Something about that seemed ominous. “About what?”

“Wellll…” She paused, biting her lip, before finally speaking. “This whole Serenity thing. Ponies have no idea what’s coming. They’re never going to see it before it’s too late, unless…” She must have seen my ears drooping, because she quickly added, “And I know, the whole secrecy thing helps you, too, but… I mean, ‘ending the reign of ponies’? How many are going to suffer because of that?”

I sighed and sat down, slowly shaking my head. “I know, but… it’s not just me. It’s hopefully not just me. If there’s any more of my hive out there, any decision I make will affect them, too. I can’t just do that to them.”

“And what if Serenity takes over?” Starlight asked.

My ears were already hanging low. I felt like curling up in myself, but I didn’t speak.

“And how much worse is it going to be for your hive,” Starlight continued, “if all that ponies know about changelings comes from Serenity?”

“It’ll be bad,” I murmured.

“Yeah,” she said. “So… maybe it’d be better if you were the one to tell ponies about all that.”

“Look, I… I know. I’m trying to figure out some way of helping everyone, but… I don’t know how. Ponies…” I sighed. “...Yeah, they probably need to know. About Serenity, anyway. I just don’t know if that’s going to help.”

We fell silent for several long seconds before I added, “I’ll think about it. We’ve got until we’re done with Baltimare before it matters. I’ll… have something by then.

She slowly nodded, and after another moment of silence, glanced to her PipBuck. “I’ve got another half-hour on my watch. Get some more sleep, I’ll wake you up when it’s time.”

“I might as well take over now. You’ve got to drive. I’ll just take a nap in the back again.” I heaved a deep sigh. “Besides, I don’t think I could get back to sleep before you’d be waking me up again.”

Starlight slid down from the rock and stepped up to me, her expression concerned. Finally, she nodded. “Okay.”

She slipped in, wrapping me in a tight hug. We held that for a couple seconds before she drew back, her face passing right before mine, and kissed me softly on the mouth.

Between the weight on my mind and the unexpected action, I didn’t have the time to return the gesture before she was drawing back again. She looked to me with a soft, almost sad smile. “See you in the morning.”

“See you,” I weakly echoed.

She slipped by me, slowly picking her way back to the camp. I watched her go, until she settled into the camp itself. Then I turned, wings fluttering as I lifted up, landing atop the rock she had just vacated. I rolled to my side, laid down, and waited.

And waited.

And waited.

The night was seemingly empty, leaving me with nothing but my own thoughts, which was little comfort. I simply lay there, eyes scanning out across the desolate and uneventful landscape, barely visible even with my night-adapted eyes.

Guard duty was always dull, but this was by far the worst it had ever been.

I made the mistake of checking the clock on Emerald’s PipBuck. Only half an hour had passed. I suppressed a sigh and laid my head back. One fifth of the way there.

A couple minutes later, I raised the PipBuck again. I stared at the screen for a long time, my thoughts stuck in a formless haze of indecision.

I could come up with so many arguments for or against it, but to tell the truth, the deciding factor was that I simply didn’t have anything better to do.

I lethargically pressed a few buttons, creating and naming a new directory, and starting up a new audio file. The final press started the recording, and then… nothing.

I stared at the timer slowly counting up as I tried to come up with what to say. It was at thirty seconds when I finally managed to come up with something. “...Dear diary? Ugh, no.” My hoof stabbed at a button, ending the recording, and I quickly deleted the aborted attempt.

Soon I had a fresh file. Once again, I watched the time slowly work its way higher and higher. It got to two minutes before I stopped it again. Again, I started over.

This time, I just stared at the screen, the file waiting for me. I stared, and thought, trying to figure out where to even begin. Finally, reluctantly, I pressed the button to start recording.

“Well… I suppose if I have to start somewhere, it would be with the day I was ...reborn.”

☢

So that’s how I came to start making these recordings. A simple, reluctant tale recorded on my PipBuck in the middle of the dark and silent night. I didn’t do it all at once, of course. I didn’t even finish my first day in the Wasteland during that watch, and I ended up going back to touch-up some parts later on, but I got the bulk of it down.

There I was, stuck in a bad situation that was only likely to get worse, feeling lost, confused, and maybe even a little depressed, and I was re-telling what was probably the single worst moment of my life.

And you know what?

It helped.

Recalling how all of this started highlighted a perspective that I had allowed to slip away into obscurity, but which seemed particularly relevant now. It was the perspective of facing some monumental challenge that I felt too small to handle. While that first recording hadn’t gotten past the first day, it sent me thinking on the day that followed; my brutal first introduction to the horrors of the Wasteland.

I had been practically helpless. I had little idea of where I was going. I had only enough love to survive a few days. I had no way to protect myself, and nearly ran myself to death trying to flee a band of homicidal psychopaths.

Starlight saved my life.

She gave me a source of love to stave off the hunger. She gave me knowledge of the Wasteland. She gave me a measure of protection, strength, and versatility.

With another pony at my side, I could survive in the Wasteland. The two of us together were stronger than either of us alone.

Then two became three. With Dusty, we could thrive in the Wasteland.

Then three became four. With Sickle, we wiped out multiple raider gangs, ones far exceeding the group that had sent Starlight and myself fleeing for our lives.

Now there was a new threat looming. A threat vastly beyond us, one great enough that it was hard to even conceptualize of how to deal with it. One that might put every pony and changeling in danger. One that knew all about us, and had every reason to destroy us. The four of us wouldn’t survive Serenity.

But what about five?

And if not five, how about six? Seven? Eight?

With enough friends and allies, any threat becomes that much smaller.

Of course, Dusty was right; it wasn’t that simple. We had a distinct lack of allies to call upon. The largest settlement in the region had a bounty out for us. The settlements that were friendly to us would probably be eager to help their fellow pony, but be quite short on the resources to do so directly. This didn’t change any of that.

But it did highlight that this wasn’t some insurmountable challenge. It was simply a challenge we could not currently face. That could change.

Especially if we were to, say, find an ancient facility holding a group of experienced pre-war changelings in suspended animation.

Now that was a cheering thought.

☢

The next day was spent traveling at a much more sedate rate.

We came across the first clumps of scraggly trees barely an hour after dawn. Another hour later, and the terrain had changed completely. We came rolling down into a valley to the sight of trees, clustered densely around a thin, muddy creek. Grass dotted the slopes, often yellow or faded, but still clinging to life in the rocky earth. As we followed the narrow ribbon of water, more spots of green stood out.

An hour later, we stopped. Green filled the horizon in a tangle, wild to a degree I had never seen before the megaspells. Plants grew everywhere, and though they often looked twisted and sinister, perhaps even warped by the magical energies of the megaspells, they were still green and alive. Long stretches of water crisscrossed through the foliage, splitting up the land into isthmuses and islands and producing a maze of water and plant-life.

According to our PipBucks, we had reached the edge of the Hayseed Swamps.

We spent most of the day driving along the edge of the wetlands, searching out the best route. Dusty spent most of his time with his nose to his PipBuck, navigating for Starlight as she slowly picked her way through the dense terrain. Several times we turned around, driving back a few miles to try a new route.

“We want to drive as far as we can get,” Dusty said, when Sickle inevitably protested turning around yet again. “A single hour of driving might be worth a whole day of travel on hoof.”

As evening arrived, we rolled along a low ridge that protruded out across the swamp like a peninsula. Starlight drove until we were well below the canopy, stopping in a patch of rocky ground. Dusty said it would be a good place to conceal the motorwagon.

We settled in for the night. Starlight laid her bedroll out near me, likely expecting me to lay my own beside hers, as usual, but I didn’t. Instead, I surprised her by lying down with her, snuggling in close and nuzzling into her chest. She was tense at first, caught off-guard and likely a little self-conscious, but she relaxed, gently resting a foreleg across my shoulders and tucking her head in close against mine.

In the morning, we started to pack.

“This is going to be a long trip,” Dusty warned as we gathered around the motorwagon’s cargo bed. “The terrain is rough, line of sight is short, and you can bet there’s going to be wildlife. We’ve got PipBucks, so at least nothing will sneak up on us, but we’ll have to stay alert.”

He lifted his foreleg, undoing the flap covering his PipBuck so we could see the screen. He showed the map of the swamps ahead of us, and beyond it, our destination. “We’re looking at probably a week to get through to Baltimare, maybe more. Worse, we have no idea what we’re going to find there. It could be completely intact, or just a glowing crater infested with raiders and ghouls. We don’t know if there’s going to be any safe-haven out there, much less any place to get supplies.

“The good news is, there’s plenty of water for the taking. I’ve got a little canteen filter, it’s not perfect, but it’ll get the worst crap out of the water. We might even luck out and kill some wildlife we can cook up. Starlight, you used to be a hunter, right?”

“Yep,” Starlight said with a quick nod. “I can clean and cook anything we come across.”

“Good,” Dusty said. “Hopefully we can make use of that, but we can’t count on it, and I don’t plan on testing whether the plants are as poisonous as everypony says. Search through the food we’ve got, grab the most calorie-dense foods you can find. Plan for at least three weeks worth, four if you can carry it. That takes priority over everything, even extra ammo.”

By the time we were done, I felt like a pack-mule. My saddlebags were about ready to burst. We’d managed to cram more than half of the food we had stockpiled into our bags. We started with dense foods, mostly oats and other grains, with a few happy finds like some tins of nuts, a package of dried fruit, and even some jars of peanut butter. Those ran out quickly, and soon we were back to the same canned and packaged food we’d been eating the whole time. The weight grew rapidly.

Even more troubling was how curtailed the rest of my gear was. At least the PipBuck served every portable-terminal need I would have, so the only other mission-critical gear was my collection of cables and one of the mini-toolkits. Almost everything else got left behind, including, much to my unease, the datastore and all but one of the love crystals my queen had left for me. That one stayed with me; it was purely sentimental, but small enough that I figured it would make no difference.

Most of the remaining weight was made up by my weapons and ammunition. I was even tempted to leave my pistol behind to save weight, but it was too valuable of a tool to go without; I kept it strapped on, with its two spare magazines, and made up the weight by shedding explosives until I carried only a pair of grenades and a single explosive charge, plus the detonator and some spare blasting caps. I even went light on rifle ammo, with only a hoofful of loose rounds to complement the loaded magazines.

It was by no means an insignificant loadout, but I still found myself concerned at the prospect of possibly going for weeks without being able to rearm. I had learned well just how quickly ammunition could go in a firefight. Hopefully we wouldn’t need it, and if we did, hopefully whatever we needed it for would provide us with alternate equipment to get us through whatever came next.

I hefted my bags, testing the balance. After a moment’s consideration, I called up my magic. In a flash of green, I turned into a pony, broadly similar to my typical disguise, but with additional muscle mass, particularly in the legs and back. Mindful of the terrain we would be passing through, I also shortened my mane and tail, styling them much like Starlight’s.

I shrugged at my bags, feeling the weight shift much more comfortably. Then I looked over to see Starlight weighed down by her own bags.

“You are such a little cheater,” she said with a poorly hidden smirk.

I merely grinned in reply.

“Don’t get too attached to that form,” Dusty said. “I want to make use of those wings. We’ve got the PipBucks for general navigation, but the foliage is going to cut sightlines to nothing. If we can get you up and scouting for us, it should make it easier to find a good path through here.”

My grin vanished, and I shrugged my shoulders to shake my packs. “You expect me to go flying with all this?”

“Short jaunts,” Dusty said. “You can leave the packs on the ground. We’ll just need you to pop up every mile or so to get a good eye on the area around us.”

I considered it a moment, and finally nodded. “Okay, I can do that.” It still meant more work for me, but I could hardly argue against the advantages. I was the only one of us who could fly, so of course I would get the job that required flying. Sensible enough, and it took only a tiny bit of love to add wings to my current form. I also returned to the gear I had stowed in the motorwagon, retrieving my binoculars.

Dusty took a bit of extra time to camouflage the motorwagon. An army-green tarp formed the base, and he gathered sticks, leaves, and vines to layer over it. He noted that most of them would wilt before we got back, but they would at least break up the silhouette.

With that, we set off.

☢

The swamps stretched on, seemingly without end. My brief flights showed me a sea of twisted green stretching off to the horizon, broken up by tiny hills and larger lakes.

Below the canopy, we traced our way through narrow strips of dry land. Sickle ended up leading the way, plowing straight through any brush and trampling a path for the rest of us to follow. It started drizzling on the third day, and would continue off and on for the rest of our journey. My PipBuck clicked frequently, warning of the trace amounts of radiation carried in the rain that fell on us, or the minute amounts in the poorly-filtered water we drank. It was minor, small enough to not be a concern over our journey, but enough that we might want to find some anti-radiation medicine when we had the chance.

And then the red pips showed up on our E.F.S. displays.

Dusty organized us quickly. Starlight came forward, just behind Sickle, with her Lancer and Recharger at the ready. Dusty and I took up the rear, protecting their flanks, and hoping we wouldn’t need to use our limited supply of ammunition.

A minute later, a trio of dark, insectoid forms flew out from the brush just twenty feet from us.

My first thought that these were changelings we were seeing, but even as Sickle roared and lunged forward, I realized they were not. They were bloated, massive flies, almost as large as a pony’s head.

Sickle smashed one with a kick of her hooves, and flashes of blue dazzled my vision as Starlight’s S.A.T.S.-aided shots plucked the other two out of the air. The whole encounter was over in a split second. The only sound that followed was the echo of the shots and the sizzle of a charred bug lying half-submerged in the shallow water.

Scenes like that repeated themselves endlessly over the next few days. We were constantly on-edge, our eyes glued to our E.F.S., waiting for the next attack. There were more of the strange bugs—some sort of mutated parasprite, according to Dusty—as well as a wild radhog, a badly decayed ghoul, some mutated plants that tried to eat Sickle, and a cluster of mutant vines that tried to entangle and crush her to death, only to find that their intended victim was stronger than them.

At least the radhog gave us some fresh meat to stretch out our supplies.

Guard duty, which had been so uneventful over all the time we had traveled with Dusty, now became a necessity. Instead of relaxing while keeping an eye out, we spent the whole time sweeping our view around, waiting for red pips to show up, and flicking on the flashlight once they had. I couldn’t even work on my recordings.

While the swamps seemed quieter after dark, only a single night passed without us waking to the sounds of gunfire. Even accounting for the amount of ground we covered, it seemed like an impossible number of predatory creatures.

It was like that for an entire, gruelling, nerve-destroying week.

Then it got worse.

As we neared the coast, dry land had become more and more scarce, and our progress slowed even further. There were times we stopped for an hour while I flew around, trying to find a way for my companions to proceed. Any thoughts of swimming were adequately quashed when something several times the size of a pony quietly cut through the water, the jagged shapes across its back sending out ripples before disappearing beneath the surface once again. Once the ripples had faded, the only sign of its presence was the red pip in our E.F.S.

It followed us.

Throughout the day, as our dry paths narrowed, it lurked at the edge of detection. Every time we thought it was gone, that red pip would return a few minutes later, in a different direction.

I was convinced it was hunting us.

Then, late in the evening, it appeared in front of us.

The lone path I had found us crossed a narrow isthmus of dry land, only twenty feet across and obscured with vines and brush. The water beside it was choked with reeds, pond-scum, and even a fallen tree. If we hadn’t known to look, we might have not seen the pair of eyes lurking just above the surface, surrounded by jagged scales.

“It’s a cragadile,” I said.

Dusty had his rifle leveled at the tiny part of the creature that was visible to us. “What in Tartarus is a cragadile?”

“A big aquatic lizard, basically,” I said. “Tough hide, predatory, lives in swamps and rivers.”

“Well it can just stay in the water,” Sickle said as she strode forward.

“Sickle, wait!” I called out, stumbling after her. “They’re still big and—”

Of course Sickle hadn’t stopped. The creature judged that she was close enough, and surged forward. Immediately, everything was wrong. It didn’t run low to the ground to snap at her. The water seemed to explode as it surged upwards on powerful hind-legs, terrible claws flashing as it lunged forward.

The air split like a thunderclap as a dazzling line of red struck the creature in the side. It stumbled, its side torn up and smoldering.

Then it regained its balance, raising its claws again. Granted, it had been a glancing blow, but it had shaken off a hit from Starlight’s Lancer and kept coming.

Sickle met it mid-windup, ducking her head to slam her helm’s horn into the creature’s chest. It grabbed at her with its huge foreclaws, and Sickle bellowed out. Then they were both on the ground, twisting and thrashing.

Starlight finished reloading her Lancer and leveled it, but had to hold her fire. Any miscalculation would strike Sickle, instead.

Blood was starting to flow heavily, and Sickle was cursing. They rolled over several times as the creature tried to haul her back into the water, but Sickle fought back. One of her forelegs rose and plunged down, striking at the creature’s side again and again. By the second strike, her hoof-blades came back bloody.

The pseudo-cragadile quickly lost strength as she continued to stab. When the claws finally fell from Sickle’s side, she reared back, jerking the blade-like horn from the creature’s chest. She snarled incoherent obscenities as she placed one hoof on its chest, and started stabbing and hacking at its neck. Blood ran down her sides; the creature’s claws had pierced through her armor, leaving deep rents in the steel.

“Whisper.” Dusty’s commanding voice drew my attention away. He stood beside me, but facing our rear, his rifle raised and his eyes alert. “Get airborne. Find us high-ground for the night.”

“Okay,” I said as I shrugged off my packs, then glanced back. There were two red marks on my E.F.S. “Are those—”

“Yes,” he replied. “One by the tree-roots, one by that thick patch of reeds.”

Looking closely, I could see the eyes protruding over the surface some thirty yards away, narrowed and staring at us. They were waiting, evaluating.

I found us a small hill that put a small distance between us and the water. Dusty took the time to clean and dress the wounds across Sickle’s sides.

“I’ve had a lot worse,” Sickle grumbled, not even flinching as Dusty sutured one of the deeper cuts.

“Claws, swamp-gunk, and who knows what else,” Dusty had said. “You might be big and tough and stubborn as all hell, but it’d be a pretty sad end to go out to an infection.”

She grunted, as if agreeing. When Dusty was done, he roamed around our campsite, cutting away brush to open our sightlines. Sickle, meanwhile, spent a short time pounding out the damage to her armor before kicking back to sleep, using the mutated cragadile’s head for a pillow.

When Starlight woke me for my turn at watch, she met me with a serious look, and silently pressed her Lancer into my hooves. I nodded.

That night was spent looking in every direction at once.

The red pip appeared, and I flicked on the flashlight. The beam seemed feeble in the oppressive darkness that surrounded us, and illuminated only the closest trees. I couldn’t see whatever lurked out there.

I glanced around, sweeping my E.F.S. around to make sure nothing was approaching from some other direction.

A minute later, the red pip disappeared. I turned off the light once more.

Some time later, the pip would return, and the cycle repeated again.

I don’t know if I’ve ever been so happy for the muted gray glow of a Wasteland sunrise as I was that morning.

☢

A few hours after dawn, as I scouted the terrain ahead, I saw the ocean.

We pressed on, eager to finally be near our destination and away from the waterways, with their lurking dangers that continued to trail after us. I think Sickle was the only one not concerned; she still carried the creature’s severed head on her back, a gruesome trophy and, if we were very lucky, a warning to dissuade any further attempts.

The smell of salt grew in the air as we traveled.

That afternoon, we emerged from the foliage into a narrow strip of sand, filled not with plants but with the great, skeletal remains of ancient ships. Most had rusted away to scrap, or had perhaps been stripped for salvage. Only one, a warship, remained upright and relatively intact. The small turrets had been stripped bare. Only the larger cannons remained, though they looked like they had rusted to uselessness long ago.

But what really caught my attention, as we cautiously moved past those great hulks, was the wreckage of smaller boats. Tiny things, completely unsuited for long trips on the sea, and incredibly simple; plain metal troughs with an engine at one end and a ramp opening at the other end.

Dusty caught my look of curiosity. “What are they?”

“Landing craft,” I said. “Which is a little odd. I thought Equestria stopped using them after the Raptors entered service, but this looks like they were conducting a landing. Perhaps some sort of exercise?”

“Unless these are zebra boats,” Dusty pointed out. “Did they use anything like these?”

“That would have made the news for sure,” I said as we walked by one of the craft in question, canted slightly in the shallows and eaten through by rust. Any markings had long since been lost to the elements.

Passing a couple more landing craft, and rounding a small, sandy ridge, we finally caught a glimpse of Baltimare.

The silhouettes of ancient towers broke the horizon like giant skeletons of the old world. I raised my binoculars, peering out at our destination. From that distance, still many miles away, I could just make out debris hanging from the tall structures. Thin strips hung between the towers, like great vines.

A giant bay lay between us and our destination, and around its rim, the tangled vegetation grew from flooded land, as if the end of the swamp and beginning of the ocean was more of a vague suggestion than a real, tangible thing. That continued right on to the city itself; what had once been streets were now water, leaving the towers that broke the surface as monolithic islands.

“What happened here?” I wondered aloud. I had expected burned-out buildings, but not a half-flooded city.

Dusty stepped up, scoping out the city with his own binoculars. “I wonder if the zebras hit it with a seismic megaspell? Something like Trotsen? Though I would’ve thought that would take down the towers.”

I merely grunted. For having been alive when they were created, I found I had fairly limited knowledge on the variety of megaspells that might have existed.

“This might complicate things,” Dusty noted. “Hopefully those offices you’re looking for are above the surface.”

“I can turn into something aquatic, if necessary,” I said, though I frowned as I said it. “Given the colorful wildlife we’ve already found in the water, I’d prefer to avoid that.”

Dusty gave a dry chuckle. “Well, we’ll know soon enough. We’re almost there.” He looked to me. “Find us a path.”

I nodded, slipped off my pack, and took to the air.

Progress was even slower from there. Almost everything was water, with few stretches of dry land to be found. Eventually, I guided us a bit further inland to a faint, plant-choked ridge that ran almost the whole way to Baltimare.

We were about three miles away from the city when I flew up to get one final view of the terrain ahead, hovering just above the canopy. It looked simple enough; simply follow this ridge all the way down, and a short trip across a narrow isthmus that connected to a portion of the city still above the surface.

It was only then that I caught glimpses of something out-of-place. In the chaotic tangle of wild plants, the geometric shape of straight edges caught my eye. I raised my binoculars, peering out at it.

Just visible between the trees was a palisade of decaying wood and rusted metal. I followed the line it suggested, catching glimpses of the structure through narrow gaps in the foliage. The roof of a crude building poked out beside a dead tree, gray and sagging. Then I saw the tower, simple and rickety. Inside, a pair of binoculars were pointed straight at me, clutched in the talons of a griffon.

For a long moment, nothing happened. I just hovered there, as if, by not moving, I might disappear.

Then the griffon moved one of its taloned hands from its binoculars and gave a slow, hesitant wave.

Uncertain of the situation and lacking any better idea of what to do, I gave a tentative wave of my own. Then I tucked my wings in, plunging below the canopy once again.

I landed heavily enough that Dusty immediately looked my way. “Trouble?”

“Not yet,” I said, before realizing how ominous that must have sounded when coupled with the speed of my return. I quickly clarified. “There’s a settlement ahead. Couldn’t see much, but they’ve got a griffon on watch, and they saw me. So, from here on, I’m a pegasus. Other than that, same cover story.”

Dusty arched an eyebrow. “Cover story?”

“Yeah,” I said. “Remember? Grew up on a farm, read lots of books, parents died, etcetera. Hmm. And all I knew about the Enclave is that they’re bad ponies. That should work.”

Starlight hummed. “So, like, were your parents from the Enclave, or did they always live here, or… or what?”

I started to quickly piece together a backstory, but within a few moments I realized the main problem with it: it was too much detail in too short of a time. “We’ll say my parents were pegasi, but let’s leave it at that. If they ask something about my past that isn’t already covered by my previous story, just say you never asked or direct them to me. Keeps things simple.”

“Assuming they’re not outright hostile,” Dusty said. “You saw a griffon, right? Just the one?”

“I could only see a watch tower and the outside of some walls,” I said. “Could be any number of ponies or anything else in the settlement.”

“I’m tempted to bypass it.” Dusty rolled his head to gesture to his bags. “We’ve got plenty of supplies to make the trip.”

“Except they know we’re out here,” Starlight said. “Besides, I could use a real bed for once.”

“And I could use a good fuck,” Sickle chimed in. “Since Dusty’s gone all super-prude again.”

“Somepony had to be on watch and un-distracted,” Dusty shot back. “And I’m not planning on walking into potential danger just because you want to have sex with half the wasteland.”

“Only half?” Sickle said with a grin, followed by a chuckle. “And shit, Dusty, you really think anypony’s dumb enough to fuck with us?”

“Wouldn’t be the first time.”

Sickle laughed. “Yeah, and how many of those fuckers are still alive, huh? You worry too much.”

Eventually, it was settled that we’d at least approach the settlement and see if it looked friendly.

It was almost an hour later when we arrived. From just inside the treeline, our E.F.S. highlighted almost a dozen contacts, none of which were hostile. Poking forward a bit, we finally laid eyes on the decrepit little settlement.

The crude walls were in terrible disrepair, with rotting wooden poles crudely lashed together with rusty wire. A few places were reinforced with metal signs tied onto the poles. Many sections of the wall bore heavy scarring from blades or claws. It was hard to tell if the way the wall bowed and sagged was due to shoddy construction, the wear of elements, or from patching places where the wall had been breached.

The tower itself, a simple box lashed to a long-dead tree, was directly over the gate. The griffon I had seen from before was still up there, and was joined by a trio of zebras poking over the wall. All appeared armed, though only half of those arms were guns. One of the zebras held a spear, while the other carried a bow.

They saw us almost immediately as we stepped out from the trees. The griffon sat up a bit straighter, then raised her talons to wave. “Ho, there!” she called out, though the rifle leaned against the side of the tower shifted as her other hand gripped it. “Who the heck are you?”

“Travelers,” Dusty called back. “We—”

“Travelers?” the rifle-armed zebra cut in, his accent thick. “No pony travels here. Why have you come?”

The griffon frowned down at him for the interruption, but said nothing.

Dusty called out again. “That’s kind of why we’re here. I’d always heard nopony comes this way because of the swamps, so we thought the place might not have been scoured clean like everywhere else. Didn’t expect to find any folk out this way.”

“And we didn’t expect to see any travelers,” the zebra replied. “Are you telling us you came all the way through the swamps to get here?”

The bow-armed zebra had stiffened, then leaned over and urgently whispered to the rifle-armed one. They conferred a moment, casting glances our way.

“We did,” Dusty said. I noted that he hadn’t advanced any further. “It’s not the most friendly of places, but manageable with some caution.” He paused, looking down at the wall. “Looks like it’s pretty rough around here, too.”

The rifle-armed zebra turned his full attention back to us. “It is,” he said, his tone quite serious, and raised a hoof to point. “Metal pony. Is that the head of a swamp-claw?”

Dusty opened his mouth to speak for her, but Sickle ignored him. “Is that what these fuckers are called? Then yeah, guess so. Bitch tried to claw me up, so I cut its fucking head off.”

The zebra stared at us silently, while the two beside him whispered to him, eyes wide and ears perked. Finally, the zebra who had been speaking to us relaxed, his rifle lowering to rest against the wall. “I think we might want to talk. Come in.”

“Thank you,” Dusty said, though he hesitated a moment before advancing.

The other two zebras continued to watch with a mixture of fear and excitement. The gate rattled and thumped as a pair of zebras, clearly visible through the gaps, unlatched and dragged it open. Up above, the griffon grinned happily. It was a little unnerving, but my E.F.S. ensured me that none of them were currently hostile.

I could see Dusty felt the same. Though he kept his posture mostly relaxed, even turning his head to look around, I noticed that his muzzle remained low, close to the grip of his rifle.

Beyond the gate were a meager hoofful of shacks, made from whatever scrap they had scrounged up and clustered around a muddy central clearing. By now, the entire place was easily within range of our PipBucks, which revealed maybe twenty beings living there. Many had turned out to see the visitors approaching the gates; thin, weary zebras, watching with wary eyes. Children peeked out through vacant doorways and past parents. A few of the adults carried melee weapons, mostly spears. Most were unarmed. Everything smelled of dampness and decaying wood.

Dusty continued to look around as we passed through the gate, but his expression had lost its hardness.

The griffon had started climbing down the ladder from the tower, her weapon slung across her back. I could see it clearly now, a crude but powerful-looking large-bore pipe gun. More interesting was the rifle belonging to the zebra who had been speaking to us. The zebra guard had hopped down from their platform, and as he approached, his rifle slung across his chest, I could see it was a zebra military rifle. It was old, patched up, and adorned with trinkets, but in apparently good condition.

The zebra in question stopped before Dusty, looking him square in the face for a second before sighing. His ears drooped a little as he raised a hoof, offering it to Dusty. “Welcome to Dawn,” he said. “...or what is left of it.”

Chapter Twenty Nine: The Sunken City

“You are guests in our home,” said Seroon, the zebra carrying the adorned rifle and, as it turned out, the closest the tiny settlement had to a leader. While not quite the oldest of the tribe, he was well up there in years, and it was impossible to miss the way the other zebras looked to him. “We should extend every hospitality we can.”

Despite the wariness he had shown at our sudden appearance, he was certainly a gracious host. While the tiny settlement had little in the way of comforts, he and a few other zebras laid out mats in the tiny central clearing for us to sit upon, and moments later, brought out food.

Dusty looked down at the plate that had been set before him. It was a decent meal of cooked meat and vegetables which, from what I could see, must have represented a significant portion of what the settlement had available. The younger zebra who set a similar plate before me was barely an adult, and from the prominence of his ribs, could have used the food far more than I could. I could tell from Dusty’s expression that he felt as uncomfortable as I did about taking food that these zebras clearly needed, and just as uncomfortable about any offense we might give by spurning the show of generosity.

“Hell, works for me,” Sickle said, already halfway through her own plate; bits of half-chewed food flew from her lips as she talked around a full mouth. “Shit’s pretty damn good, too!”

While Dusty shot her a scowl, I tried a diplomatic approach. “Thank you for your hospitality,” I said, smiling and nodding to Seroon. “I was wondering, would you permit us to offer you some gifts for your kindness?”

The question distracted him from Sickle’s poor table-manners. “It is generous of you to offer, but that is not necessary. We offer our hospitality freely to those who would come in peace into our home. We do not expect any physical reward.”

I was already opening my packs. Though they were not as bulging as when we had set out across the Hayseed Swamps, they still contained a substantial amount of food; the abundant and aggressive wildlife had at least provided a good deal of food to supplement that which we had brought with us. “I understand it is not necessary, but I’d still like to offer this,” I said as I pulled out several cans, bags, and boxes, including the package of dried fruits I had been saving. I set them before Seroon, smiling. “I’ve always believed that kindness brings kindness.”

I felt so very much like Emerald.

Seroon stared down at my offering, a silent war of emotions underway behind his expression. Finally, he sighed. “You remind me of my grandmother, young pegasus. She would say similar things. Our tribe has always strived to live up to those ideals.” He gently touched the package of dried fruits, and gave a slow, sad shake of his head. “But times have grown harsh. It becomes hard to believe in kindness when the world tries so hard to punish it.”

I held my smile. “And I would say that is when kindness is needed the most.”

He looked up, his eyes locking with mine, searching. It was several long, silent moments before his expression cracked, a faint smile showing. “It does seem to have worked well for you.” He drew in a deep breath and waved a hoof. “Please, excuse my melancholy. You are our guests, and deserve better. If times were more kind, I would never wish to bother you with our problems, but I feel as if the spirits of our ancestors must have brought about this meeting. The arrival of a kind-hearted band of warriors, capable of walking this poisoned land and braving the most fearsome beasts within it, it is too portentous to believe it to be chance. What fate has brought you here?”

Sickle snickered. “Kind-hearted, heh.” She elbowed Dusty in the side, while he scowled back and hushed her.

As for myself, I pondered how to reply. Starlight was looking to me, worried. Even Dusty chanced a glance my way. After all, we were here for me, so it seemed only fair that I be the one to decide how much to share.

I looked back to those expectant eyes and settled on my answer.

“I’m looking for my family,” I said. Seroon’s reaction was surprising. His eyes widened, his ears drooping; he looked as if he had just been told someone had died. I quickly continued. “There’s a company that had its regional headquarters in Baltimare. I believe the information there might help me find them.”

Seroon still looked stricken. “This… this family of yours,” he said, his voice suddenly quiet and hesitant. “Would they be a unicorn mare and earth pony stallion?”

I shook my head, giving a questioning look at the curious specificity of the question. “No, they were… like me.”

He let out a soft sigh, relaxing. “That is good to hear. Given the timing of your arrival, I… I feared the worst.”

“Why is that?”

“Because there were two ponies who used to live with us,” Seroon said. “They arrived a few years back, on a foundering boat. We took them in. I know our kind may have a reputation among ponies, but we have always been welcoming of anyone, regardless of their species. We’ve had many ponies live with us over the years, and many others, too.” He gestured to the griffon, who gave a happy nod. I don’t think she’d stopped grinning since we arrived, though she politely remained quiet as we talked. “Though I’m afraid they were the last. They were killed two months ago. When you said you were looking for your family, well…”

“Killed?” Starlight asked.

Seroon hesitated. Some of the other zebras exchanged glances, looking uncomfortable. A few others tensed, jaws tightening. “...Yes,” Seroon said. “We are not the only tribe in these lands. There is another. Long ago, we were kin, but now they see us only as their enemy. They drove us from our homes among the ancient towers, and into the waiting claws and teeth of these swamps. There used to be many ponies in these lands, but they hunted them down relentlessly. I’m afraid you four are the only living ponies that remain.”

While I silently contemplated the situation, Starlight spoke again. “Why would they do that?”

“Because they were deceived,” Seroon said, his expression downcast. “They still see ponies as evil. Corrupt. They don’t see that it was our own leaders who succumbed to madness and brought about the will of the stars. They don’t see that our own people were as much the stars’ pawns as ponies were. They call themselves the Legion, claiming to still be soldiers of a dead nation, and they blame ponies for every wrong the world has suffered.”

We exchanged uneasy glances before I spoke again. “I’ve heard talk like that before,” I said. “Blaming all ponies for things done hundreds of years before they were born. I’m guessing from the look of things here that they consider you to share in that blame.”

Seroon gave a dry snort. “Our ancestors were comrades, once upon a time. Now they call us traitors for opening our eyes. Our tribe took in the ponies who emerged from their underground shelters, trying to build a better world. Their tribe tried to tear it all down, bringing the death and destruction the stars call for. Our friendship with the ponies of this land made our tribe strong, but they hid in the wilderness, slowly picking away at us before slipping away again. They are tenacious in their madness.”

He heaved a sigh, his head sinking. “We have tried to live a better life, to bring some light to the world. Our ancestors named our tribe The Dawnbringers. We would seek to end the nightmare of the stars, just as the dawn brings an end to the night. Now that light is on the verge of being extinguished.” He paused, then looked up, his expression full or caution. “So it is that I must humbly beg of you. Please, kind-hearted warriors. We need your help.”

I looked over to Dusty. He looked back for a moment, contemplating the situation, before speaking. “What did you have in mind?”

“We can’t continue on like this,” Seroon said, his voice weakening. “The swampclaws harass us relentlessly, and we have already lost several tribemates to their attacks. It’s only a matter of time until we can no longer mend these walls. The only refuge from their attacks is the safety of the ancient towers of the city, but we can not contest the Legion. They outnumber us manyfold, and have already killed most of our tribe.”

“How strong are they?” Dusty asked. “How many are we talking about.”

“A great number,” Seroon said. “A hundred, maybe more.”

Dusty gave a faint grimace. “And how many of them can fight?”

“All of them,” Seroon said, his tone grave. “They consider themselves to be soldiers, one and all. They live to fight. The only ones who can not fight are those who are too young or too old to carry a weapon.”

Dusty thought on that for several long seconds before looking at me again, his expression silently questioning.

“I hope you’re not wondering what I think you’re wondering,” I said to him, my ears folding back. “That’s a lot of zebras.”

Seroon was staring at me, his eyes appraising.

“But possible?” Dusty asked, and I sighed.

“Theoretically,” I said, slow and hesitant. More firmly, I added, “But it would be extremely dangerous. Slow, too. Even if we had all of our resources, it would be difficult, but I only have thirty rounds for my pistol and the single explosive charge. That’s not much to work with.” I shifted uncomfortably, feathered wings shuffling at my sides. “...Not to mention, that’s a lot of lives to take.”

Dusty looked thoughtful; I could practically see him sliding pieces into place as he worked out a plan.

As he did so, Seroon spoke up, his voice quiet. “You must be an incredibly dangerous pony.”

I blinked as I realized he had spoken to me.

Sickle laughed around a mouthful of food before speaking. “What, Whisper? Hah! Shit, I guess she is!” This only seemed to make her laugh harder.

“Not really,” I said, trying to ignore Sickle’s laughter. “More like… situationally dangerous, I guess.”

Seroon nodded, his eyes never leaving mine. “You are an assassin.”

“No,” I quickly said, even as I thought of Big Gun and the not-quite Wild Runner. “...I just do a passable impression of one. Reluctantly. I prefer diplomatic solutions.”

“I understand,” he said. “I too would prefer another course, but the Legion seems determined to leave us no choice. We tried a diplomatic solution, after they drove us from the city. My predecessor went to reason with them. I know not what words were exchanged. We could only watch from a distance.” He grimaced. “They spoke for less than a minute before the Legion seized him, cut his throat, and dumped his body into the sea.”

I frowned, but nodded.

It was Dusty that spoke next. “How well armed is this Legion?”

“Well enough,” Seroon said. “They have at least twenty or thirty working rifles, and now they have all the emplaced guns our ancestors had scavenged from their ships. If they had any idea we had only two rifles, I imagine they would have come to finish us off for good, instead of leaving us for the swamp to devour.”

Dusty was slowly shaking his head. “I… I don’t know. It’s a bad situation.”

Seroon nodded, but I caught the subtle way his expression fell, and how his ears no longer stood quite so upright.

“We need to go into the city for our own business,” Dusty said, his eyes focused on the food he had still not touched. “We can at least get a closer look to appraise the situation. See what we’re facing.”

“Thank you for considering it,” Seroon said. “And I don’t intend to ask you to do this without compensation. I don’t know what we could offer you, but if it is within our means, you shall have it.”

Dusty gave a dismissive wave of his hoof. “Don’t worry about it.”

Seroon hesitated, then nodded again. “As you wish. Again, I’m sorry for disturbing this greeting with such talk. Please, eat. We can discuss this further once you have completed your search.” He turned to me. “And if there is anything we can do to help you find your family, you need only ask.”

“That’s very kind of you,” I said. “Thank you.”

Seroon left us to eat, even stopping to divert the approaching griffon, who pouted before turning to climb the rickety watchtower once more. A zebra mare brought around a pitcher of water, but mostly, they kept their distance. I assumed they weren’t certain what to think of us. I saw many hopeful looks, chanced when they thought we weren’t looking, but they seemed wary of engaging with us.

Personally, I considered my lessons in practical psychology. The implications of their behavior left me even more hopeful that there was something we could do to help them. These were people on the verge of giving up hope.

Dusty quietly slid up to me. “Whisper, I’d like you to run some recon as soon as it gets fully dark. I’m not sure when the best time will be to move into the city, but I’d like to get some idea of what we’re walking into. Something we can start planning with.”

“Of course,” I said. “Let me finish eating, then I can head out. I can scope things out from a distance while there’s still light.”

“Sounds good,” Dusty said, turning to rummage through his bags. “About time we got around to getting these hooked up, too.”

He drew out one of our broadcasters, presenting it to me.

We spent a couple minutes setting up the broadcasters and testing that they worked. I was a little uneasy that they sent voice traffic in the clear, for anyone to listen in on. Dusty assured me that we wouldn’t be transmitting any sensitive data, and in any case, it was unlikely that anyone would be listening on the specific frequency we used, especially if we kept transmissions brief and to-the-point. I reluctantly agreed. Besides, the thought of coding up a real-time audio encryption spell that could interface between a PipBuck and a broadcaster was enough to give me a minor headache. It certainly wasn’t something I would be able to just slap together on the fly.

I finished up the last of the meal, which was actually quite good after a week of mostly old oats, and set out. I flew below the canopy, weaving my way between trees, until I reached the edge of the overgrown forest. A quick scan around revealed no hostile contacts on my E.F.S., so I settled in between the bushes, pressing forward enough to see out through the clearing ahead.

The land opened up as it led into what was once a teeming city. The ruins on the outskirts were small and crumbling, overgrown with vines and other plant-life. Those ended where the water of the bay had overcome the land. Only a few broken roofs pierced up through the water, leaving the bay dotted by tiny artificial reefs and islands, until one finally reached the core of the city, where the skeletons of ancient towers thrust high into the sky. Even after the megaspells and the centuries of wear, a dozen towers still stood, like unyielding sentries.

I remained hiding, using the fading light to scope out the towers and approaches in my binoculars. What had looked like vines growing between the towers now showed to be bridges, cobbled together from cables, scrap metal, and other debris. While the windows of the great towers had long since been destroyed, many on the lower levels were now sealed over with scrap. More scrap, mostly signs and fallen trees, formed rickety walkways between the islands of rooftops, leaving a narrow and exposed path from the shore and the cluster of towers. Two similar paths crossed the gap on the other sides, and all ended in reinforced gates at one of the towers.

Walkways and wasteland fortifications overlooked those paths, with small clusters of zebras standing guard. I could see a pair of machine guns mounted in the lower levels of a tower beside the nearest path, and above the gate itself stood a turreted energy weapon. It must have been taken from one of the ships, and was fairly small for a cannon, but it would still make the entire approach a deathtrap.

Most of the construction seemed centered on the lower levels. There was a bit of construction along the top of the tallest tower, and a few bridges from it, but otherwise the activity seemed constrained to the first few floors. That made sense to me. There was no reason to climb high up in the tower if you didn’t have to, and even if they had well over a hundred zebras, they had a tremendous amount of living space in those towers.

After scanning over the towers some more, and tracking a group of spear-and-rifle-armed zebras patrolling around the fortifications, I turned to my map. I had the address of the C.L.T. regional offices, thanks to the other facilities I had visited, and now that I could see the city clearly, I could try to narrow it down further.

I located the submerged ancient streets on the map. The map gave the option to place a navigation marker, and I did so, with a similar mark appearing on my E.F.S. compass. Looking between the remaining towers and the map itself, I finally narrowed in on a mid-height tower, just to the west of the tallest tower and near the middle of them all. I only had to hope that they’d had their office in one of the upper levels.

The sky rapidly darkened. Somewhere, out past the western clouds, the sun had set. The gentle sea breeze rapidly turned icy, and dots of light started sparking from within the towers as the zebras lit fires and turned on lights. Almost all of them were in the lowest few levels, closest to the paths in and out. Only a single point of light shone from the tallest tower, flickering in the distance.

I waited another half-hour before closing my eyes and channeling my magic. When they opened again, they were the pupil-free eyes of a changeling, soaking in every bit of available light. With that, I rose up, spread my wings, and took to the air.

In the darkness, I was as good as invisible, while my eyes took in everything. From where I flew, roughly even with the middle of the towers, I could see how they all connected, the defenses over the approaches, and the gaps where they thought nobody could possibly come from. After all, they faced other zebras and ground-bound ponies. The sky and sea were safe.

I arced away, flying back towards Dawn.

I was descending toward the tiny settlement when faint flickers of light flashed beneath the canopy. A second later, the distant popping of gunfire reached my ears. I put on the speed, wings beating as I slapped the button on my broadcaster. “Dusty? What’s going on? I hear shooting!”

There was two seconds of gut-wrenching silence before my earbud crackled and Dusty’s distorted voice came from it. “Situation’s under control”, he said, his voice muffled, presumably from the grip of his rifle. “What’s your position?”

“I’m flying in right now,” I replied. “I’ll be there in twenty seconds.”

“Copy. Come in high, stay clear of the fire.”

“You got it.”

As I came in over the trees, I saw the swampclaw staggering away from the broken palisade. Dusty was methodically putting rounds down-range as it started to lope away.

A blinding flash of red dazzled my vision, and I swerved, suddenly disoriented. I quickly reverted my minor alteration, regaining a bit of vision as I leveled out.

Dusty had released his rifle, supporting the muzzle with one hoof. “Friendly coming in high!” he shouted, then repeated the call. Even with his warning, a couple of the zebras jerked and spun my way as I landed before realizing who I was.

Past him, through the ruined gap in the palisade, I could see the swampclaw lying some fifty yards away, while the last of the red embers cast off by Starlight’s shot faded around it. It let out a pained bellow, clawing at the ground with vicious foreclaws, while its hindlegs and tail remained still. A deep chunk of its lower back had been burnt away by the shot.

The resident griffon bound up to the teetering platform beside the wall, grinning widely. “Holy crap!” she called out, in a surprisingly high voice. “You weren’t kidding about that thing.”

Starlight was calmly walking up to the gap in the wall, swapping the dull crystal from her Lancer with a fresh, faintly glowing one. “I’m still annoyed that these things are so durable. I’ve taken out power armors with less difficulty than these things.”

“Took it down with one hit,” the griffon cheerfully observed. “Cut the spine. It’s dead, it’s just too stubborn to know it! Cool!”

“Yeah, well…” Starlight shut the chamber of her Lancer, leveling it again. There was another flash and crack, and half the swampclaw’s head vaporized. “I’d rather make it clean instead of… that.”

“Killing ain’t clean,” Sickle rumbled as she walked up to the gap. There was a fresh cut in the plating across her chest, but no blood. “‘Sides, probably be boring if it was.”

Starlight scowled. “Can still kill without making ‘em suffer. That just isn’t right.”

Dusty dropped his rifle to its sling, and nodded to the wall. “We need to get that hole patched up.”

“Don’t worry,” the griffon said, turning from Starlight. “We’ll get it all fixed up nice and quick. I don’t think they’ll be quite so eager now that you lot killed one of ‘em!”

“Eh, let ‘em come,” Sickle said, grinning under her muzzle. “These fucks are kinda fun.”

“We’ve got a job to do,” Dusty said. “I’d like to make sure their defenses are going to hold while we take care of that.”

“It’ll be fine,” the griffon said with a cheery grin.

Seroon caught our attention as he walked up. “She is right,” he said, slowly slinging his trinket-adorned rifle across his back. “The swampclaws are aggressive, but patient. They take their time. We will not see another attack before morning.”

“Are you sure?” Dusty asked, his expression concerned.

“Sure enough,” Seroon replied with a nod. “And if they were to return earlier, we can hold them off, even if I have to spend the last of our ammunition. We will survive until you return.”

“Yeah,” the griffon said, and turned her grin to me. “And you better come back, too! Starlight was telling me stories, and I’ll bet you’ve got some good ones! Oh!” She bound forward, offering her talons in a friendly gesture. “I’m Bloodbeak.” She immediately rolled her eyes, chuckling. “Don’t mind the name. It’s a griffon thing.”

“I’ll take your word on it,” I said as I offered my hoof, and we shook.

“Good!” she said, then gave me a firm pat on the shoulder. “Now go find your family.”

Eventually Dusty led us off to the side, while several half-awake zebras patched up the wall. “So,” he said, sitting before me. “How’s it look?”

“The Legion they spoke of is holed up in the towers that were the heart of Baltimare,” I said in a quiet voice, and sat down as well. “It’s well-fortified, with a few narrow and exposed paths watched over by emplaced weapons. The towers themselves are connected by bridges a few levels up. I may not be well-experienced in tactics, but it seemed to me like it would be an extremely defensible position. On the plus side, their activity seems concentrated around the lower levels, and they have to use those same exposed paths to get out of their territory. I didn’t see any boats.”

Dusty grunted, slowly shaking his head. “Sounds bad. How about the C.L.T. offices?”

“I found the building,” I said. “A tower, about halfway into their territory. I have no idea what level it’s on. I’d have to go in to find it, and I wanted to at least talk with you first.”

“Good,” Dusty said. “I’d prefer to not send you in alone, if possible. Did you find a way in?”

“The easiest way in is flying into the middle levels of the tower, but that isn’t really an option for all of you.” I frowned. “And the front door is obviously out.”

“Makes me miss Vulture,” Dusty said. “Seems like a perfect time for a roof insertion. She’s not exactly subtle, though.”

Starlight gave a soft snicker. “We could hear that contraption from a few miles away.”

“A skywagon might work, though,” Dusty said. “I know there are wrecks all over the place back around Mareford. Baltimare must have had a few. If we’ve got a pegasus, we should take advantage of it.”

“Key word there: wrecks.” Starlight shook her head. “Half of them fell out of the sky when the megaspells went off, and the others have been rusting and picked apart for centuries. There aren’t any pegasi below the clouds, so nopony ever had a use for them. A working skywagon is probably more rare than a working motorwagon. Even if we did find one I could fix up, I have no idea how long it’d take to get it working.”

Dusty frowned, thinking for a moment. “Is there any other way to get us in?”

Starlight hummed thoughtfully. “Maybe a boat? This was a harbor city, right? Must be some boats still around, and that should be an easy patch job.”

“It also has us going in where the zebras are the most dense,” I pointed out.

“Oh no,” Sickle said with an exaggerated roll of her head. “We might have to kill some of the zebras we have to kill anyway.”

“A hundred-plus zebras is too much for us to fight,” Dusty said. “We might be able to take on the zebras in our way, but it takes just one loud noise or one little mistake for all of them to come pouring in, and we die.”

Sickle shrugged. “Eh, I think we can take ‘em. Can’t be any worse than thirty mercs, and Whimper took them out all on her own.”

“How many are in the building?” Starlight asked, and I shook my head.

“I don’t know,” I said. “Given the number of towers and the number of zebras, I’d guess less than twenty, but it could be quite a bit more. It’s one of the smaller towers, but there’s still a lot of room on the levels they’re occupying, so it could be more. I’d have to get closer and count markers to get a better idea.”

Dusty was looking off into space and slowly shaking his head. “Inserting by boat is a possibility, but I don’t like it. We can cut the bridges, but that would only delay reinforcements. It still leaves a lot of zebras between us and our goal, and getting out on a boat would be much too exposed if they’re alert and shooting at us.”

“Still better than a skywagon we don’t have,” Starlight said with a frown.

“I don’t think we’re all getting in,” I said. “I know, you probably won’t like the idea, but unless we can find and patch up a skywagon before dawn, we don’t have a way to get all of you safely in and out of that tower.”

Dusty mulled it over for several seconds before slowly shaking his head. “I know you’re the one with all the stealth and infiltration training, so I’ll leave the final call up to you, Whisper. I just don’t like the idea of you going into an area like that on your own. You remember what happened at Paradise Beach.”

“Flying away wasn’t an option for me back then,” I said. “It is now. Still, I’d rather have Starlight there. It’s very unlikely that any servers are still powered and running, and while I could probably get them working again, she’s much more experienced at that. I can’t carry all of you, but I can carry her there and back.”

Starlight cocked her head to the side, eyes distant. “Huh. That could be cool. I’ve never really gone flying before. I mean, there was the time you lifted me into the wagon, but that was like five feet. That doesn’t count.”

Dusty slowly nodded. “I suppose that might work.”

“And it leaves you and Sickle free to help defend Dawn,” I noted.

“It does,” Dusty said. “Though I’m thinking we might be able to support you some. Or at least, I can.” He uncovered his PipBuck, switching to the map screen. “Which tower are you going to?”

I pointed it out, and he pointed to the shore on the opposite side. “Then I’ll set up here. If you need a distraction, give me a call on your broadcaster. I’ll draw their attention my way so you can get out.”

Sickle snorted. “And I get to sit on my ass being bored while you cunts do the fun stuff. Wonderful.”

Starlight rolled her eyes. “I’m sure we’ll find another swampclaw for you to fight or something.”

“Eh.” Sickle shrugged. “We’ll see.”

“If we’re going to do this,” I said, “we should do it soon. I don’t even know what level the C.L.T. offices are on, and if there isn’t a directory listing anywhere, that means we’ll have to search the entire tower.”

Starlight nodded. “And if they’re down where the zebras are?”

“If that’s the case, we’ll have to come up with a plan to deal with that situation,” I said. “Even if it means backing out and coming back later.”

“I still don’t like how much of a disadvantage we’re working under,” Dusty said, “but unless Seroon knows of a skywagon in good condition, it sounds like this might be our best option for getting it done.”

Unsurprisingly, he did not.

☢

Starlight and I approached the bay from the west, nearest to our destination. We kept a keen eye on our E.F.S. display for threats, but the wildlife seemed to steer clear of us.

We traveled light. Our bags were almost empty, carrying only the tools we might need and a single healing potion each. Despite that, we still carried our weapons. It was like a stark, physical reminder of what could happen if we were discovered.

We slipped out from the treeline and between the ruins of old buildings, overgrown and crumbling, while ancient rubble crunched quietly under our hooves. Most of the structures were so decayed that they would offer no real shelter, but supplied plenty of shadows to hide a lurking pony or zebra. Even with our E.F.S., we stayed alert.

Several tense minutes later, we reached a long line of debris, mostly wood and other light materials. It was the high-water mark, and several yards beyond it, the water of the bay lapped lightly at the cracked road. The street beyond was completely flooded, leaving a canal between the ruined buildings. In the gloom of the night, they perfectly framed the nearest tower, still a quarter of a mile away.

We crouched behind a weather-worn driftwood log. “Check your gear,” I whispered. Several seconds were spent checking the straps on bags and weapons, securing pouches, and otherwise ensuring nothing would be lost or rattle during our flight. PipBuck maps were consulted one final time before turning off their screens. Finally, I pressed at my earbud, ensuring it was seated securely in my ear, and raised my hoof to my mouth.

“Radio check,” I murmured into the broadcaster. “Dusty, do you hear us?”

The reply came a couple of seconds later, only slightly distorted. “I read you loud and clear,” Dusty said.

Starlight raised her own PipBuck. “How about me?”

“Loud and clear,” Dusty repeated.

“Okay,” I said, heaving a slow, deep breath, and exhaled. “Let’s get hooked up.”

Starlight’s horn lit up, her magic lifting the crude harness of weapon slings and belts. While she remained crouched, I stepped over her, and she fastened the harness around the pair of us. It took only a few seconds. “Okay, give it a test.”

I stood up as high as I could, her weight bearing down on the straps across my shoulders and back. A quick pump of my wings gave the whole thing a good shake, but it held snug.

Starlight shook faintly. For a moment, I thought it was nerves. Then I realized she was trying not to laugh.

“Is something wrong?” I asked.

“Sorry, sorry,” Starlight said, unable to help snickering quietly. “I’m just really glad Sickle isn’t around right now to get the wrong idea about this.”

I was suddenly very aware of her back pressing snugly against my chest and belly, with her tail right between my hind-legs. “I suppose this is a somewhat compromising position.”

Her snickering grew, and she quickly shook her head. “Sorry. Serious mode now. Focusing. Right.”

I chuckled softly, giving a gentle nuzzle at the back of her neck, then turned to my broadcaster again. “Okay, Dusty. We’re heading in now.”

“Copy that,” Dusty replied. “Update me when you’re hooves-down, and good luck.”

“Will do,” I said, and lowered the PipBuck again. “You ready for this?”

Starlight’s expression tightened up, and she gave a firm, determined nod.

My wings beat, lifting the weight from my hooves. I hovered just long enough to wrap my forelegs firmly around Starlight’s barrel, then began my ascent.

We cleared the rooftops, slowly arcing away to keep our distance as I gained altitude. Starlight tensed, but remained silent, her head twisting to look around. I could see our destination clearly, the tower rising some twenty floors above the waterline. I set my sights on the middle of the tower, several levels above where the Legion had built up. I continued to climb until we drew even with it, and then continued on just a little higher.

Once I judged our altitude to be high enough, I banked in. My beating wings stilled as I entered a glide, giving the muscles a much-needed break. We closed quickly, while I balanced speed with altitude, aiming for the gaping holes that had once been windows.

We sailed into the darkness, and I quickly back-winged, cutting our speed and coming to a halt just as our hooves touched the ground. Bits of debris crunched underhoof once more. Once we had stopped, everything fell into complete silence, save for the soft moan of the sea breeze and the occasional faint groan of the ancient tower.

My E.F.S. was filled with hostile contacts in every direction. I silently cursed the two-dimensional mentality behind its design. Clearly, there hadn’t been many pegasi on the design team.

I undid the harness, freeing Starlight. Once I stepped away, she stood, panting softly, legs trembling. I was worried until she turned to me, her smile beaming in the darkness, and quietly hissed, “That was awesome!”

I had to suppress a laugh, despite the adrenaline already burning at my nerves. I quickly held a hoof up to my grin, signaling for quiet, and she nodded, taking a seat to catch her breath.

While she did so, I raised my PipBuck, whispering quietly into it. “Dusty, we’re in.”

A hint of static overlapped his voice. “Copy. Update me if anything comes up. I’ve got eyes on the area. I’ll let you know if I see any activity.”

I lowered my hoof again, tucking in the loose straps of the harness as I looked around. The space we landed in might have been an open workspace at some point, or perhaps a large meeting room. Whatever it had been, now it stood completely vacant, save for the detritus of fallen and crumbling ceiling panels and the glittering pebbles of glass. The entire interior of the tower had been mostly open, with at least half of the walls being floor-to-ceiling windows. Their remains lay scattered about in dull fragments that were more dangerous as a source of noise than potential injury.

“Okay,” I whispered as I moved in close to Starlight. “This is more your area of expertise. Where can we find what floor C.L.T. is on?”

She rose to her hooves, hiding her grin again. “Right. We need a directory. Main lobby is out, so we should find the elevators. They usually have a basic directory. That should tell us what’s on the current level, at least.”

I nodded. “Lead the way.”

We carefully picked our way through the debris on the floor, working our way toward the center of the building. Soon, we were far enough in that Starlight turned her PipBuck screen on again, its faint green glow much more subtle than the harsh light of our flashlights.

Her tail flicked against me as she came to a halt. We’d reached the end of a hall, which opened into a small lobby. The doors of two elevators opened into vacant shafts along one of the walls, while the broad greeting desk opposite them stood in decaying silence, warped and ruined by centuries of sea air.

After a moment to look around the room, Starlight stepped forward, and we got to searching. She first went to a placard by the elevators themselves, while I went to the desk. In addition to open drawers with decayed papers, there was a terminal, its case pitted with corrosion. Naturally, the power button didn’t work. I turned to shuffling through the papers until Starlight got there.

She slipped up close to me when she returned. “I could barely read the sign,” she whispered, “but C.L.T. isn’t on this level.”

“See if you can get the terminal up,” I whispered in reply. “This was probably a secretary’s station. Maybe they’ll have something.”

“On it!” She slipped around behind the terminal, prying off the back of the case while I continued searching through the papers. Most were illegible. I gave up when she finally got the terminal working. It continually complained about a lack of connection to the server, while I skimmed through what little data it contained.

To our relief, one of the files was a building directory, and I smiled as the name Crystal Life Technologies popped up. “There we go. Floor eight.” I scrolled up. “And we’re on… floor fourteen.” I frowned, running the math and trying to recall the exact layout I had seen from the air. “I think that’s one floor up from the built-up area.”

“Oh,” Starlight said, grimacing. “Wonderful.”

She led us around until we found the stairs, and we slowly made our way down. As we neared the lower levels, we traded places; I led, pistol ready, while she trailed just behind me. We stepped slow and careful, producing hardly a sound.

We reached the door to floor eight. I took a slow, deep breath, readying myself. Then I cracked the door open, slowly opening a tiny sliver to peer through. Only darkness met me. With a brief moment of relief, I opened the door, and we slipped through, letting it shut quietly behind us.

It was easy to find the C.L.T. regional offices, with the name emblazoned in badly faded and flaking letters above the doors. We silently made our way in, overly conscious of every faint sound we made. I knew, intellectually, that the thick floors of a high-rise tower should muffle anything we do, short of throwing around furniture or gunshots, but every little click of hooves or tiny crunch of crumbling debris made me fear some keen zebra ear detecting our presence.

Once we were in and the door was closed, Starlight leaned in close, whispering in a barely audible voice. “Okay, we’re here. What exactly are we looking for?”

“Anything that would have a list of C.L.T. facilities in the region,” I whispered back. “Shipping data, company registries, mailing lists, anything like that.”

She nodded, and we got to searching.

The offices were in even worse condition than those above. Anything wooden was halfway rotten through after the years in the sea air, and most things made of metal were badly corroded. Desk after desk turned up nothing but decaying, water-bleached papers, all illegible. Many desks held terminals, their cases badly corroded, sometimes so badly that you could see the internals of the devices. We ignored them; if the papers turned up nothing useful, as proved the case, there was a better place to look for digital data.

The server had been somewhat protected from the elements by the room it was in, but it had still fared poorly over the years. The outside was pitted and stained. I had to hope the inside hadn’t corroded.

“Think you can get it powered up?” I whispered.

“Maybe.” Starlight paced around it, eventually turning to a device at the back of the room. “It’s got a backup power source, but it looks shot. Not sure how long my batteries would last.”

“If you can get it up and running, I can copy everything over to my PipBuck.”

“Yeah,” she said, looking more closely at the server itself. “Still, I’m having flashbacks of Paradise Beach.”

“I doubt there are any power generators to kick on,” I noted. “Still… maybe you can disconnect it from external power?”

“Exactly what I was thinking,” she whispered with a nod. “Okay. Give me a few minutes. Let’s see what I can do.”

She spent several minutes prying apart the backup power system, disconnecting power leads and testing connections. She pulled out and spliced wires, probed leads, and finally brought out one of her own spark batteries, hooking it up to the rewired system. She paused, the last wire hovering just over the battery. “I have no idea how loud this will be.”

I looked up from my PipBuck, already connected to the server. “If it’s too loud, pull the battery, and I’ll fly us out. We can always come back later and pull the hardware out. Might be a pain to access the data, but it’s an option.”

She nodded, then looked back to her work. She took a deep breath. “Okay.”

The wire connected with a soft pop, and the backup power system thumped, then hummed, a green light flickering to life on its side. A moment later, the server gave a long, quiet beep as lights lit up, followed by the quiet whine as the device came to life. The screen of my PipBuck flashed as data streamed across the cable.

Starlight sighed in relief. “So far, so good.”

“Well done,” I said, watching the boot sequence progressing. “Stand lookout. This shouldn’t take more than a few minutes, but we don’t want any surprises.”

“You’ve got it,” she said with a quick nod, and slipped off to the front of the offices.

The server was not a happy, healthy machine, but it struggled to life. It was an older Stable-Tec brand, and those ponies evidently made things to last. After two centuries in salty, humid conditions, the primary hardware still functioned. Better yet, C.L.T. had shown foresight in their server hardware. While the system reported the failure of fully half of the data storage systems, redundancy meant that all the data was still intact.

I initiated a transfer, copying over the contents of the server’s drives; looking at the tiny PipBuck hooked up to the giant server, it was hard not to reflect on how much computers had advanced in just a decade. Part of me wondered where we would be now, had the megaspells never happened.

While the files transferred, I started looking over what was there. Mostly, it was records of messages sent across various C.L.T. sites. I would have skimmed over the entire directory and continued on, but a single word in one of the subjects caught my attention.

Subject: Permafrost, Sweetdreams, and Serenity

Serenity.

I glanced over at the file transfer. There were still a few minutes remaining. I opened the message.

Skyfrost,

Despite the progress that has been made, I’m afraid we can’t give Permafrost the kind of prioritization you’re asking for. We do appreciate the strides your team has made, but we’re still too far from a feasible product. Yes, the tests have shown great promise, but the role body mass plays in survival rates is far too dramatic to expect ponies to accept. Ponies aren’t going to care if we claim that the data shows the process to be completely safe for infants or small pets. They’re going to see the projected double-digit mortality rates among full-grown subjects and decide that, if it’s not safe for them, it’s clearly too dangerous for their foals. You know how protective parents can be.

Meanwhile, Sweetdreams has produced a viable alternative, and one that’s passed every safety test. It’s something we can deliver now, and it’s been subsidized by the ministries. If we’re going to compete with Stable-Tec, we need a product that ponies can trust, and that means as few doubts as possible. Because of that, and because of the state of the world we live in, we have to shift our focus to rapid implementation of Sweetdreams. It’s not only the best choice for both projects, it’s our best shot at helping as many ponies as quickly as possible.

Please, don’t think that we’re sidelining your project. Permafrost has shown great progress, and if the mortality issues can be rectified, it promises great improvements over the Sweetdreams project. This is a purely temporary matter; getting Sweetdreams up and running will expand our resources and allow us to commit more heavily in Permafrost.

If that’s not reassuring enough, I can offer a tidbit that hasn’t been circulated yet: with the Serenity collaboration nearing completion, and with Stable-Tec's lead designer incorporating our technology into the Ministry-led Single Pony Project, Stable-Tec has opened the possibility of direct collaboration between our companies. We’re very close to working together as partners, rather than competitors. While Serenity insisted upon strict confidentiality agreements for their project, Stable-Tec has said they see their own involvement as a proof-of-concept of licensed and collaborative projects. For all of Stable-Tec's expertise in construction and protective structures, the Stables will only ever be a refuge for a tiny, privileged percent of ponies. Now imagine all those Stables incorporating our life-sustaining technologies. Think of how many lives we could save, should the worst come to pass.

Permafrost is not in any danger of being shut down or sidelined. It carries far too much promise for that. Keep up the good work, and by next fiscal year, we should be well on the way to increasing your funding well above its previous levels.

Respectfully,
Gleaming Facet, C.E.O.

I closed the message, disappointed. Serenity was hardly even mentioned, and it told me nothing I hadn’t known before about that name.

But the message did contain one thing of interest, tucked away in the file data. After following a short trail of digital breadcrumbs, I tracked back to find the message sorting matrix, and from there, it was a short hop to find the company’s entire routing information, both digital and physical.

I had the location of every C.L.T. installation in the world.

Smiling, I raised my hoof and whispered into my broadcaster. “We’ve got what we came for.”

Static overlaced Dusty’s voice in my earbud. “Good to hear. I’m not seeing any activity out here. Come on back.”

Starlight slipped into the room. “You found it?” she whispered as she huddled in close.

“Yep,” I said, watching the transfer for the final few seconds. The moment it stopped, I pulled my cables and turned the screen off. “Kill the power, then let’s get out of here.”

“Sure thing!”

While I stowed the cables, Starlight pulled a single wire, and with a plaintive beep, the server powered down.

With that, we headed back the way we came, eager to leave. We backtracked to the stairwell, cracked open the door, and slipped in.

The door had just shut when another opened below us, and the sound of hooves echoed softly in the narrow space. Two options immediately presented themselves: hide and hope they didn’t come up to where we were, or continue up the stairs to get away and hope they didn’t hear our movement.

I pressed Starlight back into the corner of the landing and crouched before her, drawing my pistol. My ears stood perked, listening intently, hoping for the hooves to grow more distant.

They didn’t. I waited, my pistol leveled. With Starlight’s PipBuck hidden and mine turned off, the stairwell was pitch black until a soft light rose from below, casting feeble, dancing shadows across the wall. It was barely enough to silhouette my pistol’s sights. I aligned them as carefully as I could, and waited. The single set of hooves slowly drew closer.

The exotic mane of a zebra poked into view, followed by the rest of him. The light flared in my eyes. He held a lantern in his teeth, the flickering flame casting off a week, warm light. A rifle lay across his back.

As his lead hoof stepped onto the landing, I engaged S.A.T.S. Two sharp cracks, like a hammer on rock, echoed in the chamber, and the zebra made a grunt of surprise, twisting and dropping the lantern as he fell to his side.

I was already up and advancing, the soft glow of Starlight’s PipBuck lighting the room as the lantern’s flame guttered and died. The zebra lay on his side gasping, his forehooves alternately scratching at the ground or clutching at his chest. I’m not sure if he recognized my presence. He was still alive, but he was out of the fight.

I lined up and put a single round into his head. The zebra stiffened and went still.

I immediately stepped back, keeping my pistol leveled. “Starlight,” I said around the bit, keeping my voice quiet. “Magic. Grab him.”

“W-what?” she said, her wide eyes jerking away from the body to look at me. “Why?”

“We’re bringing him with us,” I said. “We need to hide the body for as long as possible.”

She hesitated, but her horn lit up, and with a grunt of effort, lifted the zebra’s body. She held it at a distance as we climbed the stairs. I could tell she was uncomfortable with her gruesome cargo, but she did what she had to.

When we reached the level we had entered from, I had her set his body down in a small closet well away from the stairs. We stripped him of his rifle and its single magazine of ammunition before shutting the door.

Starlight looked to me. I could still see the discomfort in her eyes, but she nodded. She understood.

At the edge of the building, we strapped ourselves together and stepped out through the window, gliding silently away in the night.

☢

“So, what’ve you got?”

I sat beside Dusty, in the center of Dawn, and brought my PipBuck-clad hoof up. “I looked through every C.L.T. installation in the region. Mostly it’s clinics and some administrative offices, nothing that would be useful to my family.” I didn’t want to be too specific with so many ears around. “There were a total of five research and testing sites in the region, if you include Serenity as one. Paradise Beach was another. That leaves the three experimental sites. We’ve been to Alpha.” I flipped to the map. “Beta is here,” I said, pointing to a spot well west of Rust, then moving to point to another spot just south of Mareford. “And Gamma is here.”

“I think I know that Gamma place,” Dusty said, switching to his own PipBuck. “Rangers were called in to hit some bandits operating out of some ruins right about there. Looked like it had been some lab. There was a sealed section, had been shut for decades, maybe since the war. That was… almost ten years ago, I think.”

I frowned. Being known increased the chance that someone had already gotten in there. “And you didn’t open it?”

“No need,” Dusty said. “Like I said, had been shut for years. We were just there to clean out the bandits, and they obviously weren’t in there. We filed a report, but I doubt anypony investigated further. There’s enough in Dodge City to keep the salvage teams occupied without trekking days out into the desert.”

I nodded. “Well… hopefully nobody else came along to disturb it.” I set my hoof down again. “So we know where to go. That just leaves the question of what we’re going to do here.”

“Yeah,” Dusty grumbled, shaking his head. “That’s the question, ain’t it? I don’t like it. Fighting the Legion seems like a losing bet.”

“I can pick them off from a literal mile away,” Starlight said, shifting her Lancer on its sling for emphasis.

“Yeah, you could do some damage,” Dusty agreed, though without any cheer. “And Whisper could pick some off at night. Still… Whisper’s right about how long it’ll take. This isn’t a fight we’re going to win. Not quick enough to save these folk.”

“So what are we going to do?” Starlight asked.

“Right now?” Dusty shrugged. “Right now, I’m going to sleep. In the morning… I’m going to have to ask Seroon to make a difficult decision.”

☢

The morning sun rose on the horizon, casting a brilliant glow across the sea and the underside of the clouds. It was a beautiful sight, and as we gathered for a shared breakfast, many of the zebras paused to look out at the colorful scene.

Seroon, however, looked concerned over Dusty’s plan. “Why would you ask this?”

“Because I’m afraid I don’t see any other options,” Dusty said. “Even if we were able to track down and kill every single swampclaw in the entire swamp, the Legion would still have to be dealt with. We can pick them off at range, and we can infiltrate behind their lines to take out some more, but that’s the kind of thing that agitates folks. Most likely, all we’d do is provoke them into attacking sooner rather than later. We can hurt them, but we wouldn’t win that fight. I hate to say it, but if you stay here, it’s going to end badly for you.”

Seroon’s ears had fallen. “To abandon our home again…”

“I know it’s hard,” Dusty said. “Hell, I know just how hard it is, but sometimes…” He sighed. “As long as you’re alive, you can always make a new home.”

Seroon slowly looked around at the huts and patched walls that surrounded us. The silence lingered for several long seconds before he spoke again. “We have already been forced from our homes once by the Legion.” His eyes fixed on Dusty. “Our ancestors were stranded here, to never again see the land of their childhood. They forged a new home here, because events forced them to… and because a home is more than simply a patch of land.”

He solemnly nodded. “If you can lead us safely through the swamps, we will follow.”

Chapter Thirty: Exodus

The tribe was ready to move by noon.

They accepted Seroon’s decision with surprisingly little resistance. A few voiced concerns or hesitation, but a few gentle words and a little reasoning from him was all it took to unify them.

With that, the tribe set to gathering up all of their possessions and preparing for the journey. Starlight and I remained on watch while the tribe worked. Bloodbeak joined us a few minutes later, climbing up to the tower with her thin bags. She and Starlight immediately fell into chatting again. Mostly, they talked about food. Every now and then, Bloodbeak would cast a glance my way.

It took less than two hours for the village to pack. Even the most heavily laden zebra carried less than I did.

“The land provides,” a younger zebra said as she strapped on her bags, a spear resting across her back.

“Most of the plants here are poison,” Seroon added, “but not all. Our ancestors learned which are safe to eat. It is not food that concerns me.”

We gathered in the center of the town. The faces around us were full of concern. We were heading out into no-mare’s land, where monsters lurked. Most of the zebras had nothing more than a sharp stick to defend themselves with. Children huddled close to parents; there were a half-dozen of them, most of whom didn’t appear to understand what was going on, only that their parents were worried. Those parents tried to put on a brave face, but it only did so much. This was the second time they had to leave their homes, and the children were quick to pick up on what was happening.

“Stay close,” Dusty said. “Sickle and I will be in the lead. Starlight, Whisper, you’ll be near the middle, covering the flanks. I want that Lancer ready to respond to a threat in any direction. Seroon, I’d like you and any other skilled fighters or hunters watching the back. Everyone else, especially the children, stay in the middle. No matter what happens, nobody wanders off alone or gets isolated. Okay?”

There were nods and grunts of agreement, and Dusty turned to Sickle. “Let’s get going.”

“‘Bout fucking time,” Sickle muttered under her breath, and began plodding along.

We slowly streamed out through the gate. Many of the zebras paused there, whispering a few words and touching the gate one last time before leaving it behind.

As we departed, Dusty slipped back to the middle of the group. “Hey, Whisper.” He glanced back, motioning to Bloodbeak. “You too.”

The griffon trotted up to join us with a curious tilt of her head. Once she was walking alongside Dusty, he continued. “I want us to keep moving as much as possible. Hopefully without more than a couple short breaks each day. I’d like to have one of you up in the air, scouting ahead for paths and wildlife.”

I winced; Dusty had evidently not noticed that Bloodbeak had been using a ladder, or at least not made the same realization I had.

To my surprise, she chuckled. “Oh, I can’t fly,” she said, and lifted her right wing. Her expression tightened as she stretched it as far as it would go, which ended up being hardly at all. While it looked intact enough lying against her side, the wing was a useless knot of muscles and feathers. “Legion bullet got me in the wing, and it healed up all wrong.”

“Oh,” Dusty said, his expression ashen despite her apparent cheer. “Sorry, I hadn’t realized.”

“Nah, it’s okay,” Bloodbeak said, relaxing her damaged wing. “I got used to it years ago.” She glanced my way. “Not to say I don’t miss flying! But hey, could have been a lot worse. At least I crashed where these guys found me. It’s how we met!”

Starlight cut in. “They couldn’t fix it? I thought zebras were really good with alchemy and healing and stuff?”

Bloodbeak chuckled awkwardly. “Eh, turns out, not so much.”

“Zebras in general, perhaps,” Seroon chimed in from behind us; he was with a few other armed zebras at the rear of our column, including one carrying the new rifle we had brought back. “But our ancestors were soldiers, not shaman. The skills they brought with them were of a very different sort.”

“Mareford has some good doctors, even a surgeon,” Dusty said. “I don’t want to get your hopes up too much, but they might be able to help.”

“Woah, wait,” Starlight said. “We’re going to Mareford? Aren’t we kinda, uh… you know…?”

“Is there something wrong?” Seroon asked.

Dusty shook his head. “Nothing wrong, no. It’s the largest settlement in the area, and they’re generally good sorts. They’ll take care of you just fine. Just, we’re not welcome there right now, thanks to a certain pony.”

“Why not Gemstone?” Starlight asked.

“Too small,” Dusty said. “I’m sure they’d want to help, but a group this size would probably strain them to the limits. Same for Rust or any other place. Mareford’s the only settlement that can take on a group this size.” He turned to me. “Anyway, we need that scouting.”

I sighed and shrugged off my bags. Bloodbeak immediately snatched them up, smiling. “I can’t help with the scouting, but at least I can carry your bags while you’re out!”

“Thanks,” I said, offering a smile in return, and took to the air.

☢

The first attack came barely an hour after leaving Dawn.

The swampclaw lurked in the overgrown shallows just ahead, unaware that I had seen it on my E.F.S. as I flew overhead. When it charged, Starlight was waiting. A S.A.T.S.-aimed shot to its face sent it into a limp tumble, ending in a twitching heap at Sickle’s hooves. The pair in the shallows further to our side remained still, watching.

A small flight of mutated parasprites came across the group later in the afternoon. In the evening, a young zebra mare was barely able to warn Sickle before she wandered into the reach of a carnivorous plant. Naturally, Sickle continued on anyway, and when the vines grabbed at her, she tore the plant apart. The zebra that had attempted to warn her looked on in awe.

As dusk approached, Dusty found a patch of dry and relatively clear ground. We spent some time clearing out some more of the brush, opening up sightlines, and preparing for the night.

The roaring started just after dark. The swampclaws kept their distance, calling out. Trees rustled and cracked. Red marks would show on our E.F.S., circling around, and rarely, indistinct forms would move just beyond the reach of our lights. We alternated guard shifts, with one of our group and two zebras at a time, keeping a keen eye out for encroaching threats. When not on watch, we tried to sleep.

Every time I started to drift off, another roar bellowed out across the swamps. My heart lurched, adrenaline pounding as I jerked to life, only to find the situation completely unchanged. Then I would lie down again, trying to force myself to sleep, only for the scenario to repeat itself.

I don’t think I ever properly got to sleep.

I was surprised at how calmly the zebras took it, particularly the children. They’d wake up to the sounds, eyes peering out in the darkness for a few seconds before closing again. The only sound made was a young infant who would cry when woken until his mother gently calmed him.

There was a miasma of lethargy over the group when we set out that morning. I forced my way through it, focusing on my scouting. As I wearily circled around and skimmed over the tree-tops, I could see the swampclaws still lurking, moving with our group. Only a tiny bit of their head and the occasional jagged back-plate broke the surface, leaving thin wakes in the water. Every now and then, one would rise up, scurrying over a patch of dry land to plunge into the water on the opposite side. While our group slowly picked their way through dense vegetation and wound their way through patches of dry ground, they lazily floated along nearby.

A sharp crack and dazzling line of red light sent a spray of mud and steam flying as one of the swampclaws darted across another patch of ground. Down below, I could see Starlight silently curse as she reloaded. Her ears sagged, her eyes as tired as mine were.

The swamp noticed our passage. It seemed every bit of hostile wildlife in the region was drawn to us, as if we had led a buffet out to meet them.

While the swampclaws hung back, hardly an hour went by without running into some kind of danger. Most were the mutated bugs that were so easy to deal with.

As I flew ahead of the group, a trio of mutated bats, which Dusty later identified as bloodwings, darted up at me from the treetops. My tired wings barely responded in time, banking sharply to the side to avoid their initial attack, then wheeling around and beating hard for the rest of the group. Warned by a quick call over the broadcasters, my companions were ready when I flew overhead, trailing the three vicious little beasts. Two fell in the first pass, one to Dusty’s bullets and another to the spectacular overkill of Starlight’s Lancer. The third was too dimwitted to not follow me on a second pass.

Worse was the pair of timberwolves, their wooden bodies charred and smoldering with balefire. I was banking over the group as the beasts charged into the rear. Several rifles snapped and cracked, and with the aid of S.A.T.S., I was able to wheel around and put a few rounds into one before it closed. The rifle fire seemed to do nothing to the magical creatures. Starlight’s Lancer was significantly more effective. The line of angry light struck the lead timberwolf low in the chest, blasting several pieces of charred wood to splinters, and the rest of the beast fell to pieces in a tumble. Then she was reloading, and the second one lunged at the zebras in the rear.

Seroon stumbled back, as did the other rifle-armed guards, while a pair of spear-armed zebras met the timberwolf’s charge. The impact was tremendous, as hundreds of pounds of charred wood slammed into their tiny spears. One zebra fell, his spear snapping in half, while the other desperately jammed her own spear into the beast’s chest, staggering with the impact but holding the beast back for a single crucial moment.

The timberwolf bit the spear, the haft igniting as it tore it from her grip, but that moment of delay had been enough for Sickle to cover the distance. She met the beast head-first, smashing her armor’s horn into its chest—and then bellowing in pain as the green flame enveloped her head. She jerked and tore away, ripping away several pieces of the timberwolf as she staggered back.

The creature lashed out and writhed for a moment, and was just getting its claws under itself again when Starlight finished reloading. A moment later, all that was left was a heap of smoldering, shattered wood.

Sickle tore off her helmet and plunged her face into the shallow water nearby. I swooped in to hover over her, leveling my rifle and putting a single shot into the water some twenty yards away. The pair of eyes ducked beneath the surface again, the water rippling as the swampclaw turned around and backed off from its potential meal.

“Fuck off,” Sickle snapped when Dusty spoke with her, but he was insistent.

“Drink it,” he said, holding the healing potion out. “Burns are bad enough for infection even in clean conditions, and this is as far from clean conditions as we can get.”

She grumbled a bit more, but eventually relented. I didn’t get a good look at the wounds while I kept watch. The best look I got was that evening, when we stopped to eat. Even after the healing potion, her muzzle was a knot of scarred and inflamed tissue, without even a trace of hair.

By the time night fell, I was exhausted. As we made camp, the swampclaws resumed their taunting. Roaring, splashing, tearing at vegetation. This time, I fell dead asleep.

I woke to the ear-pounding sound of gunfire. I lurched upright, grabbing at my rifle as the hammering blasts of Bloodbeak’s rifle lit the area around me like snapshots, the flash overpowering the flickering light of the low fire. There were shouts all around. I scrambled to my hooves in a maelstrom of chaos, with just enough clarity of mind to keep my rifle pointed at the ground until I had made sense of the situation.

A shout drew my attention, and I spun around. A light swung over, illuminating the hulking grey-green hide of a swampclaw as it barreled into a pair of dazed zebras. The towering beast reared back, raising its massive claws to strike, only to flinch back as Dusty’s rifle hammered at it. By then, I had brought my own rifle up. I switched straight to automatic and keyed up S.A.T.S. before tonguing the trigger. My rifle chattered, and I held the front sight over the creature’s chest as well as I could. The suppressor did little to quiet the weapon, but I later realized that it was the reason I had no muzzle-flash obscuring my view.

The beast was already loping away by the time my magazine ran empty. In the gloom and confusion, I couldn’t even tell if it was hurt.

A crack and red flash lit up the area for a split instant, followed by the agonized howl of a wounded swampclaw. I spun back around to see the scattering embers of Starlight’s shot as the swampclaw she had shot floundered at the edge of the light.

More screams sounded to my side, and my head snapped around. There was a third swampclaw! It had made use of the distraction to dart in, and I watched in horror as its jaws snapped down around a stumbling zebra’s flank. I fumbled through reloading as it reared back, the zebra giving a cry of pain as he was hauled off his hooves. Another zebra bravely charged forward, trying to sink her spear into the beast’s belly. It snapped the spear with a swing of its claws, sending the would-be rescuer staggering back.

Then it turned and ran into the darkness.

Several zebras were yelling and snatching up weapons, but Dusty bolted forward.

“Stop!” he shouted, stepping in front of the zebra with the broken half-spear. “Stay in the camp, or they’ll pick us off one-by-one! Form a perimeter!”

To their credit, the zebras stopped. Even in that emotional moment, they recognized the needs of survival. Dusty was completely right; the only way they would survive was to be practical and consolidate.

That was little comfort when the agonized scream echoed through the foliage. Tears glistened in the firelight, but the zebras held their ground.

I spread my wings, darting up into the air. “Starlight!” I called out as I swung over, coming to a quick hover beside her. “Lancer!”

She immediately levitated it up. I dropped my rifle at her hooves and snatched the Lancer’s bit in my teeth, then turned and bolted towards the treeline.

Past the edge of the camp, the world was almost pitch black. I turned up my PipBuck screen as bright as I could as I flew after the pair of marks on my E.F.S. I didn’t have far to go. The swampclaw had thrown the zebra down on a patch of dry ground. As my PipBuck lit up the scene, it revealed the beast towering over its prey. Even in the monochrome light, I could see the blood glistening on the zebra’s mauled body, and could hear his pained groans as he twisted in on himself.

The swampclaw backed away as I came to a hover, skulking back several steps from its catch, as if trying to lure me in.

I wasn’t playing that game. I leveled the Lancer, my eye lining up on the telescopic sight. S.A.T.S. had recharged, and I hit it again.

Trying to line up a telescopic sight on a target some twenty yards away was more difficult than I had expected. It was probably only a few seconds, but even with the aid of S.A.T.S. it felt like an eternity before I lined the crosshairs over the dim green image of the swampclaw’s face.

I tongued the trigger. A sharp hum discharged beside my head, followed by a blinding flash and powerful crack as the weapon blasted its way through the atmosphere to reach its target.

The muzzle jerked down as I fired; despite conceptually understanding how such weapons work, witnessing the Lancer at work had established the fact that it was exceptionally powerful, and my mind had instinctively decided that exceptionally powerful weapons must have exceptionally powerful recoil. Still, despite my best efforts to throw the world’s easiest shot, my vision cleared to show the swampclaw spasming on the muddy ground. The entire front of its head, from the eyes forward, was missing.

I quickly looked around as I slung the now-useless Lancer. Seeing no other hostile contacts, I dropped down.

The zebra was in horrible shape. His flank had been torn open to the bone, and his entire underside was covered in blood. The green light made it hard to make out the details, but I could still see the pair of deep gashes along his chest and belly, dark holes in the stark lighting. The silhouette of his belly was all wrong. He twitched slightly, making a weak groan through clenched teeth.

I wrapped my hooves around him, wings pumping as I lifted off and flew back to camp as quickly as I could. He hung limply beneath me, giving only a couple more weak groans.

The entire camp was awake when I returned, with the armed adults forming a circle around those who couldn’t fight. A few scooted to the side, making a clearing for me to land. I set the wounded zebra down and landed beside him.

He was completely still. Another zebra, an older mare with tears in her eyes, sat by his head, cradling it.

“He was just breathing,” I said, moving as if to treat his wounds, until realizing I had no idea what to do. I could see his ribs laying bare, and bits that should be inside hanging on the outside. The wounds were beyond my limited ability to treat. They were beyond even the power of our remaining healing potions.

I still fumbled about, trying to do something, anything. My hooves went to his wounds, as if trying to stop the bleeding. “He was just breathing,” I quietly repeated. The zebra at his head made no move to help. Instead, she stroked along his muzzle. He was completely still. Even the bleeding had ceased.

My hooves slid away as I sat back.

A hoof gently touched my shoulder. I looked back to see Seroon’s face. His face held firm, but I could see the sadness in his eyes.

He gave a tiny nod. “Thank you for bringing him back to us.”

I swallowed. “I’m… sorry.”

He simply shook his head, and turned to the mare opposite me. They shared a brief, silent exchange of looks, and then he was walking away, returning to the circle of guards. With that, the mare turned and called on a few of the other zebras forward. They were arranging a funeral.

Feeling a little out-of-place, I slipped away. It was only as I left that I saw the children looking on. There was sadness there, but not the fear or anguish I would have expected. This was not the first time they had seen such a thing.

Starlight took one look at the blood staining my coat and led me to a shallow patch of water just outside the camp. While I watched with flashlight and E.F.S., she cleaned the blood from me.

Somewhere behind me, I heard Dusty’s voice. “I’m sorry.”

He was speaking to Seroon, who softly replied, “You do not need to apologize. Only a fool would expect this journey to be without danger. I am saddened by Zeren’s loss, but that is not on you. If we had stayed, he would have died just the same, and many more would join him. You have given us the opportunity for a better future.”

Dusty was quiet for a moment before replying. “That’s a very practical outlook.”

“We may strive for peace,” Seroon said, “but we are descended from warriors. We understand. As do you, I expect.”

They fell into silence again, and my attention returned to Starlight’s hooves, scrubbing the blood from my coat. A few minutes later, I was clean, though wet and cold. I just sat there for a while until Starlight spoke.

“Are you okay?”

I sighed. It took a few seconds to articulate my thoughts. “I’m becoming far too familiar with death for my comfort.”

Starlight didn’t say anything. She just slipped her foreleg around my shoulder, giving a comforting squeeze.

☢

The swampclaws still followed us the next morning, but they kept their distance. Starlight took pot-shots at any eyes she saw peeking out from the water, but the aquatic environment protected them well. Only a single shot scored a solid hit, vaporizing the top of a beast’s head. Most shots just sent up sprays of water and a cloud of steam.

By mid-day, we’d had enough. As the group paused for a quick break, Starlight passed me her Lancer and the charging pack for its crystals. I flew around the perimeter, hunting down red marks. I’d fly in over lurking swampclaws, hover, and send a blast straight down at them. Shooting accurately while in a hover is much harder than it sounds, but I managed to kill at least one, and wounded another. The rest scattered.

I returned Starlight’s weapon when we set out again, but kept up my patrols. The swampclaws tried to draw near the group a couple more times. The sight of me swooping over them was enough to send them under again.

There were no more attacks. That night, we rested in silence. We never saw the swampclaws again.

The rest of the wildlife wasn’t quite so considerate, but were also much less of a threat. One zebra managed to get herself bit by a mutated parasprite, but the laceration was easily treated. Another zebra was wounded after a slippery bloodwing darted in and attacked him. It was only on him for a few seconds before Sickle tore it away and slammed it to the ground, but that was enough to leave the young stallion weakened and semi-conscious.

While Dusty fed the zebra a healing potion, Sickle tore the wings off the squealing bloodwing, letting it squirm for a while before tossing it out into the nearby shallows.

Still, while we handled the threats, it was tiring. I think Starlight handled it the worst. She was constantly alert, looking for new threats, until the physical and mental fatigue left her exhausted. Dusty handled it the best, naturally. I suspect a career as a soldier had left him well-equipped in that regard, even better than my own experiences as an Infiltrator. I had to struggle a little, mentally connecting the similarities of being hunted in the wilderness with living a hidden life among ponies. Dusty, meanwhile, seemed to just “switch off” and relax as soon as he was no longer on watch. I don’t think I’ve ever been so jealous of a pony being able to go to sleep at the drop of a hat.

Though I suppose Sickle handled it just as well, if only because she didn’t seem to care about anything.

Not that she was exactly relaxed and casual. She was gruff and snippy, and more than one zebra got shoved aside when they unwittingly got in her way. “Shit, we’re saving these dumb cunts,” she grumbled as she tore into a meal that, I silently noted, the zebras had prepared for us. “They got like ten stallions, too. You’d think these fuckers could give a mare a good rutting as thanks.” She muttered obscenities under her breath as she slapped back a couple of pills and downed an entire bottle of beer. None of us were surprised to see the bottles included in her “essential” traveling supplies.

“Or, shit,” she continued, “that little bitch I saved. Got half my face burned off doing it, too. Least she could do is show some thanks.”

Starlight grumbled quietly, and after a moment of chewing, decided to speak more clearly. “You ever try, I dunno, not being a horrible pony? I mean, hell, I saw some of ‘em looking at you like you were Luna herself, until you started treating ‘em like shit. Seriously, if you’d stop acting like a giant bitch all the time, they’d probably love you.”

Sickle snorted. “I don’t give a shit what they think of me.”

“What?” Starlight raiser her head from her food, cocking her head to the side and leveling an unbelieving look her way. “But you… you literally just—”

Sickle sneered, made extra grotesque by how the bare skin of her muzzle bunched up. “I want ‘em to fuck me, not write me a love letter.”

Starlight stared for a second before shaking her head. “You know, ponies—zebras too, I imagine—are a lot more likely to… have sex with someone they don’t hate.”

I raised a hoof as I contributed my share. “Speaking as someone experienced in manipulation and applied psychology, Starlight is correct.”

Sickle gave a dry chuckle as she turned back to her food. “And that’s why I’ve had more sex than all of you cunts combined.”

I decided to not argue that point. She was probably correct, if by a more narrow margin than she imagined.

Starlight turned back to her food as well, though I caught the forming smirk. “...Yeah, but we’ve had better sex.”

I wanted to sigh, but instead snickered.

“That’s brahminshit,” Sickle said matter-of-factly. “‘Cause I know Whisper ain’t done the hellhound thing.”

Starlight’s expression tightened, and for a moment I thought she was embarrassed, until she hissed, “Hey, quiet about that!”

I appreciated her concern, but with how the conversation had turned, I couldn’t help adding a little fuel to the fire. “Yes. You know that because I told you so.” I smiled. “And we all know that a pony such as myself would never tell a lie.”

Sickle stared at me for several seconds, the thin glint of her eyes narrowing inside her helmet. Finally, she snorted, turning back to her food. “Nah. No way the runt’s going for that.”

I knew even at the time that I probably shouldn’t taunt her like that, especially when she was already expressing frustration, but it was too entertaining at the time. It was somewhat less entertaining later that night; while she had no partners, she also had no shame, and thus no problem about relieving a little of that tension right in the middle of that night’s camp.

☢

Our progress through the swamps was slower, with an entire group in tow. I wouldn’t say it was uneventful, as there were plenty of animal attacks. I might, however, say it was relatively uninteresting. After the twentieth time Sickle smashed some over-enthusiastic wildlife, it began to lose its life-or-death response. At least it gave her some outlet that didn’t involve alternately leering at or threatening our traveling companions.

Finally, as I took one of my regular scouting flights, my eyes caught the edge of the swamps.

It was just after dark when we left the dense vegetation behind. Our PipBucks had led us unerringly right back where we started, and there was a feeling of resolution as Dusty pulled back the dirty tarp, revealing our motorwagon. There were a few impressed murmurs from the Dawnbringer zebras, and particularly from Bloodbeak. Myself, I just felt relieved at the return of normalcy it signaled. It was, in retrospect, a little strange to feel so attached to a vehicle we had only owned for a few days prior to leaving it.

Though I have to admit, it was also quite relieving to be able to shed some of the supplies I had been carrying, while also replenishing my half-depleted ammunition.

The next morning, the zebras looked to the east, murmuring quietly about the lack of sun. We prepared to set off.

“We don’t have room for everyone to ride,” Dusty said, “but we can load all the supplies into it and travel light. We’ve still got a good distance to travel, probably most of a week on hoof.”

Seroon had turned to look west, into the increasingly sparse ground of the Wasteland. “Is the entire land bare?”

“Mostly, ‘fraid so,” Dusty said. “There’s enough for folks to get by on, but proper farms are few and far between. Don’t worry, Mareford has plenty.”

“But I assume there will be little along the way.” He frowned a little, looking back to the motorwagon. “Most of a week, you say? Our supplies should be sufficient.”

“We’ve got plenty to spare if they’re not,” Dusty said. “Still, we’ll want to travel fast. Starlight, Whisper? You two take the motorwagon. You’ll be on scout duty.”

Starlight looked up from her PipBuck. “I don’t think we’ve got the charge to keep her running circles around the group.”

“Don’t need circles,” Dusty said. “You just hop from one bit of high-ground to the next along our route. Get good eyes out, and fall back immediately if you find any hostiles. I just want to make sure no raiders see a group walking the wastes and decide to pay a visit.”

Seroon spoke up, once again reminding us of how isolated the Baltimare area must have been. “What are raiders?”

“Ponies like me,” Sickle said with a cruel grin. “Only without all the charm and etiquette.”

Dusty grimaced. “And it’s sad that she’s pretty much right.”

“I’m surprised she even knows that word,” Starlight said.

“Yeah, see?” Sickle said, looping a very unwelcome hoof around Seroon’s shoulder, and flicking her head in Starlight’s direction. “If I were still a raider, I’d be over there stomping her face in for being disrespectful. Then, I dunno, maybe see how much of her gun would fit up her uptight ass before pulling the trigger.”

Dusty glared icily at her. “Sickle, knock it off, right now.”

“Oh, fuck off, Dirt,” she said, though she released Seroon, who eyed her warily. “They need to know this shit if they’re going to survive.”

“And they’ll get it,” Dusty replied, “but not from you, and not like this. Knock it off.”

Sickle’s head lowered, and she practically growled in reply. “You know, I’m getting really fucking tired of you telling me what to do.”

“You’re a big mare,” Dusty said, unflinching. “Deal with it.”

She leaned forward, and they stared into each other’s faces for several long, tense seconds. Then Sickle cracked a smile. “Well, shit, look who finally grew some balls.” She reached up, giving him a body-jarring but otherwise friendly slap on the shoulder before turning and strolling away. “Just don’t baby ‘em, Dusty.” He waited until she had walked off before rolling his shoulder, wincing slightly.

We got moving shortly afterwards. After more than two weeks of tromping through overgrown foliage and flying endless patrols, it was a wonderful luxury to kick back in the worn seat of the creaking, jostling motorwagon. Even the blast of dusty air as we rolled across the valley was a welcome relief.

When we reached the top of a hill, Starlight and I would crawl out and climb onto the vehicle’s roof. I sat against the gun, sweeping my binoculars around, while Starlight peered through the scope of her Lancer. Down in the shallow valley, the narrow line of zebras, ponies, and a single griffon made their way across the land. When they drew even with us again, we crawled in through the motorwagon’s windows and rolled off for the next ridge, bouncing and rattling across the uneven terrain.

After a week of unrelenting tension, it was more than just relaxing. It was fun. I’d have gladly driven around those hills and valleys all day long, not to get somewhere, but just to enjoy myself.

Even the increasingly barren terrain didn’t dampen the mood. Instead, it made things easier. From the top of a hill, we could see everything for miles. After weeks of stress, we no longer had to worry about something sneaking up on us with no warning.

Suffice to say, we had the easy job. While we still kept an eye out, we relaxed and talked. When the conversation ran out, we fell into a comfortable silence, leaning gently against each other. I even eventually got to doing more recordings, after the long hiatus of our journey through the swamp. I’ll admit, I was a little self-conscious of doing so with someone listening in, and especially so when that someone was one of the key players in the events I was documenting, but I’d made a point of honesty with my companions. Especially Starlight.

“‘Sneaky little Whisper’ indeed,” she said in echo of my dictation, and shot a smirk my way. “So you were really trying to steer me around, there?”

“Yes,” I said, with a somewhat guilty smile. “I know Dusty was a bit rough and quick to leap to judgment, but you have to admit, you did antagonize him.”

“Yeah, because he was being a jerk!”

“Yes, because he was being a jerk,” I agreed, then added, “but he also had good reason to be suspicious. I just wanted you to go a little easy on him until he finally accepted us. I’ll note it worked, too. He’s much more welcoming, now.”

Her smirk had turned into a thoughtful frown as she considered my words. “Well… yeah, but, you know, you could have just said that at the time.”

I gestured to my PipBuck, as if pointing to the recording I had just made. “I did.”

“You… well, I mean, I guess, but…” She stopped, cocking her head to the side as she tried to find the right words.

I filled them in for her. “But it’s probably a little different hearing the precise logical reasoning behind a conversation, especially where one party is trying to convince the other party of something. When you get to a fine enough level, the difference between ‘convincing’ and ‘manipulating’ is essentially all semantics.” I gave a wry smile. “The joys of an Infiltrator’s training.”

“Weird bug things,” she said, with a weak snort of amusement. Then, more seriously, she asked, “So, you’re always thinking like that?”

“To some degree, I suppose. Even if I’m not intentionally doing so, I’m aware of the mechanics in action during any social interaction. It’s not something I can just forget.” Not exactly the most reassuring thing I could say, I suppose. I added, “If it’s any better, those mechanics are like tools to assist with one’s intent, and I do have good intentions.”

“So… you’re manipulative and sneaky and sometimes weird, but you do it with good intentions.”

I couldn’t help chuckling. “And right there, you’ve pretty much summed up an Infiltrator’s profession.”

“Urg,” she said, sticking out her tongue for a moment before concluding, “I think I’d go insane trying to think like that all the time.”

“Handling of stress is one of the big selectors for Infiltrator training,” I said. “It can be an extremely restricting life, at times. I don’t think you’d enjoy it. You are… much too free and open in your emotions.” I smiled, leaning over to nuzzle her. “Speaking as our resident emotional gourmet, I mean that as a compliment.”

Starlight shook as she quietly snickered, ending with her elbowing me in the side. “You really know how to be incredibly creepy, you know?”

“I can’t help it,” I said, leaning back against the gun-mount, and feeling her weight shift against my side. “It’s fun. Most of the time, I have to hide myself away and play a role. I may be good at it, but you know, there’s always something so relieving in being able to relax and be honest and myself for a while.”

Starlight gave a soft, thoughtful hum at my side. A moment later, she snuggled in closer, resting her head against me. She opened her mouth to say something, but seemed to think better of it. Instead, she gave me a gentle nuzzle. The warmth of her affection flowed freely.

Much of our trip was spent in such a way, quiet and relaxing. Bloodbeak begged to go with us after our lunch break, and we allowed her, unable to say no to the enthusiastic griffon. She perched on the back of the motorwagon as we drove, laughing and cheering, her wings spread as much as she could manage with her injury. Her enthusiasm continued even after we stopped.

“That thing is awesome!” she said as she hopped down to join us. “It’s so fast! Like flying on the ground! Are there more of these things? Does Mareford have them? Where can I get one? Where did you get this one?”

“We found it,” Starlight quickly replied, and shot me a glance. I nodded in reply.

“Cool!” Bloodbeak said, grinning as wide as a griffon could. “Where could I find one?”

We had to explain the rarity of the vehicles to her, which left her disappointed for merely a moment before she enthusiastically launched into exclamations and questions about other interesting machines the motorwagon carried, such as the minigun and two sets of damaged power armor. Soon she had changed gears again, branching into other subjects and prying for information about our adventures. I’m afraid I can’t really recount all of it, as it rapidly turned into a blur of words and topics ranging all over the place, and I quickly lost track of it all. Considering my field of expertise, I think that says a lot.

I hope it doesn’t sound unkind, but I’m glad she only asked to come with us a couple of times. Her exuberance was a little exhausting, and I liked having the time alone, with just Starlight and my recording. Still, there was something uplifting about watching her perched atop the speeding motorwagon, grinning and carefree. There was a simple joy to it, which seemed to shine all the brighter against the bleak backdrop of the Wasteland.

☢

It was on our third day when our scouting paid off.

While I was still idly scanning the horizon, my attention was mostly on my recording. I was trying to work out how to describe our “recruitment” of Sickle when Starlight’s ears pinned back.

“Shit,” she said, loud and clear, still peering through her Lancer’s scope.

I hit the button to stop recording. “What?” I asked as I brought up my binoculars, trying to find what had caught her attention.

“That alicorn,” she said, her voice tight. “It’s back.”

The distant flicker of motion caught my eye from across the valley below, looking almost black at that distance. It was only as I finally got my binoculars in place that I could make out the purple coloration. Her wings beat a couple more times as she flared and landed, then folded neatly at her side. Her ethereal mane continued to flow behind her.

I dropped my binoculars to their strap, raising my PipBuck and depressing the button on the broadcaster. “Dusty! The alicorn is back.”

There was a moment of silence before my earbud crackled. Dusty’s voice was firm, almost taunt. “Say again.”

“The alicorn is back,” I repeated. “To your… southwest, she just landed on a ridge.”

Another pause. “Shit. Eyes on. Mount up and get back here. Make it quick.”

“On it,” I said. Starlight was already slipping in through the vacant front window, while I dropped into the cargo bay. “Go!” I called out, rapping a hoof against the roof for emphasis.

The vehicle thrummed with arcane energy as the spark-driven motor engaged. The vehicle lurched and shot forward, the wheels grinding in the dry ground and sending a spray of pebbles and dry dirt out behind us. Moments later, we were careening down the slope of the hill, bouncing and rattling like mad. I clutched the grip of the machine gun with one hoof and the edge of the bay with another. It felt dangerously precarious as the vehicle rocked under me, but the big gun was oddly comforting.

If the alicorn hadn’t seen the rag-tag group we were escorting, she needed only to follow the cloud of dust we left in our wake.

We skidded to a halt near the group, the vehicle shuddering and sliding beneath me before coming to a halt so abruptly that I fell back atop our supplies. I was already upright when Dusty hopped onto the side of the motorwagon. “Starlight, keep pace beside the group, between them and the alicorn. Whisper, you’re on the gun. Keep it ready, but don’t fire unless she tries to attack us.”

“Understood,” I said as I resumed my position, with a bit too much adrenaline pumping through my veins to feel embarrassed at my fall.

He slid forward to be more even with Starlight. “Keep track of how much juice this thing uses keeping pace with us. Every hour or so. I want to make sure we’re not going to run her dry.”

“You got it,” she said.

As soon as he hopped down, Starlight had us moving again, circling around the rear of the line to position us between the line of zebras and the distant alicorn.

She simply stood there, unmoving, watching us slowly pass through the valley below.

☢

“What is she?” Seroon asked us that evening, when we had stopped for the night. The sun had set somewhere behind the clouds. The fading light left only a subtle difference between the ground and the sky beyond, as the silhouette of the distant alicorn steadily faded into the growing darkness.

“They’re called alicorns,” Dusty said with a shrug. He was more focused on his food, though his eyes regularly rose to scan around. “Like the princesses of old, only… not. Beyond that, I couldn’t tell you. Radio said they used to be the… servants, I think, of some so-called goddess. Sounded like monsters.”

“It said some of them were nice,” I said, thinking back to the radio broadcast we had heard in Mareford. The alicorns had been a minor element of the transmission, especially when contrasted with the news of Celestia’s survival, but our own passing encounters with this alicorn had led to it sticking in my memory. “I’m not sure what she’s doing, or why she’s following us.”

“It’s been following us for a few weeks,” Dusty said to Seroon. “I guess we lost it going through the swamps. Was hoping it wouldn’t find us again so soon. Damn thing creeps me out.”

Seroon slowly nodded, staring out into the night. “So you do not know what her intentions are?”

“I watched that alicorn turn a pony inside out,” Dusty said, following up with a snort. “I don’t plan on taking chances.”

Starlight grunted before swallowing a bite of food. “Ugh, don’t remind me of that, I’m eating.”

“Blood and guts everywhere,” Sickle said gleefully. “Just tore their chest right open, ripped everything out, made the guts dance around in her magic!” Then she leaned over to Starlight, grinning. “You going to finish that?”

Starlight muttered and hunched over her food, eating with renewed determination. Sickle snickered, returning to her own meal.

“To be clear,” I said, “the pony was already dead. Not that it makes it any less gruesome, but it is ever so slightly less concerning than if she had done that to a living individual.”

“Assuming that alicorn even sees the distinction,” Dusty said. “Only ponies I’ve ever seen do anything like that are raiders.”

Sickle gave a laugh. “Nah, raiders ain’t anything like that. They’ll cut you up and laugh when they do it, ‘cause it’s fucking fun. It’s all violent and messy, and all like, I’m alive and you ain’t, hah hah! You know, enjoying the moment.” She chuckled, gesturing with the blades on her legs before setting her hoof down again. “That big bitch, though? She wasn’t having any fun with it. It was like…”

She stopped for a moment, trying to find the wording, then suddenly pointed at me. “It was like how Whisper talks. Was all thinky like and shit.” She lowered her hoof, returning to her food. “Not like a raider at all.”

I frowned, while Dusty very succinctly summed up my own concerns. “So it calmly and deliberately butchered a dead pony,” he said, frowning as well. “That doesn’t much reassure me, Sickle.”

“Hey, at least you don’t have to worry about her making you play jump-rope with your own intestines,” Sickle said with a shrug.

Dusty snorted. “I don’t plan on giving it that chance. I’d rather go down fighting.”

“Yeah,” Sickle said, grinning again. “Lots of ponies talked tough like that.”

Seroon had remained silent, still staring out into the darkness. When our conversation died off, he finally spoke again. “It is hard to believe anything could survive in this desolate land,” he said, his voice quiet. “So empty and lifeless, and yet, there seem so many determined to make it even more lifeless.”

“Mareford is a safe place,” Dusty said, looking up from his meal. “You don’t need to worry about any of this stuff, there. No raiders or—”

“I’m sorry,” Seroon said, holding up a hoof. “I do not mean to sound as if I doubt your words. You seem an honest stallion, and you have put much effort into helping us. I am sure this Mareford is as you say. My concern is more… general. The state of the world as a whole, rather than our small part in it.”

“Ah,” Dusty said, leaving it at that.

“It’s not that bad,” Starlight said, then quickly amended herself. “Well, I mean, it kinda is, but there’s plenty of good parts, too. More than there are bad parts, at least.”

Seroon considered her words for a moment, and slowly nodded. “I assume you’ve seen a good deal of those ‘bad parts’, then?”

“More than I’d like,” Starlight replied, and shrugged her shoulder, her Lancer shifting against her back. “But that’s why I have this, so I can help ponies.”

“Same reason I joined the Militia,” Dusty said. “And why I left it.”

It seemed like a good time to chime in. “My life has always been about helping others, even if it put my own life in danger. There are lot of horrors out there, but there are good people, too. I know how far the world has fallen, but I honestly think things are improving. It’s certainly better than I once thought it was.”

I know, I’d planned on using the same “isolated farmer” backstory, but a good act requires flexibility, and given the mood, this bit of optimistic honesty felt far more appropriate. Besides, Seroon already thought I was an assassin, or something close to it, and given the zebra history of assassins, I expected he might understand better than most ponies.

Sickle had paused to look around at us, then grinned at Seroon. “Fuck, I’m just here ‘cause I get to have fun killing ponies, and I get paid for it. I mean, sure, being a raider had its perks, but I think this wins out.”

“Don’t mind her,” I said. “She enjoys provoking people.”

“I enjoy fighting and fucking more,” Sickle replied, kicking back with yet another bottle of beer. “But since I ain’t getting any of that right now…”

I smiled a little. “She also complains more than anypony in our group.”

“Oh!” Sickle started laughing. “You mouthy little cunt. Don’t forget that I can stomp your whole fucking head in!” Despite the suggestion of violence, there was no anger to her voice.

So I turned my smile to her. “You can try.”

Sickle froze. For a moment, I worried I had pushed the ‘playful banter’ too far. Then her laughter returned, and she flicked her empty bottle at me. Despite my best effort, and the fact that the bottle was actually aimed at the ground by my side, I still flinched. That just made Sickle laugh more. “Oh, yeah. So scary!” She fell into snickering as she returned to the final scraps of her meal.

I relaxed again, satisfied in my reading of Sickle. Seroon was still watching her, as if still trying to decide what to make of her. I offered an observation.

“She could go wherever she wants, do whatever she wants, and pretty much nobody could stop her. Out of all the things she could be doing, she fights raiders and travels with us.”

Seroon considered that for a moment longer before offering me a small smile and a nod, as if to say, “I trust your judgment.”

Sickle, meanwhile, turned to leer at a couple of the other zebras. “So, hey, speaking of fucking…”

☢

Traveling at a walking pace truly highlighted just how much faster a motorwagon was for long distance travel. Days passed to cover the same distance we had covered in one.

Starlight and I had it easy, her driving while I stood by the gun. Everyone else walked, and the toll was starting to show. Everyone looked worn down and tired, except for myself, Starlight, and Dusty.

The alicorn was persistent. She remained at a distance, standing atop a hill alongside our course. She stood like a statue, her hair flowing in the breeze as if it were weightless. The only time she moved was for the short flight to the next hill.

Once or twice a day, she flew off in a different direction, away from us. At first, we thought she had lost interest, but she always returned, less than an hour after leaving.

The first day was tense, images of a rapidly dissected pony dancing in my memories, as we waited to see if she was going to attack.

By the third day, she was simply a feature of the terrain. We still kept a wary eye on her, but the nerves and adrenaline had gone. She seemed no more interested in closing the distance than we were.

Sickle kept up her crude behavior, and it was with only a little surprise that one night’s rest was interrupted by the sounds of her aggressive copulation. It turns out that one of the younger stallions lacked a mate and had no significant prospects, and Sickle had discovered this. I’m not sure what methods she had used to seduce him, though knowing her, I’m sure they were fairly direct. I worried for a bit that they might have been too direct, given her past, but I doubt he would have tried to hush her if that were the case. Not that his efforts were terribly effective.

He walked with his head low and ears pinned back the next day, while a few of his peers lightheartedly teased him. His embarrassment was broken only by the occasional smile or chuckle, though he mostly kept quiet and tried to avoid attention. He also seemed to make a point of staying away from Sickle.

Sickle, of course, strutted along quite happily. I wouldn’t say she mellowed out, as I’m not sure she ever would, but she was at least less obnoxious in her behavior.

We continued on through the dusty, empty land, until the jagged line of ruined skyscrapers peeked out over the hills.

☢

We came to a halt on a low hill, overlooking the wide, flat valley. A few farms dotted the land, wherever a small patch of fertile land could be found. Beyond them lay the high walls of Mareford. We were just two miles away; close enough for Seroon and his company to easily finish their journey, far enough that we wouldn’t be seen and identified.

“Hardwood can probably help get you settled,” Dusty was saying as he helped unload the last of the zebra’s belongings from our motorwagon. “I don’t know if he’s in charge of anything, now, but he’s always been a good sort, willing to help ponies out. Cinder Block might, too. Most ponies should know where to find them. If nothing else, you can always go to the town hall. I have no idea who’s in charge now, but there’ll probably be some pony there that’ll help.”

While he helped unload, I sat on the roof beside the gun. Mostly, I watched the final preparations for our departure. Every now and then, I’d look back, away from Mareford. The alicorn stood on a hill a good mile away from us, watching.

“Thank you again for this,” Seroon said, smiling softly as a younger stallion helped him strap on a pair of packs. “This is an unfamiliar journey we find ourselves upon, but you have started us off better than we could have hoped for.”

“Heck,” Dusty said with a quiet chuckle. “We were going this way, anyhow.”

“And we are better off for our paths having crossed,” Seroon said, offering a hoof. “I hope our paths cross again, someday.”

“So do I,” Dusty replied, giving a friendly shake. When they were done, Seroon turned to help another of his tribe, and Dusty quickly spoke up again, reaching into his bags. “Just one—well, two more things, I guess.”

Seroon turned back to him with a curious raise of an eyebrow, and Dusty pulled out a small sack, which looked to weigh a few pounds. It clinked and rattled as Dusty passed it over to Seroon. “This should help out some. At the very least, it should help keep you on your hooves for a while as you get settled.”

Seroon’s eyes widened in surprise at the generous gift, and a couple other zebras murmured happily. Then Seroon peered inside the bag, and his expression changed to one of confusion. “Are these… bottlecaps?”

Dusty blinked. “Oh. Right.” He glanced my way, cracking a smile as he caught my eyes, then looked back to Seroon. “Ponies use them as money around here.”

Seroon had followed his gaze to me, and I shrugged. “I thought it was weird, too.”

He smiled, closing the sack again. “That is very generous of you. I hope there is some way we can repay this gift in the future.”

“Don’t worry about it,” Dusty said, and Seroon nodded.

“And the second thing?”

Dusty hesitated, his smile slipping away. “Yeah. It’s… probably best if you don’t mention our names.” He glanced awkwardly our way. “Most of the ponies there are good folks, but we’ve had some misunderstandings. I don’t even know if it’s still an issue, but I wouldn’t want you to get caught up in that just because somepony heard our names.”

Seroon fell silent for a long moment, his head tilting ever so slightly as he considered Dusty’s statement. Finally, a small smile creased his lips. “Our tribe has always been willing to endure hardships in order to do what is right. You have given our tribe a chance to survive, and for that, we are in your debt. The least we can do to repay that is to be honest about how you have helped us.”

“I just don’t want—”

Dusty halted as Seroon raised a hoof to silence him. “I understand,” the older zebra said. “I appreciate it, as well, but it is as you said.” He glanced my way, his smile growing just a hair. “Kindness brings kindness.”

Dusty shut his mouth, still for a second. Finally, he smiled, giving Seroon a nod.

Minutes later, the small tribe started the final stretch of their journey. Most of them passed by us and our motorwagon, taking one last opportunity to thank us. Bloodbeak was practically bouncing as she called back to us. “Come visit! I want to hang out and hear more stories! And maybe get another ride! Bye!” Then she hustled to the front of the line, her eyes turned to the tall walls ahead with just as much eagerness.

We watched them set out, while Dusty leaned against the side of the motorwagon, smiling silently. Starlight balanced atop one of the armor plates as she walked up to sit on the hood beside him. After a moment of silence, she tilted her head toward him. “You know, for someone who can be such a dick, you’re a big softie, ain’t you?”

Sickle snorted, then started laughing, managing to slip in something about a “soft dick” between laughs.

“Oh, grow up,” Starlight said, although she didn’t quite suppress her own snicker.

“Yeah, yeah,” Sickle said between chuckles, the dry ground crunching under her spiked hooves as she walked off behind us.

Dusty shook his head, giving a short huff of amusement before switching to business. “How are our supplies?”

I lazily kicked one of my hind legs, dangling over the cargo bay. “We’ve still got a full drum of water, we won’t have to worry about that for a good long while. I’d guess a month or so. Food’s getting low. Hard to say precisely how long it’ll last. A week, maybe a little more.”

“With our ride, we’re only a couple days from pretty much anywhere,” Dusty noted. “Speaking of, how are we doing for power?”

“Enough to top off the wagon’s charge,” Starlight said, tapping her hoof on the hood. “Might have a few spark batteries spare after. He’s kind of a hungry thing.”

Dusty nodded. “We’ll have to look into getting more spark batteries when we get food, but nothing’s critical just yet. We can take care of other things, first.” He looked back to me. “That Gamma site is maybe an hour or two away. You ready for this?”

My heart lurched. I nodded. Only a couple of hours, now.

Somewhere behind us, Sickle bellowed out a shout. “Hey, purple bitch! Why don’t you bring your giant cunt ass over here instead of just staring all the time!”

“Damnit!” Dusty shouted as he spun around, trotting over to her. “Don’t provoke the damn alicorn! We don’t even know what it can do!”

Sickle wasn’t listening, however. She simply grinned. “Oh, hey, it worked.”

“What?” Dusty’s head snapped around as I looked out past them. Sure enough, the alicorn was rising up from where she had stood, her broad wings pumping as she lifted up into the sky. She was flying straight for us.

“Shit!” Dusty spat, then spun. “In the wagon, now!”

“Oh, come on,” Sickle said, still grinning as she lazily followed after us. “It’s been boring since we left the swamps. This could be fun!”

Starlight slid nimbly through the window, already starting up the motorwagon as Dusty scrambled in through the side. He shouted back at Sickle. “Get in or we’re leaving you behind!”

“You can’t leave me. Some of that shit in there’s mine.”

Despite her protest, she still climbed in, the vehicle rocking under her weight. The whole thing shook as she sat heavily behind me, but she seemed content to leave me with the gun, as cramped as the arrangement was.

The moment the vehicle settled, the motor hummed loudly, and with a lurch, we shot off down the hill, leaving a rising cloud of dust in our wake.

I leaned to the side, tracking the alicorn’s flight, to see if she was following us, or if she diverted to follow the Dawnbringers. Either would have been bad.

Instead, she descended in a slow glide, eventually back-winging to touch down on the hill we had just abandoned. She remained there as the distance rapidly grew.

We continued on, the motorwagon bouncing and rattling as we tore across the dry landscape, until she was finally out of sight.

Chapter Thirty Two: Echo

The ways that fear influences an individual is a complex subject.

The common adage describes the reaction as “fight or flight”, but I consider that to be overly simplistic. In both cases, the individual is still taking an action. Fear can, after all, be a great motivator, although it’s equally capable of motivating one into making bad decisions as it is to make good ones. For example, fear might convince a pony that their only chance of survival was to charge the powerful and terrifying alicorn standing before us, with all of our stolen weapons arrayed behind her.

I find a spectrum of action-to-inaction to be a better way of classifying the reactions to fear. When an individual chooses fight or flight, it’s typically because the action was one that immediately presented itself as the solution to their problem, and they took it, possibly without fully considering the actual merits of that action. When no good options present themselves, or too many compete all at once, individuals tend toward the other side of the spectrum: inaction. They freeze up, question themselves, and fail to take any decisive action to save themselves.

Neither extreme is a good response to fear, and both can be thoroughly deadly. Given an option of the two, however, I felt some measure of relief that our group fell more into the “inaction” side of the spectrum.

Except for Sickle, who I don’t think was actually afraid. If anything, I think she was amused by this development.

The alicorn wasn’t attacking. She stood tall, her wings spread in an upright fan that I had always associated with the princesses and other royalty, as if making themselves seem larger than they were. Her head was held high, with her muzzle tilted slightly upwards, and her eyes hard as she stared back at us.

Given the lack of attack, I took just a moment to quickly appraise our options. That was a fairly simple appraisal, given how limited our options were. We couldn’t flee, as even if we hadn’t sealed the door behind us, that would still leave us with the alicorn between us and freedom. Not that I expected we’d even make it to the door, if she decided to stop us. Fighting struck me as exceedingly long odds, between our lack of weapons and how swiftly I had seen her casually disassemble a pony.

It was a strange situation, being uneasy with the conclusion that talking was the best option.

Dusty evidently came to the same decision I had, but was quicker to act upon it. He was also rather more indelicate than I would have chosen to be. “What do you want?”

The alicorn’s head turned to fix him with a stare, her head tilted ever so slightly. There was a long second of tension before she spoke. Her voice was strong but elegant, her enunciation precise. “Understanding.”

As vaguely creepy single-word non-answers went, that was certainly up there.

While I was thinking that, Dusty spoke again. “What’s that got to do with us? Why have you been following us?”

“Because you are intriguing,” she replied, before taking a few slow, casual steps, her movements precise and elegant. Regal. She stepped smoothly across the debris-strewn ground, without having to look where she placed her hooves. Instead, her eyes turned to me. Something about the intensity of her stare struck me as a predator hungrily eying its prey. “Especially the insect.”

My ear gave the tiniest twitch, and I took a half-step back. I don’t like to be “intriguing” to dangerous individuals. Surprisingly, her expression immediately changed. Her head tilted slightly once more, her expression softening into something more contemplative.

She hummed softly, almost absently, before speaking. “So there is a difference in implication between ‘bug’ and ‘insect’. Interesting.”

That wasn’t the direction I had expected the conversation to take, and while I couldn’t say that ‘thoughtful and inquisitive pony-disassembling alicorn’ was unthreatening, it was at least less so than ‘regal and imperious pony-disassembling alicorn’.

“...It’s mostly about correlation with their common use,” I said, my voice coming out in a low creak. I cleared my throat and, as she had yet to reply, continued. “They both carry diminutive connotations, but ‘insect’ is almost always used in a condescending manner. ‘Bug’ is more varied in its use.”

She had looked away, staring off into space as she gave a tiny nod. She seemed lost in thought. “Hmm. I see. Yes, that makes sense…”

I was tempted to allow the silence to continue as long as she would allow it, but I couldn’t see how that would do anything but delay whatever was coming. At least if I spoke up, I might be able to guide the conversation.

Unfortunately, I only saw one easy way to steer the conversation, and it was a concerning topic. At the same time, it was also a topic of conversation that I was, for better or worse, very curious about. “You find me intriguing?”

She blinked once, her attention snapping back to the here-and-now, her eyes returning to me with their previous intensity. “Part of that interest lies in your uniqueness. Changelings are a rarity in the Wasteland. Prior to coming across you, we remember only two other changelings.

My ears perked up at that, and not only for the change of pronouns. Perhaps it was optimism, or perhaps it was just reading too much into a simple statement, but I had the feeling she wasn’t speaking of Serenity. “You know of other changelings?”

“Knew. One was dead, and we assisted in their dissection. The other we worked alongside, and only briefly.”

I swallowed, silently hoping that she had nothing more to learn through dissection. “The one you worked with, where is she?”

“Dead, I expect,” the alicorn replied with a dismissive flick of her wings. She started to slowly walk again, circling me as if to get a better view of me. Despite the apparent attention, her expression was haughty almost to the point of boredom. Her mane and tail trailed unnaturally through the air behind her, almost as if it were floating underwater. “It was over two hundred years ago.”

I added ‘ancient’ onto the growing list of troubling descriptive terms for this alicorn. There was the added concern that she would have been my contemporary, yet I had no knowledge of her. It did fit with my earlier impression that the Ministry of Arcane Science had progressed further than I had thought. The possible M.A.S. connection fit unpleasantly well with the whole ‘dissection’ comment, as well.

Cautiously, I asked, “And the other part?”

She frowned, coming to a halt beside me. I stayed still, hoping she couldn’t hear how much my heart-rate had kicked up with that simple expression. “At first, you were simply a curiosity, a single specimen of a species that had been seemingly exterminated. A changeling, near death, feeding on a pony.”

Her eyes flicked Starlight’s way before returning to me. “We know very little of your kind, but it was enough to make you very intriguing. Much of what we remember is nothing more than rumor and speculation.” She paused, her frown returning for a moment before she spoke again. “For example, there was one rumor that your species shared a telepathic hive-mind of some form. Is there any truth to that?”

I blinked, a bit surprised by that, then shook my head. “No.”

Her frown deepened as she looked away. “No. No, of course not. Foolish.” She slowly paced away, wings folding at her side as she muttered quietly. “...Grasping at straws… focus…”

Great, I thought. Now the powerful, terrifying, vaguely creepy ancient alicorn is talking to herself.

And she was still between us and all our weapons.

“So,” Sickle rumbled from behind us, “are we fighting, or am I in for another long and boring talk?”

The alicorn replied almost absentmindedly. “A fight would imply some degree of parity.”

Sickle’s armor rattled as she cocked her head to the side, then turned to look at me.

I translated. “I believe she’s saying that any violence between us would be too one-sided to be accurately described as a fight.”

“That is precisely what I intended,” the alicorn said, turning back to face us once more, or more specifically, me. She was in regal mode once more, her head held high. “But we are getting sidetracked. I have yet to fully answer Whisper’s question.”

She stared at me for a couple of seconds, until I cautiously nodded. She gave a prim nod in reply, and spoke. “While we knew very little of your kind, it was enough to catch my interest. I have been seeking an understanding of many things, but you offered an understanding of the most significant. I decided to follow and observe you. I have watched your interactions with ponies, both honest and dishonest, and I have listened in on your conversations and recordings. Those observations led me to two significant conclusions.”

Her head turned, scanning over us. “One: you, as a group, with the possible exception of the former raider, are motivated to help ponies in general.”

Her gaze fixed on me, hard. “And two: you, specifically, know what it is like to be a part of something greater than yourself, only to have that torn away.”

I tensed, though my exoskeleton made that much less obvious than it would have been otherwise. Oh shit, I thought. She sees a connection between the two of us.

On the plus side, I was pretty sure she was less likely to kill us outright. On the other hoof, that was because she expected something from us. From me.

“...I suppose that would be accurate,” I said, concealing the nervousness I felt over this development.

“I have been trying to make sense of things,” she said, her voice softening. “This world is… chaotic. Without direction.” She paused, frowning slight as she thought. After a moment, she spoke again. “You know of my kind.”

It was a statement, not a question. All the same, I nodded. “Very little.”

“The radio said you were servants of the Goddess,” Dusty said.

The alicorn went rigid. Her mane and tail flared slightly in the intangible currents. “She was our mother.”

Thankfully, Dusty shut his mouth rather than continuing on that vein.

The alicorn shook her wings out before tucking them neatly against her side once again, and the regal demeanor returned. “We have heard many things said about our mother. Some called her, and her daughters, monsters.” Her eyes fixed on me. “They see only the surface, but not beyond. They clung to their short-sighted fears, and failed to see what we were attempting to accomplish.”

I slowly, cautiously nodded. “I can appreciate how appearances and first impressions can be misleading,” I offered. “What was it that you were hoping to accomplish?”

“It should be perfectly obvious,” the alicorn said, staring down her muzzle at me. “We sought to help ponies.”

Somehow, I didn’t find that statement terribly reassuring. “I’m afraid I know very little about you,” I said. “How did you seek to help ponies?”

Her wings spread abruptly, her mane flowing behind her. “By making them like us,” she said, her voice filling the space with her declaration. “Perfect, immortal beings, combining the strengths of every tribe. Untouched by age, disease, and radiation. We would have elevated ponies above their meager life of scavenging. We would have turned this wasteland into a paradise, and brought forth a new society that could thrive and prosper.”

She folder her wings again, her expression hard. “And for that, one of the ponies we would have saved murdered our mother.”

“I’m sorry for your loss,” I said, hoping it wouldn’t be taken poorly.

“Hmmph.” She looked away, her expression still hard. After a few tense moments, it started to relax. “I would say you have no idea what I have lost, but I suspect you’re one of the few beings in the Wasteland who might be capable of conceiving it.” She sighed, staring off into space. “We had everything. My sisters, our mother, our purpose. We were one. Our thoughts were legion. They were always there, in Unity. Now?” She slowly shook her head. “Now there is only silence. I can no longer hear them.”

I’ll admit, that was a little creepy. Not so much for the suggestion that she had been hearing voices, as I could assume from that statement and her earlier question that there must have been some form of telepathy involved. More concerning to me was what might have happened to the mental state of an extremely powerful individual who was suddenly deprived of that.

How would I have responded if my own sisters had been a constant presence in my own mind, like a conversation always going on in the background, only to wake and be met with crushing silence? If I was reading her earlier inquiry about a telepathic hive-mind correctly, it suggested significant reason to be concerned.

She shook her head again, as if clearing her thoughts, and I thought I heard her murmur something to herself before speaking again. “That pony may have destroyed our best chance at a better world, but I am still a daughter of the great and powerful Goddess, and some of that greatness lives on in me. I will find a way to use that power in honor of her memory, to accomplish that which she died for.” Her eyes locked onto mine. “And you will help me do this.”

Sickle gave a quiet snort of amusement, and out of the corner of my eye, I caught Dusty’s glance toward where our weapons floated.

Myself, I tried to remain steady under her gaze. “How are you expecting us to help you?”

She turned, slowly pacing with precise, graceful steps. “I have been thinking of how to carry on our mother’s work ever since she was cruelly murdered. The means of our ascension were destroyed by that short-sighted pony, which left me uncertain of how to proceed. But then, I came across you.”

She paused, looking my way for a moment before returning to her pacing. “A changeling, with the magic of transformation and a keen knowledge of what it is to be a part of something greater than themselves. A creature that could help resurrect our plans for Unity.”

“Changelings can’t change others,” I said.

“Of course not,” she said with a dismissive flick of her ethereal mane. “But your kind’s transformative magic is more advanced than any unicorn’s. We remember much of the study and creation of magic, and we remember its unlimited potential. We remember many experiments, delving into magics once thought impossible. I will dissect your magic, figure out exactly how it works and how to replicate it, and with that, we will finally have a means to raise ponies above this downtrodden life.”

Starlight spoke suddenly. “You’re not dissecting her!”

The alicorn halted, shooting her an annoyed look. “It’s a metaphorical dissection, and in any case, the subject of the statement was her magic, not her. I probably won’t need to do any invasive physical examination to understand her magic.”

“Probably,” Starlight echoed, clearly no more relieved than I was.

“If all you want to do is study my magic, then—”

“It’s hardly the only thing I want to do,” the alicorn said. “But it will suffice to start with.”

“...Okay. If all you want to do right now is study my magic, then I think we can accommodate you. We’re in the middle of going somewhere, though, so you’ll have to do so while we travel, and of course we’ll need our equip—”

“No,” she said, shaking her head. “Studying on the move is too awkward and unproductive.”

I swallowed, hoping this wasn’t going where I thought it was going. “Then I’m afraid you’ll have to wait for us to finish our own tasks.”

“No,” she said again. “I am working to save all ponies. That is more important than your tasks. We will stay here.”

Yes, it was going where I thought it was. “You said you’re immortal. I’m sure you can afford to wait a few days or weeks until we’ve taken care of what we need to do.”

“And how many ponies will die while you pointlessly delay their salvation for your fruitless search? What if you die? It would be almost impossible to find another changeling that cares for ponies enough to help. No, this is more important.”

“So, what, fuck changelings?” Starlight abruptly said, her voice sharp with anger. “Whisper’s trying to save her kind, too, you know!”

“I have yet to decide about changelings,” the alicorn said with a shuffle of her wings that seemed to approximate shrugging. “On the one hoof, they are undeniably versatile creatures, and I might even describe them as more fit for survival if not for the crippling emotional dependency. I would consider incorporating some of their capabilities into our ascension, if possible. On the other hoof, changelings are a parasite that feeds on ponies, and from what I have observed, are currently one of the greatest threats in the Wasteland. If allowed to continue, they are likely to become the single most significant obstacle to our Unity. I am left undecided as to whether they should be integrated or destroyed.”

Starlight stared, wide-eyed and open-mouthed, as this alicorn casually contemplated the genocide of my entire species.

Metal rattled as Sickle plodded forward. The alicorn turned to face her, a wary glare flashing before settling into an imperious display of condescending indifference. She stood tall, looking almost bored as she stared down her muzzle at the armored mare.

Sickle halted just a couple feet away, staring right back into the alicorn’s eyes. It’s easy to forget just how big Sickle is, having gotten used to her being around, so it was a bit surprising to realize she stood eye-to-eye with the alicorn. With her bulk for comparison, Sickle managed to make the alicorn look small, if only just.

Sickle just stood there, staring at the alicorn, her expression unreadable under her helm.

After a couple of seconds, the alicorn gave a derisive snort. “I do hope you’re not attempting to intimidate me.”

“Nah,” Sickle said. “Just thinkin’.” She went silent for a moment before continuing. “Yeah. I wouldn’t normally do this, but I’m wondering. Your mom. You anything like her?”

The alicorn’s head rose just a hair higher. “I would like to believe so.”

“Yeah, I thought so,” Sickle said. A touch of a smile crossed her lips, half-hidden behind the bars of her muzzle. “I think I see why that pony killed her.”

The alicorn’s eyes widened, much as I’m sure everyone else’s did. Then she bared her teeth in a snarl. Purple magic flared, throwing Sickle into the wall with a tremendous crash of metal. “You dare!”

To my side, Dusty twitched, almost launching into action, but the alicorn still stood between us and our weapons.

I hurried forward, hoping to do what I could; if we couldn’t fight and couldn’t flee, then words were the only way we were getting out of this intact. “Wait! Please!”

Her glare turned to me, and I nearly staggered back under the withering look she gave me. “Just… please listen. I’m sure you’ve noticed Sickle can be a bit blunt, but I think she actually had a good point.”

“Of course I had a good fucking point!” Sickle called out. She didn’t even sound angry, despite being pinned to the wall in a field of purple magic. Well, no more angry than usual.

The alicorn kept Sickle pinned in place, but her attention remained on me. “And exactly what point would that be, insect?”

I knew I was taking a gamble pressing this, but what option did I have? I took a steadying breath, and began. “Your approach needs a lot of work.”

She blinked. I could only imagine Starlight sharing a similar reaction behind me. That was perfectly fine with me; surprise and confusion was much preferable to righteous anger. I continued. “We said we were willing to help, but instead of accepting what help we were willing to offer, you’re pushing for more, until we aren’t—”

Her head drew back in surprise. “You do not want to help?”

“I do,” I said, firmly. “But with your approach, you seem determined to turn potential allies into actual enemies. We have things we need to accomplish, things that are important to us, but rather than work in a way that helps all of us achieve our goals, you were insisting on only solving your own goals while hindering ours. If that’s how you’re planning on approaching your Unity, then there are going to be many who don’t like that. They’ll fight you, and if they can kill a goddess, I’m sure they can kill one of her children. You’re putting your own goal at risk by approaching it this way.”

Her expression turned distant, her head tilting again. She murmured quietly to herself. “Logical. Fits the data. Possible problem. I don’t…” She blinked and shook her head again, and with another crash of metal, Sickle fell to the floor.

She laughed as she picked herself up. “What, tired already?”

“Goddesses’ sake,” Dusty muttered. “Are you trying to get yourself killed?”

“I ain’t scared of her.”

“You’re too dumb to be scared.”

Starlight thumped a hoof against Dusty’s shoulder. “Guys, seriously, could you not do this right now?”

I watched Sickle as she stood, rolling a shoulder as if stretching, but she didn’t seem any worse for wear after the alicorn’s treatment. In fact, she was smiling.

The alicorn was looking at me again. “I do not appreciate the implication that my mother’s death was her own fault.”

“I wasn’t commenting on whether it was right or wrong,” I said. It was a nicely diplomatic answer, I thought. “I merely intend to show why others might act as that pony did.”

“Hmm.” She frowned, but after a moment, slowly nodded. “You are more experienced in dealing with ponies than I am. That is one of the topics I seek understanding of. You will help me with this.”

“Okay. First lesson: ask me to help you.”

She blinked. “Did I not just do so?”

“You did not,” I said. “You told me to help you. It’s an important distinction.”

“Hmmph.” She stared at me for a second before speaking again. “Fine. Will you help me?”

“I already am.” I stepped up, as if to take charge of the conversation, while trying to ignore the huge size difference. “There are many different ways of convincing someone to help you. So far, you’ve been using demands and the unspoken threat of your intimidating nature, but that’s one of the poorest long-term options. They might help you, but they’re not motivated to do so. They’re motivated to protect themselves, and the moment they find a better option to do so, they’ll take it, whether it’s abandoning your work or turning on you.”

It was my turn to start pacing as I spoke, and despite the alicorn’s imposing nature, I noticed that she watched intently, almost like a student listening to her teacher, if that student were twice as tall and significantly more powerful. “Furthermore, it’s going to be complicated by the moral judgement of your actions. Forcing others to work for you looks like extortion at best, and slavery at worst. Many will have strong feelings on that. There are many who might be amicable to your goals, but who strongly and even violently oppose you for your methods.

“And if that isn’t reason enough, seeing such things will lead people to question your motives. You made some impressive claims, ones which will be hard for people to believe. If they see you taking unscrupulous means to accomplish those claims, it’s going to make others doubt your honesty. If all they see is you using the threat of force to get others to do as you wish, with unverified claims of noble goals and benefits for them, it’s going to be hard to believe you.”

The alicorn’s brow creased. “Are you saying you do not believe me?”

“To be honest, I do have some reason for skepticism,” I said. “I don’t disbelieve you, but your forceful demands and complete lack of compromise or negotiation suggests a disregard for the concerns of others. That’s enough to make some question whether your concept of an ideal world will really be what they consider an ideal world, and that’s especially true when you’re willing to even consider the genocide of my entire species.”

I ended with a pointed look at her.

“I did say there were good arguments against it,” she said, though her ears flicked back as she did so.

“A willingness to exterminate innocents does not speak well of your ideal future,” I said, my eyes holding firmly to hers. I could hear my heart pounding in my ears, but I stood steadily.

Her ears had pinned back, and she held my stare for a few long, uncomfortable seconds before her gaze wavered ever so slightly. “I… can see how a non-pony might find that disconcerting.”

Dusty snorted. “Yeah, plenty of ponies, too.”

“Hell yeah,” Starlight said. A glance their way showed me that she was glaring daggers at the alicorn.

“I see,” the alicorn said, frowning. After a moment, she nodded. “Very well. I shall avoid mentioning such things again.”

“No,” I said, meeting her eyes once more. “You’ll need to do more than that. Whatever your ideal future is, genocide needs to have no place in it.”

“I can understand why you would have personal feelings on the matter,” the alicorn said, “but I am working to create a better world for as many as—”

“No,” I said, more firmly. “Any future that necessitates the genocide of innocents is insufficiently good. It would still be causing death and suffering, you’re just moving it around. We can do better than that. If you really want to make the world a better place, then we have to do better than that.”

Another long moment of contemplation. “That does sound good in theory,” she said, although her voice was cautious, “but I am concerned with the difficulty of taking such a course.”

“You said you wanted to honor your mother. Do you really think taking the easy way out would be the best way to do that? Or do you perhaps think that striving for something better, regardless of the difficulty, would honor her more?”

She looked to the ground in thought, silent and frowning, with only her eerie mane and tail slowly drifting in the still air. I remained still as well, tense as I awaited her answer.

Finally, she spoke. “You are very clever and talented at manipulating others, changeling.” Her eyes looked up to me, my heart pounding a little harder at the intensity of her look. “All the more so for how logical your arguments are. Yes, I would prefer the best possible outcome. I am concerned with the practicality of achieving such a goal, but… if you have any ideas, I would be willing to listen.”

I huffed out a quiet sigh of relief. I felt that the hard part was passed, and now I was on to the much simpler matter of working out a convincing plan to save the world, and maybe convincing her that genocide was wrong.

Somehow, this was an improvement.

“Okay. Good. The basic plan is pretty simple. Actually, it’s pretty much exactly what we’ve been doing this whole time. The short version is, we go out and help others. Stop raiders that are hurting others, help people get what they need to survive and prosper, that sort of thing. Make the world better for them. Go from there.”

“That sounds like such a petty effort,” the alicorn said, though her tone didn’t carry the scorn I might have expected of the statement. “I intend to improve life for all ponies, not just a few dozen.”

I held up a hoof. “Okay, first off: all people. Not just ponies. Zebras, griffons, donkeys, and yes, even changelings. They’re all worth saving.”

She slowly nodded. “I suppose that is a worthy goal, if it is possible.”

“It certainly is,” I said. “Second, this isn’t about solving the world’s problems in one fell swoop. It’s about setting things up so that’s even possible. It’s like building a house. You need a good foundation to build on.”

“That’s a simplistic metaphor.”

“That’s what metaphors are for,” I said. “But the reasoning is solid. Try this: imagine that you were an ordinary pony.”

Her frown deepened. “Hmmph.”

“Now imagine how that ordinary pony might react to somepony like you. Don’t think about what you know, think about what they see. Imagine they see you, using threats to force others to follow your orders, maybe even following through on those threats if they continue to refuse. Then instead imagine if their experience of you is seeing you save ponies from raiders, leading them to safety, maybe even giving up a generous share of your own food and supplies so they can get back on their hooves. Which one do you think is going to motivate people more to help you?”

“It seems to me that both would be very well motivated to assist me,” she said. Then her ears flicked back. “But yes, I believe I understand what you are attempting to say. We… we remember our first reactions to alicorns. To our Unity. There was much fear there, so many ponies who didn’t understand what was happening. If only there had been some way for us to understand how wonderful that change would be.” She stared off into space, her voice quieting. “We remember using time-altering magics. If only I understood how they worked…”

The thought of time-manipulation sounded like trouble on a colossal scale, not the least of which for the very tempting possibilities that immediately leaped to mind. “I’m guessing these changes you’re speaking of were not voluntary.”

She was frowning, still looking away. “No, they were not.”

“But if ponies saw alicorns as benevolent and helpful, and had the opportunity to see what benefits come with it, perhaps it could have been.”

“Yes, I was paying attention to what you had said,” the alicorn said with a flicker of a glare, though she looked away again just as quickly. “And… yes, I can see the benefits that would bring. It would certainly be slower, but…”

“But is less likely to have people actively opposing you,” I said.

“Yes,” she said, a smile touching her lips. She was regaining that regal stance once more. “And more likely to understand that I am saving them.”

“Which leads us to another question,” I said, taking a step forward to take charge again. “How will you respond if someone decides they don’t want to be like you?”

She scoffed, but followed it with a grin. “They will see the benefits offered to them, and with this plan, they will have no reason to fear it. They will not refuse the opportunity.”

I shook my head. “I can tell you now, if you’re expecting ponies, or anyone else, to be of a unanimous mind on something, you’re only setting yourself up for disappointment. I can assure you, there will be those who see what you’re offering, understand it fully, but still not want to take part in it. I want to know how you would respond to them.”

She simply waved a hoof. “Nonsense. Who would turn down such a gift when they aren’t blinded by petty fears?”

“I mean no offense,” I said, “but I would.” Her head snapped back as if I had struck her, and I quickly continued. “I’m no stranger to change, but I’d rather stay what I already am than become an alicorn. If you’re truly immune to the effects of radiation, disease, and aging, I might want to see if I could incorporate such alterations through my own shapeshifting, but it wouldn’t be the sort of change you seem to have in mind.”

She stared wide-eyed at me for another moment before blinking, then shaking her head. “No, well, that is hardly surprising. You are a changeling, you can achieve such a change on your own without my interference. Ponies do not have that option. They will gladly accept this gift.”

I could have glanced back at the rest of my group, hoping for backup. I expected that, of the three of them, at least one would be willing to decline. Despite how helpful it would be, I didn’t want to put them on the spot like that.

Fortunately, I didn’t have to. In the moment of silence that followed her statement, Dusty spoke up. “Uh, yeah, I think I’ll pass, thanks.”

The alicorn’s head snapped around, eyes wide, her reply sharp with surprise. “What?”

“Hell, it’s a nice offer and all,” he said with a shrug. “I kind of like myself how I am, thanks.”

The alicorn’s ears had fallen, her expression sagging like a little filly that had just seen their ice cream fall into the dirt. “But… you…”

Dusty quickly held up a hoof. “Hey, it’s okay, I get it. Ain’t like I couldn’t find a lot of benefits to magic and flight, but I’m fine without. Who knows, maybe when I get older I might change my mind, but for now… yeah, I’ll pass.”

“Same here,” Starlight said. “Flying was fun, but… no. Plus, uh… well, I’d rather not be quite that big. Sorry.”

Then they both glanced to Sickle.

Sickle wore one of the most delighted grins I’d ever seen on her. “You want to give me wings and magic? Are you fucking stupid?”

I quickly stepped in before anyone could answer that question. “I’m sure there will be those who would gladly take what you’re offering, but there will be others who do not. They’ll still need our help, too.”

“But…” Her gaze wavered, her stance off-balance, as if her whole world was crumbling around her. “If they will not accept my gift, and you claim I should not force them to accept it, then…”

I stepped up, unnoticed in her apparent existential crisis. I was close now, my horn level with her neck. So many options presented themselves.

I raised a hoof, gently touching it to her chest. I offered a small, comforting smile. “Then you give your gift to those who do accept it, and find another way to help those who decline.”

She absently brushed my hoof away, seemingly before realizing I had stepped in close. Her gaze focused on me, her confusion clear in her expression. “But how?”

“You’ve been watching us. You’ve seen us help ponies, and others as well. None of us are an immortal alicorn. You could do a lot of good simply by spreading Generosity and Kindness.”

Her ears flicked back. “Magic. Laughter. Loyalty. Honesty.” Her expression went abruptly still. “We remember these.”

“They’re all things that the world could use much more of,” I said.

She remained still and silent for several long, tense seconds. I considered saying more, nudging her in the right direction, but I expect that wouldn’t have worked any more than the reassuring touch had.

Slowly, her stance straightened once more, her head rising and her expression setting, looking bold and confident as she declared in a firm, clear voice, “I have come to a decision.”

A little melodramatic, I thought, but I certainly wasn’t going to say so to her. “And that is?”

“I will accompany you,” she declared. “I will study your magic for any way to implement my plan, while assisting you with yours, until I have gathered enough data to make an informed decision as to which course is best for all—” I caught the momentary hitch as she changed words. “—people.”

Once she had finished, a flicker of a frown broke the confident image she was projecting. Her eyes darted towards me. “Would that be acceptable?”

I looked back. Starlight looked tense, but gave no reply. Sickle looked like she didn’t care about anything we were talking about. Dusty merely looked back with a level look, and gave a tiny shrug.

I turned back. “I suppose that could be acceptable, yes. That is, assuming that talk of genocide is no longer in consideration.”

“I believe the data will speak for itself,” she said, the frown vanishing. “I will not refuse a course of action without giving it due consideration, but you have already provided good arguments against it. Unless I make some discovery that directly contradicts that, I expect it will prove to be an unnecessary or even inappropriate action.”

Progress, I suppose. “I guess that will have to do.” I drew in a deep breath and sighed. “Very well. If you wish to accompany us, we can do so, though there will have to be some conditions.”

A hint of a frown appeared. “Conditions?”

“Yes. The main condition is that, while you’re traveling with us, if we tell you to not do something, then you can’t do that.”

The frown deepened. “If your decision is well-reasoned, then you hardly need such a rule. If it is not well-reasoned, then I should hardly be expected to obey it.”

“You seem to be reasonably logical and have listened to my arguments with an open mind, which is why I’m willing to consider this arrangement. You’re wanting to travel with us, and that means whatever you do, you’ll have done with our assistance, however small. That means we’re at least partially responsible for what you do. If you’re asking us to take on this responsibility, then you will have to make some concession to that fact.”

Her head tilted slightly. “Even if you consider yourself responsible for any action I undertake while in your company, do you truly believe I would do something objectionable?”

I couldn’t help giving her a flat, ‘are you serious?’ sort of look. “You’re open to the idea of exterminating an entire species of intelligent beings. That does raise certain concerns about what else you might be willing to do.”

She scoffed, waving a hoof dismissively. “We have already discussed that. I think your personal stake in the matter is clouding your objectivity.”

Dusty gave a sharp, humorless laugh before I could even reply. “Shit, lady, I thought you’d been watching us. If you think Whisper’s not happy with it because she’s a changeling, you weren’t watching very close. That changeling isn’t the only one who doesn’t like all this talk of mass murder, but she’s the one that’s actually giving you a chance.”

Thank you, Dusty. I nodded in agreement. “And I’m not saying you have to do exactly what we tell you to do, forever. It’s just while you’re traveling with us. If you find the arrangement too constraining, then you’re welcome to part ways with us, though personally, I hope you’ll find enough value in what we do to stay.” You’re less likely to go off and do something terrible that way. “I think we have a lot we could learn from each other.”

She hummed softly. “Mmm. Yes, I believe we could.” She considered it for another moment before giving a sharp nod. “Very well. If it will ease your mind, I shall agree to take no action that you explicitly forbid so long as I remain in your company.”

I could read all sorts of loopholes into that statement. “So long as you make an attempt to follow the spirit of what we say, then that is acceptable.”

A flicker of a frown appeared again, though the tilt of her head made it look more confused than offended. “I… shall try.”

“Good. Which comes to the second, and I think final, condition, which is the same condition that falls on all of us: if we end up in any combat-related situation, and I expect we will, then Dusty’s word is law. When he tells you to do something, you do it immediately and without question. You can object afterwards, even leave if you decide to, but not in the middle of a fight.”

“Hmmph.” The frown had returned once more. “I would question that, but I have seen your group in many fights, and have witnessed its efficiency. It is hardly what my sisters and I shared, but I suppose such an arrangement of authority is the best that a collection of disjointed minds can come to approaching a true unity. Very well. I shall accept this restriction.”

“Good,” I said. “I guess that’s it. Well, I suppose I should include the return of our equipment in our agreement.”

“Yes, of course,” she said, floating our weapons back to us. As my magic reached out for my equipment, she spoke again. “I do hope this displays at least some indication of goodwill on my behalf. I am not ignorant to the fact that you are a deceptive creature, and could very well be attempting to convince me to return your weapons only so you could turn them upon me.”

I slung my rifle, trying to look as casual as possible as I did so. “If I wanted to kill you, I would have stabbed you in the neck with my horn. I was close and you were distracted. And then, given your size and plainly obvious magical nature—” I gestured a hoof at her eerily flowing mane. “—I probably would have followed up by hitting you with magical bolts until I was drained of energy or convinced you were completely dead. I assume you have seen how I’ve dispatched threats in the past?”

“Yes,” she said. “Enough to know that, if you were of a mind to kill me, you would give absolutely no indication of that fact before striking, and you would do so with ruthless and cold-blooded efficiency. I must admit, it does make your objection to my earlier comments seem somewhat hypocritical. Still, you passed up an opportunity to try, so I suppose I will extend a measure of trust. Not that it truly matters. Your tiny horn and weak magic could not kill me any more than those weapons you use.”

Noted. Despite that little tidbit, I did feel the need to clarify something. “It’s not hypocrisy. I’ve killed individuals who have caused direct and intentional harm upon others, or who were trying to do so. You were talking about killing individuals because of what someone else of their species might do.”

She stared off into space for a few seconds, considering this. “Hmm. I think I see. Most species lack the Unity we shared, so I suppose it only makes sense to judge them separately.” She abruptly scowled. “I certainly wouldn’t want to be judged off the actions some of my sisters have chosen after our Unity was… disrupted.” She quickly shook her head, then looked to me. “This whole conversation would have been much simpler if you had just presented this argument to begin with.”

I blinked. “I hadn’t thought it would be quite so effective,” I admitted. “I take it you’ve decided against genocide as an option.”

She gave a sharp, imperious nod. “Yes. Unless some critical new piece of information turns up, I believe it would cause more harm than good.”

“Well… that’s good.” I looked back to my companions. Starlight had a thoroughly mixed expression, somewhere between surprise, amusement, and confusion. She met my eyes and gave a helpless shrug.

“Okay,” I said, retrieving and stowing the rest of my small arsenal. Dusty had already finished, still eying the alicorn warily. “Then I guess there’s just one final thing we should address before traveling together.”

Her eyes narrowed slightly. “What is it now?”

“Do you have a name?”

Her expression immediately relaxed as she stared off into space. It took a couple of seconds before she replied. “We remember many names,” she said, her voice distant. “Many names, but none of them are… mine.” She stared for another moment before blinking, her attention returning to me. “I have chosen a name for myself: Echo. I feel that name befits me.”

“Echo,” I said, and raised a hoof to gesture to the dim glow coming down the exit ramp. “Shall we go?”

“Oh, good,” Sickle rumbled. “You dumb cunts are finally done talking. I was about to nod off.”

Echo frowned, looking sideways at Sickle. “I understand you prefer to put on an abrasive front, but while we are traveling together, I would appreciate if you showed at least some fraction of the respect I am due.”

Sickle laughed. “Respect? Right. And I’d appreciate it if you ate my ass, you retarded purple bitch.” She even turned, shaking her armored flanks at the alicorn, her tail raised high to give a clear view.

“Okay, knock it off,” Dusty called out, stepping between them.

Echo had grimaced at Sickle’s reply. “Surely you can’t be serious.”

“Nah,” Sickle said, chuckling. “Doesn’t have to be the ass. I ain’t that picky. As long as you put that snout between my legs and get to work, it’s all good.”

My wings fluttered as I took off, interposing myself between the two of them and gently nudging Echo away. “Okay, yes, Sickle got her crude comments in again, let’s move on, shall we?”

Echo scoffed, then raised her head and walked on as if it was all beneath her notice.

Behind me, I heard the metallic rattle of Dusty thumping Sickle on the shoulder, followed by a quiet but angry, “The hell is wrong with you?”

Sickle’s reply was much less quiet. “The fuck are you talking about? What, because I’m not playing all super-nice with her? Hey, you cunts want to be little bitches, lick her hooves and suckle her teats, you go right ahead. If she’s just going to act like she’s got a colossal fucking log rammed up her ass, then yeah, she gets treated like the uptight cunt she is. If she wants to pull that log out, hey, we all win.” I could practically hear the sneer that followed. “‘Sides, ain’t like I wouldn’t return the favor. Big bitch like that? I bet we could get some good rough fucking in, even if she is a mare. Been a long time since I wrestled with a pony my size.”

I quickly ushered Echo away, moving up the ramp and into the outside world. After the darkness of the underground facility, even the overcast skies were surprisingly bright.

Hoping to distract from Sickle’s crudeness, I got down to business. “So! We’re still planning on doing some traveling, but our motorwagon is a bit crowded. With Sickle taking up the rest of the room in the back, I’m afraid the only open space would be the back seat, which will probably be a little cramped.”

“That sounds quite unpleasant,” Echo said, looking over the vehicle as it came into sight. “Also, unnecessary. I will simply follow you from above.”

I nodded, pleased with her decision. Seeing as I sat in the back seat, it would have been cramped for me, as well. “I assume that means you can keep up with it?”

“Of course,” she said, walking up to the vehicle. “Though if we have the time to spare from analyzing your magic, I would enjoy the opportunity to examine this vehicle. We remember a good deal of the working of arcane technology, but we do not remember ever working with a motorwagon. A simple disassembly and reassembly should answer any questions I have.”

“Maybe if we’re going to be in one place for a while and don’t need to travel,” I said, while hoping such an opportunity didn’t present itself. I had only a vague idea of how complex such a machine was, and I had no idea if she’d actually be able to reassemble it. Then, as an afterthought, “but you should probably ask the others, as well. Dusty’s kind of in charge, and I think Starlight considers the vehicle to be hers.”

“I will do so,” she said. There was a flicker of a frown, and she added, “I must admit, I prefer machines over ponies. They are… simpler.”

I nodded, feeling a little more comfortable with this topic. “Very true. Machines are built for a clear, defined purpose, and produce entirely predictable results from their input. Ponies—or any other people—are much more complex. While their behavior can still be predicted if you have the correct information, the amount of complexity makes it much harder to get all the information you need.” I gave a little shrug. “It becomes easier with practice.”

Echo had stopped, her head high as she stared off into space. “Hmm. Yes, I suppose that does make for a very good metaphor, even if I had not originally intended it to be one.” Her focus returned. “I simply meant to say that machines are much simpler in their function, mechanically. I can disassemble even a complex machine and reassemble it into working order with ease. So far, doing so with ponies eludes me.”

And we were right back down to creepytown. “I can’t say I’m surprised,” I said, cautiously. “Most living things do not respond well to being disassembled.”

She dismissively waved a hoof. “I am not concerned with that. The goal is not to perfect disassembling ponies. That is trivially easy. The goal is to perfect reassembly, so that I can repair damage. I can repair a pump or skywagon that has not functioned for two hundred years. It… frustrates me that I can not do the same for a pony.”

“I don’t think it’s possible to bring back the dead.” Other than necromancy, anyway, but I wasn’t going to suggest that to an already morally-ambiguous pseudo-goddess.

“Of course it’s possible. It’s simply more complex than I had initially thought. My efforts to reassemble ponies has been incomplete. Superficial. It’s like…” She paused, cocking her head to the side for a moment before giving a sharp nod. “Like a computer, yes. Repairing a pony is like repairing a computer that is still running. Damaged hardware can damage the data in the computer. Disassembling it while it is operating, in an attempt to repair it, can also do so. A pony is the same, with the hardware being the body and the software being their brain and thoughts. I simply need to figure out how to repair that hardware in a way that preserves that software.”

“If you’re talking about healing living ponies, I’m sure there are healing spells that—”

She scoffed. “Of course there are. We remember them quite well, even if I do not understand them well enough to use. No, I am looking for more in-depth knowledge, a proper understanding of how ponies function, so as to better aid them. Cures that go beyond simply knitting flesh and bone.”

I considered that, and nodded. “I suppose that’s a noble enough of a goal,” I said, if a little reluctantly. “But I think we’ll have to say no more disassembling people. Ponies aren’t going to take that well.”

“I doubt they will care much,” she said with a shrug. “I have been making use of raiders. Many of them were ponies that you four have killed.”

“No, that’s… well, yeah, it might help a little, but there’s still going to be plenty of ponies who find the idea of dissecting other ponies to be rather creepy. Not to mention disrespectful. No non-raiders, at least. And definitely no living people.”

“I do not—” She cut herself off, her mouth shutting. Then, more slowly, she said, “I suppose there were two raiders who were alive when I disassembled them, but seeing as I was going to kill them anyway, it hardly makes a difference.”

Okay, that was one I had to put my hoof down on. “It absolutely makes a difference. What you’re talking about is essentially torture. It’s that sort of thing that makes raiders so despised, and while you might have better intentions, it doesn’t change that the means are horrific. If you truly want to make the world a better place, you need to start by being better.”

“I am better,” she grumbled, and when I went to speak again, she quickly cut me off. “Yes, I understand what you are saying. It is simply a lot to think on, and a lot of complication added into an already complex situation. It seems as if all these restrictions simply get in the way of doing what needs to be done. I have to wonder if the world would already be a better place if we didn’t have the absurd restrictions constraining our actions.”

“Just the opposite,” I said. “I might have missed the last two hundred years, but I’ve caught up quickly, and I understand ponies rather well. As far as I see it, the world is still so badly off because people do take those shortcuts. They do horrible things in the name of survival or personal interest, or even occasionally for some greater good, but in the process, they keep spreading this misery around. If you pursue your own noble goals through such horrible means, you’re simply continuing the same process that has kept the Wasteland going for centuries.”

Echo had fallen silent, staring at the ground, deep in thought. I continued. “You recited the Elements of Harmony just a few minutes ago. You understand what they are, correct?”

Her ears pinned back. Her voice was quiet, distant. “We remember them very well.”

“Then you should know that Equestria was at its greatest when the ponies there embraced the values the Elements represented. Those were the values that made Equestria such a wonderful place. It was only when ponies started to compromise them, forget them, that things became so bad.”

Echo frowned, silent.

“If we’re going to make the world a better place, we need to bring those values back.”

Her eyes returned to me, staring. “And you think this would be sufficient?”

I nodded. “I’ve seen it. You probably have, too. You’ve been watching us, right? Did you watch Emerald?”

“The innkeeper,” Echo replied. “Yes.”

“Someone who embraced the ideals of Kindness and Generosity. She made Gemstone into a wonderful place, one that is already on its way to being what Equestria once was. That’s what one pony—one changeling, even—can do. She made a small part of the world a better place, and she’s inspired others to do the same. That’s the only way the world is going to get better than all of this.”

“By embodying the Elements,” Echo murmured, as if to herself. After a moment of thought, her gaze hardened, glaring at me. It was hard to read the intent behind those eyes. I couldn’t tell if she was angry, suspicious, or something completely different.

“Is there something wrong?” I asked, almost fearing the response.

She didn’t answer. Instead, she held her stare for a long moment, until her ears flicked and her attention turned back to the ramp. My companions were walking up to join us.

Echo abruptly spread her wings to their full extension, her head rising. “I shall follow you from above,” she declared before turning her hard glare back to me. “We will continue this discussion later.”

She immediately beat her wings, lifting into the sky, while I staggered at the volume of air she displaced. As I caught my balance, Dusty trotted up to me. “Problem?”

“I don’t know,” I said, looking up to watch Echo ascending. “I think I might have upset her, but I’m not entirely clear why, or why she immediately broke off the conversation instead of talking. Maybe she just wants some time to think. I’ve thrown rather a lot at her.”

“Well that sounds ominous.” He sighed, shaking his head, while Sickle walked past us to the motorwagon. Finally, Dusty fixed me with a look. “Okay, what’s the plan? Are we really taking her with us? Or is this just delaying until we’re sure of a way to kill her safely?”

“We’re not killing her,” I quickly said. “She’s not malicious. She’s just… unguided. She seems like a child, in some ways.”

“Oh, great,” Dusty said, clearly not comforted by the comparison. “Have you been around children? I saw a little colt throw a shitstorm of a tantrum because he ate all of the filling out of his birthday snack-cake and that made it ‘broken’. Now you’re saying this alicorn might be like that?”

“No,” I said, shaking my head. “Foals do stuff like that mostly because they have no sense of cause and effect. Many times they don’t even have a concept of object permanence. She clearly understands these things, and she seems quite intelligent. When I said she was like a child, I don’t mean that her mental faculties are limited. I mean that she lacks the experience necessary to understand why something might be moral or not.”

He grimaced. “No concept of morality. Yeah, really not selling me on this.”

“Consider that she’s trying to get help with that,” I said. “She’s been listening to me, and I think we’ve already made some good progress. She’s looking for guidance. I think we can help each other.”

“Assuming she doesn’t decide we’re part of the problem and kill us. Or decide that changelings really do need to be exterminated, and kills you. Or decides that us not wanting to be ‘perfect’ alicorns is unacceptable and forces us to change. Or just kills us, because why not?” He shook his head. “Look, I get that you want to help her, and yeah, she’d be pretty damn useful, but she’s a fucking ticking bomb, and I don’t like the idea of keeping her around waiting to see if she blows up on us.”

The motorwagon shook as Sickle flopped down in the back with a grunt, followed immediately by calling out, “A bomb, huh? Bigger or smaller than the balefire eggs I just sat on?”

He turned to her. “You know what I mean.”

“Sure, sure,” Sickle said, lazily waving a spiked hoof. “It’s just that what you mean is stupid.”

“Look,” I said, drawing his attention back. “I said a lot about ideals to her, about the Elements of Harmony, and that applies just as much to us as they do to her. I think she’s hurt and lost, and we need to help her because it’s the right thing to do.

“And yes, if she does decide to hurt others, we’ll do what we can to stop her from doing so, but we’re not going to do so preemptively just because she might become a problem later on. We have to be better than that.”

Dusty grunted, looking away. “I don’t much like it, but… hell, you’re the whole psychology expert, I guess.” He looked back. “Fine. It seems like a dangerous gamble, but this one’s your call. But if she does try to hurt somepony, I’m doing what I can to stop her.”

I nodded. “Of course. And while I hope it won’t come to that, I will help. I don’t intend to sit back and let innocents be hurt if there’s anything I can do about it. The thing is, I think she’s one of those innocents, right now.”

Dusty frowned, silent for a moment before sighing. “Yeah, maybe. She’s just a lot more dangerous than most.”

“So is Sickle,” I said. “Hell, apparently so am I.”

“Yeah, yeah,” Dusty said, waving a hoof. “I get it. Shit. I won’t kill the alicorn, ‘less she does something bad enough to force my hoof.”

“Good enough,” I said. “Not that I’m entirely sure we could stop her, even if we wanted to. I’m not sure what alicorns are capable of, but she seemed confident in her safety.”

“I know they can be killed,” Dusty said. “Heard that much on the radio, at least.”

I nodded. “Hopefully we’ll never have to find out,” I said. With that, I turned to the motorwagon. Starlight was already inside, watching us through the side window.

“As an aside,” I said casually as I approached the vehicle, “Echo’s observation of us apparently included conversations, even fairly private ones. It’s quite possible she has some form of magical eavesdropping that’s letting her listen in on every word we’ve said.”

Dusty froze, one hoof on the side of the motorwagon. “...Shit, you mean she just heard me talking about… that? You think you could have told me that a little earlier?”

“If she heard you considering it, she also heard why you’ve decided against it. Consider it to be a demonstration of morality.”

“Hmmph.” He pulled himself into the motorwagon, grumbling. “Still could have told me.”

I said nothing as I hovered up beside the window and slipped in. In the front seat, Starlight gave a quiet chuckle. “Sneaky bug,” she murmured, before turning to me. “Also, holy shit that actually worked!”

I groaned softly as I sank into the rear seat. “So far. We’ve got a good ways to go before we can really say it ‘worked’.”

“Hey, we’re all still alive, and it sounds like she might kinda maybe sorta help us.”

I shrugged, though I did give a thin smile. What had started as a particularly dangerous situation was now… a somewhat less dangerous situation with more potential. It wasn’t perfect, and it could still collapse around us at any moment, but we had made progress. A better outcome was in sight.

Starlight had turned to Dusty. “Where to?”

“Start heading out west,” he grumbled. “Somepony has been complaining about the lack of adequate company, so we’re stopping by Rust to see if that shuts her up for a bit. Not that I’d mind a real bed, for a change.”

“Rust it is,” Starlight said, and the motorwagon started off. Soon we were rolling along at a good clip, with Starlight casting the occasional glance to her PipBuck’s map, and the strange alicorn trailing us in the sky above.

We continued on across the dry, dusty desert, and thick plumes of dark smoke rose from the horizon before us.

Chapter Thirty Three: The First Blow

I’d seen many horrible things since waking up in that ancient facility.

Chief among those were the death and devastation at my hive, the deaths of so many of my sisters, and of course, the sight of my queen lying dead.

While it wasn’t so painful as those events, seeing the ruin brought upon Rust was certainly up there. That simple little settlement had been the first place to offer me some sense of security after my tumultuous first few days in the Wasteland. It was spartan and run-down, but it was still a place where ponies banded together, refusing the decay and destruction of the Wasteland.

Now, the town lay dead. The walls were scorched, with embers still smoldering in places. Some of it had collapsed, including the main gate itself. The central structure, with its machine-gun armed tower, was a burnt-out shell. Despite the metal construction that was abundant in the town, little was still standing. Some of those still-standing walls sported ragged holes, and in some cases, it looked as if the metal had softened and sagged. I was pretty sure I was seeing the signs of magical energy weapons at work.

Just outside the gate lay the emaciated form of a dead pony. They were blackened from the flames that had burned away flesh, leaving them practically skeletal.

Above it all, smoke hung like a towering column of clouds, a beacon announcing the destruction that had taken place here.

I followed closely behind Dusty as he moved forward, our weapons ready. I’d retaken my pony guise in anticipation of our arrival, but now I was tempted to strip it away once more. I held off for the moment; my armor was just a thought away.

Dusty didn’t say anything, but I saw where he was leading us. We were moving to a small rise that ran along one side of the small settlement, and which approached it near a section of collapsed wall. It would give us a good vantage point and a point of entry.

I’m sure none of us expected to find the individuals responsible still here, but I imagine many of us hoped to be proven wrong. Even Sickle had gone quiet, her mouth drawn into a thin, tight frown.

Echo had rejoined us, though she had said nothing. She strolled along behind us, seemingly unconcerned. I’m not sure if she was bored or simply observing, but there was something detached about her demeanor. I didn’t really think on it much at the time; I had more immediate concerns.

We paused for a moment on the ridge, maybe a hundred yards from the walls, but there was nothing new to be seen. As we were getting ready to move out again, a distant clang of metal striking metal echoed across the gap. Dusty cast a quick glance to us, cinched his rifle’s stock in tighter against his chest, and advanced.

Pips started appearing on my E.F.S. as we approached the gap in the wall. Dusty halted at the edge of the opening, peering in briefly before looking back to us. “I count five contacts. They’re showing as non-hostile, so hold your fire unless they give us a reason. Could be survivors.”

We nodded, except for Echo, who simply watched in silence.

We were moving again. I followed off Dusty’s flank as he advanced down what had once been a narrow alleyway. The building to our left had been partially wood, and had collapsed into a smoldering heap, leaving the air thick and hot with smoke. To our right was a fully metal building, and appeared reasonably intact until we reached the corner and could see the front of it, riddled with dozens, if not hundreds, of bullet holes. The mangled corpse of a pony lay in front of the building. The thick metal armor the guard had worn had not protected her, as every bit of exposed flesh had been shredded by whatever had opened up on her.

I was starting to get a better grasp on our position, trying to match the ruins I saw now with the settlement as I had last seen it. We were crossing the street when I realized that the ruined building in front of us had been Mustard’s inn. Now, what walls remained were almost universally pierced or crumpled, and much of the supporting structure seemed to be entirely missing. It looked as if something gigantic had torn through it, scattering the remains. The burnt remains of tables, chairs, and beds were scattered among the wreckage. I spared a glance at a charred bed-frame as we passed it by, distantly pondering whether it might be one I had slept in.

Another clang of metal interrupted my thoughts, followed by a groan of metal shifting, and finally, a distant voice. I couldn’t make out what was said, only that it was said firmly.

We advanced carefully down the street, past a scattered pile of ashes, a discarded pair of saddlebags, and the scorched, barely legible “Stuff” sign. From the direction of the pips, it appeared the unknown entities were at the town workshop.

At the corner, by a half-collapsed shack, we paused again. The heap of metal and charred wood stood about shoulder-high, giving decent cover as we crept up.

Dusty carefully peeked his head up.

The moment he cleared the top of the wall, his eyes went wide, and he lowered his head again, staring at the wall in front of him.

I peeked my head up to see what had alarmed him.

Perhaps fifty yards away, I could see two ponies, with glimpses of movement beyond them. They were clad in Enclave armor, though the backs were painted blue, and one of them appeared to have a small, thin rainbow painted across her armor’s flank.

Neither were looking in my direction, but I still crouched down to hide again. This posed a problem. I had no idea why the Enclave would be here, but I didn’t imagine the reason was anything good. Fighting would be problematic. Starlight’s Lancer was the only weapon we carried that could reliably harm them, though I imagined Sickle might do some damage if she got her hooves on them. Dusty and I would have to rely on volume of fire to get some rounds into the few places the armor didn’t cover.

Though, we also had Echo with us. I had no idea how capable she would be against them. I didn’t even know if she’d join in a fight. She still stood back, watching us, but otherwise unconcerned.

“What the fuck?” Dusty muttered before turning his head towards us. He spoke quietly. “Fall back. We don’t want this fight.”

I nearly jumped when Echo spoke in a clear, firm voice, her conversational level of volume shockingly loud. “I do not believe these ponies will fight. Even if they did try, they can not harm me.”

A stallion’s shout echoed between the buildings. “Shit! Marks south-east! Lots of ‘em!”

Dusty cursed under his breath. I could hear another pony, a mare this time, and while I couldn’t make out the words, the tone of giving orders was clear. After a few quick orders, she called out clearly, voice amplified by her armor. “We are investigating these ruins. Show yourself and state your intentions.”

Dusty cursed a couple more times before shouting back. “I’ll stay right here, thank you very much. As for—”

Echo had stepped forward to look at the pegasi, prompting a fresh shout from the distant stallion. “Shit, it’s that creepy-ass alicorn!”

“Hold fire!” the mare snapped, and at the same instant, Echo’s purple magic flashed outward. I flinched back; for just an instant, I had thought she had exploded in magic, but I quickly realized she had put up a magical shield, a perfect sphere of energy that surrounded her completely.

The pegasus mare barked a few more sharp commands before calling out again. “We didn’t come here for a fight. We were on patrol when we saw the smoke, so we came to investigate. Do you know what happened here?”

Dusty shouted back, “We were coming here to spend the night, except we get here and find the place burnt down and you guys picking through the ashes. The damage sure as hell looks like Enclave-issue weapons.”

I expected her to argue that, but I was surprised. “Could be,” she replied. “But not us. I don’t know how up-to-date you are on current events, but the pegasi aren’t quite as united as we used to be. Look, we’ve found a survivor, and we’re trying to dig them out. It’s hard enough going, but this little standoff is delaying us. I don’t mean to be rude, but I need you to either come out and meet face-to-face, or back off until we’re done here.”

Dusty sat back, considering how to reply.

Echo’s hum was nearly muffled by her shield, and I almost would have missed it if she hadn’t stepped forward a moment later.

I lurched. “Echo, wait!”

She didn’t. Instead, she kept walking, while shooting a sharp look my way. “If we are to help ponies, then we shall do so now.”

“Crap,” Dusty muttered, and after a final moment of consideration, lowered his rifle. “Okay, we’re coming out.”

“Wait, really?” I said, ears perking up in surprise. It seemed rather incautious for Dusty.

“There’s nowhere to run or hide,” he grunted quietly. “If they wanted to kill us, there isn’t much we could do about it either way, and not much reason for them to hold their fire. Plus, this gets Sickle in close.”

“Am I going to get to pluck a birdie?” Sickle asked with a grin.

Dusty ignored her and stood, keeping his rifle low. Reluctantly, I followed suit.

Echo’s shield stood between us and the pegasi, though it was translucent enough to see through. One of the pegasi, the stallion, stood with his head down, the twin gem-tipped barrels of his mounted guns tracking Echo as she advanced. The other, the mare, stood in a slightly more relaxed posture. She looked to still be alert, but not tense, even as the alicorn advanced.

“Just keep the weapons lowered,” the mare said. “We’re not interested in a fight.”

“Neither are we,” Dusty said, though it was perhaps less convincing when said around the bit of his rifle. At least he kept it pointing downward, though it would take only a moment to bring it up to a firing position. It’s not as if I could really criticise him on that point; I was holding the bit of my own rifle, too.

As we approached, I saw the other two pegasi among the ruins of the workshop. One had gotten himself under a support beam and was holding it up, while the other stood guard nearby, watching the scene unfold. They, too, had the curious blue paint on their armor, though I could see now that it wasn’t uniform in its application. While the first two had their backs painted, the one under the support beam had a simple stripe along either side, while the fourth pony had her chest painted blue and bands painted around her legs.

The nearest stallion stepped back, still tracking Echo as she approached. “Uh, Sergeant? You sure about this?”

Echo continued to walk forward, right past him, as he backed up. His head swiveled, as if trying to decide whether to focus on her or the rest of us, and settled on her. I was quite fine with that, though I hoped her defenses were as good as she claimed they were.

The mare—a sergeant, apparently—watched her as she stepped past, then turned back to us. “I appreciate the gesture of trust. I know this is an awkward situation. If you’ll give us a few minutes to finish our rescue efforts, I’d like to ask you—”

“That will not be necessary,” Echo stated, her horn lighting up. The stallion started to shout something, and my own gut lurched as the adrenaline hit once more. Then I saw the purple glow of her magic wrap around the ruins of the structure. Metal groaned and shrieked as she lifted away what must have been several tons of ruined structure.

“Downdraft,” the pegasus mare said, her voice tight. “Please stop pointing your weapons at the alicorn.”

“It is not as if they could harm me,” Echo said as she continued to tear open the structure, metal bending and cracking under the force of her magic. “Though it is rather impolite.”

“Right,” the stallion, Downdraft, said, taking another step back and standing a little more upright.

The pony who had gotten under the support beam stepped back as it was lifted away, but he remained close by, peering into the space that was opening up. “I see her,” he said, and as a piece of bent skywagon was torn away, he slipped in again, climbing over the remaining debris. I craned my neck, trying to see. I only caught a glimpse of an ash-caked flank.

“She was bleeding, but it’s stopped,” the pony said. He quickly unlatched and removed his helmet, his long blue mane spilling out across his shoulders. I couldn’t help but consider how awkward that must be to tuck away inside the helmet, as well as how starkly his pale pink coat contrasted with the black armor. Those thoughts were interrupted as he spoke again. “I’m getting minimal response. Might be internal damage. Might just be dehydration.”

Starlight pressed forward. “Here, let me see her.”

The sergeant’s attention snapped to her. “Are you trained in medical care?”

“A little,” Starlight replied, “but I’ve got plenty of experience and some healing potions.”

“So does Soaring Heart,” the sergeant said. “Don’t worry, she’s in good hooves.”

The tension seemed to have broken. Dusty let his rifle hang from its sling, and I followed suit. Echo finished moving the last batch of debris, and as she set it down, her shield vanished. Even Downdraft relaxed a bit more, seeing the “creepy-ass alicorn” helping them.

The sergeant looked over the scene before turning back to Echo and giving an appreciative nod. “Thank you for the help.”

“It was a trivial task,” Echo replied, her head held high, while her eyes remained fixed on the injured pony. We all moved in a little closer to get a better view.

The pony lay across a toolbox, and was contorted at an angle that made me concerned for the state of her spine. A few cuts, none serious, were covered in dried blood. Pale ash was caked in her coat, hiding all but a faint hint of red. It was only then that I connected that frail form with the energetic and enthusiastic pony I had met here before: Singe.

Soaring Heart was carefully moving his hooves along her body, examining for further injuries. “I’m not finding any major broken bones, though a couple of her ribs might be fractured. No signs of internal bleeding. I’m a little worried about her spine, but I think it’s intact.”

“Why don’t you give her a healing potion?” Starlight said. “Or hell, I’ve got one.”

The sergeant answered for him. “We have limited supplies. We need to make sure it’s needed before administering healing potions. If we use them for somepony that doesn’t need it, we might not have any when somepony does.”

I immediately thought of Emerald. I tried to push the thought away, but it held its ground. Fortunately, it did lead into another thought. “I think we can help with that,” I said, and turned. “Sickle, do you still have that spare PipBuck?”

“Hmm? Yeah, I got it in one of these cans. Just a ‘sec.” She popped open the metal cans strapped to her side and started rooting around, grumbling a bit. “Woulda been a good fight, too.”

She eventually pulled out the PipBuck and tossed it to me. I caught it and climbed over a ruined table to get to Soaring Heart. “Here, use this.”

“I don’t have the tools to—” He stopped as he saw the clasp, then smiled. “Oh, that’ll do nicely.”

While he tended to Singe, Dusty struck up a conversation with the mare in charge. “Dusty Trails, former sergeant in the Mareford Militia Rangers.” He offered his hoof.

She took it, giving a friendly shake. “Sergeant Hail Burst.”

“Good to be talking,” Dusty said. “So what exactly is the Enclave doing here, patrolling the Wasteland and rescuing civilians? Not to put too fine of a point on it, but last time I saw Enclave soldiers, they were gunning down unarmed ponies.”

She grimaced. “Not our Enclave,” she said, practically spitting the words. “It’s the politicians. The whole damn Council. They betrayed us, started a coup, and a bunch of featherbrains in the military actually listened to them. Now it’s a damned civil war. You want the politics, talk to our commander. Far as I’m concerned, you see somepony in Enclave armor doing shit like that, you’ll be doing us a favor if you take them down. Fucking traitors, the lot of them.”

There were grunts and nods of agreement from the other Enclave soldiers.

“Is your commander around here?” Dusty asked.

“She’s back at camp,” Hail Burst replied. “You’re welcome to come back with us. She’s had us out doing goodwill flights, trying to make contact with the locals on top of the usual patrol duties. I’m sure she’d want to speak with you.”

Dusty sighed, looking back over his shoulder. “We might have to take you up on that. We were going to stay the night here, but…”

There was a moment of silence before Hail Burst spoke again. “If we find out who did this, our whole unit will come down on them. We’ve seen enough of this shit already.”

Dusty grunted softly and nodded.

“She’s stable,” Soaring Heart said. His head was tilted at an awkward angle to read from the PipBuck’s screen without moving Singe’s leg. “No internal bleeding, and the spine is intact. She does have an incomplete fracture of the left foreleg, some fractured ribs, and extensive contusions. The most immediate concerns are a minor concussion and moderate dehydration.”

“Okay,” Hail Burst said, turning her attention to him. “Treatment?”

“Treat for shock and get some fluids in her. Not much else to do. Fluids are going to be a little tricky. If she wakes up in the next few hours, we’ll need to get her to drink something. If not, we’ll have to hydrate her another way. We could set an IV, but I’d rather get her back to camp and get a feeding tube in place. Should splint her leg, too, but that’s low priority. Administering a healing potion isn’t necessary at the moment, but if her condition doesn’t improve, it might become necessary.”

“Got it. She’s good to move, then?”

“Yes. Give me a few minutes to get her ready and on the stretcher.”

“Do it.” She turned back to us. “Our camp’s not far to the east,” she said, then her armored head shifted as she looked at Dusty’s side. “...Well, not far by wing. Can’t say how long it’d take on hoof.”

“We have transportation,” Dusty said. “Can’t say we’ll keep up with pegasi flying all-out, but we can cover a day’s worth of hiking in an hour or two, depending on terrain.”

“Impressive,” she said with an approving nod. “In that case, we can escort you there. At least that way there won’t be any tensions over a group of well-armed ponies approaching the camp.”

Though the helmet obscured her face, I caught the way it turned slightly in Sickle’s direction.

“I appreciate it,” Dusty said, “but I think you’d better get her to some care. We’re not leaving just yet. I saw several bodies on the way in. I’d like to do something for them before moving on. Doesn’t feel right just leaving them lying there.”

Hail Burst paused for a moment before turning back to her team. “Soaring, Downdraft. As soon as you get the civvie ready to go, take her back to camp. Sunfire and I will stay and help these ponies.”

“You got it,” Soaring Heart replied, his focus remaining on his patient as he strapped her into the folding stretcher.

While I was quite thankful for Hail Burst’s gesture in offering to help, it proved to be entirely unnecessary. Echo strolled casually through the ruins, plucking bodies from the dirt and ash, and even tearing open the ruins of a building to retrieve the occasional half-concealed corpse.

It didn’t help that the sight made me think back to Paradise Beach.

Minutes later, we had a funeral pyre going. As the flames rose, we stood around, staring into the fire. It was a long time before Dusty broke the silence. “I know somepony’s supposed to say something at these kinds of things, but I’ve never been good at it. Not the type, I guess.”

“Yeah,” Sickle rumbled from behind us. “They’re dead. Talking ain’t going to do shit.”

“Charming,” Starlight muttered.

“The talking isn’t for the dead,” I said, “so much as the ones still alive.”

“Eh, I prefer doing over talking,” Sickle said with a metal-rattling shrug. “Though you know, even though I thought half the ponies here were a bunch of dumb cunts, I think I’d like to find the ponies that killed ‘em.”

“I hear that,” Dusty said, nodding grimly.

☢

It was just after sundown as we rolled up to the Enclave camp.

Hail Burst and Sunfire flew just above us, along with Echo, both guiding us to their camp and giving a clear signal to any sentries that we were not some hostile force.

Despite that, there was something unnerving about entering an Enclave camp. Even without the stories we had heard and the rare sighting, it was a military encampment with a large number of power-armor clad troops. The black armor had been designed to be intimidating, and while the aesthetic was probably less effective on me than on a regular pony, the intent was clear.

The splotches of blue paint and the occasional rainbow did little to dampen that effect.

We followed Hail Burst’s directions as we pulled up past some simple earthworks and scrap barricades, and parked in a small clearing, surrounded by tents. The camp itself was a compact square, consisting of several tents neatly clustered around a few buildings made from scrap, with a small tower at each corner. Despite the structures being made of scrap, they looked almost professionally made, and more impressively, the obvious bolts made it look like each shelter could be rapidly dismantled and moved. There was little else in the way of equipment, aside from a few suits of power armor receiving maintenance in a makeshift workspace beneath an overhead tarp.

Several soldiers peeked out from tents or from the outer fortifications to get a look at us, and while I’m sure our motorwagon drew some interest, the real focus of their attention was Echo. They watched her warily, and several weapons tracked her, even as she landed alongside our escort.

Most of the soldiers I saw were clad in power armor. Despite the number of them, there was just one that really caught my attention. Her armor was more thoroughly painted, with the helmet and torso a solid blue, and a broad stripe of rainbow ran across her back. She walked toward us with a pair of armored ponies trailing at her flanks, and with her confident stance, she gave the immediate impression of being the pony in charge.

“So you’re the ponies Soaring Heart told me about,” she said in a clear but slightly scratchy voice. Dusty stepped forward to meet her, and she stopped to extend a hoof. “Commander Aurora, former XO of the Cumulonimbus and current commanding officer of this unit. It’s good to meet you.”

“Dusty Trails,” he replied, before taking a moment to introduce the rest of us.

She greeted each of us in turn, ending with Echo. “You’ve been giving my sentries some concern,” Aurora said, looking up to the alicorn. “And I’ve got to admit, I’ve got some questions. You’ve been watching our camp for a few weeks, even after multiple relocations, and now we find out you’re not alone. Why?”

“Our collaboration is a recent development,” Echo replied. “I have been observing these individuals since before your vessel was brought down, but did not make contact with them until this afternoon. As for why I was observing you, the reason is the same as the reason I was observing them; you intrigued me.”

Dusty cut in. “The Cumulonimbus, wasn’t that the Raptor that went down a month or two back?”

Aurora grunted softly. “It was. Seems half the Wasteland saw it happen, too. Now we’re here, and caught up in everything going on below the clouds. Speaking of, I’ve got an injured civilian, and I hear that a local settlement has been attacked and razed. Do you have any insight into the attack and who was responsible?”

“I’m afraid not, ma’am,” Dusty replied. “Whoever did it was well-armed and ruthless. Not many groups could bring that level of firepower. With Big Gun dead, I doubt it was Mareford or his former mercs; even if they had attacked, they would have taken the town for themselves. Given that the place was razed, my first instinct would have been raiders, but with the amount of magical energy weapon strikes I saw, I find it unlikely. Second instinct was Enclave, but I suspect you’d know more about that than I would.”

“Yes,” Aurora said. Her helmet lacked the mask that most of the other helmets had over the muzzle. It let us see her frown. “We do have a reputation, don’t we?” She sighed. “And not undeserved, I’m sad to say. But no, it’s unlikely that this was a Council attack. They’ve got bigger concerns than what’s happening below the clouds, and even if they decided this one lonely settlement needed to be removed, it’s unlikely they’d get groundside without our patrols seeing them. The Council has learned to keep its forces concentrated.” She shook her head. “You said it’s only unlikely that it was raiders?”

“Very unlikely,” Dusty said. “Magical energy weapons are too rare for the damage we saw. Not many places they could get them.” His ears flicked back, his jaw tightening. “...Unless they hit Gemstone, too.”

Aurora gave a small smile. “That, at least, I can say has not happened. We’ve been in contact with the settlement of Gemstone. Nice place, good ponies. We have a patrol fly by a few times a day. They haven’t been hit.”

“Good to know,” Dusty said, as we both relaxed again.

“I can nearly guarantee it was not raiders,” Echo said. “I have destroyed every raider camp I could find in the area. As far as I am aware, there is not a single raider alive within fifty miles of Rust.”

“Then I take it that was your hoofwork we’ve come across on our patrols,” Aurora said. “I know raiders aren’t as prevalent as we had been led to believe, but I had been thinking their numbers seemed particularly low around here. You did this all on your own, then?”

“These ponies have destroyed three raider encampments in recent months,” Echo said with a nod, “and I have personally destroyed another half-dozen.”

Aurora eyed her for a long moment, clearly uncertain about the strange alicorn, before turning back to Dusty. “Getting back to the attack, I’m hoping we’ll find something. I’ve already ordered several more patrol flights over the area. Unless the ponies responsible have wings or a vehicle like yours, they’ll be moving slow, and my scouts should locate them. In the meantime, I’ll see that you have a place to stay for the night, and I’d like to talk some more with you, get a better picture of local events, if you don’t mind. I also understand that the medics were getting the civilian casualty settled, if you’d like to see her?”

“Is she awake?” Dusty asked.

“Not last I heard, but she hasn’t been there long. I was giving the medics time to look over her and start treatment before intruding. Follow me.”

Aurora led us to their medical post, set inside one of the scrap-built buildings. It was cramped inside, and far from the standards of a pre-war hospital, but it was still reasonably clean and cluttered with basic medical gear. I recognized Soaring Heart, now without his armor, along with a few other unarmored ponies. One was leaning over Singe.

They had cleaned most of the ash from her coat, though that improvement contrasted with the plastic tube that had been inserted into her nose and taped into place, and several bandages covered much of what wasn’t hidden under the blanket.

One of the pegasi turned to Aurora as she approached. “Commander.”

“Lifeline. How’s the patient?”

“Stable, but in poor shape. We set a nasal tube to get her hydrated. Blood volume is good. Brain activity is mostly good, with only minor irregularities from the concussion. We’re holding off on medication for the moment. Fortunately, she has a PipBuck. It’s making diagnosis and monitoring significantly quicker and easier, so I’m confident with a more conservative treatment. I don’t think we’ll get any more brain swelling, but we’re standing by with meds and potions if necessary.”

“Good,” Aurora said. “When do you think she will regain consciousness?”

“Soon,” Lifeline said. “She’s already partially responsive. She was tracking lights when we opened her eyes. I could try waking her up now, if you’d like.”

“If it won’t complicate her treatment,” Aurora said, but Lifeline was already moving over to Singe.

“Thank you for caring for her,” Dusty said. “Don’t take it wrong, but having the Enclave come to the rescue was the last thing I expected.”

“No, I understand,” Aurora said, watching Singe. “Given recent history, I couldn’t blame anypony for being wary of us. The Council has caused a lot of damage.”

“You’ve mentioned this ‘Council’ a couple of times, now,” Dusty said. “Not really sure who you’re talking about. We don’t know what’s going on above the clouds until something falls on us.”

Aurora gave a reaction halfway between a chuckle and a grimace. “The Council. They’re the ponies that were in charge of the Enclave. Top elected officials, generals, the like. I could go on for hours about what they’ve done, but the short version of it is, they lied to us, betrayed us, and murdered innocent ponies all for the sake of their own privileged positions. Worse, they used good ponies to do it. I’ve got soldiers under my command who have nightmares of the things they did, all because the Council lied to them about the situation.”

Dusty grunted. “That sounds uncomfortably familiar.”

“Fucking politicians,” Aurora muttered, then took a deep breath, sighed, and straightened up again. “In any case, we’re done with their lies. The pegasi that remain loyal to the Enclave, the real Enclave, are fighting to bring the Council to justice.”

“And that’s why you’re here?”

“Indirectly,” she replied with a shake of her head. “No, we’re here more by chance. We had a little mutiny on our cloudship. It ended badly. We all ended up in the brig or locked in our quarters. We probably would have been executed as traitors, but our ship was brought down shortly after that, and some of us managed to escape before it crashed. We don’t really have a safe place to go above the clouds, so we set camp here. I sent some scouts above the clouds to try to find a safe place or other Loyalists, but so far, no luck.” She shrugged. “In the meantime, if we’re stuck groundside, we might as well make ourselves useful.”

“And I take it those markings are to visually distinguish your side from the pegasi on the Council’s side?”

“Yes,” Aurora said. “Though I wouldn’t depend on it. I don’t know if other loyalists are doing the same thing, but it seemed appropriate.”

Across the room, Lifeline had been murmuring something. I hadn’t been paying attention, until I heard a weak groan.

“She’s waking up,” he said before leaning over her again. “Can you hear me?”

I leaned to peer around him. Singe lay with her mouth hanging halfway open, giving slow, shallow breaths. Her eyes were barely open, wavering as if it took a monumental effort to open them even that far. Her mouth moved, producing a weak and indistinct mumble.

“You’re in a medical center,” Lifeline said, a hoof resting gently on her shoulder. “You were in an incident, but you’re safe now. Do you understand what I’m saying?”

Her eyes wavered, struggling to focus on the face before her. Her mouth opened, croaking out another groan. Then her eyes closed again, clenched tight, as her groan deepened.

“It’s okay,” Lifeline said, reaching into the pouch at his side. “I’m going to give you a mild painkiller.”

As he was talking, her eyes opened, blurrily fixing on him. I could see her chest moving as her breathing picked up, and her eyes darted around, fixing on various ponies.

The last one she looked at was an armored soldier, standing guard nearby. Her eyes widened, her body tensing. The expression was clear: recognition and fear.

Aurora’s head turned slightly, tracking Singe’s gaze, and she gave a tight frown.

Singe moaned out a weak, alarmed groan and tried to flail out, but in her injured state, she was barely able to lift her legs. Lifeline gently put his hooves over her forelegs, speaking calmly to another medical pony. “Restrain her legs. No, higher up, that’s the injured leg. Good.” He turned back to Singe. “Ma’am, you need to stop trying to move. You’ll worsen your injuries.”

“Nnnno,” Singe groaned, finally forming coherent words as she tried to struggle. “Ge’way. Let… let me go!”

“Calm down, you’ve been injured. We’re trying to help.”

She groaned louder, ignoring him.

Lifeline looked back. “You ponies! Any of you friends or family? Does she know you?”

Starlight answered. “We traded with her a few times.”

“Worth a try,” Lifeline said. “Get over here, try to calm her down before I have to sedate her.”

Starlight and I stepped forward, slipping past a couple of Enclave ponies to get close to her bed. Starlight spoke softly. “Hey, Singe, right? Do you remember us?”

Singe’s struggles slowed as she slowly focused on us. She looked confused as she looked at Starlight, and even more when she looked at me. Her struggling slowed down.

But then her eyes widened more. “N-no,” she groaned, tears running down her cheeks as she struggled with renewed vigor. “You can’t… can’t trick me! You’re not real! You’re not ponies!”

My blood ran cold.

“This is the opposite of helping,” Lifeline grumbled, holding onto her. “Soaring, get the sedative.”

I ignored them, pushing in close. “Singe, we’re trying to help you. What did you see? Who did this?”

“You did it!” She blurted, her head lolling as she tried to look around for an escape. “All of you did it! I know! You can’t trick me. I-I saw what you really are! Let me go! Please, just… please, let me go…”

Her struggles ended, and she closed her eyes, chin tucking to her chest as if trying to shut out everything around her. She went silent, except for the occasional weak sob.

Soaring was approaching with a needle, but halted when she went still.

I raised a hoof, earning a sharp glance from Lifeline as I reached out to gently touch her chest, but he didn’t stop me. “Singe,” I said, keeping my voice quiet and soft despite the tension rising inside me. “What did you see? What did they look like?”

Her eyes cracked open, fearfully meeting mine. She shivered faintly, swallowed, and spoke in a hoarse voice. “Th-they looked like ponies, but… but some of them… changed. I-I saw what they looked like underneath. They were… monsters. You could be, too. Just… just leave me alone...”

I swallowed before quietly offering, “Bug ponies?”

She cringed, nodded, and closed her eyes again.

I looked over my shoulder, meeting Dusty’s eyes. After a moment, he turned away, snorting. “Shit.”

Aurora looked to him, then to me. “Is she talking about changelings?”

My ears perked up at that. “She is,” I said, stepping away from Singe. “I’m surprised you’ve heard of them.”

“Military history is a standard part of Enclave officer education,” Aurora replied. “Though I’m surprised that you have heard of them. I would have expected changelings to have died out. They don’t seem very well-suited for the way things are groundside.”

I sighed. She was right; this was hardly a love-filled land. “We’ve had some encounters with changelings.”

Echo snorted. “She is severely understating her ‘experience’ with changelings.”

I tensed in alarm, shooting a glance her way. Her expression was hard, her eyes narrowed accusingly at me.

This was going to be trouble. My options were rapidly dwindling.

“We should discuss this outside,” I said, returning to Aurora. While most of her face was hidden, her frown and general bearing seemed suspicious. “Given what she’s been through, I think it’d be best if we don’t force her to listen to this discussion.”

Aurora’s frown held, but after a moment’s consideration, she nodded.

We exited into the open air of the camp. Aurora followed behind, still flanked by a pair of soldiers, and even with the lenses hiding her eyes, I was acutely aware of her attention.

I halted, heaved a deep sigh, and turned to take the only remaining course of action I had available. “What Echo was so indelicately suggesting back there is that I am a changeling. I’m from a different hive than the ones responsible for this attack, and in fact, am directly opposed to them.”

I really, really didn’t want to share this, but of the few options available, it was the one course of action that offered a reasonable chance of success.

Aurora’s attention remained fixed on me. To her side, the soldiers posture shifted. It was subtle, but it was enough to show they were prepared for a fight. When Aurora spoke again, the tone was neutral but firm, a combination that immediately struck me as dangerous. “You’re a changeling?”

“Yes,” I said. “And given that Singe just saw other changelings wipe out her home, I didn’t want to say so in front of her. She’s been through enough already.”

“How considerate,” Aurora dryly replied before looking around at my companions. “And the rest of you?”

“All ponies,” I said, “and all aware of what I am.”

“I see. I have to say, I don’t like individuals coming into my camp without telling me about such a dangerous secret.”

“It isn’t any danger to you,” I said. “On the contrary, sharing this information is dangerous to me. You’re military. I’m sure you understand the need for operational secrecy.”

“Hmmph. Well, now your little secret is out. So tell me, what exactly is it that you’re doing here?”

“Right now? Trying to get back on-topic to deal with the changeling hive that’s quietly declared war on ponies, rather than the changeling that’s trying to help fight back.”

“And who has already lied to us.”

“Who hid a detail that was unimportant at the time, and who told you the moment it became important.” I raised a hoof, gesturing to her. “I know my kind doesn’t have the greatest reputation, but given what you’ve said of your own conflict, I’m sure you can appreciate what it’s like to be saddled with a reputation due to the actions of others.”

Her mouth snapped shut, head drawing back a hair. I couldn’t know for sure if the tactic I took would provoke or soothe her, so I continued on to smooth things over.

“I don’t generally tell ponies what I am, partially because most will see me as untrustworthy simply for being a changeling, and partially because it is the one meager advantage I have in a world that is particularly harsh for my kind. The best I can do is let my actions speak for me, instead. That’s why I try to help ponies where I can, and why I’ll offer any information or assistance I can give to combat the changelings who did this. They need to be stopped.”

While Aurora regarded me in silence, Dusty spoke up. “I almost shot her when I found out,” he said, “but it didn’t seem right after she revealed herself and risked her life to save us. She’s helped ponies and fought alongside us, even against the changelings that attacked Rust. She’s on our side.”

Starlight stepped in close, her side pressing to mine. “She’s good.”

Aurora was still frowning as she looked around at us. After another moment, she sighed. “Now this is an awkward situation, isn’t it? I can’t say I trust you—”

“I’m not asking you to,” I quickly said, “but I can give you information on this hive, and offer my help in dealing with them. All I’m asking you to do is listen.”

She considered that a moment longer, then slowly nodded. “Fair enough. Let’s see what you have to say.”

☢

We sat in Aurora’s tent. It was larger than the others, likely to accommodate meetings such as this, but it still felt slightly claustrophobic, especially with Echo, Sickle, and three power-armor-clad ponies in the space. I felt particularly exposed; Aurora had asked me to show what I really looked like, and I had complied, leaving me sitting in the midst of them in my natural form.

Aurora sat behind a makeshift desk, considering the few details we had been able to provide. She had removed her helmet, letting us see her face, as well as the short, multicolored and almost neon green-and-yellow mane, which contrasted with her purple-blue coat. Her expression was concerned. “This does seem like quite the mess, doesn’t it?”

I nodded. “Yes, ma’am.”

“A dangerous and potentially genocidal faction, based in a heavily fortified underground position, with significant resources and some substantial tactical advantages.” She shook her head, sighing. “And we have only a vague idea of their intentions. I’m curious about this attack. What does it get them? Was it merely a warm-up, a real-world operation to test their preparation for large-scale operations? Or did they have a specific reason to attack this settlement?”

“Rust was one of the primary sources of water in the area,” Dusty said. “Taking it out is going to be a big problem for some settlements. Mareford lives off of Rust’s water.”

Echo scoffed behind us, her first contribution since effectively outing me. “If they are quite done telling you what they know, then it is time for me to share what I know. These changelings left the water pump undamaged and unguarded. If it were their intention to deprive the region of water, then they are doing a terribly inefficient job of it. Water was not the only material Rust provided. As I understand it, they were the largest provider of good-quality metal, and it appears that several portions of the buildings were simply removed rather than being destroyed.”

Aurora looked her way. “Really? How sure are you about that?”

“As sure as I could possibly be, without having physically examined the structures prior to their destruction,” Echo replied. “We remember a good deal of engineering experience, and I can confidently say that those buildings would not have withstood their own weight with the materials that were present. The multi-story buildings showed signs where supports had been removed, and the damage was consistent with the use of cutting tools rather than weapons fire and demolitions. Further, there were marks on the ground that appeared to be produced by at least one heavily laden skywagon, and at least one place where intact metal plates and supports had been removed from the wreckage and set aside.”

That keyed a memory in my mind. “When we were escaping from Serenity, I overheard one of the changelings there say something about needing to find a source of structural steel.” I gave a weak shrug. “I have no idea what for.”

“That should be perfectly obvious,” Echo said, raising her nose. “Their efforts to repair the Cumulonimbus require a substantial amount of materials. More, I expect, than they were willing to strip from their own Stable.”

Aurora’s eyes had widened, her ears pinning back. “They’re doing what?”

Echo frowned and spoke with a slight but deliberate slowness. “Repairing the Cumulonimbus.”

Aurora gaped at her for a few moments—an expression at least partially mirrored by several other ponies in the room—before abruptly blurting out, “They took the Cumulonimbus? How? There was at least a company of Council forces holding the wreckage! My scouts didn’t report any fighting there!”

“There was no fighting, and these Council forces never held the Cumulonimbus,” Echo said. “It seems they are either unaware of the vessel’s location, or are convinced that there is nothing worth recovering.”

“But—” Aurora stopped, shutting her mouth. There was a moment of silence as she glanced at me, then returned to Echo. “Are you telling me that those were changelings?”

“Of course,” Echo said.

Aurora sighed, sitting back heavily.

Echo continued. “I have been observing many activities in the region. The crash of your cloudship was quite dramatic, and I observed everything that happened afterwards. There was considerable traffic to the site, but I noted that these Enclave imposters were not traveling above the clouds. Instead, they were traveling to a location on the ground.” She gestured a hoof to us. “A location that was eventually identified as Serenity.”

Aurora pondered the situation, frowning down at the maps and papers on her desk. “I can’t say I like the idea of some third party getting ahold of a cloudship, much less the Cumulonimbus. On the other hoof, at least this keeps it out of the Council’s hooves.”

I spoke up. “We can’t let Serenity have a Raptor. You saw what they did to Rust. A Raptor would let them do that to any settlement in Equestria, without any chance of reprisal.”

“I’m quite well aware of a Raptor’s combat capability, and I can assure you, you’d be mistaken if you think they’re impervious to what the ground-bound ponies can throw at them.” She slowly shook her head. “I have a very limited force, with no prospects of resupply. I have to conserve what strength I have.” She picked up a piece of paper. “According to the latest reports from my scouts, the defensive force at the Cumulonimbus is larger than mine, and several of the Raptor’s cannons are operational. We couldn’t retake it without crippling losses.”

“Allowing them to have that much firepower is going to be even more crippling to the ponies down here,” I said. “This isn’t just some power grab. If you know your history, you should know what the original Queen Chrysalis thought of ponies. Serenity’s queen is every bit her namesake, if not worse. She doesn’t simply not care for ponies, she despises you. To her, you’re the reason for everything wrong in the world. She holds the belief that the only thing a pony is good for is food, and I don’t doubt for a moment that she will happily exterminate any pony that isn’t useful to her!”

“I agree it’s a problem,” Aurora said, frowning as she fixed me with a firm stare. “If I had the ability, I would stop them, but I don’t. We’re a hoofful of ponies with limited resources. Trying to retake a well-defended cloudship from a superior force would be throwing away my soldier’s lives. I’m trying to help as many ponies as possible, but there’s a limit to what we can do. I have to prioritize, and I’m sorry, but the fight against the Council has to be my priority. Once they’ve been defeated and the Enclave is stable once more, we can easily take down a single rogue Raptor.”

I sat back, ears drooping.

“I’m sorry,” Aurora said, her voice softening. “I’ve seen too many innocent ponies die already. All of us have. Some of us even bear some responsibility for it and are trying to make up for that. Every single one of us is fighting to put an end to such things. We’ll do what we can to help the ponies of the Wasteland, to maybe make up for some of the things that have been done in the Enclave’s name, but we can’t be everywhere at once. Fighting this Serenity head-on just isn’t an option for us right now.”

She was right, of course. Even with the arsenal they had, and the few dozen soldiers, they couldn’t take on Serenity directly. Besides, they had their own fight. I sighed and nodded.

“I wish we could do more,” Aurora said. “We’ll keep our patrols flying, and if the opportunity presents itself, we can hit supply runs and raiding parties. And I can promise you this: when the Council is finally put down, we’ll be back. The Enclave isn’t going to turn its back on ponies ever again.” She raised a hoof, touching her armor’s blue-painted chest. “It’s why we took up these colors.”

Despite my disappointment at the situation, that caught my attention. “An expression of Loyalty?” I guessed.

Aurora’s expression brightened just a fraction. “You’ve heard of Rainbow Dash?”

I nodded. “The mare in charge of the Ministry of Awesome, and the bearer of the Element of Loyalty.”

“Ah, someone knows their history,” Aurora said with an approving nod. “Yes, Rainbow Dash. The Enclave’s greatest traitor.”

I blinked, my surprise and confusion obvious on my face.

“Guess you didn’t get that story down here,” Aurora said, smiling. “We heard it plenty. Had it drilled into our heads. The Council said she turned her back on us after the Great War, abandoned us, and even tried to bring down the Enclave herself. Her name became synonymous with betrayal. Dashites, they call us. They’d even take traitors and brand her cutie mark over their own, so everypony could see how disloyal they were.”

Starlight drew back half a step, her expression horrified. I might not have a cutie mark myself, but I could certainly see the significance. A cutie mark was something immensely personal and significant to a pony. Destroying it was like destroying a part of what made them a pony. The closest comparison I could think of for a changeling was the loss of my hive.

Aurora scoffed quietly, shaking her head. “Ends up, she was just the first pony to see what was really going on. She saw what the ponies in charge were doing, even way back then. She didn’t abandon us. She was refusing to abandon other ponies, and the Council, or what passed for them at the time, saw her as a threat to their power. She wasn’t a traitor. She was their first victim. They banished her, cast her down to the surface, maybe even killed her.” Her hoof returned to her chest. “So now we wear her colors, to honor her memory as we finish what she started.”

To her side, one of the soldiers was faintly nodding in agreement.

I managed a weak smile; while the prior conversation still weighed heavily in my mind. I liked the sentiment. “If nothing else, I imagine she’d be pleased to see so many ponies wearing her colors.”

Aurora gave a soft laugh. “I imagine she would.” She lowered her hoof, regarding me for a moment as her smile faded again. “I’ve got to admit, I hadn’t ever expected to have a friendly conversation with a changeling.”

That drew a dry, humorless chuckle from me. “The last few months have been rather exceptional at providing unexpected experiences.”

She nodded. “Very true. That said, I’m curious how many more of you there are. You’ve said a lot about this other hive, but not much about your own. If there’s a friendly changeling hive, I think I’d like to meet them.”

I grimaced. “I’m afraid I’m it, at the moment. My hive was destroyed. I’m still looking for survivors, but I haven’t found any.”

Her smile faded. “I’m sorry. I hope you have luck in finding them.”

“Thank you.”

A silence followed, and after a moment, she spoke again. “Well, I think I’ve kept you long enough. We have a spare tent cleared out if you’re planning to spend the night. Vapor can lead you to it.” She gestured to one of the armored soldiers beside her. “The rules might be a little loose at the moment, but this is still a military encampment, so I’m going to have to ask you not to wander without an escort.” She looked my way. “And no impersonating my ponies.”

“Of course,” Dusty said, standing. “Thank you for your hospitality, and I hope things go well for you.”

We said our goodbyes, and I retook my disguise before exiting her tent. It seemed like such a token gesture; no doubt the story would have spread across the entire camp by the morning, if it hadn’t already. Still, I could at least put on some pretense of having some degree of control over my own secrets.

And on that note, there was a certain pony I needed to deal with.

The tent Aurora had provided was the same size as her own and the other large tents, and without the extra power-armor-clad ponies, it gave us enough room to relax, if not quite enough to call it spacious. Echo strolled along behind us, as usual. She had just entered the tent when she staggered to a stop; I had turned, blocking her path.

“When we agreed to allow you to accompany us, it was under certain conditions,” I said, my voice firm, but as neutral as I could manage. “It’s obvious that you’ve taken issue with me, but if you’re going to stay with us, you will not try to harm any of us like that again.”

She scoffed, glaring icily down at me. “I did not harm—”

“There are plenty of ways of harming people other than direct physical injury,” I said, as her ears flicked back in agitation at being interrupted. “You tried to undermine me, attacked my credibility, and deliberately exposed me to harm. If you have some issue with me, or anyone else here, then bring it up with us, but so long as you’re traveling with us, you will not try to hurt anyone like that again. Do you understand?”

Her mane had grown, flowing in agitation in the still air. “You spoke a lot about ideals and their importance, but as soon as—”

“Honesty is not just about telling the truth,” I said. “That’s what this is all about, isn’t it?”

She blinked, her head tilting slightly as she processed my interruption. “...That is quite literally what the word means,” she replied, still glaring.

“It’s a lot more than that,” I said, refusing to back down even under that intimidating glare. To my side, Starlight was watching with wide eyes and a magical grip on her Lancer, and I couldn’t help but notice how Sickle had moved to the side, still relaxed, but with her attention clearly focused on the alicorn.

“It’s as much about intent as anything else,” I continued. “What I said might have been misleading, but it was not something that would cause any harm to anyone. What you said was intended to harm me, and I suspect was done without any consideration to the real damage your statement could cause to others.”

“Damage to others?”

“You didn’t just try to hurt me,” I said. “You undermined the credibility of everypony here, and potentially exposed them to real harm. I missed the worst of the changeling paranoia, but we all studied it. Some ponies had their lives destroyed just because someone thought they might be a changeling. Some ponies who had been victims of changelings were treated with suspicion and ostracized. When you outed me, you didn’t just say I was deceiving them. You said that every pony with me was trying to deceive them, too. If these soldiers decided that I was a threat that had to be dealt with, do you really think they would stop with just me?”

Her ears flicked. “If you hadn’t been trying to mislead them, none of that would have happened.”

“And,” I continued forcefully, “you tried to out me in front of Singe, who had just seen changelings wipe out her entire settlement. She was already terrified that we were all changeling imposters intent on hurting her, and you didn’t even consider how that information would hurt her.”

She frowned. “While I most certainly did not intend to distress her, that hardly compares to the lies you have told. You are a changeling imposter. You intend to lecture me on the values expressed by the Elements of Harmony, but you flout the very nature of one of them.”

“Not as much as you seem to think. I prefer honesty.”

She scoffed again. “You are a professional liar.”

“And that’s why I prefer honesty,” I said. “I know how damaging a lie can be, but I also know how much more devastating the truth can be if it’s used as a weapon. That’s why intent is important.”

“Nonsense. The truth might be unpleasant at times, but ponies deserve it.”

“You almost put Sickle through a wall because of a cruelly delivered piece of truth.”

Echo flinched, ears flicking back. “...She was being intentionally insulting. That is hardly the same thing as simply being honest.”

“And I then delivered the exact same truth, with different wording and intent. Same message, but it’s no longer insulting.”

She silently considered this, still frowning.

With her protests halted for the moment, I took on a more conversational tone. “Ponies like to imagine the truth is nice and simple, but it’s very complex. An incomplete truth can be as misleading as any lie, if not more. If you went up to Singe and told her I was a changeling, that would be technically factual, but the impression you would give her is far from the truth. She wouldn’t know every other piece of information that would be necessary to see the truth. She wouldn’t know anything about my history, who I am, or what I’ve done. She’d have every reason to think of me as being like the changelings who attacked Rust. Trying to tell her the truth like you did would mislead her more than any deception on my part.”

She remained silent, thoughtful.

“The Elements aren’t about being perfect,” I said. “Applejack, the bearer of Honesty, told the occasional lie. Rarity could be self-centered. Pinkie Pie had her sad days. Sometimes Rainbow Dash let her friends down. Even Fluttershy had the occasional temper tantrum. And Twilight… well, I’m not quite sure what the opposite of Magic is, but I know there were times when she was a bad friend, especially when she was younger.”

Echo’s eyes had widened, once again staring off into space with a vacant expression.

“You remember this,” I asked, “don’t you?”

“We do,” she quietly replied, eyes unfocused.

“I might be an Infiltrator, but I try to be honest. No, I’m not perfect. I’ve told plenty of lies, of course. I try to make sure they help others, but sometimes I’ve failed at that. There are lies I shouldn’t have told.” I raised a hoof toward Starlight. “It’s almost cost me friendships, nearly gotten me killed, and caused all manners of problems. I’m trying to be more honest, but I’m not going to be perfect. Nobody is perfect. What matters is our intentions. I don’t try to mislead ponies in ways that will harm them, I don’t cheat them, and I keep my promises. That’s what makes me different from ponies like Big Gun or this Council Aurora was talking about. I may have to lie, both directly and through omission, but I still try to deal honestly with ponies.”

She thought on that for several seconds. “This seems… very counter-intuitive.”

“It doesn’t have to be,” I said. “The simplest distinction is whether your actions help or hurt others.”

“That does not clarify anything,” Echo said, turning to look at me again. “You have all killed many ponies. That seems like ‘hurting’, to me.”

“Ponies who were directly trying to hurt others,” I said. “There’s a big difference between being imperfect and intentionally trying to harm others. The ponies we’ve killed were ones who murdered and tortured other ponies, or who were trying to do so. We did so because we wanted to help others, not because we wanted to hurt them.”

Sickle chuckled from across the tent. “Well, I wanted to hurt them. It’s fun.”

“You should probably ignore anything Sickle says in regard to morality,” I said with a frown. “Though I should note that she goes after raiders that hurt other ponies, rather than innocents.”

“Of course I do,” Sickle said. “Raiders give a better fight. More fun. Plus, I get paid more.”

Echo looked critically at Sickle. “Many of the arguments you have presented seem… familiar, but the result still seems hopelessly muddled. Perhaps you could clarify, Whisper; given that Sickle enjoys hurting others, and has admitted to have tortured, raped, and murdered many ponies, why should I not kill her for the sake of helping others?”

“For the same reason we haven’t,” I said. “It’s not necessary. She changed her ways, even if only a little. Now she goes after raiders and such, rather than innocent ponies. If she does start going after innocent ponies, then we’ll stop her, but I doubt it will come to that, and I doubt we would need to resort to killing her to do so.”

“I’d like to see you try,” Sickle said, rattling as she flopped down on her side. “Might be funny.”

Echo hummed softly, considering her for another moment before nodding. “Yes, I think I understand.”

“Good,” I said, nodding as well. “Then, while I won’t ask you to lie for me, or even to support any mistruth I might give, I need to ask that you won’t directly call me out on any misleading or incomplete statements like you did in there.”

“Unless I believe you are attempting to bring unnecessary harm upon an individual.”

I smiled as she made that connection. “Yes, exactly. Very good.”

She smiled as well, mane flowing a little more actively, as if she were energized by the recognition of her success. “Good! Now that we have resolved that… small misstep, we should begin studying your magic. We have much work to do. Hmm. I should find something to take notes on. I wonder if these ponies might have some scrolls and quills I could make use of.”

I sighed as the moment of satisfaction passed. “If you don’t mind, I’m exhausted. The last six hours or so has been one stress after another, and I need some time to rest and recover. On top of that, I’d rather not be doing flashy magic in a military camp that’s already rather wary of me. Could it wait until we’ve left? We could even lend you the spare PipBuck for taking notes, once we get it back.”

“Hmm.” Her smile had vanished, replaced with a thoughtful frown. She nodded. “I do not like delaying, but I suppose that is an acceptable reason. I would not want to compromise the quality of my work due to excessive stress on the subject. Very well, we shall begin tomorrow.”

“Good,” I said, turning to Dusty, who was waiting patiently beside me.

He spoke before I could. “Serenity is going on the offensive, and they’ve already infiltrated at least one settlement. How likely do you think it is that they’ve infiltrated this group of soldiers?”

“That’s something I’ve been wondering myself,” I said. “My PipBuck hasn’t shown any hostile contacts, but we know how unreliable that can be when an Infiltrator is involved. Personally, I think the odds are low. Soldiers tend to be a close-knit group, and being isolated like they are would make it much harder to infiltrate their ranks. Even if someling managed to avoid suspicion, the knowledge that changelings are in play is going to increase suspicion of any unusual behavior.” I paused, looking to the entrance of the tent. “All the same, I think it would be a good idea to keep a watch.”

He simply nodded.

“I shall assist,” Echo declared. It seemed strangely comforting that she was contributing.

I had found more of my sisters, long dead, talked a potentially genocidal alicorn down to something approaching a reasonable pony, came across the destruction of an entire settlement, was surrounded by Enclave soldiers, had my identity revealed, and was faced with the knowledge that Serenity, having already murdered a number of ponies, had claimed a weapon of tremendous power. So much was happening.

I wondered what the next day would bring.